Random entries, random exits, random
results. This is why you fail. This
video is a professional trading blueprint.
It shows you the right path step-by-step,
whether you've placed 1,000 trades
or you're a complete beginner.
Let's start with market structure.
Market structure refers to the overall map of
the market, the patterns of highs and lows,
and the price swings connecting them over time.
If you look at any price chart, you'll see the
market structure laid out before your eyes—the
static record of how price moved in the past.
When prices keep rising or falling,
that creates a trend. In an uptrend,
each new high is higher than the last one. We call
that a Break of Structure (BOS). At the same time,
each low stays above the previous low
point. That bullish momentum continues
until the price finally dips below a
prior major low, which is a Change of
Character (CHoCH). You can tell a trend is
losing steam when the price fails to make
a new high after the latest rise. That's
a sign buyers may be losing their grip.
In a downtrend, you'll see the opposite:
lower lows and highs that can't quite reach
the last high. This bearish pressure from
sellers keeps pushing the price down. The
trend stays in place as long as those lower
highs and lows keep coming. But if the price
manages to top the last high, the trend
could be reversing to bullish territory.
Sometimes the market takes a breather and moves
sideways between trends. This happens when the
highs and lows are roughly equal, creating a tight
range. We call this a consolidation period. The
price stays stuck, bouncing between supply
and demand until it finally breaks out above
the usual highs or below the normal lows of that
channel. That's when a new trend could be born.
For a trend to flex its muscle, it needs
to keep printing those new highs and lows.
But only one candle testing highs doesn't mean
much. If you see several candles close above
past resistance in a row, that's a stronger case
for buyer control. And the reverse is true for
downtrends: a few candles breaking below support
strengthens the argument for seller dominance.
Another thing to watch is how far each new swing
travels. If every price leg is bigger than the
last, this tells you the dominant force is gaining
momentum with every cycle. The growing imbalance
between supply and demand is fueling increasingly
larger price movements. So, even if the market
has entered a sideways phase, seeing progressively
larger waves suggests the current bigger trend may
still be healthy. Speed matters, too. A swift move
to new highs or lows over fewer candles is more
powerful than a gradual climb or descent. It's a
sign of intensifying pressure driving the price.
Trading is all about finding edges, and support
and resistance levels are one of the most powerful
edges you can have. But these invisible lines
on your charts can make or break your trades.
Basically, support and resistance are
price levels where the market tends
to pause or reverse. Support is an area that
catches falling prices. Resistance is an area
that stops prices from rising further.
And it's all about supply and demand.
At support, buyers step in. They see the price
as a bargain and start buying. At resistance,
sellers take over. They think the price is
too high and start selling. Here's the key:
these levels aren't exact prices. They are more
like zones where interesting things happen.
But why should you care about support and
resistance? First, they help you understand
market structure. You can see where price is
likely to pause or reverse. This knowledge is
gold for timing your entries and exits. Second,
these levels show you where other traders are
placing their orders. Big players often cluster
their orders around support and resistance. And
when you know where the big money is, that's your
edge. We'll talk about that later. Third, support
and resistance levels are self-fulfilling. Traders
expect price to react at these levels, so they
place their orders accordingly. This collective
action makes those areas even more interesting.
Now, let's dive into the minds of buyers and
sellers at these key price points. At support
levels, buyers tend to step in, seeing the
price as a good deal. They believe the price
is undervalued and expect it to rise from this
point. This buying pressure often causes the
price to bounce off support. At resistance
levels, sellers become more active. They view
the price as too high and anticipate a drop,
leading to increased selling pressure. This
behavior creates a self-fulfilling prophecy. As
more traders watch these levels and act on them,
their collective actions make the levels
more likely to hold, at least temporarily.
Market memory plays a crucial
role in shaping these zones.
Traders remember past price levels where
significant buying or selling occurred. These
memories influence future trading decisions. The
concept of "trapped traders" also contributes to
market memory. Imagine a trader who bought
at a certain price only to see the market
drop. He might be eager to sell at breakeven
when the price returns to his entry point.
This creates resistance as these
trapped traders exit their positions.
Support and resistance zones often form around
round numbers ending in zero or double zeros.
This is partly due to the psychological
comfort we find in round numbers. Many
traders place orders at these levels,
creating natural support and resistance.
The strength of support and resistance
levels can change over time. A level that's
been tested multiple times without breaking
becomes more significant in traders' minds,
but it also becomes more likely to eventually
break as more traders are watching it and
positioning themselves around it. When a
support or resistance level does break,
the ensuing price move can be dramatic. This is
because many traders place their stop-loss orders
just beyond these levels. When the level
breaks, it triggers a cascade of orders,
accelerating the price move. This behavior
is often exploited by large market players
who might push the price through a level to
trigger these stops before reversing the move.
High-quality support and resistance levels have
several special traits that make them stand out
on a chart. One of the most prominent features
of strong levels is the presence of sharp,
big reversals. These are points on the
chart where the price makes a sudden and
significant change in direction. For
example, if price is falling rapidly
and then suddenly bounces back up just as
quickly, this sharp reversal could indicate
a strong support level. This dramatic price
movement suggests that there's a significant
imbalance between buyers and sellers at
these levels, leading to quick reversals.
High-quality support and resistance levels often
show multiple instances of price bouncing off
them. This repeated behavior reinforces the
importance of these levels. For instance,
if you notice that a stock price has
bounced up from a level several times,
this could be an important support level.
These multiple bounces demonstrate that
traders consistently recognize these levels and
act on them, creating a self-fulfilling prophecy.
Swing highs and lows are another important
feature to look for because they represent
areas where the balance between buyers and
sellers shifted significantly. High-quality
levels often demonstrate the ability to act as
both support and resistance. This characteristic,
known as role reversal, happens when a broken
support level becomes a new resistance level,
or when a broken resistance level becomes a
new support level. This phenomenon happens
because traders remember these levels
and adjust their behavior accordingly.
One of the key traits of high-quality support
and resistance levels is that they are visually
obvious on a chart. These levels should stand
out clearly even to an inexperienced trader. If
you have to squint your eyes to identify a level,
it might not be as significant as you think. The
most powerful support and resistance levels are
those that are immediately apparent when you look
at a chart. This visual prominence is important
because it means that many traders are likely to
notice and act on these levels, increasing
their potential impact on price movements.
Support and resistance levels that
have been recently respected tend to
be more reliable than older levels. This is
because market conditions change over time,
and levels that were significant in the
distant past may no longer be relevant.
Look for levels that have influenced
price movements in the recent past,
as these are more likely to continue playing
a role in current and future price action.
Round numbers often act as psychological support
and resistance levels. For instance, many traders
might set their take-profit orders at $100 if
a stock is approaching that level from below,
or they might set stop-loss orders just
below $100 if the stock is trading above
it. This clustering of orders around numbers can
create noticeable support and resistance effects.
The strongest support and resistance levels
typically combine multiple traits. For example, a
level might be a round number, have acted as both
support and resistance in the past, show multiple
bounces, and be easily visible on the chart. The
more of these characteristics a level exhibits,
the more likely it is to be a significant support
or resistance point. And when drawing support
and resistance lines on your charts, remember
that they don't always need to be exact. Prices
can sometimes break slightly past these levels
before reversing (known as a false breakout), or
they might reverse direction just before reaching
the level (an imperfect reversal). So, you might
need to draw a wider zone rather than a precise
line to capture all the relevant price action.
Now, before we continue, let us know in the
comments what topics you'd like us to cover.
Please tell us what you want to watch next.
Now, let's talk about support and resistance
flips. When price breaks through a support level,
it shows a shift in power from buyers to sellers.
The former support level then often becomes a
new resistance level. This happens because
traders who bought at a support level and
are now facing losses may sell when the price
returns to that level, creating resistance.
When price breaks above a resistance level,
that level can become a new support level,
as traders who missed the initial move
up may buy at the former resistance,
now viewing it as a good entry point.
These flips demonstrate the psychological
aspects of trading. Traders remember price
levels where significant shifts occurred,
and their collective actions around these
levels can create self-fulfilling prophecies.
The strength of these flipped levels often depends
on how decisively the original level was broken.
A strong, high-volume break of a support or
resistance level is more likely to result in
a reliable flip than a weak break on low
volume. The number of times a level has
acted as support or resistance in the past
also influences its strength after a flip.
A level that has been tested multiple times
before breaking is often more significant.
When a support or resistance level is broken,
wait for a retest of that level before entering
a trade. If a former support level holds as new
resistance (or vice versa), it can confirm the
breakout. Sometimes a level will fail to hold
after flipping. For example, a broken support
level might not hold as resistance. These failed
flips can lead to strong moves in the opposite
direction as traders who were counting on the
level holding are forced to exit their positions.
When trading support and resistance flips,
consider the overall market context. In strong
trends, flipped levels are more likely to hold,
while in choppy or ranging markets, they may
be less reliable. Volume can provide additional
confirmation. High volume on the initial break and
again on the retest can increase the likelihood
of a successful flip. And it's also important to
note that not all support and resistance levels
will flip cleanly or hold after flipping. The
market is dynamic, and even strong levels
can be broken under the right circumstances.
One powerful aspect of support and resistance
flips is that they often mark the beginning
of new trends. When a long-standing resistance
level is finally broken and then holds as support,
it can signal the start of a significant
uptrend. When a strong support level breaks
and then acts as resistance, it might
indicate the beginning of a downtrend.
Volume is a key tool in trading support and
resistance. It's like a secret code that
reveals the strength of these levels. When
you mix volume with price action, you get a
powerful method called Volume Price Analysis. As
you already know, not all levels are the same.
Some are strong and some are weak. And how do you
know which is which? That's where volume comes in.
Think of volume as the fuel that drives the
market. When there's a lot of volume at a price
level, it means there's a lot of interest there.
This can create strong support or resistance. The
Volume Profile tool is great for finding these
key levels. It shows you where most trading
happened. The areas with the most volume are
often important support and resistance zones.
When you look at a volume profile,
focus on three main levels. First,
the Point of Control (POC). This is where
most trading occurred. It's often a strong
support or resistance level. Then, the Profile
High. This can act as resistance. And lastly,
the Profile Low. This can act as support. These
levels matter because they show where buyers and
sellers were most active. They're like battle
lines where the big players fought over price.
When price nears a key level, watch the volume
closely. If price breaks through with high volume,
it's often a real breakout. But if
it breaks through with low volume,
it might be a fake-out. On the flip side, if price
touches a level and bounces off with high volume,
that's a strong rejection. It means the level
held firm. But if it bounces with low volume,
the level might not be as strong as it looks.
Here's a cool trick: when price makes a big move
away from a level, use the Volume Profile to see
where the most trading happened during that
move. That spot often becomes a new support
or resistance level when price returns to it
later. Let's say you see a big price drop.
You can put a volume profile on that drop to find
where the most trading occurred. That area might
become resistance when price rises again. If
it does, it could be a great place to sell.
Remember, the market moves in waves. It trends
for a while, then pauses in a congestion phase,
then either keeps trending or reverses.
Understanding how volume works with these
moves is key to reading the market. When you're
looking at a potential trade, don't just look
at the price. Check the volume, too. Is it above
average? That's a sign of strength. Is it below
average? That might mean the move is weak. If
you're thinking about buying at support, look
for high volume as price touches that level; that
shows strong buying interest. If you're thinking
about selling at resistance, look for high volume
there, too. That can mean strong selling pressure.
As we already talked about, false breakouts and
liquidity runs are common traps in trading. When
price breaks through a key level, don't
just jump in right away. Wait for volume
to confirm the move. A true breakout
should come with above-average volume.
And if volume is low, it might be a
fake-out. But here's a cool trick:
sometimes a failed breakout can be an even
better trade. If price breaks out on low
volume and then quickly reverses, that can be a
strong signal to trade in the opposite direction.
Don't forget about timeframes. What looks
like a breakout on a 5-minute chart might
just be noise on a daily chart. Always check
higher timeframes to get the big picture before
making your decisions. Learning to read volume
in conjunction with support and resistance takes
practice, but it's worth the effort. You'll see
trading opportunities you never noticed before.
Trading support and resistance will
differ considering if the markets are
trending or they are ranging. And most
traders don't think about this aspect,
which is a major mistake. In a strong
trend, support and resistance levels
can help you catch big moves. When the
market is trending up or down with force,
it's not wise to fight it. Instead, look
for ways to join the trend at good prices.
Here's how to use these levels in
a strong uptrend. As price climbs,
it will often pause and drop back a bit. These
dips often stop at old resistance levels which
now act as support. Sometimes price will move
sideways for a while. This is like a pause in the
trend. It can form a small range near a support or
resistance level. Watch for breakouts. When price
breaks above the high of the consolidation,
it can signal the trend is ready to continue.
In a strong downtrend, you'd use the same ideas
but in reverse. Look for bounces from resistance,
consolidations, and breakdowns below support.
Ranging markets are trickier. Price bounces
between support and resistance without a
clear direction. Here's how to use these
levels. First, identify the range. Look
for clear areas where price has turned multiple
times. Wait for tests of these levels. As price
approaches support or resistance, watch
closely. How it acts here can tell you
a lot. You then look for rejection signals. If
price touches support and bounces up with force,
it might be a good time to buy. If it hits
resistance and drops hard, consider selling.
Be cautious of false breakouts. Price often pokes
above resistance or below support only to reverse.
Look for wicks or multiple wicks outside the
range. Watch for consolidations near the top
or bottom of the range (a consolidation within
the consolidation). If price forms a tight range,
it can signal a potential breakout. Of
course, use volume. High volume on a
bounce off support can signal a strong move. Low
volume might mean the move is weak. In ranges,
you're often looking to buy near support and sell
near resistance, but be ready to change your view
if the range breaks and a new trend starts. And
consider the timeframe. Levels on a daily chart
might not match what you see on a 5-minute
chart. Be clear about your trading horizon.
In the market, there are always two competing
forces: buyers, who represent demand, and sellers,
who represent supply. When there are more
buyers than sellers at a certain price level,
it creates a demand zone. When there are
more sellers than buyers at a price level,
it forms a supply zone. In these zones,
you often see large unfilled orders from
big institutional traders like banks and
hedge funds. Supply and demand trading is
powerful because it allows you to trade in line
with what the institutions are doing. These big
players can't hide their massive orders.
And by identifying supply and demand zones,
retail traders like us can spot where they
are likely to be executing their trades.
You see, the price is constantly moving up and
down, and this movement is a direct result of the
supply and demand from market participants.
When there are more buyers in the market,
they bring demand, and this applies upward
pressure on prices, pushing them higher. When
there are more sellers, they bring more supply to
the market, putting downward pressure on prices
and pushing them lower. This dynamic between
buyers and sellers is what we call Order Flow,
and it's the engine that actually
drives price action and market movement.
Now, there are two main types of
orders that make up this order flow:
passive orders and aggressive orders. Passive
orders are limit orders placed by traders who
are willing to wait for the price to come to
their desired level. They are not in a rush to
get in. Aggressive orders are placed by traders
who want to execute immediately at the current
market price. They are not waiting around for a
specific price; they want in fast. This constant
battle between passive and aggressive orders
is really what causes those explosive price
movements you see on your charts when there's a
significant imbalance between supply and demand.
So, your job is to identify where
major imbalances are likely to occur.
Now let's break down how to actually identify
them on your charts. The first step is to
look for those explosive movements where
price makes a strong push in one direction
before quickly reversing. This could be
a sharp rally followed by a sudden drop,
or a steep decline followed by a rapid bounce
back. These movements often signal that there
was a significant imbalance between buyers
and sellers that caused price to spike. Once
you've spotted one of these big moves,
the next step is to mark out the origin
of that move—in other words, the area on
your chart where that explosive rally or
decline actually started. This is going to
be your potential supply or demand zone.
Now, there are a few different types of
zones to look out for. First ones are
Base Zones or Range Zones. These form when
price is consolidating in a tight range for
an extended period of time before finally
breaking out. You can think of the edges
of that range as areas of supply and demand
where a lot of orders have built up. So when
price revisits those levels after a breakout,
there's a higher probability of a reaction.
We can also have Pivot Zones. These form
at key turning points in the market,
like swing highs and lows, or where you see price
making a sudden change in direction. They're often
marked by one or two candlesticks with distinct
characteristics. For a potential demand zone,
you want to look for a strong bearish candle
where the next candle closes back above its high,
signaling a shift from selling pressure
to buying pressure. For a supply zone,
you are watching for a strong bullish candle
where the next candle closes below its low,
indicating a shift from buying to selling. The
key is that these pivots are happening quickly;
price isn't spending much time
in these areas before reversing.
To identify fresh zones, you also want to
pay attention to the overall structure of
the price action. There are two main types of
structures to look for: Continuation and Reversal.
A continuation structure forms when there's an
existing trend in place and price is just pulling
back or correcting against that trend before
continuing in the same direction. These are your
Rally-Base-Rally and Drop-Base-Drop patterns.
If it's an uptrend, you'll see a strong rally,
a tight range where price forms a small base,
and then another rally continuing the uptrend.
For a downtrend, you'll see a sharp drop, a base,
and then another drop, resuming the downtrend.
Reversal structures form when price is reversing
from one trend direction to the other. These are
your Drop-Base-Rally and Rally-Base-Drop patterns.
So, in an uptrend that's starting to lose steam,
you might see price drop into a base
and then launch into a new rally,
marking the start of a reversal. And in a
downtrend that's starting to turn around,
you'd see a rally, a base, and then a strong
drop signaling the beginning of a new uptrend.
Now, let's talk about the key principles
that make this strategy so effective.
The first thing to understand is that supply and
demand zones are not just random levels on your
charts. They are areas where the imbalance
between buyers and sellers is most extreme.
When you see explosive price movements like huge
rallies or steep drops, that's often a sign that
there was a serious mismatch between the amount of
buying and selling pressure. What's happening in
these situations is that the aggressive orders
from one side are rapidly consuming all the
available orders from the other side until a new
equilibrium is found. The areas on your charts
where these big clashes take place are what we
call fresh unmitigated supply and demand zones.
One of the key things that separates these
high-probability zones from ordinary support
and resistance levels is the amount of
time price spends in the zone. You see,
when there's a major imbalance
between buyers and sellers,
the price won't hang around that area for very
long. It will quickly spike up or down. So,
when you're analyzing your charts, one of
the things to look for is zones where the
price only spent a short amount of time before
making a strong move in either direction. The
less time price spends in that area, the
more out of balance supply and demand are,
and the higher the probability of a successful
trade when the price returns to that zone.
Another key principle is to focus on fresh
unmitigated zones rather than ones that
have already been tested multiple times.
When price revisits a zone, it can absorb
some of the pending orders that were sitting
there, making the imbalance less extreme. So,
as a general rule, the more times a zone has been
hit, the weaker it becomes. This is why it's so
important to understand the difference between
an unmitigated zone and one that's already been
tested a few times (a mitigated one). The trading
opportunities are very different. Now, of course,
there are times when a zone can remain valid even
after being tested if there is still a significant
order imbalance, but generally, you want to
prioritize fresh zones when planning your trades.
So, the key things to look for are:
Zones that form after explosive price movements.
Zones where price only spends a short amount of
time before spiking up or down.
Fresh zones that haven't been
tested or absorbed by the market yet.
Now, let's talk about how to validate
whether a zone is likely to hold. The first
thing you want to look for is a clear Break
of Structure (BOS). This means price needs
to make a decisive move away from the zone
and take out any nearby swing highs or lows.
If there's no clear break of structure and
price just hovers around the zone, that's a sign
that the zone might not be as strong as it seems.
Another key concept is the idea of Flip Zones.
This is when a previous supply zone turns into
a demand zone, or vice versa. For example,
let's say you have a strong supply zone
that's been holding price down for a while, but
then suddenly price rips through that level and
closes above it. That's a pretty good indication
that the zone has flipped from supply to demand
and could now act as a support level for
future pullbacks. But here's the thing:
in order for a flip zone to be valid, you need
to see that initial interaction between the two
forces. Don't just assume a zone has flipped
because price moved past it. Look for that
clear battle between buyers and sellers and wait
for one side to decisively overpower the other.
Another important factor to consider is
Inducement. This refers to the presence of
liquidity in front of the zone that could
potentially absorb any move against it.
For example, if you're looking at a demand
zone, you want to see some buy orders stacked
up in front of that level. This could be in
the form of a swing low or a consolidation
pattern—anything that suggests there are
traders waiting to buy at that price. If
there's no liquidity in front of the
zone and price just slams into it,
chances are those big players aren't going to
be too interested in getting involved. But if
there are orders they can trade against, they're
much more likely to step in and defend the level.
Of course, even if a zone checks all these
boxes, it's not guaranteed to hold forever.
That's why it's also important to look
at how fresh the zone is. In general,
zones that have been tested
multiple times are less likely
to produce strong reactions than those
that are being hit for the first time.
Now let's talk about the difference between
supply and demand zones and traditional support
and resistance levels. While there are similar
concepts, there are some key distinctions. First
off, support and resistance are levels where
price has previously reversed or consolidated
multiple times in the past. Supply and demand
zones, on the other hand, are all about fresh
unmitigated levels. Rather than focusing on areas
that have already been touched multiple times,
these zones represent imbalances between buyers
and sellers that have just recently formed.
The key difference is that support
and resistance trading relies on the
assumption that past levels will continue to
hold in the future, whereas supply and demand
trading looks for new untested zones where the
order flow is likely to be more significant.
Remember this: support and resistance
levels are essentially supply and demand
zones that have already been confirmed. Once
a fresh demand zone gets tested and holds,
it then becomes an established support level.
The same goes for supply zones; they become
resistance after they've been touched. So, while
trading support and resistance can certainly be
effective (especially if a level has proven itself
multiple times in the past), the probability of
a reaction tends to diminish with each subsequent
test. This is why you should focus on fresh zones
where the initial imbalance between buyers and
sellers is likely to be the most significant.
Now, let's talk about some specific entry and
exit strategies you can use around these key
levels. One of the simplest and most effective
ways to enter a trade is to simply set a limit
order directly on the level itself. This
approach assumes that the zone will hold
and that price will reverse once it hits your
order. However, there are a couple of potential
downsides to this aggressive strategy. If you
set your order too far away from the zone,
you might miss out on the trade entirely if
price never quite reaches your price. Or,
the second scenario: price might just
break through your zone with ease.
A more conservative approach is to wait for
a specific candlestick pattern to form at the
level before entering a trade. For example,
you might look for a bullish reversal pattern
like a pin bar or an engulfing candle
at a demand zone. The idea behind this
strategy is that these candlestick
formations can give you a bit more
confirmation that the zone is likely to hold
and that price is getting ready to reverse.
Another technique you can use to fine-tune your
entries is to look for specific structures on
lower timeframes. For example, let's say you've
identified a strong demand zone on the 1-hour
chart, but you want to get more precise with
your entry. Instead of just buying blindly at
the level, you could drop down to the 15-minute
chart and look for a reversal pattern like a
double bottom or a Change of Character
(CHoCH) to form at the zone. In this way,
you can often get a tighter entry
with a better risk-to-reward ratio.
Now, let's talk about how to evaluate the strength
of a supply or demand zone. One of the first
things to look at is how quickly price moves
away from the zone after it's formed. Generally
speaking, the faster price shoots away from a
level, the stronger that level is likely to be.
Quick and significant moves away from a zone
indicate a strong imbalance. So if you see
price just rocketing away from a zone, that's
a pretty good sign that there is some serious
order flow happening there and that institutions
are likely defending the level aggressively.
Another factor to consider is the amount
of time price spends at the zone before
making that initial move. The less
time price hangs out at a level,
the more likely it is to be a key turning
point in the market. So if you see price
just kind of dip into a demand zone and
then immediately start rallying higher,
that's often a signal that big buyers have stepped
in and are absorbing all the available supply.
The actual size of the move
is important, too. Obviously,
if price barely budges after hitting a supply
or demand level, that's not exactly a big
endorsement of its strength. But if you see
an extended move in the opposite direction
after a zone is tested, that's a sign that
the level is probably pretty significant.
Another thing to watch for is the volume during
the formation of the zone. Generally speaking,
you want to see a noticeable uptick
in volume as price is testing a key
level. This indicates that there's a lot
of interest and activity happening at that
specific price and that institutions are
likely absorbing or distributing there.
Another factor that can affect the strength
of a zone is whether or not it causes a break
of market structure. A supply or demand
zone that causes a break of structure is
generally stronger. It takes a significant
amount of money to break market structure,
making the zones more likely to hold in the
future. So if you see a zone forms and then price
just starts trending in the opposite direction
and breaking through key levels on the chart,
that's often a sign that there is some
serious institutional backing behind the
move and that the zone is likely to
be a key focal point going forward.
When it comes to candlesticks, most price
action books will advise you to memorize
a plethora of candlestick patterns or spend
hours staring at charts. I'm going to give
you a better method to read them. First
and foremost, when you open up a chart,
take a look at the recent candles and focus
on their spread. The spread is the difference
between a candle's opening and closing price,
which forms the real body of the candle.
This spread reveals the market sentiment for
that particular time period. A wide spread
indicates strong market sentiment, while a
low spread indicates less trading activity.
Next, you look at the upper and
lower wicks of candlesticks,
also known as shadows. These wicks reflect
the buying and selling pressure in the
market. Consider them as rejection areas
where the market simply didn't accept the
prices represented by the wick. The length of the
wick, whether at the top or bottom of the candle,
should always be a main point of focus. It
instantly reveals strength, weakness, or
indecision in the market. And most importantly, it
shows you where buyers or sellers are stepping in.
Now, considering the spread of
the candlesticks and their wicks,
here are the key patterns you should consider.
When the body of the candle takes up at least
half of the entire bar range, you are looking
at a Trend Bar. Trend bars are the heart and
soul of market fluctuations. They represent
strong market sentiment and suggest a likely
continuation in the direction of the candle.
When you analyze a chart, pay attention to
instances of consecutive trend bars closing
in the same direction. If you spot several trend
bars in a row, all pointing in the direction of
the prevailing trend, it's a clear sign of
strength in that direction. If you notice an
absence of trend bars over the past 10 or so
candles, the market is likely consolidating.
A Trend-Based Long Wick Candle is characterized
by a candle with a wick sticking out in the same
direction as the moving trend. The smaller the
body and the longer the wick, the better the
quality of the candle. Large wicks indicate price
moved a lot during the candle but got rejected,
signaling supply or demand. The upper wick
acts as resistance while the lower wick acts
as support. In an uptrend, if a long wick candle
forms at a key support level, it means sellers
tried to push prices lower but failed to close
with momentum, causing the wick to stick out.
This suggests a potential continuation of the
previous trend. The length of the wick is the
first point of focus because it instantly shows
strength, weakness, and indecision in the market.
The Momentum Candle is characterized by a
larger spread compared to the previous candles,
showing a clear directional movement in price.
In an uptrend, you'll notice each candle getting
larger and larger, moving a greater distance per
candle. This shows a gain in bullish momentum.
In a downtrend, each candle gets larger and
larger, moving a greater distance per candle,
indicating a gain in bearish momentum. When
you see consecutive candles increasing in size,
it's a clear signal that the trend is gaining
momentum in that direction. In an uptrend,
it means buyers are in full control and there
aren't enough sellers to cause wide swings in
the opposite direction. In a downtrend, growing
candles show sellers are dominating the market,
and there aren't enough buyers
to counter their pressure.
An Inside Bar is characterized by a bar
that neither takes out the high nor the
low of its predecessor. An inside bar is
easily recognizable due to its relatively
small spread. The inside bar signifies a loss
of momentum and uncertainty in the market.
The smaller candle suggests consolidation after a
larger move as neither buyers nor sellers are able
to push the price beyond the previous bar's range.
The inside bar is also hinting at a potential
breakout in either direction. When an inside
bar forms at a crucial spot, such as a major
support or resistance, its break can trigger
quite a few traders in and out of position.
When you see several candles in a row failing to
break through a specific price level, each forming
long wicks in the same direction, you're looking
at a Multiple Candle Rejection. In an uptrend,
if multiple candles try to push above a resistance
level but fail each time, closing with long upper
wicks, it's a clear sign of rejection at that
level. These wicks form a selling pressure zone.
Multiple candle rejections show the repeated
failure of price to breach a key level,
suggesting a strong buying or selling presence
at that point. When buyers try to push prices
higher but fail multiple times, it indicates
that sellers are stepping in aggressively to
defend that level. The long upper wicks represent
the failed attempts of buyers to gain control.
Similarly, when sellers try to drive prices
lower but encounter repeated rejection,
it suggests strong buying interest at
that level. The long lower wicks signal
the inability of sellers to close below that
price. These wicks form a buying pressure zone.
As price approaches a key level, you'll notice the
candles getting smaller in size. Their spread gets
lower and lower. This pattern of successive
candles shrinking in size is a clear sign of
Decreasing Candles. Decreasing candles indicate
a loss of momentum as prices approach a critical
point in the market. The smaller candles suggest
that the distance traveled per candle is getting
shorter, which is an early signal that the
current trend is losing steam. For example,
in an uptrend approaching resistance,
decreasing candles show that buyers
are losing control and momentum. In a downtrend
nearing support, decreasing candles reveal that
sellers are losing their grip on the market.
To increase the quality of your trade setup,
look for decreasing candles that finish with
multiple long wick candles at the key level.
This combination suggests
a strong loss of momentum.
With this method, you'll soon realize that reading
price action isn't about memorizing dozens of
candlesticks. It's about observing price bars
as they form and understanding what the market
has done and is currently doing. The context of
the price move is crucial. A candle can have a
completely different meaning depending on where it
appears in a price trend. Is it at the beginning,
middle, or end of a trend? Is it at a support or
resistance or in the middle of a consolidation
phase? Always analyze candlesticks in the context
of the overall price move, never in isolation.
Now, let's talk a bit about pullbacks.
A pullback is a temporary price movement
that goes against the prevailing trend. It's
a period of price retracement or correction
before the trend resumes its original
direction. Pullbacks occur when price
moves in the opposite direction of the trend
for at least one bar. The psychology behind
pullbacks involves a temporary shift
in market sentiment. During an uptrend,
a pullback occurs when bearish pressure briefly
overcomes bullish pressure, driving prices lower.
However, this doesn't necessarily indicate a
trend reversal. If the lower prices fail to
attract enough selling pressure to break the
previous swing low, it suggests the pullback
is merely a correction within the larger
uptrend. As sentiment shifts back to bullish,
more buying enters the market. Shorts will cover
their positions and the uptrend will resume.
Now, not all pullbacks are created
equal. We can classify them into
two main types based on their depth:
Shallow Pullbacks and Deep Pullbacks.
Shallow pullbacks are corrections that
retrace only about 25% to 30% of the
current leg of the trend. They indicate
that the trend is still quite strong as
the counter-trend moves are relatively minor.
However, because the pullbacks are so shallow,
it can be tricky to time your entries
and define your risk when trading these.
Deep pullbacks are corrections that retrace
roughly 50% or more of the current trend leg.
These are often viewed as more favorable
trading opportunities as they allow you to
get into the trend at a better price with
a more attractive risk-to-reward ratio.
One of the main benefits of trading pullbacks
is the potential for higher probability
entries. When a strong price action signal
occurs at a key level following a pullback,
it indicates a high likelihood of the trend
continuing. Confirmation is key when trading
pullbacks. Look for candlestick patterns
to confirm the pullback is ending and the
trend is likely to resume. In an uptrend, the more
subdued the bearish pressure during the pullback,
the higher the odds of a successful
trend continuation. If done correctly,
trading pullbacks will allow you to buy low
in uptrends and sell high in downtrends.
When it comes to breakouts and false breakouts,
you need to understand how to distinguish between
the two. A true breakout can lead to a powerful
new trend, while a false breakout can trap traders
on the wrong side of the market. One key thing to
watch for is how price behaves after breaking out
of a trading range. If it quickly reverses and
comes back into the range, that's a sign of a
potential false breakout. Often these false moves
are engineered by large institutional traders to
build liquidity before driving the market in the
opposite direction. To avoid getting caught in
these traps, it's wise to wait for a retest of the
breakout level before entering a trade. Look for
price to hold outside the breakout level on the
retest. In a true breakout, price should continue
in the breakout direction, making new highs or
lows. However, if the breakout fails and price
remains stuck in a larger trading range, that's a
sign that the attempted trend change has failed.
Another thing to consider is the overall market
context. In a bull market, upward breakouts tend
to be more reliable and profitable, while bear
markets favor downward breakouts. Trading with a
prevailing trend will tilt the odds in your favor.
Remember, the market doesn't have to respect the
levels we draw on our charts. False breakouts
will occur with varying degrees of aggression.
There are two main types of patterns that
every price action trader should know:
Reversal Patterns and Continuation Patterns.
Reversal patterns signal that the current trend
may be coming to an end and the price could change
direction. The Head and Shoulders is the most
popular reversal pattern. It often signals that
an uptrend is about to reverse into a downtrend.
The opposite is an Inverted Head and Shoulders,
which can form at the bottom of a downtrend,
hinting at a potential bullish reversal. Double
Tops and Double Bottoms should be your main focal
point. These form when price tests the level twice
but can't break through, suggesting the trend
is losing momentum. A double top often leads
to a bearish reversal, while a double bottom
can result in a bullish reversal. Triple Tops
and Triple Bottoms are similar, with the price
testing a level three times before reversing.
Continuation patterns suggest that the current
trend is just taking a breather before likely
resuming. Flags and Pennants form quite
often. These appear as brief consolidations
or pullbacks against the prevailing trend.
They usually lead to the trend continuing
once price breaks out of the pattern in the
direction of the prior trend. Triangles are
usually continuation patterns with the trend
expected to resume in the direction it was going
before the triangle formed. Rectangles
are my favorite continuation patterns.
These are sideways channels where price bounces
between support and resistance. I like to trade
false breakouts that occur contrary to the
prevailing trend. So in an uptrend, look
to trade false breakouts below support. And in a
downtrend, trade false breakouts above resistance.
While knowing these classic patterns is
important, you need to look at them through
the lens of price action. Simply memorizing
patterns is not enough. You must understand
the market dynamics and psychology behind
them. This means paying close attention to
market structure and the key levels on the chart.
Look for price zones where the market has changed
direction multiple times before. If a chart
pattern forms near one of these key levels,
it can add significance to the pattern
signal. The overall trend is also crucial.
"Trend is your friend," as they say. In
an uptrend, bullish continuation patterns
are more likely to succeed. In a downtrend,
bearish continuation patterns have a higher
probability. You always want to trade in the
direction of the path of least resistance.
When a reversal pattern forms, it's signaling
that the trend may be in trouble, but it's not
a guarantee. Often times reversal patterns
will fail and the prior trend will resume.
Don't jump in on the first sign of a reversal.
Wait for price to confirm it. During pullbacks
or retracements against the main trend,
continuation patterns can offer low-risk
entries. If you expect the trend to resume again,
look for fake-outs against the current trend.
When a pattern breakout fails and price quickly
reverses, these are good opportunities to enter,
capitalizing on trapped traders who
thought the trend was about to change.
No two patterns are exactly alike in the real
world. As you analyze more and more charts,
you'll develop a keener eye for the subtleties
that separate successful patterns from failures.
You'll start to recognize how certain
patterns tend to play out in specific
markets, timeframes, or conditions.
Of course, no pattern is guaranteed.
Approach patterns with the combination
of respect and skepticism they deserve.
Price action becomes 10 times more effective with
the help of volume. Volume is the lifeblood of the
markets. It reflects the actual buying and selling
pressure behind every price move. When you're
looking at a chart, the price bars show you what's
happening, but the volume bars reveal why it's
happening. Volume tells you about the intensity,
urgency, and commitment behind the price action.
Here's how you can use volume to confirm or
question what you're seeing in the price. First,
look for convergence between volume and price. In
an uptrend, rising prices should be accompanied by
rising volume. This shows genuine buying interest
that can sustain the move. In a downtrend, falling
prices with increasing volume signals strong
selling pressure that could drive prices lower.
Be wary of divergences. If prices
are rising but volume is falling,
it's a warning sign. The uptrend may be losing
steam. Buyers are less committed. An upside
breakout on low volume is suspect. Likewise,
if prices are falling but volume is drying up,
sellers may be losing control. The
downtrend could be nearing exhaustion.
Look for volume spikes near support and
resistance. Major players often show
their hand at key levels. If there's a volume
surge as price tests a support level and holds,
that's often a sign of strong demand
absorbing the selling pressure;
the support is likely to hold. Also track
volume during breakouts. A valid breakout
(up or down) should occur with an expansion
in volume. This confirms the price action.
But a breakout on low volume is more likely to
fail, trapping traders in the wrong direction.
Also, watch for Climactic Volume. After a strong
run-up, a huge volume spike with a wide range
price bar can signal buying exhaustion—a
Buying Climax. Supply may be taking over.
The uptrend is in jeopardy. The reverse is true
for a Selling Climax after an extended decline.
Monitor the volume patterns in consolidations.
Is volume contracting as the price range narrows?
This can be a sign of decreasing volatility
and building pressure for the next move. Also,
look for high volume reversal bars. A wide range
bar on massive volume that reverses an existing
trend is a red flag. For example, a bearish
momentum bar with huge volume after an uptrend
is a sign that sellers have taken control. Think
of volume as the fuel and price as the vehicle.
A rally or decline can only go as far as the fuel
in the tank. As a price action trader, you always
want to be on the stronger side of the market—the
side with more aggressive volume behind it.
Market prices move based on the flow of buy and
sell orders. More buying pressure pushes prices
up while more selling pressure pushes prices
down. For substantial price movements to occur,
the market needs to interact with areas of high
order concentration, also known as liquidity. So,
liquidity means all the buy and sell orders
waiting to be filled. Now, here's the interesting
part. If there isn't enough liquidity, the big
players (the Smart Money) will create it. For big
traders like banks or hedge funds, liquidity
is critical. They deal with large amounts of
money. In less liquid markets, their big trades
can push prices around a lot. This makes it hard
for them to buy or sell without losing money.
Now, if you understand where liquidity sits,
you can identify Magnet Areas—those
price levels that attract price movement.
Your main task is to find Liquidity
Pools. Liquidity pools are like busy
trading spots in the market. They're areas
where lots of buy and sell orders gather,
and they form at key price levels.
These could be previous highs or lows,
round numbers, or other important points.
We'll talk about these in a minute. Now,
traders often place their orders at these
levels creating a cluster of potential trades.
There are different types of liquidity pools:
Major Liquidity Pools: These form at the highs
and lows of longer timeframes. These are big,
important levels that many
traders watch. You might see
them on weekly, monthly, or even yearly charts.
Medium Liquidity Pools: These show up on shorter
timeframes like 1-hour charts. These are still
significant but not as big as the major pools.
Minor Liquidity Pools: These appear on
very short timeframes like 1-minute or
5-minute charts. These are smaller and might
only matter for very short-term traders.
Liquidity pools work by attracting price.
When price approaches a liquidity pool,
a few things can happen. It might reverse as
lots of orders get filled at that level, or it
might pause there before continuing. Sometimes it
might even break through quickly if there's enough
momentum. And big players are constantly trying to
hunt these liquidity pools. They often push price
to these levels to trigger a bunch of orders,
causing a sharp move. So, liquidity zones are
key areas where Smart Money players often target
to protect their positions and to trap other
traders. These zones act like magnets for price,
drawing it in and often causing significant moves.
So, let's talk about each type of liquidity zone
and how Smart Money uses them to their advantage.
First area is around Structural Highs and Lows.
These are major turning points in price action—the
peaks and valleys you see on a chart that stand
out from the rest. Smart Money loves these
spots because they know traders often place their
stop-losses just beyond them. Let's say we have a
strong uptrend with a series of higher highs and
higher lows. Traders often jump on this trend,
placing their stops just below the most recent
low. And Smart Money knows this. They often push
the price down, breaking that low and triggering
all those stop-losses. This flood of sell orders
drives the price down further, often before Smart
Money steps in to buy at a discount. The same
happens in downtrends. Retail shorts place their
stops above recent highs. Smart Money spike the
price up, hit those stops, then drive the price
back down. To spot these zones, look for clear
swing highs and lows. The more obvious they are,
the more likely they are to attract attention.
Trend Lines are another favorite tool of traders.
The diagonal lines that connect a series of lows
in an uptrend or highs in a downtrend. They
are simple to draw and easy to understand,
which is why so many traders rely on them. Big
players often target these trend lines, especially
long-standing ones. They know that many traders
will have stop-losses placed just beyond these
lines. By breaking a significant trend line, they
can trigger a cascade of orders. For instance,
in a long-standing uptrend, many traders will be
long with their stops just below the trend line.
Smart Money might push the price down to break
this line. As stops are hit, more sell orders
flood in. Smart Money can then step in and buy
at lower prices before resuming the uptrend.
Equal Highs and Lows, also known as Double Tops
and Double Bottoms, are also exploited by Smart
Money. These patterns form when price reaches the
same level twice, creating a potential reversal
point. Traders often see these patterns and
place their trades accordingly. For a double top,
they might go short with a stop just above
the equal highs. For a double bottom,
they might go long with a stop just below the
equal lows. Smart Money knows this and often
pushes the price just beyond these levels
to trigger stop-losses before reversing.
This creates a liquidity pool that
they can use to their advantage.
Trading Sessions, particularly the Asian, London,
and New York sessions, often create their own
ranges. These ranges can become significant
liquidity zones, especially at their highs and
lows. Big players often target the session's
highs because they know many traders use them
for entries and stop placements. For example,
many traders use the Asian session range as a
guide for the London session. They might place buy
orders above the Asian high and sell orders below
the Asian low. Smart Money might push the price
just beyond these levels to trigger these orders,
creating liquidity that they can trade against.
They might spike the price above the Asian high,
triggering buy orders, only to sell into
this liquidity and push the price back down.
The Previous Day's High and Low are other
significant levels that many traders watch.
They often serve as support and resistance
levels for the current day's trading. Again,
the big boys frequently target these levels.
For instance, many traders place buy orders
just above the previous day's high, expecting
the upward momentum to continue. Smart Money
will push the price up to trigger these
orders, creating a pool of liquidity.
They can then sell into this liquidity,
potentially reversing the price direction.
The Previous Week's High and Low also attract a
lot of attention. You might not even know where
those levels are. These levels often act as key
support and resistance on higher timeframes,
and Smart Money often exploit these levels knowing
that many swing traders and position traders use
them for stop placement and entry orders. For
example, in a downtrend, many traders might
place sell orders below the previous week's low,
expecting the trend to continue. Smart Money often
push the price down to trigger these orders,
creating a liquidity pool they can buy into.
Supply and Demand Zones are other liquidity zones.
These are areas where price has shown significant
rejection in the past, and these zones are prime
targets for Smart Money manipulation. Smart Money
know many traders place their orders around
them. For example, many traders might place
buy orders at a strong demand zone. Smart Money
might push the price into this zone, triggering
these buy orders and creating liquidity. They
can then potentially sell into this liquidity,
driving the price even lower. That's why you see
so many demand zones that should work in theory,
but in reality, they fail. The same happens with
supply zones. Traders often place sell orders
at these levels, expecting price to drop. Smart
Money might spike the price into the supply zone,
triggering these sell orders, then buy into this
liquidity to potentially drive the price higher.
Fair Value Gaps (FVG) are also targeted. These are
areas on the chart where price has moved rapidly.
These gaps often act as magnets for price, drawing
it back to fill the gap. Smart Money often uses
these gaps as targets. For example, if there's a
bullish fair value gap below the current price,
many traders might place buy orders in this area,
expecting price to come back and fill the gap.
Smart Money might push the
price down through this level,
triggering these buy orders and creating
liquidity. The same happens with bearish
fair value gaps above the current price.
Traders often place sell orders in these
areas. Smart Money might spike the price up
through the gap, triggering the sell orders.
That's why maybe 90% of fair value gaps
fail, but that's a topic for another video.
Round Numbers ending in zero or double zeros
are psychologically significant levels that
attract a lot of attention. These levels are
prime targets for Smart Money manipulation.
Smart Money knows that many traders place
their orders around these round numbers.
They might place buy orders just above a
round number or sell orders just below it.
The big boys often push the price to these levels
to trigger these orders, creating liquidity that
they can trade against. For instance, if
there's a round number at the $50 level,
many traders might place buy orders slightly above
it, expecting the price to rise above this level.
The big boys might push the price up to trigger
these buy orders, creating a pool of liquidity.
They can then potentially sell into this
liquidity, driving the price back down.
Understanding all these liquidity zones and how
Smart Money targets them is key. It helps you
avoid common traps. As you practice, you'll start
to see patterns. You might notice that price often
reverses after taking out a previous high or
low. Or you might see that certain levels keep
causing price to pause or reverse. And please
don't just draw liquidity zones all over your
chart. Focus on the most important ones. Too many
zones can make your analysis confusing. Also,
pay attention to how price reacts when
it reaches a liquidity zone. Does it
reverse sharply? Does it pause and then
continue? Or does it blow right through?
This can give you clues about the strength
of the move and what might happen next. You
might notice that certain types of zones
work better in certain market conditions
or for certain currency pairs or stocks. This
is where keeping a detailed trading journal
with your findings can be incredibly valuable,
allowing you to refine your strategy over time.
Now, let's talk about Liquidity Inducement.
Inducement is about creating situations that
make other traders want to trade at certain
levels. This creates available liquidity
for bigger players to use when they want to
enter or exit their positions. To understand
this better, let's look at how the market is
structured. When we look at charts, we
see highs and lows. Above these highs,
we assume there's buy-side liquidity, and below
the lows, we assume there's sell-side liquidity.
Buy-Side Liquidity is all the liquidity that
buyers will use, created mainly by stop-loss
orders of sellers and buy-stop orders of buyers.
In a bullish market, price often uses buy-side
liquidity to fuel the next upward move. To have a
big bullish move, the market needs sell orders to
generate more liquidity. Also, the buy orders from
stop-losses of sellers generate more buy orders,
which is why you often see a surge
in buying when price breaks out.
Sell-Side Liquidity is the opposite.
It's the liquidity that sellers will use,
created mainly by stop-loss orders of
buyers and sell-stop orders of sellers.
Imagine you see a double bottom on your
chart. Price hits the same low point twice,
forming a support level. Many traders might
want to buy at this support level. Now,
think about where these traders would put
their stop-losses. They'd likely put them
just below the lows. This creates a pool
of sell-side liquidity below the lows.
This is important because big players need this
liquidity. They can't just jump into the market
with huge orders. That would cause wild price
swings and could work against them. Instead,
they use liquidity inducement to their advantage.
These big players create patterns or situations
in the market that encourage other traders to
place their orders in predictable spots. This
builds up pools of liquidity that the big players
can then use to enter or exit their positions.
Now, before we continue, let us know
in the comments what topics you'd like
us to cover and please drop us a like
to help us with the YouTube algorithm.
Now, let's talk about how big players
use this liquidity. They often create
what's called a Liquidity Sweep. It's when big
players in the market try to take advantage of
areas where there's a lot of buy or sell
orders waiting. These areas are like pools
of money just sitting there ready to be used.
For instance, if there's a strong support level
with many stop-losses just below it, price
might sweep down to hit those stops before
reversing. This action sweeps the liquidity,
letting larger players fill their orders.
Knowing about liquidity sweeps can help you in two
main ways. First, you can look for where sweeps
have already happened as this might show where
big players have been active. Second, you can use
this knowledge to guess future moves by spotting
where available liquidity might be. One way to
trade these liquidity sweeps is by identifying the
inducement before a potential zone of interest.
This is where price action might encourage traders
to enter positions, creating more liquidity for a
potential move. For example, if you're looking at
a possible buy zone, you might see price dip below
a previous low before the main move up. This
dip could make sellers enter short positions
or exit longs, creating liquidity that larger
players can use to enter their long positions.
Liquidity goes hand-in-hand with the market
structure. Market structure refers to the
overall pattern of price movement. It's
about identifying trends, key levels,
and the flow of the market. Liquidity is about
where buying and selling activity clusters.
These two concepts work together to shape
market behavior. Here's how they interact:
Areas of high liquidity often become key
points in the market structure. A level with
lots of buy orders might become a strong support
level. If price keeps bouncing off this level,
it becomes part of the market structure.
Key structural levels tend to attract liquidity.
Traders often place their orders around important
structural points like trend lines or previous
highs and lows. This creates a feedback loop where
structure and liquidity reinforce each other.
Breaks in structure can drain liquidity. When
price breaks through a key structural level,
it often leads to a surge in trading activity.
This can temporarily drain liquidity from other
areas as traders rush to adjust their positions.
Liquidity flows with structure. In a strong trend,
liquidity tends to cluster in the direction
of the trend. For example, in an uptrend,
you might see more liquidity above the current
price as traders anticipate further rises.
Structure helps predict liquidity. By reading
the market structure, you can often predict where
liquidity might be. For instance, after a series
of higher lows in an uptrend, you can expect
liquidity to gather below each of these lows.
Liquidity confirms structure. Sometimes the way
price interacts with liquidity can
confirm or deny the current market
structure. If price easily breaks through
what should be a liquidity-rich level,
it might signal a change in the overall structure.
Both liquidity and market structure guide price
movement. Price often moves towards liquidity
but within the constraints of the larger market
structure, and institutional activity links
them. Big players in the market often use
their understanding of both liquidity
and structure to plan their trades.
Both liquidity and market structure change
over time. Just as market structure evolves,
so does the distribution of liquidity. What
was a key liquidity level last week might
not be as important now. So, keeping track of
both helps you stay in tune with the market.
The interplay between liquidity and structure
can help you spot truly important levels in the
market. Areas where structural levels align with
high liquidity are often the most significant.
In trading, we often talk about
Market Structure Shifts (MSS)—the
big changes in the overall trend of the market.
Inducement often plays a role in these shifts.
For example, before a major trend change,
you might see price action that looks like
it's continuing the old trend. This can trick
traders into entering positions in the direction
of the old trend, creating liquidity for the
Smart Money to use when reversing the market.
Liquidity inducement isn't something bad. If you
can spot it happening, you might find good trading
signals for entries. Look for areas where there's
a lot of liquidity. When the market is going up,
look for buy entries just below recent
lows. That's where big players often buy,
scooping up all the sell orders.
When the market is going down,
look to sell just above recent highs. That's where
big players often sell into all the buy orders.
For exits, think about where other
traders might have their stop-losses
or take-profit orders. These create pools of
liquidity. As price approaches these areas,
be ready to exit your trade. The price might
reverse once it hits these liquidity pools.
Every time the market makes a new range, mark the
high and low. If you're trading in this range,
you might enter at one end where there's
internal liquidity and exit at the other
end where there's external liquidity.
Also, you want to trade where there's low
resistance. This means there should be little
stopping for the price to move in your favor.
Start on a bigger timeframe like the daily
chart. Mark major liquidity levels. Move
down to a smaller timeframe like the 1-hour chart.
Look for price approaching your marked liquidity
levels. As price gets close to a liquidity
level, switch to an even smaller timeframe
like the 15-minute chart. Watch for signs of
a Stop Hunt—a quick spike through the level
followed by a reversal. If you see this, get ready
to enter a trade in the direction of the reversal.
Also, don't jump on every breakout. Wait for
the price to show it's really going to keep
moving in that direction. And always consult
multiple timeframes. Check larger timeframes
to see if a move fits the bigger picture
or if it might be inducement. If you see
the price quickly reject a level after breaking
it, be ready for a possible reversal. And don't
put your stops right at obvious levels.
That's where inducement often targets.
There are several tools and indicators that can
help you spot and analyze
liquidity in the markets.
Volume: This is one of the simplest and
most effective tools. High volume often
shows high liquidity. So, look for volume
spikes which can indicate liquidity events.
Market Depth Charts: These show pending
buy and sell orders at different price
levels. They can help you see where
liquidity pools might be forming.
Time and Sales (Tape Reading): This
shows real-time trades. Large trades
or clusters of trades at certain
prices can indicate liquidity.
Order Flow Indicators: These advanced tools try to
show the balance of buying and selling pressure.
Volume Profile: This shows where most trading
has happened at different price levels,
helping identify high liquidity zones.
It's best to use a mix of tools and combine
them with market structure and price action. Also,
these tools don't directly show liquidity; they
show things that often relate to liquidity. You
still need to interpret what they're telling you.
Liquidity and order flow analysis are
closely linked. Order flow analysis is
all about understanding the buying and
selling pressure in the market. This
pressure often shows up as liquidity. Order
flow analysis looks at the actual orders
coming into the market. It tries to spot where
big players are buying or selling. Basically,
order flow analysis can help you
find where liquidity is building up,
when liquidity is being used up, and potential
price levels where big players might be active.
In order flow analysis, you need to get
familiar with several concepts. First one:
Volume Clusters. Order flow analysis often
looks for clusters of orders at certain prices.
These clusters are actually liquidity pools. Next
concept is Absorption. When a price level absorbs
a lot of orders without moving much, it's often a
sign of high liquidity. Here's a familiar concept:
Imbalances. Order flow tools might show imbalances
between buy and sell orders. These imbalances can
create or drain liquidity. It's a lot to talk
about, but that's a topic for another video.
Retail traders like you and me can
level the playing field by using
liquidity analysis to compete with
institutional traders. Here's how:
Know the closest liquidity pools. Mark
the areas where lots of buy or sell
orders cluster. When price hits these spots,
it often bounces or breaks through fast. You
need to be ready for both scenarios.
Watch for traps and liquidity sweeps.
Big players set traps to trick small
traders. They often push price to key
levels. Don't fall for these fake-outs.
Use multiple timeframes. Check both
higher and lower timeframes. This gives you a
fuller picture of liquidity across different
market views. It helps you spot potential
reversals or continuations more accurately.
Track order flow. Pay attention to how orders
are coming in. Look for big buy or sell walls
in the order book. These can signal where
institutions are placing their orders.
Identify liquidity gaps. These are areas on
the chart with little trading activity. Price
often moves quickly through these zones.
Knowing where they are can help you set
better entry and exit points.
Study market structure. Look
for key swing highs and lows. These
often mark areas of high liquidity.
Focus on session overlaps. When major
trading sessions overlap, liquidity tends
to increase. This can lead to bigger price
moves. Use these times to your advantage.
Don't chase breakouts. Many traders jump
on breakouts only to get burnt. Instead,
look for pullbacks to liquidity zones after a
breakout. This is often where Smart Money enters.
Use Volume Profile. This tool shows you
where the most trading has happened at
different price levels. High volume nodes
often act as strong liquidity areas.
The Wyckoff Method is built on three key
laws that explain how markets work. These
laws help you see what's really moving
prices, not just what's on the surface.
Let's start with the Law of Supply and Demand.
This law is the engine that drives the market.
It's pretty simple: when more people want to buy
than sell, prices go up. When more want to sell
than buy, prices go down. But it's not just about
numbers of buyers and sellers. It's about how
much money they're willing to spend. It's about
the intensity of their actions. One big buyer
can have more impact than many small sellers. The
Law of Supply and Demand says that price, volume,
and trend all work together. Price shows which way
the market is going. Volume shows how strong that
move is. When price and volume agree, it confirms
the market direction. We'll talk about this later.
The Law of Cause and Effect tells us that big
moves in the market don't just happen out of
nowhere. They need preparation. It's like a
rocket launch. Before a rocket can take off,
it needs a lot of fuel. In the market, that fuel
is buying or selling pressure building up over
time. The size of the cause determines the size of
the effect. A small cause leads to a small move.
A big cause can lead to a big move. This is why
Wyckoff traders look for signs of Accumulation
(buying) or Distribution (selling). These are the
causes that can lead to big price moves. This law
helps explain why markets sometimes seem to move
for no reason. There's always a reason, but it
might have been building up for a while before you
noticed it. The Law of Cause and Effect also says
that if there's no preparation, there will be
no move. This helps you avoid false signals. If
you don't see a cause building up, you shouldn't
expect a big effect. It's all about preparation in
the market. This often shows up as trading ranges.
These are periods where price moves sideways,
bouncing between support and resistance levels. To
the untrained eye, these might look boring, but to
a Wyckoff trader, they're exciting. They're where
the cause is building up for the next big move.
Lastly, we have the Law of Effort versus Result.
This law helps us spot when something's off in
the market. It's about comparing the effort
(usually measured by volume) with the result
(the price movement). Here's how it works:
the market is always trying to move one way
or the other. These attempts can be short
or long. Either way, they represent effort,
which we see as volume. If you see a lot of
volume (meaning effort) but prices barely move
(meaning result), that's a red flag. It might
mean the current trend is running out of steam.
On the flip side, if prices move a lot on
low volume, that move might not last. This
law helps you spot divergences. A divergence
is when the effort and result don't match up.
It's like a warning sign that something might
be about to change. The Law of Effort versus
Result is like a lie detector for the market
and is especially useful for spotting trend
changes. Often before a trend changes, you'll see
a mismatch between effort and result. It's like
the market is trying hard to keep going in the
same direction, but it's running out of steam.
The Wyckoff Method breaks down
market action into four main phases:
Accumulation, Markup, Distribution, and Markdown.
Accumulation is the first phase. It happens at
market bottoms. This is when big players start
buying. They do this quietly so prices don't go
up too fast. During this phase, prices often move
sideways. It might look boring, but a lot is
happening under the surface. In accumulation,
most people are scared to buy. They think prices
might keep falling. But Smart Money sees value.
They buy when others are afraid. This phase can
last a while. It takes time for big players to buy
all they want without pushing prices up too
much. Look for these signs in accumulation:
Prices stop falling and move sideways.
Volume is low but picks up on price dips.
Price drops don't last long.
Strong buying when prices fall a bit.
The Uptrend or Markup phase comes
next. This is when prices start
to climb. The big players who bought
during the first phase are now letting
prices rise. They might even buy more,
pushing prices higher. In the uptrend,
more people start to notice the market.
They see prices going up and want to join
in. This extra buying helps push prices even
higher. Look for these signs in an uptrend:
Prices make higher highs and higher lows.
Volume often increases as prices rise.
Pullbacks are short and shallow.
Each new high is met with strong buying.
The third phase is Distribution. This happens
at market tops. Big players who bought low are
now selling. They sell slowly, just like they
bought slowly. They don't want to crash the
market by selling too fast. In distribution,
most people are excited. They think prices
will keep going up forever. But Smart Money
knows better. They are quietly selling to
these eager buyers. Distribution can also take
some time. Look for these signs in distribution:
Prices stop rising and move sideways.
Volume might increase, but price rises don't last.
More volatility with sharp ups and downs.
Each new high is quickly sold into.
The last phase is the Downtrend or Markdown.
This is when prices start to fall. The big
players have finished selling. Now there aren't
enough buyers to keep prices up. In the downtrend,
fear takes over. People who bought high start
to panic and sell. This pushes prices down even
faster. Like the uptrend, the downtrend often
moves in waves. Again, look for these signs:
In a downtrend, prices make
lower lows and lower highs.
Volume often increases as prices fall.
Bounces are short and weak.
Each new low is met with more selling.
Most of the money in a trend is made
in phase two (the uptrend) and phase four (the
downtrend). The transition phases (Accumulation
and Distribution) are often trickier to trade.
They are more about preparing for the next trend.
One key skill in using the Wyckoff Method
is identifying Changes in Market Character.
This is when the market shifts from one phase to
another. For example, the shift from accumulation
to uptrend or from distribution to downtrend.
These changes often happen gradually. The
market doesn't suddenly switch from one phase
to another. Instead, it transitions slowly.
Now, let's break down Wyckoff
Events. They're like clues
that help us figure out what's
really going on in the market.
First, we have the Preliminary Support
(PS). This is when big players start to buy,
trying to stop prices from falling more.
It's like putting a floor under the market.
You might see prices stop dropping
as fast or even bounce a little.
Next comes the Selling Climax (SC). This is a big
moment. It's when scared sellers dump their
positions. Prices often fall hard and fast,
but the big players are buying during this panic.
They're getting ready for prices to go up later.
After the selling climax, we see an Automatic
Rally (AR). Prices bounce up a bit. This happens
because the selling pressure eases off. It's like
the market taking a breath after all that selling.
Then we have the Secondary
Test (ST). Prices fall again,
but not as low as before. This is
important. It shows that the big
drop might be over. Big players are still
buying, keeping prices from falling too far.
Now we come to the Spring. This is a tricky move.
Prices dip below the low point of the secondary
test. It looks like the market might fall more,
but it's often a fake-out. Prices quickly jump
back up. This is a key sign that big players are
done buying and are ready for prices to go up.
After the spring, we see a Sign of
Strength (SOS). This is a strong move up,
often with lots of trading. It's like the
market saying, "We're ready to go up now."
And then we have the Last Point of Support
(LPS). This is one more dip before the real
uptrend starts. It's like the market
taking one last breath before climbing.
These events don't always happen in this exact
order. Markets are tricky and always changing,
but knowing these events helps you see the
big picture. If you see signs of accumulation,
like the Preliminary Support or Spring,
it might be a good time to think about
buying. If you see signs of distribution,
like a Buying Climax or Sign of Weakness,
it might be time to be careful or even think
about selling. The end of an accumulation phase,
like after a successful Spring, can be a great
time to buy. The end of a distribution phase
can be a good time to sell. But remember, you
don't need to catch the exact bottom or top.
What matters is catching the main move. And
don't get too hung up on naming each event.
What's more important is understanding what these
events mean. They are showing you the transfer of
risk in the market. Like I said before, in
accumulation, Smart Money is taking on risk,
betting prices will go up. In distribution,
they are passing that risk to others.
Volume is a key part of the Wyckoff Method.
It helps confirm what price is telling us.
The main idea is simple: volume should match
price moves. If prices go up, volume should
too. If prices fall, volume should rise. When
volume and price don't match, it can mean trouble.
Wyckoff saw the market as a fight between buyers
and sellers. Volume shows who's winning. High
volume on up moves means buyers are strong. High
volume on down moves means sellers are in control.
We talked before about Wyckoff's Law of Effort
versus Result. This law says the effect of a
price move should match the effort behind it.
The effort is shown by volume. The result is
the price change. Here's how it works: big
volume (the effort) should lead to big price
moves (the result). Small volume should lead
to small price moves. If there's a mismatch,
it can signal a change coming. High
volume with little price change often
means accumulation or distribution. Low
volume with big price moves usually isn't
sustainable. Rising prices with falling
volume can mean the uptrend is weakening.
Volume helps confirm price action. It's like a
lie detector for price moves. Price alone can
sometimes lie, but price and volume together
usually tell the truth. In accumulation,
watch for high volume on down days that don't
push prices much lower. This can mean big players
are buying, soaking up the supply. It's a sign
the downtrend might be ending. In distribution,
look for high volume on up days that don't
push prices much higher. This often means
big players are selling into strength.
It's a sign the uptrend might be ending.
During trends, volume should generally increase
in the direction of the trend. In an uptrend,
volume should be higher on
up days. In a downtrend,
volume should be higher on down days. But
it's not just about whether volume is high
or low. The spread (the body of the price bar)
matters, too. Wyckoff and later traders like
Tom Williams saw the relationship between
volume and spread. Here's what to look for:
Wide spread and high volume: usually bullish.
Wide spread and high volume (down): usually
bearish.
Narrow spread
and low volume: often means consolidation.
One common pattern is a Climax. This is a
day with very high volume and a wide price range.
It often marks the end of a move. In a downtrend,
it might be a selling climax marking
the end of the drop. In an uptrend,
it could be a buying climax signaling the end
of the rise. After a climax, watch for a Test.
This is when prices return to near the climax
level but on lower volume. If the test holds,
it can confirm the end of the old
trend and the start of a new one.
Volume can also help spot manipulation. If
you see a big price move on low volume, be
suspicious. It might be a false move designed to
trick traders. We'll talk about this later. Real,
sustainable moves usually come with solid volume.
In the Wyckoff Method, volume isn't just about
quantity; it's about quality, too. A day with
steady buying is different from a day where all
the volume comes in one big spike. Learn to read
the quality of volume, not just the quantity.
One key skill is spotting
divergences between price and volume.
If prices are making new highs but volume
is dropping, it can mean the uptrend is
weakening. If prices are making new lows but
volume is drying up, the downtrend might be
running out of steam. Volume patterns can
also hint at what's coming. For example,
expanding volume as prices move sideways
often precedes a breakout. The direction
of the breakout is uncertain, but the increase
in volume suggests something big is cooking.
In accumulation, you might see a series
of high-volume down days that fail to
push prices lower. This is often followed by
an upward surge on even higher volume. This
pattern can signal the end of this phase
and the start of markup. In distribution,
you might see a series of high-volume up days
that fail to push prices higher. This is often
followed by a downward plunge on even higher
volume. This pattern can signal the end of
distribution and the start of markdown. Volume can
also help with timing. In a strong trend, wait for
a pullback on lower volume before entering.
This often provides a good entry point with
lower risk. And one final point about this: volume
often leads price. You might see volume patterns
change before price patterns do. This can give
you an early warning of potential trend changes.
The Spring and the Upthrust are key patterns
in the Wyckoff Method. A Spring is a quick
drop below support that bounces back fast.
An Upthrust is a quick push above resistance
that fails fast. Both are fake-outs that
run stops outside support and resistance.
Smart Money concepts renamed them as liquidity
sweeps or liquidity runs. Why do they happen?
Because big players often push price past
key levels to trigger stop-losses. This
lets them buy or sell at better prices. It is
like shaking a tree to make the fruit fall.
Let's look at Springs first. In a trading range,
price might dip below support. If it jumps back
up fast, that's a Spring. It means there's strong
buying down there. It often leads to a
move up. Here's how to spot a Spring:
Price is in a range.
It breaks below support.
It doesn't stay there long.
Then it jumps back above support fast.
Upthrusts are the opposite. Price pops above
resistance but falls back quickly. It shows
there is strong selling up there. It often leads
to a move down. Here's how to spot an Upthrust:
Price is in a range.
It breaks above resistance.
It doesn't stay there long.
Then it drops back below resistance fast.
Both patterns show a fight between buyers and
sellers. In a Spring, sellers try to push price
down, but buyers win. In an Upthrust, buyers try
to push price up, but sellers win. For a Spring,
the plan is to buy when price jumps back above
support. For an Upthrust, you sell when price
drops back below resistance. But it's not always
that easy. You need to look at the bigger picture,
too. For Springs, check if the overall
trend is up. A Spring in an uptrend is
stronger than one in a downtrend. Look for
signs of accumulation before the Spring.
This makes the pattern more likely to work.
For Upthrusts, check if the overall trend is
down. An Upthrust in a downtrend is stronger
than one in an uptrend. Look for signs of
distribution before the Upthrust. This
makes the pattern more likely to work.
Volume is key in these patterns. In a Spring,
you want to see high volume on the drop and
even higher volume on the bounce. This
shows strong buying. In an Upthrust,
you want high volume on the push-up and
even higher on the drop. This shows strong
selling. Some traders do well without focusing
on volume; the price action itself can be enough.
The context matters a lot. A Spring or Upthrust
at the end of a long trend is more powerful than
one in the middle of a range. It might signal
a big trend change. One trick is to look for
smaller ranges near the edge of bigger ranges.
These often lead to good breakouts. You might see
Springs or Upthrusts in these smaller ranges
before a big move. Sometimes you won't see
a Spring or Upthrust at all. This is called a
Structural Failure. It happens when price fails
to reach one side of a range and then breaks out
the other way. This can be a strong signal, too.
Fibonacci's effectiveness depends on how you
apply them. And the key is to use them on the
correct price swings. When you're looking at
a price chart, you'll see many price swings.
You might connect two points on the chart that
seem significant to you, but another trader might
choose different points. This doesn't mean one of
you is wrong; it just highlights the subjective
nature of this tool. To apply Fib retracements
correctly, you need to start by determining the
dominant trend. Once you've identified the
trend, your next step is to find the most
obvious swing high and swing low. These are the
points you'll use to draw your Fibonacci lines.
In a bullish trend, you'll draw the Fib
retracement from the swing low to the swing
high. This makes sense because in an uptrend,
you're looking for potential support levels
where the price might pause or reverse during a
pullback. In a bearish trend, you'll draw from
the swing high to the swing low. You're looking
for potential resistance levels where the price
might stall or reverse during a bounce. When
drawing these lines, it's important to use the
wicks of the candlesticks for your swings, not
just the bodies. The clarity of your chosen swing
points is probably the most important aspect.
The clearer the swing low and high, and the
more defined the trend between these points, the
more reliable your Fib levels are likely to be.
One common mistake is trying to force Fib levels
to fit where they don't naturally apply. Remember,
not every price move will align perfectly with
Fib levels, and that's okay. The most helpful
Fib retracements are those that are obvious
on the chart without much effort to spot them.
If you find yourself squinting at the chart or
trying to convince yourself that a level fits,
it might be best to look for a clearer setup.
When applying Fibonacci retracements, think about
the market structure. In an uptrend, for example,
you might look for buying opportunities near
these Fib levels as the price pulls back. The
idea is that the trend will eventually continue
and these retracement levels offer potential
entry points at a better price. Number one rule
is that Fibonacci levels work best in trending
markets. Without a clear trend, these levels lose
their significance and impact on price movement.
When you spot a trend, look for the logical
price swings to place your Fib retracement tool.
This step is critical and often where most
traders struggle. The trick is to find the
most relevant high and low points that represent
the current market conditions. So in this uptrend,
I would draw the Fib retracement from
this swing low to this swing high. For
this downtrend, I would draw it from
this swing high to the swing low.
Once you've placed your Fib levels, you'll
notice several key retracement levels.
The most commonly used are 23.6%, 38.2%,
50%, and 61.8% levels. These lines can act
as potential support areas in an uptrend
or resistance zones in a downtrend. Many
traders focus primarily on the 61.8% retracement
level as it's often considered the Golden Ratio,
but I wouldn't discount the power of other
levels. In strong trends, price might only
retrace to the 38.2% level before continuing
in the trend direction. In weaker trends,
price might extend to the 78.6% level. Now, it's
worth noting that these Fibonacci levels don't act
as exact support or resistance points. Instead,
they help you find areas where price might react.
So think of them as zones rather than precise
lines. Remember, Fibonacci levels often become
self-fulfilling prophecies in the market.
Many traders watch these same levels. This
collective action can create real support
and resistance zones. And please note that
Fib levels struggle in sideways or ranging
conditions. If the market is consolidating,
it's often better to wait for a clear
breakout before applying a Fibonacci analysis.
Here's another common mistake: when you
apply Fibonacci retracements to very small
price moves or shorter timeframes, you might run
into some issues that can make your trading less
effective. Think about it this way: on shorter
timeframes, price movements are often more erratic
and less significant. These small, rapid price
changes don't always reflect the true market
trend or important levels. When you try to use
Fibonacci retracements on these short-term moves,
the levels you get are often too close together.
This closeness makes it hard to tell which levels
are truly important and which are just noise.
Another problem with using Fibonacci on short
timeframes is that you're more likely to see
false breakouts and price spikes. These quick,
sharp moves can trick you into thinking a
level has been broken when it hasn't really.
This can lead to poor signals like entering
a trade too early or exiting one too soon.
Think about it. Stops and take-profit
points are key for managing your trades.
But when you use Fib retracements on short
timeframes, it becomes tricky to place these
effectively. The retracement levels are
so close together that they create narrow
confluences. This means there's not much
room between levels, making it hard to set
stops that protect you from normal market noise
while still giving your trade room to breathe.
So, what's the solution? Focus on larger
timeframes. When you apply Fib levels,
you get a clearer view of the long-term trend.
This helps you apply Fibonacci retracements in
the right direction, aligning with the overall
market movement. When you use Fib retracements
on larger timeframes, you're looking at more
significant price moves. These bigger swings
are more likely to represent important market
levels. The levels drawn on these larger moves
are spaced further apart, making it easier to see
which levels might be important. And you don't
have to stick to just one timeframe. You can use
a Multi-Timeframe Approach. You might start with
a larger timeframe to find the overall trend and
major Fibonacci levels, then zoom in to a smaller
timeframe. Another benefit of placing Fibs on
larger timeframes is that it can help you avoid
overtrading. When you focus on smaller moves,
it's tempting to take many trades, thinking each
small retracement is significant. But by zooming
out and looking at the bigger picture, you can
be more selective with your trades, focusing on
the moves that are more likely to be significant.
When we talk about retracements, we are looking at
how much a price pulls back after a strong move.
These pullbacks can be shallow or deep.
Shallow Retracements happen in strong trends.
When a market is moving with conviction,
it doesn't pull back much before
continuing its journey. In these cases,
you'll often see the price only retreat
to the 23.6% or 38.2% areas. The trend
is so strong that it doesn't need much
time to refuel before zooming off again.
When you spot these shallow pullbacks, it's a sign
that the trend is healthy and likely to continue.
Deep Retracements are more common when
a trend isn't fully established yet. The
price might make several ups and downs,
testing previous highs or lows without
breaking them. Deep retracements often reach
the 61.8%, 78.6%, or even 88.6% Fib levels.
And these deeper pullbacks can be tricky.
They might make you think the trend is over,
but it's not always the case. It's more
like the market is taking a longer break,
perhaps reassessing its direction
before deciding to continue.
The key difference between shallow and
deep retracements is in what they tell
us about the strength of the trend. Shallow
retracements signal a strong, confident trend.
The market barely hesitates before pushing on.
Deep retracements suggest more uncertainty. The
trend might still continue, but it's taking its
time to gather strength. If you see a shallow
retracement in a strong trend, it might be a
good opportunity to join in the direction of
that trend. With deep retracements, you might
need to be more cautious. While they can still
lead to continuation of the trend, there's also
a higher chance the trend might be losing steam.
And if the price retraces 100% of the last move,
it might be a sign that the trend has failed.
Now, when price reaches a Fib level,
look for specific candlestick patterns.
These patterns can confirm if the
level is likely to hold or break.
It's like getting a second opinion before
making a trade. There are a lot of candlesticks,
but the most useful patterns at Fib levels are
Engulfing Patterns and Candles with Long Wicks.
Candles with a long lower wick show up at the
end of a down move. This long wick shows that
sellers tried to push price lower, but
buyers stepped in and pushed it back up.
When you see it at a Fibonacci support level, it
might mean the down move is over. If you spot a
candle with a long upper wick at a Fibonacci
resistance level, pay close attention. They
often signal the end of up moves. Buyers try
to push price higher, but sellers took control.
Engulfing patterns are also decent
signals. In a bullish engulfing pattern,
a large green candle completely covers
the previous red candle. This shows buyers
taking control from sellers. A bearish engulfing
pattern is the opposite, with a large red candle
covering the previous green one. These patterns at
Fibonacci levels can be strong reversal signals.
From my experience, using candlesticks
with Fibonacci levels works best on
longer timeframes. This is because bigger
moves tend to respect Fib levels more,
and candlestick patterns on longer timeframes
often carry more weight. Let's say price is in
an uptrend and pulls back to the 50% Fib level.
This level acts as a potential support. If you see
a candle with a long candlestick forming right at
this level, it's a decent sign that the pullback
might be over. The Fib level shows where buyers
might step in, and the candle shows that they
actually did. Here, price is in a downtrend
and bounces up to the 38.2% Fib level. This
level will act as a potential resistance in a
downtrend. If an engulfing candle forms here,
it implies the bounce might be over. So the
Fib level shows where sellers might return,
and the engulfing candle shows they're actually
taking control. These engulfing patterns at
Fib levels show a sudden, strong shift in who's
controlling the market. And an engulfing pattern
that completely swallows several previous candles
at a key Fibonacci level is hard to ignore.
Volume can add another layer of confirmation
to candlestick patterns at Fibonacci levels.
A reversal candle with high volume at a Fibonacci
support level is more convincing than one with low
volume. The high volume shows strong buying
interest right where buyers were expected to
step in. Now, one common mistake is to focus only
on exact Fibonacci levels. As I said, in reality,
these levels are more like zones than exact
lines. A candlestick pattern doesn't have to
form exactly at a Fib level to be valid. If it's
close, it's worth paying attention to. And another
key point is to look at the bigger picture.
A candlestick pattern at a Fib level is more
meaningful if it aligns with the larger trend.
For example, a bullish pattern at a Fibonacci
support level in an overall uptrend is typically
stronger than one that goes against the trend.
The Golden Zone Method is a smart way to trade
using Fibonacci levels. This method focuses on
the 50% and 61.8% area, which we call the
Golden Ratio. First, you find a clear trend
in the market. You then apply Fibonacci tools
to this trend. You've practically marked the
key levels where the price might turn around.
The strategy gets interesting when the price
starts to move against the trend. When price
starts going up, you watch closely as it moves
past the 50% Fib level. The key is to see if the
price can break and close above the 61.8% level.
In the perfect scenario, the price reaches
the zone but doesn't close above it. And
this could be a signal that the downtrend
is ready to continue. In the real market,
the price will touch and even go a bit above this
area, but this doesn't invalidate the setup. So,
it's okay if the price goes above the 61.8 line.
Once it returns below it, that's a good sign for
our strategy. This moment is when we get ready
to make a move. We are looking for signs that
the price is about to turn back down. Maybe it's a
bearish candle forming or other factors lining up.
The idea is to catch the market just as it's
deciding to follow the original trend again.
In this chart, once we see the price bounce off
the Golden Zone, we start looking for a move back
up. The next target might be the 38.2% Fibonacci
level. If the price breaks above the 38.2% level,
it could mean the previous uptrend is picking
up steam again. After the 38.2% level,
the next stop might be the 23.6% level. This
is another place where the price might pause or
bounce a little. But if the uptrend is strong,
even this level might not hold. In that case,
we could see the price go all the way back to
where the downward move started. We call this
a 100% retracement. So, these Fib levels aren't
just targets for where the price might go. They're
also useful for managing your trade. You can use
these levels to decide when to take some profits.
For instance, you might decide to sell a
part of your position when the price hits
the 38.2% level and more at a 23.6% level. If
the price never got higher than the Golden Zone,
you might put your stop-loss
just above that line. This way,
if the market suddenly changes direction
after you entered, you're protected.
Fibonacci and Moving Averages Combo is
also a viable method. When used together,
they create a synergy that can confirm your
signals. Fibonacci alone can point to possible
support or resistance levels, but they lack
the weight of confirmation. This is where
moving averages step in, adding an extra layer of
validation to your analysis. Moving averages serve
two key purposes in this partnership. First, they
help you spot trends. A simple look at the slope
of a moving average can tell you if the market is
trending up, down, or sideways. And second, moving
averages act as dynamic support and resistance. As
price moves, these lines shift, creating flexible
barriers that price often respects. And when a
Fibonacci level lines up with a moving average,
you've found a spot of Confluence. In this
example, price has been climbing steadily.
You draw your Fibonacci retracement from the
recent low to the high. The 50% retracement level
catches your eye. Now you notice the 200-period
Exponential Moving Average (EMA) is sitting
right at that same level. This is confluence
in action. The Fibonacci tool and the moving
average are both pointing to the same price
area as significant. This confluence increases
the odds of price reacting at this level. You
might see price pause, bounce, or even reverse
at this point. It's not a guarantee, but it's a
strong hint from the market. This combination is
powerful because Fib retracements can sometimes
seem arbitrary, and moving averages on their
own can lag behind price action, but together
they create a more robust analytical framework.
Probably my favorite strategy is to look for
confluences between the Fib levels and Supply
or Demand Areas. It doesn't happen often, but
when it does, it can be a sign of something
special. In this example, notice that the price is
approaching a key demand area that lines up with
a Fib level. That's a confluence perfect for
a trade. If the price bounces off that area,
it could be the start of a beautiful uptrend
that you can ride. On the flip side, if you
see the price approaching a major supply
area and that coincides with a Fib level,
it could be a sign that the buyers are
about to run out of steam. If the price
gets rejected at that level, it might be time
to start hunting for short opportunities.
Let's talk about demand areas first. These are
places where lots of people want to buy. When
the price gets near a demand area and it's also
close to a Fibonacci level, it's extra special.
This tells us that the price might start going up
soon. Think about it like this: you're looking at
an uptrend. Then the price is going down, but
then you notice it's getting close to a demand
area. The price is also near a key Fibonacci
level. You may want to monitor closely this area.
Supply areas are spots where lots of people want
to sell. When the price climbs up to a supply area
and it matches a Fibonacci level, it's another
special moment. This might mean the price is
about to turn around and start falling. Picture
this: the market is in a general downtrend. Then
the price has been climbing for a while. Then you
see it's approaching a supply area. The price is
also near an important Fibonacci level. This is
when you start thinking the upward move might be
running out of steam. These confluences are like
secret messages in the market. They don't happen
all the time, but when they do, you pay attention.
Here, price bounced off a demand area that lines
up with the Fibonacci level. This is a good time
to enter a buy position and ride the price up as
it starts a new upward move. And here price hit
a supply area that matches a Fibonacci level
and then started to fall. This was a good time
to sell as price started a new downward move.
We'll start with the Engulfing Momentum
Candlestick. This signal occurs when a large
candle fully engulfs the body of the previous two
candles. Basically, a big candle that completely
covers the smaller ones right before it.
This isn't just a regular occurrence. It's
a sign—a clear indicator of a strong move in the
market. This is what we call an engulfing pattern.
The psychology behind this pattern is all about
market sentiment and the sudden shift in the
balance between buyers and sellers.
Before an engulfing pattern occurs,
there usually is a clear trend. This trend
indicates a prevailing direction where
the majority of market participants are
either buying or selling. At some point,
the market starts showing signs of exhaustion.
For a bullish engulfing momentum bar, this might
be at a support area or at a demand zone where
buyers believe the price is attractive enough
to start buying in large quantities. For a
bearish engulfing one, this could be at a
resistance or at a supply zone where sellers feel
the price has peaked and it's a good time to sell.
The engulfing momentum candle represents a strong
shift in sentiment. If it's bullish, buyers have
overwhelmed the sellers, pushing the price up and
covering the range of the previous two candles.
This suggests that the demand has suddenly
outstripped the supply. In a bearish pattern,
sellers have come in strong, indicating an excess
of supply over demand. The immediate effect of an
engulfing momentum bar is to signal a potential
reversal. It shows a decisive change in market
dynamics. For bullish signals, it could mean the
end of a downtrend phase with prices likely to
rise. For bearish ones, it could suggest the end
of an uptrend wave with prices expected to fall.
The Long-Wick Engulfing Candlestick
is my favorite price action strategy.
This candlestick not only indicates a strong
rejection of prices but also signals a potential
momentum shift in the market direction. This
candle typically shows a large body with a long
wick that extends far beyond the body's edges.
The engulfing part means that the body of this
candle is larger than the body of the previous
candle, completely overshadowing or engulfing it.
This visual on your chart is your first
clue about a significant shift in market
sentiment. The long wick represents a
point where supply surpasses demand,
pushing the price back down (or vice versa,
depending on the direction of the wick).
Let's say the long wick is at the top of the
candle. This suggests that as the price went up,
it hit a level where sellers were waiting to
take profits or considered the price too high,
outweighing buyers. This results in the
price being pushed back down sharply,
leaving behind a long upper wick. The rejection
indicated by the long wick is significant because
it shows that a certain price level could not
be sustained. Buyers tried to push the price up,
but the overwhelming number of sellers
at that level rejected this move. If the
candle also engulfed the previous candle, it
shows increasing selling momentum despite any
buying pressure that might have been present
initially. Sellers took control and managed
to push the closing price below the open one of
the previous candle, indicating strong supply.
If the wick is at the bottom, it means sellers
drove the price down. But buyers stepped in,
finding the lower price attractive, thus
pushing the price back up, showing rejection
of lower prices. If the body of the candlestick
also engulfs the previous candle, it suggests
increasing buying momentum. Buyers were not only
able to overcome the selling pressure indicated by
the long upper wick, but were also strong enough
to close the candle higher than the previous
candle's body, indicating strong demand. This
is a powerful price action signal. It provides
a clear signal that the market sentiment might
be changing direction. Look for these patterns
at major resistance or support levels because they
can signal the end of a trend or the reversal of a
price direction. A bullish long-wick engulfing
candle at a key support level might suggest a
potential upward reversal, tempting buyers
to enter the market expecting future gains.
When you see multiple rejection wicks
and candles are changing their color,
you are witnessing a strong signal. In this
example, observe these two consecutive candles
at a similar price level where the first is
bullish with a long upper wick followed by
a bearish one with a similar long upper wick.
This formation can tell you a lot about what's
happening in the market. Starting with supply
and demand, the first candle (the bullish one
with a long upper wick) indicates that
buyers initially pushed prices higher.
The long upper wick shows that as the price
reached higher levels, an ample supply emerged,
overpowering the buyers and pushing the price
down from its peak before the candle closed. At
these higher price levels, sellers are more
than willing to step in and take control.
Now when the next candle opens, it starts where
the first one left off but turns bearish with
a long upper wick as well. This second candle
confirms the presence of strong selling interest
at these levels. The fact that this candle is
bearish and mirrors the wick of the previous
bullish candle intensifies the signal. The
sellers are not just reacting spontaneously.
They are firmly establishing their ground, showing
that they are prepared to sell at these prices,
thus increasing the supply. The repeated rejection
at this price level signifies that the supply has
surpassed the demand, possibly leading to a trend
reversal or at least a significant pullback. From
a psychological perspective, this signal plays
a vital role. Consider the first bullish candle.
Traders who bought during or just before
the high might have expected the momentum
to continue. The subsequent price dip could
lead to a change in sentiment from optimism
to concern or even fear. This emotional shift
is crucial as it might prompt those buyers to
sell quickly to cut losses when they see prices
failing to go higher, which adds to the selling
pressure. If this pattern appears at a known
resistance level, the message it sends is even
stronger. Traders often place their stops
around these levels, and the activation of
these stops can accelerate the price movement
downward as the bearish sentiment takes hold.
The Over and Under Pattern is one of the
most effective price action strategies.
This pattern essentially signals a critical
shift in the market dynamics, hinting at a
potential weakening or reversal of a trend. So in
any trading market, prices are driven by supply
and demand. These forces are represented by
the actions of buyers and sellers who push
prices higher or lower. A trend, whether up or
down, continues as long as there is an imbalance
favoring either buyers or sellers. For example, in
an uptrend, buyers prevail, consistently willing
to buy at higher prices, thus creating a
sequence of higher highs and higher lows.
The Over and Under pattern comes into play
when there is a noticeable shift in this trend
structure. When the price suddenly drops below a
previous major low and then makes a lower high,
it suggests a break in this structure. This is the
first clue that the prevailing buying pressure is
weakening. The scenario is similar but reversed in
a downtrend. When prices push above the previous
low but then form a higher high, it indicates
that the selling pressure is diminishing.
Let's consider the psychological aspects driving
this pattern. In an uptrend, as the price drops
to form what initially appears as a normal
pullback, buyers are typically prepared to
jump in, anticipating another push to higher
highs. However, as the price fails to reach
a new high and instead falls below the previous
low, it disrupts the expectations formed by the
market participants. This unexpected change often
leads to uncertainty and a shift in sentiment,
causing some of the buyers to step back and
reassess their positions while potential sellers
might see an opportunity to enter the market. The
pivotal moment in the Over and Under pattern is
when the price breaches a significant level.
This action is a powerful signal because it
challenges the established market structure.
It's not just a simple breach; it's a signal
that the previous consensus is no longer valid.
This can lead to rapid shifts in supply and
demand. Buyers who were previously supporting
the price by buying at dips might pull back,
and sellers may start to dominate, pushing the
price down further in what was an uptrend. From
a supply and demand perspective, this pattern
reflects a shift in the balance. The initial
move past the previous high increases the demand
suddenly. But this failure to continue in the same
direction indicates exhaustion and the possible
reversal of roles between buyers and sellers.
Another important strategy is the Weak Break of
Structure. This signal is subtle but powerful.
Now, a weak break of structure occurs when the
price marginally surpasses a previous high in
an uptrend (or a low in a downtrend) but fails to
sustain this momentum and quickly retraces. This
scenario often indicates that the market does
not have sufficient conviction to support the
new highs or lows, leading to what we call
a weak break of structure. In any market,
price movements are fundamentally driven by the
imbalance between supply and demand. A weak break
of structure typically occurs at points where
this balance is delicate and easily disrupted.
Consider a scenario where a price level
has historically acted as resistance. As
prices approach this level, sellers begin
to dominate the market, believing that the
level will hold and prices will drop again.
Buyers, on the other hand, push the price up,
testing the resistance. If the buying pressure
is strong enough, it might initially break the
resistance level. However, if this break is
weak—meaning it only goes slightly above the
resistance level and quickly retraces—it suggests
that the buying pressure was not truly powerful
enough to shift the market sentiment decisively.
The sellers still have substantial influence,
and the demand was not sufficient to maintain the
higher prices. If the price cannot sustain itself
above the previous resistance, it indicates that
demand is weakening. The price often falls back to
lower levels as sellers regain control and buyers
withdraw, waiting for more favorable conditions.
One instance of a weak break of structure may
not be meaningful, but consecutive weak breaks
of structure can form a pattern that highlights
a significant loss of momentum. For instance,
if the market attempts to break a low multiple
times, but each time only succeeds marginally
before retracing, it suggests a consistent
lack of supply at lower price levels.
This scenario often precedes a
stronger move in the opposite
direction. Consecutive weak breaks will allow
you to anticipate potential market turns.
The next strategy involves finding instances of
Momentum Gain and Momentum Loss. Momentum refers
to the speed or strength of price movements.
And this can be observed through the lens of
consecutive candles increasing or decreasing
in size from a supply and demand perspective.
When you see consecutive candles getting
larger and larger, this usually signals a
Momentum Gain. Imagine a scenario where each
candle represents a day of trading. If each
day the price moves higher than the previous
day and the size of the candle gets bigger,
it indicates strong buying pressure; more buyers
are entering the market, willing to buy at even
higher prices. This buying pressure pushes
the price up, creating larger bullish candles.
This can often be seen in an uptrend
where each candle is getting larger
and moving a greater distance per candle,
showing a gain in bullish momentum. The
increasing size of the candles indicates
that buyers are becoming more aggressive.
Momentum Loss can be found when the candles
start to decrease in size. This suggests that
the movement in price is losing strength. If
you observe that after a series of large bullish
candles, the candles begin to shrink in size,
it could be a warning sign. Shrinking candles
suggest that although the trend is still
upward, the buyers are not as aggressive as
before. The distance traveled per candle gets
shorter, signaling that the buyers are losing
control and the bullish momentum is weakening.
This shift could be due to various reasons,
such as traders taking profits after a
price surge or simply the market running
out of steam. When buyers begin to pull back, the
supply may start to match or exceed the demand,
leading to smaller price movements. Momentum
loss is not only about shrinking candles,
but also about where these candles appear. If
this pattern occurs after a prolonged uptrend
at a key resistance level, it could be a strong
indicator that the trend might reverse or at least
stall. This is because at resistance levels, the
price has historically struggled to move higher,
and with weakening momentum, the likelihood
of breaking through these levels decreases.
The plan here is to ride the wave of increasing
buyer enthusiasm during momentum
gain phases. On the other hand,
noticing a momentum loss with decreasing candle
sizes could signal a time to be cautious.
Now, if you liked what you saw, we have
plenty more interesting guides for you.