TICK index is a very short-term (intraday)
indicator that measures the bullish or bearish
activity in New York Stock Exchange (NYSE)
stocks throughout the day.
The TICK is an indicator that gives traders
an intraday look at the “internal” strength
or weakness of the market— that is, the
strength or weakness beyond whether the overall
market is up on a point or percentage basis.
By comparing the number of stocks advancing
to stocks declining, the indicator reflects
the market’s up or down momentum at a given
moment.
So TICK measures the difference between the
number of New York Stock Exchange (NYSE) stocks
trading on an uptick (meaning, last price
higher than the previous price) and the number
of stocks trading on a downtick (last price
lower than the previous price).
For example, if at a given moment 5,200 stocks
were trading up from their previous prices
and 4,800 were trading down from their previous
prices, the TICK reading would be +400 (5,200-4,800).
Positive, rising TICK readings are a bullish
signal; the opposite is true for a negative,
declining TICK.
(However, very high or low TICK readings often
indicate temporary market exhaustion.)
A declining TICK in a rising market indicates
stocks are beginning to trade off their highs,
signifying the uptrend may reverse, at least
temporarily.
Likewise, a rising TICK in a declining market
indicates stocks are starting to trade off
their lows, and a reversal of the downtrend
is possible.
Let's step back and look at the big picture.
Why is TICK important?
How is this relevant to you as a day trader
or scalper and why you need to pay attention
to TICK.
Well, because the TICK index is recording
the buying and selling action of an entire
index.
This tells us how many stocks are selling
"at or below" asking price and how many stocks
are being bought "at or above asking price".
It tells you how aggressive are buyers overall
"at one moment in time".
If all major markets suddenly have aggressive
sellers, then you would want to know this
and maybe not take a position until you found
out why.
If all the markets suddenly have aggressive
buyers, then perhaps a highly liquid ETF like
$SPY will be in play for a quick scalping
play.
There's momentum created by this sudden buyers'
market.
So, how to read TICK index
TICK offers traders a short-term perspective
of overall market SENTIMENT.
This is extremely valuable for scalping trades.
The ratio of stocks on an up-tick versus the
number of stocks on a down-tick present a
short-term actionable point.
TICK Index value between +200 and -300 indicate
a neutral market sentiment.
Bullish is when values become higher than
+200 and bearish when it is lower -300.
Very bullish is when its value is higher than
+500 and very bearish when it is lower than
-500.
And TICK values higher than +1000 or lower
than -1000 indicate extreme conditions, and
a reversal or correction of the market is
likely.
When confirmed with other tools, TICK readings
can be used to identify intraday turning points.
Let’s look at a few strategies that combine
TICK index with price patterns and important
market levels.
First strategy.
TICK Range Trading
TICK overbought and oversold levels can vary
depending on conditions.
A reading above +500 indicates an overbought
condition and a reading below –500 indicates
an oversold market.
Readings above +1000 or below –1000 are
extreme conditions and we will try to concentrate
our attention on these levels.
A simple trading approach is to place trades
when the TICK signals an overbought or oversold
market as price is testing the support or
resistance levels of a trading range.
Here we have a one minute chart with a resistance
zone (established by these swing highs).
As the market traded into this resistance
zone, the TICK moved above +1000, signaling
an overbought market.
Price then rejected that area, and the TICK
indicator turned down.
A short sale would have been placed when price
dropped back below the resistance level.
A protective stop would be placed just above
the high of rejection, which is the top of
this swing move.
Here’s an important point: you must scalp
these overbought or oversold readings only
if the price is at an important key level
in the market.
You don’t trade simply because the TICK
is at 1000 or -1000.
Use it in conjunction with price.
Here are several valid TICK trades, around
support/resistance levels.
The second strategy involves TICK divergences
TICK divergence setups are probably the most
popular use of the TICK indicator.
Divergences between price and the TICK occur
when price makes a higher high (or lower low)
and the TICK makes a lower high (or higher
low).
These signals are often followed by short
term reversals or corrections.
In this example, after a swing to the upside,
the price again retested its intraday high
at the upper end of the resistance zone, and
the TICK exceeded +1000.
However, this TICK overbought high was lower
than the previous TICK overbought high.
This divergence between price and the TICK
meant the market was rallying with fewer stocks
making upticks — a sign of internal weakness
— and set up another short sale opportunity
when price dropped back below the lower resistance
level.
In the case of a long TICK divergence signal,
price makes a new low but the TICK indicator
makes a higher low.
In this example, price fell to a new low but
the corresponding TICK low was higher than
its previous intraday low.
A long trade would have been entered when
price traded back above the first low just,
with a stop placed below the most recent low.
As always, keep an eye on ley levels.
If a divergence occurs at an important area,
it has a better chance of completion.
Also, wait for a trendline breakout to increase
our chances of a successful trade.
This way, you will also filter some bad divergences
signals.
Here are some valid TICK divergence trades.
The third strategy involves a zero line crossing
of TICK index
In addition to its usefulness in trading ranges,
the TICK can also set up trades in trending
markets.
In a strong uptrend, any countertrend movement
is usually marked by the TICK fluctuating
between –100 and +100.
In these situations,–100 becomes the oversold
level.
More often than not, the TICK tests the zero
line.
These tests offer opportunities to enter in
the direction of the prevailing trend.
In this example, SPY was in an uptrend and
the TICK reached an overbought level above
+500, which indicates a strong, uptrending
market.
In such a situation, the goal is to buy on
a pullback.
As we talked in previous strategies about
key levels, let’s use a FIB retracement
to confirm the zero line crossover.
As the TICK dropped below zero, price also
reached the 50 percent Fibonacci retracement
line.
The combination of the TICK oversold signal
and the 50 percent retracement offered a higher
probability for an up move.
You can also use this technique with pivot
points.
In this example, we have a downtrend, the
TICK moved toward the 0 level and the price
stopped at this pivot line.
You can also add a moving average, to confirm
better the short term trend.
Here are other examples of TICK zero line
crossover trades, at the 50% Fib level.
The TICK Index offers traders the advantage
of observing market sentiment for a short
period of time.
This gives a small window into an opportunity
for a trade.
It also gives an opportunity to NOT take a
trade.
Patience is required when trading this setup.
The TICK should be given time to bottom out
in an uptrend or top out in a downtrend; and
don’t expect a sudden price reversal when
the TICK indicator simply hits the zero line.
Other technical factors should be consulted
before entering any trades, such as employing
a price pattern, as presented in the previous
examples.
So the TICK indicator should be used to set
up or confirm a trade, not as a stand-alone
tool.
By utilizing the TICK in conjunction with
price patterns, technical indicators, and
in the context of the overall trend and market
environment, you can make better buy and sell
decisions.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.