You’ve probably heard the word “pullback”
or “retracement” or “correction” quite
frequently if you’re interested in trading
the financial markets.
So, what is a pullback?
A pullback in a market is a pretty easy concept
to define and understand.
It’s a period when price retraces back on
a recent move, either up or down.
It’s basically a reversal of a recent price
move.
Why are pullbacks important?
For a number of reasons: they are opportunities
to enter the market at a “better price”,
they allow for optimal stop loss placement,
improved risk reward and more.
A pullback entry is more conservative than
a “market entry” for example and is considered
a “safer” entry type.
Ultimately, the goal of a trader is obtain
the best entry price and manage risk as good
as possible whilst also increasing returns
and the pullback entry is a tool that allows
you to do all three of these things.
So here is why pullback trading is very important:
First, when identified correctly, will offer
you higher probability entries
The very nature of a pullback means that price
is likely to continue moving in the direction
of the initial move when the retrace ends.
Hence, if you see a strong price action signal
at a level following a retracement, it’s
a high-probability entry because all signs
are pointing to price bouncing from that point.
Now, it doesn’t always happen, but waiting
for a retrace to a level with a signal, is
the highest-probability way you can trade.
Markets rotate back to the “mean” or “average”
price over and over; this is clear by looking
at any price chart.
So, when you see this retrace happen, start
looking for an entry point there because it’s
a much higher-probability entry point than
simply entering “at market” like most
traders do.
Second, it offers better risk rewards.
Pullback entries theoretically allow you to
place a “smaller” stop losses on a trade
because you’re entering closer to a key
level.
So, if you choose to do so, you can place
a stop much closer.
For example: a 100 pips stop and 200 pips
target can easily become a 50 pip stop and
250 pip target on a retrace entry.
Of course: you don’t need to place a smaller
stop loss, it’s optional, but the option
is there on a pullback entry if you want it.
And, at the same time, a pullback entry allows
more flexibility with your stop loss placement.
Of course, there are some negative aspects
in what concerns waiting for a pullback.
You will have less trades in general.
A lot of the time, markets simply don’t
retrace enough to trigger the more conservative
entry that comes with a pull back.
Instead, they may just keep going with minimal
retracements.
This means you will have less chances to trade
as compared to someone who isn’t primarily
waiting for pullbacks.
Also, you will have more missed trades.
Some potential good trades will “get away”
when waiting for a retracement that doesn’t
happen, for example.
This can test your nerves and will annoy you
sometimes.
But, missing out on trades is not the worst
thing in the world and it’s better to miss
out on some trades than to over-trade.
Now that you now the pros and cons of a pullback
approach, let’s take a look at some of the
different pullback entry type, so that you
can get a clear look at what they might look
like.
1.
Pullback entry without any price action signal
In this chart, you can see price pulled back
to the key horizontal level shown in the chart.
There was no obvious price action signal here
but we can see price quickly sold-off from
that level after just barely pushing above
it.
This provided a very high potential risk reward
scenario if you decided to enter on a “blind
entry” at that level with a tight stop loss.
That’s the most aggressive entry.
As soon as the price hits an important level,
you sell or buy at market immediately.
You do not wait to confirm your buy or sell
signals with reversal candlesticks or signals
from indicator.
You just immediately buy or sell at market.
If price hits the key level and bounces back,
you make money, if not, you lose.
It’s that simple.
2.
Pullback to key level with price action confirmation
A more conservative trading strategy is to
wait for price to retrace back up or down
to an existing key level on the daily chart
time frame, then watch for an obvious price
action signal to form there.
This is one of the highest-probability ways
to trade.
A way to look for confirmation when using
pullbacks would be to look at Japanese candlestick
formations because these tend to be reliable
signals of a reversal in price action.
In particular, on this chart an engulfing
pattern forming right on key level could be
a sign that price is ready to turn.
For additional confirmation, you can apply
technical indicators such as stochastic or
MACD to determine if it’s a good time to
enter a trade or not.
Take note though that using too many technical
indicators doesn’t necessarily improve their
reliability.
In fact, too much indicators might lead to
an extremely cautious trading strategy that
misses out on several valid trade signals.
3.
Pullback to a moving average
Markets have a tendency to retrace to the
mean or average price, which you can see by
putting a moving average on your charts.
Moving averages are useful for identifying
and confirming support and resistance levels.
Most S/R levels, like market highs and lows,
pivot points, round numbers etc.
Are static levels.
Moving averages offer dynamic zones of support
and resistance because are changing depending
on recent price action.
On this daily chart we added a 20 EMA, a short-term
moving average to identify the trend.
A simple EMA could be considered as a dynamic
area of support or resistance but also the
area between two exponential moving averages
could also be considered as a dynamic area
of support or resistance.
When price retraces back to this area you
should watch closely for price action signals
forming there to get a high-probability entry
and get in on a trending market.
Using candlestick patterns with a moving average
helps to clarify the trend.
It also helps you to evaluate the pullback
pattern better.
Hence, combining candlestick patterns with
a moving average is a simple yet effective
approach for trading pullbacks.
This is EUR/JPY on the daily chart.
We have a pin bar right on the 20-period EMA,
a high probability pullback trade.
So, start paying attention to price action
patterns around moving averages.
4.
Pullbacks to the 50% - 61.8% Fibonacci area
Price has a tendency to retrace approximately
50% of any major move and often times even
short-term moves.
This is a well-documented phenomenon and if
you look at any chart you can see it happens,
a lot.
Hence, you can watch for pull backs to these
50% areas as they will very often be high
probability levels for price to move beyond,
and as a result, price moves back in the direction
of the initial move from that 50% level.
It doesn’t happen every time of course,
but it happens often enough to make it a critical
tool in your pullback trading tool box.
I prefer to pay an extra attention to the
50%-61.8% fib area of a move, and look to
trade entries.
This chart shows the 4hour activity on the
pound dollar.
This is the first strong upswing after a downwards
move.
We drew the 50% and 61.8% retracement levels
of the bullish thrust.
The area between them is the retracement zone.
This sharp retracement down found support
at the retracement zone.
The candlesticks that followed confirmed the
bullish pressure.
As you can see we had 2 pullbacks, unable
to break below the 50% and 61.8% retracement
area.
You can use trend line breakouts for your
pullback entry, or search for obvious candlestick
patterns, or even entries based on oscillators
or indicators.
Trading pullbacks in a trending market is
one of the most efficient trading strategies
out there.
The beauty of a pullback trading system is
that you enter the market or place your first
trade only after confirming which way the
market is going.
Doing this is going to help you eliminate
entering the market with a false signal.
Since most markets remain within a range bound
or consolidation phase most of the time, and
the market trends only about 20 to 30 percent
of the time, finding an established trend
to trade pullbacks can be a challenging task.
As a trader when you are trying to apply a
pullback strategy, you need to act like a
sniper.
You need to wait and have discipline and patience
before pulling the trigger.
Also, very important, you need to make sure
that you have identified the correct turning
point, where the pullback move is likely to
end.
It’s your job to find a way to generate
a high probability pullback signal where the
price is likely to resume the prevailing trend.
If you can successfully do this, you can buy
low during an uptrend and sell high during
a downtrend, and this can only bring profits
in the long run.
If you learned something new and found value,
don’t forget to subscribe, click the bell
icon so you’ll be notified each time we
upload and leave us a like to show your support.
Until next time.