I read many many trading books over the
past 10 years and the problem is that a
lot of them kind of say the same thing
that's a head and shoulders this is the
macd buy at support sell at resistance I
quickly came to the conclusion that good
game-changing trading books are rare so
today I want to recommend you some books
that will actually upgrade your trading
most of them contain an aha moment a
concept or an idea that will definitely
help you become a better Trader you know
the drill like subscribe and stick
around for the full
video after I learned the basics of
technical analysis I often felt nervous
when entering a trade mostly because I
was unsure about the price action and
whether the trade really had the power
to continue the trend well this book
explains the basics of candlesticks
along with the influence of volume to
provide clues on where the market may be
headed next understanding volume is the
missing yet critical piece to really
read the charts it will help you to
understand Market sentiment around the
price action by looking at changes in
volume it explains the concept of volume
never being able to mislead why and how
markets are moved by the smart money the
methods presented in the book can be
used as a strategy or as an additional
reference for your
strategies this is a must read for
anyone who takes trading
seriously trading is about controlling
emotions this book talks about the
emotional mistakes people make this is
one of the most practical trading
psychology books out there its greatest
strength is the balance it strikes
between Theory real life examples and
concrete action plans the author talks
about the problems Traders tend to run
into and gives very specific plans for
how to deal with them you will learn to
dig through your psychological issues
layer by layer and find what is holding
you back in your trading what is
different about this book is the fact
that you'll actually find steps to
resolve mental barriers hindering you
from performing at your Peak if you are
willing to put in some work it will make
a big difference in your trading read
this book get a pen and start taking
notes being able to know the experiences
of professional Traders is a powerful
knowledge this book shows you that there
are many ways to succeed in the
financial Market the author interviews
professional traders who succeeded using
technical analysis is fundamental
analysis mechanical trading systems and
discretionary trading you will be
surprised to read how different the top
Trader strategies can be the facts
relate to the 70s and 80s but the
principles used as as relevant today as
they were back then the book contains
many tips and gems of wisdom from some
of the best traders to apply to your own
trading every single interview has
something just full it doesn't contain
exact strategies technical analysis or
charts you will not learn how to trade
but you will just understand that there
is no Holy Grail in trading and that
there is no one exact way how to trade
instead you get the mindsets of these
great Traders and many great ideas for
being successful in the
market market manipulation wof and
volume if you read this book you will
learn a lot about price action and the
deception that a market can do to you
when
trading this book explains why price
moves occur and how to recognize the
underlying forces at work in the
financial Market an excellent read if
you want to go deeper into the volume
trading and find more about the
relationship between price spread and
volume you you'll learn the basics of
volume spread analysis and you'll
discover the causes of price movements
namely the imbalance of supply and
demand you'll also learn the main signs
that will allow you to identify the
participation of the large players on
the chart which will allow you to make
sensible analysis about where the price
is most likely to go you will have many
aha moments and by using these
techniques you will have an advantage
over the average r
Trader the wov method is not a
mechanical rule-based trading
methodology but rather a discretionary
method relying on you being able to do a
good job in analyzing the market well
this book is one of the best ways to
learn the big picture to learn the
foundation of successful wov trading the
book begins with supply and demand
Concepts and Order flow each of those
components are then examined at a deeper
level and you'll get a clear
understanding of price and volume
Dynamics you'll also understand what is
really behind accumulation and
distribution and how it actually works
the book outlines each phase in the
accumulation or distribution process and
then gives detailed explanation of why
each step occurs and what to look out
for in different scenarios
you learn the logic of the market cycles
and usual patterns that appear
repeatedly during accumulation and
distribution if you want to truly
understand Market structure and how to
profit from it this book will speed up
your learning curve without a
doubt what makes you a better Trader is
not just learning technical analysis and
calculating when to get in and when to
get out it's about learning from other
people's psychology this book will help
you with various psychological aspects
of trading the approach of sharing
stories of other Traders helps with
connecting with this book on a personal
level it contains lots of stories from
different Traders and it's very easy to
relate to them even as a beginner and it
doesn't just help you see and understand
the problems you have with trading it
also gives you actionable ideas to
correct those mistakes as well the
advice stories and perspectives in this
book will keep you focused motivated and
most importantly will help you find the
path to self-mastery You'll discover
Insight on keeping your emotions in
check self-discipline and risk
management it covers real problems faced
by Traders in their own words like
focusing on a few good setups handling a
series of loss
Revenge trading setting goals and even
diet and sleep very useful if you know
you have the technical ability to trade
but you are still struggling to actually
apply your
ideas this book takes it down to the nyr
of technical analysis price action
without oscillators only with the 20 EMA
as an indicator
when I read it the first time I came
from a background of indicator based
trading I couldn't imagine trading
without magd and stochastic on my charts
this book is one of the few materials
I've read that actually helped me and
will probably change your approach to
trading it will help you understand the
psychology behind the market and the
rationale behind its moves this is one
of the few books that will actually
teach you how to trade by understanding
the actions of the market participants
you'll learn how to see through price
action to recognize Market traps and to
capitalize on high quality opportunities
that occur daily you'll understand how
indicators reveal what happened whereas
raing price action gives an immediate
heads up as to what's really going on
and the psychology behind it this is not
a trading strategy book rather a book
trying to teach you the language that
the market speaks you can apply the
concepts for scalping day trading and
even swing trading if you are serious
about trading and want to learn pure
price action you need to read this
book most people want to learn a trading
strategy but they forget a very
important part their mindset if your
mindset is not right whatever trading
system you use you're going to lose
money and this book can fix this there
are very few trading books that are must
reads and this is one of them a must
read for any Trader as I said this book
covers one of the most important skills
in trading your mindset the author
teaches you how to read the market from
an objective perspective and how
conflicting beliefs can get in the way
of this reading it will change your
perspective of trading this is not how
to trade book for beginners it assumes
you already know how to read charts and
conduct technical
analysis instead it focuses on trading
psychology and talks about your
emotional defense mechanisms and what
attitude is required to avoid the
pitfalls that cause 90% of traders to
fail full with psychological and
behavioral principles this book will
help you get to the bottom of your trade
issues and figure out out how to
decondition yourself from making errors
reading this book forces you to take a
step back and analyze yourself to accept
that your trading results are a result
of your mental framework you learn to
overcome the fear of missing out losing
money being wrong and if you implement
it right you will gain consistency in
your
trading this is a good book for
intermediate Traders very concise and to
the point this book is not so much a
technical analysis book although it does
cover some topics but instead covers
other aspects like calculating target
entry and exit points and the importance
of planning this book basically shows
you when to trade and when not to the
author is using just a few key
indicators that he uses every day in his
trading and Conant trates on intraday
trading and how to use many different
time frames in order to form an opinion
on what the market will be doing in the
short term allowing you to choose good
entry and exit points for your trades it
also has a decent part on risk
management and also some practical
trading strategies the book is very easy
to read and explains very well the
author's trading approach it helps you
as a retail Trader to realize where you
are in relation to the market and it
stresses the importance of a
professional approach to retail
trading after you'll read this book
you'll realize that trading successfully
is more than technical analysis this
book addresses the most important issue
and the final piece of becoming a
successful Trader mastering emotions and
understanding how your instincts and
mind are working against you this book
is aimed at experienced traders who
achieve mediocre results the author
assumes that the poor trading results
happen in spite of the fact that most
Traders are intelligent and understand
the basics of fundamental and technical
analysis the author States the main
reason for trading failure is the
natural human tendency to add to losing
positions and to close winning positions
too early to in the profits many Traders
have the knowledge but fail to execute
it despite winning enough trades the
most important Edge that a Trader can
have is emotional stability courage and
perseverance every Trader takes losses
but only a few know how to protect their
account remain detached from the results
and take a day off when anger or anxiety
are about to interfere with their
strategy this book covers the emotional
war that unfolds inside your mind when
contemplating an entry and when you are
in a tradeit the author shows you the
reality and what you believe to be
rational thinking drift apart once money
are involved and how it threatens your
performance I had many aha moments
reading this book like assuming you're
wrong on every tradeit until the market
proves you right a must read to improve
your mindset
now quite a few books in this video
cover the psychological aspect of
trading if you want to learn how to
trade without the emotions and without
stress make sure you watch this video
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time