Why it is so hard to make consistent money
day trading or scalping?
Because you are probably have the wrong indicators,
and you’re using them in a wrong way.
I’m fixing this problem today and you’ll
discover a consistent way to trade and read
the market, just by using VWAP indicator and
Heikin Ashi candles.
Before we start, if you want to show your
support, please drop a like to help us with
Youtube algorithm and turn on the bell, so
you don’t miss when new videos are released.
Professionals rely on two important factors
when making trading decisions— Price and
Volume.
These two elements tell you everything you
need to know about price and where it may
be headed.
So it makes sense that you must develop a
POWERFUL strategy that is based on price and
volume.
With this scalping strategy, I keep my charts
relatively clean, with a minimal number of
indicators displayed.
Here is what I have on my charts:
1.
Price action in the form of Heikin Ashi candlesticks
2.
Volume Weighted Average Price (VWAP) indicator
3.
Optional, one momentum oscillator, to find
periods of expansion or contraction and to
identify divergences
Heikin Ashi
Heikin Ashi are visually appealing because
you can easily filter the price of the present
move of the overall trend and provides a clearer
visual representation of the trend.
Heikin Ashi candlesticks are different from
normal candlesticks.
These price bars are average bars and it does
not reflect exact open, highs, lows and closes
for that period like a normal candlestick.
The various bullish or bearish reversal patterns
consisting of 1-3 candlesticks are not found
here.
There are no hammers or engulfing candles
Rather, these candlesticks can be used to
identify potential reversal points and, more
important, trending periods.
These charts are filtered from noise, thus
making the short-term trend easier to observe.
So these charts will help you to view trends
and identify potential reversals.
The Heikin Ashi candles are totally different
in appearance when a strong trending move
is underway relative to pullbacks.
Upward trending moves typically have long
upward candles with very little or no lower
shadows.
When a strong uptrend is underway, and the
buying is aggressive, the lower shadows will
typically disappear.
The same concepts apply to downtrends, except
strong down trending moves will be composed
of Heikin Ashi price bars with little or no
upper shadows.
The bars will also typically be long and moving
lower.
During pullbacks or weak trending moves, you’ll
see lots of bars with lower and upper shadows.
This doesn’t necessarily indicate a reversal,
but it does mean the trend is in a corrective
phase or slowing.
So typically during strong trending moves
you’ll see strong up bars with no lower
shadows, and strong down bars with no upper
shadows for a downtrend.
And just because one up candle, or a couple
of candles with upper shadows, appear during
a downtrend doesn’t mean the trend is reversing
– it may just be pausing.
The same is true for uptrends.
VWAP
Volume Weighted Average Price, or VWAP, is
probably the most important technical indicator
for day traders and scalpers.
Essentially, VWAP is a moving average that
takes into account the volume of the shares
being traded at any price.
Other moving averages are calculated based
only on the price of the stock on the chart,
but VWAP also considers the number of shares
in that stock, that are being traded on every
price.
Basically, VWAP is an indicator of who is
in control of the price action - the buyers
or the sellers.
When a stock is traded above the VWAP, it
means that the buyers are in overall control
of the price and there is a buying demand
on the stock.
When a stock price breaks below the VWAP,
sellers are gaining control over the price
action.
VWAP is often used to measure the trading
performance of institutional traders.
Professional traders who work for investment
banks or hedge funds and need to trade large
numbers of shares each day cannot enter or
exit the market by just one single order.
The market is not liquid enough.
Therefore, they need to process their orders
slowly during the day.
After buying or selling a large position in
a stock during the day, institutional traders
compare their price to VWAP values.
A buy order executed below the VWAP would
be considered a good fill for them, because
the stock was bought at a below average price
(meaning that the trader has bought their
large position at a relatively discounted
price compared to the market).
Conversely, a sell order executed above the
VWAP would be considered a good fill because
it was sold at an above average price.
This is how VWAP is used by institutional
traders to identify good entry and exit points.
Institutional traders therefore try to buy
below or as close to VWAP as possible.
Conversely, when a professional trader has
to get rid of a large position, they try to
sell at the VWAP or higher.
Day traders who know this, may benefit from
this market activity.
If there is a large institutional trader aiming
to buy a significant position, the price will
break over the VWAP and move higher.
This is a good opportunity for us day traders
to go long.
Conversely, if there are big players wanting
to get rid of their shares, they start selling
their shares at the VWAP.
The price will reject the VWAP and start to
move down.
This is an excellent short selling opportunity
for day traders.
If there is no interest in the stock from
market makers or institutions, the price may
trade sideways near VWAP.
And you will want to stay away from that price
action.
I hope you see how trading based on VWAP will
keep you on the right side of the trade.
VWAP Bands
Well informed traders know that VWAP is a
“must have” indicator.
However, it takes an experienced trader to
understand when price is overbought or oversold
in relation to VWAP.
This skill is essential to finding and trading
the best opportunities.
The key aspect of the VWAP indicator are its
bands, based on standard deviation.
This VWAP bands reveal hidden support and
resistance that are based off the standard
VWAP indicator.
These bands allow even the most novice traders
to identify undervalued and overvalued price
zones.
By studying how the price interacts with the
VWAP bands, you can begin to discover the
price-action characteristics of that market.
And I prefer to add not just 1 set of bands,
but 2.
One VWAP with standard deviation bands of
1, and the second one with standard deviation
of 2.
This way you get multiple levels of dynamic
support or resistance.
Strong buying pressure above VWAP (or strong
selling pressure below it) is an indication
that market participants are seeking to push
price to a new area of value.
When this type of aggressive buying (or selling)
occurs, it usually leads to significant moves
in the market.
The beauty of the VWAP bands is that they
reveal these hidden areas of support and resistance,
allowing you to see value opportunities like
the Pros!
The ability to see these hidden levels allows
you to anticipate price movement at important
action zones.
In essence, as price trades away from VWAP
(the blue center line) the bands above and
below it become targets.
Likewise, as price reverses from the outer
bands the probability of reaching VWAP increases
significantly.
So how do you actually take signals, using
VWAP and Heikin Ashi.
Well, when analyzing the market, you must
look for specific signals to determine the
best point of entry and exit.
Ideally, the more signals appear in a specific
price point, the stronger it is.
In the context of trading, we call this a
confluence.
To be able to spot confluences in a price
chart, you first need to have a decent grasp
on basic technical analysis concepts.
This means identifying and plotting support
and resistance levels.
Confluences appear in the chart as a merging
of two or more elements in a certain price
level.
Points where a support or resistance level
aligns with VWAP bands.
These are key areas to buy or sell a position.
In this example you can clearly see how the
price shifted to a downtrend channel.
However, the downtrend channel ended when
the price hit a major support level here.
At this level, we also had VWAP lower bands,
revealing that sellers are losing steam and
buyers are starting to get aggressive.
Once we identified a possible confluence point,
we just need to analyze price action, using
Heikin Ashi.
Green candles forming after the price rejected
the confluence area means a shift in momentum.
This area turned out to be a great support
confluence point and a strong level to consider
an entry position.
Stop loss always goes below the support level,
below the confluence area.
And you take profit as the price reaches VWAP
bands, partially closing a part of your position.
Here the price met a major resistance level.
At this area, we also had VWAP upper bands.
So we found our possible resistance confluence
area.
Now we just need to read price action, using
Heikin Ashi.
Observe how the price rejected our area, with
several red candles.
A good entry signal.
We then had a strong downtrend, shown by these
consecutive red candlesticks.
See that the bearish price action has no upper
candle wicks.
This indicates that the declining momentum
is strong.
Stop loss above the resistance level.
And profit targets at VWAP bands, depending
on recent price action.
In this chart we identifed at least three
points that indicate the support level.
Then, we also found this rising trendline.
And of course the VWAP bands.
As expected, price found support around our
confluence area.
After this, we identified the first green
candlestick with no shadows.
This is a good signal that a strong bullish
trend might be starting.
The advantage of this strategy is that you
combine price and volume, and at the same
time you eliminate noise by using Heikin Ashi.
And you also rely on both static and dynamic
support and resistance levels.
Powerful stuff!
If things are unclear, or you find a setup
and you don’t know if the confluence area
is worth trading, you can add a momentum oscillator,
for confirmation.
In this example, after this consolidation
above the support level, price made a strong
breakout rally and found resistance right
here.
The VWAP bands are also positioned in this
area.
On top of that, we can clearly spot a Bearish
Divergence pattern on the RSI that had formed
when price stalled at the static resistance
and VWAP bands resistance.
This price level represented a high-probability
resistance confluence point and a strong level
to consider a short position.
In this example, these are the things you
should notice right away:
This support level, where price has tested
the area on previous occasions and the level
held.
Then notice that there are VWAP Bands as well,
providing another confluence factor to that
support level.
And RSI showed a bullish divergence, meaning
price action and the RSI are no longer showing
the same momentum.
A bullish divergence is signaled when the
RSI indicator has a higher low that correlates
to lower lows in the price action.
This showed increasing bullish momentum
As heikin ashi changed colors from red to
green, we enter a long trade, with a stop
loss below the confluence area
Here, notice this support level that was broken,
and price was heading up….so this was a
potential support-turned-resistance level.
The confluence trading factor comes into play
here, when you notice that VWAP Bands align
right in this area
And for momentum confirmation, you look at
the MACD.
A bearish divergence is present, with a lower
high on the MACD that correlates to higher
highs in the price action.
This means decreasing momentum and a posible
reversal in the uptrend.
This is confluence trading with price action
and momentum confirmation.
As always, if you got any value from this
and learned something new, drop a like to
help us with Youtube algorithm, and make sure
you click the bell icon to stay in touch when
new videos are released.
Until next time.