Before a pin bar becomes a pin bar, it will
look like this…very bullish.
When you are watching this candle developing
on your charts, you may have an urge to place
a trade.
Your greed tells you to enter, because you’ll
miss a future price move.
And you’re not alone in feeling this urge
to enter.
When reactive traders see candles like this
one, they feel the urge to take a position
in the direction of the candle their seeing.
And when the pin bar is completed, your fear
takes over.
If you entered when this candle looked bullish,
by now you would start to feel a little bit
under pressure in regards to what the market
may do next.
Your trade has gone from being at a profit
to being at a loss.
And if the market goes down any lower, you
will start to consider whether it’s a good
idea staying in the trade.
Again, fear and greed.
I always think like this when I’m considering
a trade.
If you didn’t already know, there are different
types of pin bars which appear in the market.
When I say types I don’t mean one pin bar
has a bigger wick than the other, I mean the
causes behind why a pin bar forms in the market
can be different depending on where the pin
bar is found.
There are 2 main causes: when a pin bar appears,
big player took a significant amount of profits
off their existing trades or when they’re
starting to place trades in order to make
the market reverse.
And the best types of Pin Bar setups form
when there has been a sustained moved (either
up or down) and price retraces to an area
of "value" or "interest".
The Strategy explained
At its core, a pin bar is considered a reversal
candlestick.
But, if you try to trade pin bars as reversal
signals when the price is moving in the direction
of the trend, then you are not doing it correctly.
So, to avoid this situation, you’ll use
2 exponential moving averages.
One with a period of 50, and the second one
with a period of 100.
These are very common and followed by many
other traders.
• If the 50 EMA is above the 100 EMA, then
the market is in an uptrend.
• If the 50 EMA is below the 100 EMA, then
the market is in a downtrend.
Our strategy involves trading pullbacks, in
the direction of the 2 EMAs, using high volume
pin bars.
When markets trend, they do not just go up
or down in a straight line.
There’s always a period of “rest” before
continuing the trend.
Markets ALWAYS have these pullbacks when trending
and these are great opportunities for you
to get into a trade before the market resumes
its trend.
The area between the 2 EMA is the “sweet
spot” for our entries.
You want to find high volume pin bars, in
the direction of the main trend, rejecting
these levels.
The volume of the pin bar must be higher than
the previous 3 bars.
BEST Signals To Trade
So, what makes a tradable Pin Bar?
I mainly look for several points:
• The "wick" (or tail) should be at least
2 times, ideally 3 times, the length of the
body.
• The body should be present towards either
the upper or lower extreme of the Pin bar.
• The wick should stand out when compared
to surrounding bars.
Generally, Pin Bar signals are only relevant
for the next 4 - 5 bars.
So, if you watch the daily time frame and
a pin bar forms, it will make most of its
impact on future price moves within 4 - 5
days of its creation.
This is because Pin Bars are short duration
setups, and because of this, it makes sense
that they will normally only affect the outcome
of the bars immediately in the future.
Pin Bars should not be traded on their own.
There are many factors that influence whether
or not you should trade a Pin Bar and for
that reason you shouldn’t take a trade solely
based on the fact that a Pin Bar has formed.
This is why we’ll use EMAs for trend direction
and volume to spot interest and active participation
in a future price move.
Also, pin bars that are in heavy traffic or
choppy, range bound markets should not be
traded.
The reason for this is that there is no clear
trend and there are too many areas of interest
for price to stall at.
Finding areas of value
So, pin bars should only be traded when they
form in areas of "value" or "interest".
The more of these areas of interest that converge
together near where the Pin Bar has formed,
the more significant the Pin Bar signal becomes,
this is known as "confluence".
You can use support and resistance levels,
supply and demand areas, but in this video,
we’ll focus on EMAs.
As well as being used to evaluate the trend
direction and strength, EMAs can be used as
dynamic levels of support and resistance.
In some cases, price can be seen to bounce
off certain EMA values almost religiously
during retraces in trending markets.
And when volume confirms the pin bar, you
have several factors which increase the probability
of a successful trade.
The only problem with EMAs is that everybody
uses different period values depending on
the time frame and markets they are trading.
My advice is to pick two periods and stick
with them, as once you get some experience
under your belt, you will start to learn how
they behave in different market conditions.
I prefer the h4 and daily time frame, and
I use the 50 and 100 day EMAs, but the choice
is completely up to you.
You can change the parameters as you wish.
Just understand the concept and adapt it to
your needs.
We trade Amazon on the hourly time frame.
One of the first things you should look for
when you open a chart are the 2 EMAs, to determine
trend direction and find possible areas of
dynamic support or resistance.
In this case, the trend is down, so we look
to short the market.
And this is our pin bar, showing rejection
and indicating a potential trend continuation.
The volume of the pin bar is higher than the
previous 3 candles, so there’s active interest
in the market.
When the low of the pin bar is broken, that’s
our signal to initiate a sell position.
Stop loss above the pin bar.
And in this case, above the 2 EMAs, which
is almost a perfect setup, with another layer
of protection.
Take profit at the next swing low in the price
structure.
A risk to reward ratio of around 2.8.
Perfect trade and we even left profits on
the table.
We move to pound yen on the M30 time frame.
The 50 EMA is above the 100 EMA, so we look
for buy opportunities.
We have our pullback to the EMAs, and here’s
our pin bar.
But look at the volume, is lower than the
previous 4 or 5 bars.
So, this is a no trade.
The volume condition isn’t met.
This is unfortunate, because the price indeed
went up.
But in the long run, the volume confirmation
will save your account for many losing trades.
So don’t neglect it.
Let’s move to EURJPY, on my favorite time
frame, the H4.
The same situation.
The trend is up because the 50 EMA is above
the 100 EMA, so we look for long trades.
We have a small pullback to the 50 EMA, and
with this pin bar rejecting the area.
Volume is higher than the previous bars, so
all conditions are met.
When the high of the pin bar is broken, that’s
the signal to initiate a long position.
Stop loss below the low of the pin bar, and
below the 50 EMA.
As for take profit, the distance until the
next swing high doesn’t offer a positive
risk to reward ratio, so we must estimate
our self a potential target.
I’ll set a target of 3, but I’ll monitor
closely the price action at this resistance
area.
In order to be a valid tradeable pattern,
the pin bar must reject the area between the
2 EMAs.
This is a key point in trading pin bars.
In this case, again, we are dealing with a
bullish trend, so we’ll look for a continuation
trade to the upside.
This is the pin bar, rejecting the 50 EMA.
Volume is higher than the previous candles,
so this is a valid setup.
Once we’ve identified the pin bar at the
value area, we wait for the high of candle
to be broken.
Stop loss below the low of the pin bar, and
below the 50 EMA.
We are very close to the most recent high,
so we aim for a risk to reward ratio of 2
or even 3.
Let’s continue.
I see a somewhat deeper pullback to the 100
EMA.
And a pin bar forming right on top of it.
The real body is relatively small, and the
tail of the candle is much longer.
Volume is definitely higher than the previous
bars, we there’s active participation, an
interest in that particular area.
So we’ll enter long at the high of the pin
bar.
We gave a gap up, so the entry price would
be somewhat higher.
Stop loss below the pin bar and below the
100 EMA.
As for targets, I see this major resistance
here, which could stop the price increase,
so let’s take our profit a few points below
this area.
A risk to reward ratio of around 2.5.
Okey, that’s frustrating.
Price almost hit our take profit, but instead
it reversed and stopped us out.
There’s a lesson to be learned here.
What could we have done to manage the trade
better when in profit?
As we entered below the 50 EMA, near the 100
EMA, in the future, when price goes up and
consolidates above the 50 EMA, a safer money
management technique is to move the stop loss
to break even.
We don’t allow a profitable trade to become
a losing one.
Some traders will claim that the bigger the
Pin Bar the better, but my experience has
shown that if the Pin Bar is much larger than
the average trading range of the preceding
bars, then it will most likely become a continuation
pattern rather than a reversal pattern.
When presented with a massive Pin Bar like
this one on Bitcoin, my advice is to stay
on the sidelines and wait for a better opportunity
to present itself.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.