Trading is a game of deceptions and traps,
and you must learn to play accordingly.
I learned this the hard way, with my own money.
When you enter the trading game, one of the
first concepts you learn about is the moving
averages.
And for a good reason, moving averages represent
one of the most visually effective tools for
scanning markets.
Their simple concept of filtering out noise
and to identify trend biases appears compelling.
Traders gravitate towards moving averages
because of their clean visual communication
of uptrends and downtrends.
When prices cross above or below these lines,
we get excited, it subconsciously triggers
decisions, seeking confirmation of emerging
directions.
In fact, one of the foundational rules of
technical analysis is the moving average breakout.
And I can show you a lot of textbook examples
showing this principle in action.
A moving average acting as dynamic support
turns to resistance once broken.
And the previous line acting as resistance
morphed into perfect support on retest.
It's the kind of signal every technical trader
lives for.
We all took this kind of trade in the past.
But as obvious as some of those patterns look
in hindsight, there is an important thing
most people miss.
Only a small percentage, maybe 15-20%, of
moving average breakouts actually play out
as cleanly as the textbook examples.
It all comes down to understanding how moving
averages work.
A moving average shows the average price of
market over a period of time, like the last
50 candles.
Traders pay close attention to when the price
crosses above or below the moving average
line.
That's because it signals whether the trend
is turning from up to down or vice versa.
But here's the thing - smart traders know
other traders are watching those moving averages
too.
So sometimes they'll push the price briefly
over or under the moving average, even if
the main trend is still going the other way.
Their goal is to trick people into thinking
the trend has changed, so those traders jump
in - and then the big traders reverse the
price back where it came from, trapping those
followers with big losses.
The reality is that the vast majority of moving
average breakouts end up being fakeouts or
false breaks that fool traders.
Just because the moving average is broken,
the new level doesn't guarantee anything about
what comes next.
More often than not, price action just wicks
through this zone, then continues the initial
move.
Some call these "false breakouts", others
see them as liquidity runs.
And while they cause trouble for traders who
get trapped, if you spot them coming, you
have a chance to profit.
Those "false breakouts" can really mess with
your head.
As I was losing most of my trades using this
signal, I started to understand why it happens
though.
Common moving averages, like the 20, 50 or
200, are like battle zones between buyers
and sellers pushing price both ways.
So it makes sense the price action wavers
in and out sometimes before settling again.
What really sunk in for me is that chasing
moving average breakouts after a strong trend
is likely to lose money overall, especially
as a beginner.
Those massive explosive moves that seem so
easy to catch are actually pretty rare.
And even if the break is real, actually hanging
on through volatility and exiting at the right
time takes a lot of experience.
I had a major breakthrough when I finally
grasped the concept of liquidity.
Liquidity is all the orders that are stacked
up in the market waiting to be executed.
Liquidity usually builds up on both sides
of the moving average, especially when there’s
a breakout.
This is because there are lots of traders
using similar entries and exits.
Buyers who think the market's going up tend
to buy when price moves above a moving average,
placing their stop losses below it.
Sellers who think price is going down put
their stop losses above the moving average
when price moves below it.
And this is exactly why a lot of times moving
average breakouts don't have real buying or
selling conviction behind them.
And as soon as stops get taken out above or
below, prices whip right back the other way.
That ends up leaving a bunch of trapped traders
who helped fuel the reversal with their stop
losses.
The momentum they provided can really move
the market away from the moving average in
the opposite direction.
During strong trends, it's smarter to wait
for these failed breakouts to happen before
entering.
The risk is way lower versus chasing the initial
moves.
And the potential reward is way higher if
price bounces hard after squeezing those stop
runs.
Let me explain the strategy I use.
The first thing I watch for is a strong trend.
To me that means the price has been steadily
rising or falling for at least a couple days
without reversing more than a few percent.
You want to see higher highs, higher lows,
multiple breaks of structure and no major
change of character.
During these trends, institutional traders
have the market under their control and can
manipulate prices more easily.
Once a strong trend is in place, I'll monitor
the moving averages.
Usually a 50-period is all I need, but you
can select any period you want, just make
sure you use a common one, like the 20 or
200.
I'm looking to see if the price crosses above
or below that average line, but stays there
for only a very short time, only for a few
candles.
That's a red flag it might be a false breakout.
The next thing I check is volume.
On a real trend change, you'd expect volume
to spike as more orders pile in.
But with a false breakout, volume is often
lower than normal.
That tells me not many people took the bait
of the fake signal.
If I see a liquidity run, that’s the strongest
signal I can get.
Armed with those signs, I'll enter a position
against the false breakout - so if it crosses
above the moving average during a down trend,
I'll short the market, and vice versa.
Let me give you an example to help explain
it better.
In this chart, oil prices had been steadily
increasing on high demand.
The 50-day moving average was rising strongly
in line with the uptrend.
Multiple breaks of structure during this trend.
And here, price dipped under the 50-period
average for just a couple of candles before
rebounding right back above.
Volume was surprisingly low for such a market-moving
event.
And look at this liquidity run, below this
level.
I call it a double trap.
This move below the moving average trapped
price action traders, waiting for a break
below this level, and at the same time, trapped
moving average traders.
To me, it seemed like a false breakout designed
to attract short sellers before resuming the
rally.
Sure enough, prices had reversed all the way
back up, causing big losses for anyone who
shorted the "breakdown".
The smart play here was going long against
the fake signal, in line with the previous
trend.
On the flip side, there’s a similar situation.
Price has been tanking for days.
Multiple breaks of structure to the downside.
Lower lows and lower highs.
And the move above the 50-period line.
Again, it was barely above for a few candles,
on lighter than usual volume.
Observe the liquidity run, trapping another
group of buyers, to the upside.
And of course, price reversed direction and
broke below the moving average once again,
accelerating its fall further.
The play here was going short against the
fake signal, once price moved below the 50
SMA.
It doesn’t matter the market you trade,
that’s the beauty of this strategy.
Here gold prices had been making higher highs
and higher lows, in an upward trend, with
the 50-day moving average reflecting the positive
momentum.
Then, gold took a quick nosedive below the
moving average.
We even had a liquidity run during this period.
Despite the initial panic in the market, the
volume during this drop was notably lower
than expected for a significant trend change.
The correct trade was a long one, once price
moved above the 50 SMA.
After a prolonged downward trend, a false
breakout presented an opportunity.
The price briefly rose above the 50-day moving
average, moved past this level, that being
a liquidity run, causing a stir among traders.
We had low volume during this move, so long
positions were off the table.
As price reversed direction and dipped back
below the moving average, that was the time
to enter a sell position, in line with the
previous trend.
In this recent trend where the market had
been climbing steadily, the 50-period moving
average was on my radar.
As price briefly dipped below the moving average
and registered also a liquidity run, this
move caught the attention of many traders.
But, the volume during this dip was surprisingly
low.
A textbook false breakout, trapping sellers
on the short side.
And true enough, within the next candles,
the price bounced back above the moving average.
This was the ideal time to enter a long trade,
capitalizing on the trapped traders below
the moving average.
Here the market had been on a positive trajectory
for days, aligning well with the 50-day moving
average.
Then, out of the blue, the stock dipped below
the moving average, setting off alarm bells
for many traders.
Observe also this liquidity run and the low
volume during this dip.
All our conditions were met: strong trend,
a move below the moving average, liquidity
run and low volume.
Fair enough, the stock swiftly climbed back
above the moving average, and that was the
perfect moment to initiate a long trade.
By recognizing the patterns of smart money
manipulating prices with false breakouts,
you take the emotion out of the trade.
You're not getting swept up by the crowd being
baited by a fake signal.
Instead, you profit from the liquidity run
that inevitably follows.
Some key aspects to remember:
Only trade these set-ups during strong trends,
when major players have more control
Watch for breakouts that last only a short
time, like a few candles
Check volume - it should be unusually light
Take a tight stop in case it turns into a
real breakout
It's an easy strategy, but it requires staying
cool-headed and trusting your analysis of
the market structure.
Don't get fooled by hype and focus on the
big picture trend.
Pay attention to the signs of possible manipulation
by big money.
When you spot a false breakout, get in position
to profit as the price retraces where it came
from.
By following trends and outsmarting the tricks
of institutional traders, you will too start
seeing bigger gains.
Just keep practicing spotting the patterns.
Study old charts to compare tells of real
versus fake signals above or below moving
averages.
And most important, when you find another
liquidity run, above or below a previous key
level, you have found the strongest signal.
With experience, you'll get better and better
at differentiating between genuine trend changes
and traps set by smart money.
This strategy won’t work perfectly each
time, but it has served me well over the past
months.
There will always be ups and downs of course.
But as long as you focus on the big picture
and remember your edge, you'll come out ahead
more often than not.
That's how I've succeeded trading moving average
breakouts - by recognizing these traps and
turning them to my advantage instead of becoming
victim to them.
Now it’s your turn!