Does it feel time and time again like you
are being watched and your stops are being
hunted?
Then you are not alone.
This is a common complaint of many retail
traders.
The problem is that you probably are entering
at the wrong times in the market.
Today we’ll fix this and I’ll share a
very simple scalping and day trading strategy,
to trade any market.
The concept of the strategy is derived from
the 2 major phases of price movement: expansion
and contraction.
So, like, subscribe, and stick around for
the full video.
Contraction/expansion
Markets go through periods of contraction
when prices move in narrow range while traders’
interest comes down.
These periods of narrow range are called contraction.
When markets are doing nothing, they are giving
a message: we have a balance between bulls
and bears.
Neither is strong enough to take the market
in their direction.
Soon enough, one of these forces – either
the bulls or the bears will emerge as the
stronger force.
Then comes a period of expansion, when the
winning force will take the market sharply
in its favor, trapping the losing force.
This is the period when markets will move
outside the previous ranges, in one direction.
Inside bar contraction
Identifying the waves of contraction and expansion
is a powerful skill to have and one of the
simplest way to find these periods is by analyzing
inside bars.
Inside bars on a candlestick chart represent
the consolidation of price action where the
bulls and bears are both struggling to move
the price higher or lower from its current
position.
You can easily spot an inside bar when a given
bar’s high and low are fully contained by
the bar directly preceding it.
This signals a narrowing of price action,
a contraction that can be used to anticipate
upcoming movements outside of this range.
Basically, when there is contraction, pressure
is building.
Double inside bar trick
On their own, inside bars can be quite tricky,
especially if you are unexperienced.
You can find hundreds of inside bars during
a trading day, if you trade lower time frames.
A double inside bar setup will solve this
problem and will highlight the period of contraction
even better.
A double inside bar is when there are two
consecutive ‘inside bars’ which have failed
to breach the high and low of the previous
bar.
It reflects contraction and indecision.
This price action set-up, although rare, is
more significant than just an inside bar.
The colors of the bars are irrelevant – the
fact that we have two consecutive bars inside
the previous bars range is the main aspect
here.
Double inside bars are a rare contraction
signal.
So rare, it would be a shame to miss the opportunity!
You can trade both trend continuations and
key reversals.
If this setup is present at a key technical
level, maybe a key support, at a round number
or a FIB level, or at a pivot level, or near
a moving average, it can often reflect a change
in sentiment.
And a great opportunity for you to take advantage
of.
We’ll cover many scenarios later in the
video.
If there is no technical level in the way,
then the safest way is to trade the setup
as a continuation one, with the prevailing
trend.
Inside bar indicator
Let’s simplify the process of searching
and analyzing candlesticks, and let’s use
an indicator which displays inside bars.
I use this one.
It finds and reveals all inside bars on the
chart.
Your job is to simply find the double inside
bar setup, when you see two consecutive arrows.
Here’s the trading plan:
• In a trending market, you will trade only
with the trend, by trading continuation breakouts.
• In a range bound market, you will sell
the top of the range and buy the bottom
In both cases, the location of the double
inside bar is very important.
My preferred locations to trade are near:
1.
Levels of support and resistance
2.
Trend lines
3.
Moving averages
4.
Fibonacci levels
5.
Daily Pivots
6.
Round numbers
We trade Bitcoin, on the 5 minutes time frame.
We see a clear downtrend, with price making
lower lows and lower highs.
And now we are in a range.
In this case I would prefer short trades,
in the direction of the dominant trend.
Here’s our double inside bar setup.
As we are near the resistance level of the
range, the plan is to short a breakout to
the downside.
Price broke the upper level of the channel,
but we ignore the signal.
Remember, you don’t want to fight the existing
trend.
Next candle brought a downside breakout, so
we entered short.
Stop loss goes on the other side of the channel,
or above the previous swing high.
It all depends on the size of the channel
and recent price action.
As for take profits, as I’m trading the
5 minutes charts and I’m scalping, I target
the next swing in the price structure, at
least.
In this case this swing.
Then you can use a trailing stop, a breakeven
stop, or whatever money management technique
you prefer.
But your trade should offer a positive risk
to reward ratio.
Now we see another double inside bar below
the first signal.
As we are already in a trade, we ignore this
one.
Let’s find another trade.
Price again seemed to form another range,
again, in a downtrend.
So, we’ll keep looking to sell the market.
Here’s our signal, 2 consecutive inside
bars.
If we zoom out, we see that the signal appeared
below this breakout.
This seems like a break and retest situation,
and the location of the double inside bar
setup favors a short trade.
Here’s our breakout.
Stop loss on the other side of the channel,
or above this swing high.
As we are already very near the previous swing
low, we expect price to break it and to continue
the downtrend.
Let’s try a risk to reward ratio of 3, but
we’ll keep an eye on price action.
Another good trade and we even left some profits
on the table.
Again, you can play with the take profit,
and try different techniques.
Let’s continue.
Here’s our signal.
We have a double bottom here and a small break
of structure.
But at the same time, the setup appear at
this swing high, in a downtrend.
So, this situation isn’t so clear.
I still favor the short trade, but if the
breakout occurs to the upside, I’ll still
risk a long trade.
Okey, we have a downward breakout, so a short
trade it is.
Stop loss above this swing high, above the
channel.
Take profit at this swing low, a few points
above it.
Let’s change the market, let’s trade GBP/USD,
and let’s add a moving average.
If price is above the 200 EMA, you’ll trade
only long breakouts above the double inside
bar setup
If price is below the 200 EMA, you’ll trade
only short breakouts below the double inside
bar pattern
In this example, price is below the 200 EMA,
so in this case we’ll target short positions.
Here’s the signal.
We have consecutive inside bars around this
resistance area.
We have a triple rejection in a small amount
of time.
As price broke the channel to the downside,
we entered short with a stop above the channel
and a take profit around this swing low.
That’s a risk to reward ratio of 2.
We move on.
Price broke above the 200 EMA, so now we are
looking to buy the market.
And here’s the signal to enter.
Consecutive inside bars, right at the 200
EMA.
You buy here, at the breakout of the channel.
Stop loss below the channel and below the
200 EMA.
Take profit at the next swing high.
That’s a risk to reward ratio of 4.
We lost the trade, despite the fact it was
actually a pretty good signal.
Let’s once again change the market and trade
Tesla.
I see a downtrend, lower lows, lower highs.
And here’s the double inside bar pattern.
I favor short trades, but if price breaks
to the upside, I’ll still take a long trade.
The pressure remained to the downside, so
we had a downward breakout, in line with the
previous trend.
Stop goes above this swing high and we target
the previous swing low.
This offers a risk to reward ratio of 2.3.
Another signal, after we closed the previous
trade with a profit.
The location of the pattern, below the previous
swing low, favors another short trade.
Which indeed happened, as price broke once
again the previous low.
Stop loss above the channel.
As we don’t have an immediate swing low
to target, we set a risk to reward ratio of
2.
The beauty of double inside bars is that they
can be traded as both continuations and key
reversals.
And it’s all price action based.
By scanning the market for trends that are
in place, you can start to identify periods
of price contraction where a trend has stopped
making higher highs and higher lows in a bullish
trend, and lower lows and lower highs in a
bearish trend.
When price breaks from these contracted areas,
it reveals that either the buyers or sellers
have regained control of the trend and can
help you time your entry and ride
the momentum.
This is not a perfect strategy, you will encounter
losing trades and for this reason you could
put your own spin on it, additional confirmations
or other types of analysis.
If you can back up consecutive inside bars
with other technical tools, it might be worth
opening a position.
Just make sure you don’t overcomplicate
it and stick to the main concepts of this
strategy: finding periods of contraction and
ride the momentum move after the breakout.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time.