So today I want to share with you an intriguing
scalping trading strategy.
This strategy leverages a simple yet powerful
phenomenon - that a market’s open price
sometimes matches its highest or lowest point
for the day.
When this occurs, it creates a scalping opportunity.
You see, on such a day, the market has essentially
revealed where it sees strong support or resistance.
Picture this - the open price matches the
initial low.
This tells us buyers stepped in early and
established a clear support, showing where
they'll defend the price going forward.
Similarly, an open equal to the high indicates
sellers wasted no time capping further upwards
moves, laying out a firm resistance.
These congruent levels provide prime entries,
if you trade accordingly.
Think about it…when the open equals the
low, indicated on most platforms by a green
candle, it tells us buyers were able to push
the price up substantially right from the
open.
This demonstrates eager demand exists among
buyers at those levels.
Upside momentum is likely to continue, presenting
a high-probability buy entry.
Conversely, if the open matches the high,
denoted by a red candle, it reveals sellers
could immediately press the price down from
the highs.
This shows willingness to sell around those
areas.
Downside momentum typically follows, offering
a short setup.
When analyzing the markets, it's important
to have the proper tools to easily identify
these signals.
Unfortunately, TradingView does not have a
built-in indicator to directly find the signals
of the open matching the low or high.
The best solution I've found is to use two
simple indicators together:
First one is the “Open Price” - This displays
a horizontal line marking the open level right
on the chart.
It allows a quick visual check to see if open
matches the high or low.
The second indicator is the Opening Range
Breakout - This draws upper and lower lines
connecting the highs and lows of the first
5 minutes of each candle.
So make sure to set it to the 5 minute timeframe
you want to trade.
The two-indicator approach is the cleanest
workaround for easily finding signals, if
you monitor multiple markets.
Now we can visually compare the open price
to the Opening Range high/low lines.
When the open price line tags the low line,
we have a potential buy signal.
If it touches the high line, it's an opportunity
to sell.
It's a bit manual, but that’s the closest
solution within TradingView’s library.
The opening minutes each day will provide
powerful clues about potential scalping opportunities,
but also an overall directional bias.
The key point is that when the open matches
the high or low, it suggests there is strong
momentum.
This often leads to increased volatility.
And this presents an opportunity for us, scalpers,
to jump in and capitalize on future swings.
The plan is simple: to catch quick moves based
on the early momentum.
A match between the open price and its highest
or lowest price confirms the likelihood of
an established directional bias for the whole
session.
If the open price drove strongly up from lows,
it raises the probability of an extended bounce
play for trend followers.
Vice versa for an open matching the high,
signaling brief downside potential.
The main advantage of this scalping strategy
is definitely its simplicity.
There's no complex indicators or customized
formulas to configure - just basic pattern
recognition of the open in relation to the
initial high and low.
These signals require little time investment
to analyze and execute on.
You can simply monitor the 5-minute chart
for a few moments at open and immediately
identify an opportunity.
And with potential trades taking shape in
minutes, everything must be streamlined and
optimized.
Usually, a buy or a sell signal is generated
within the first 5 – 15 minutes of the trading
day.
You can play around with the time settings
and see which one works best for you.
As volume increases during the first 5 minutes,
it naturally causes prices to oscillate more
widely.
This volatility stretching the highs and lows
creates prime openings for strategic plays.
In this chart, the OPEN price is matching
the DAY's low, and this reveals that smart
institutional players have stepped in overnight
or pre-market to dominate the session.
The sellers didn’t have any power to move
price, not even one tick below the open.
This is very bullish in my opinion.
When the open builds on this support, slowly
but steadily through buying pressure, it frequently
initiates an extended trend up, as demand
proved stronger than selling.
In this example, the open matches the high,
suggesting selling pressure dominated early,
with supply outweighing demand right from
the market open.
Often this indicates institutional or other
professional traders were taking profits or
establishing new short positions pre-market.
Seeing this action telegraphed so clearly
in the opening minutes is extremely valuable
for day traders and scalpers looking to ride
the overall trend.
It informs you that big players expect short-term
downward momentum, at least initially.
There are 2 types of entries.
The first one - entering long on the first
push above the first 5 minute candle or immediately
after the candle has formed.
Quality liquidity lies below, and the initial
bounce often has follow-through, as momentum
traders join to ride the wave up.
The second entry - at the 50% Fibonacci retracement
of the initial candle, if the candle is larger
in size.
You see, sometimes it’s better to wait for
a retracement, and then enter, in the direction
of the initial candle.
The aggressive entry comes after you monitor
that first critical 5-minute candle.
By waiting the first candle to form, you allow
the initial dust to settle, while key levels
establish.
For an open equal to the high, I'd set a sell
order a tick below the 5-minute candle's low.
Smart money likely capped upside there, and
a break suggests distribution might persist.
Conversely, an open matching the day's low,
presents buy triggers on a push above the
5-minute high.
The low confirms underlying support, and a
break above signals buyers could maintain
control pushing prices up further.
As you are scalping, always risk small with
tight stops above or below the 5-minute range.
And a quick tip - volume-backed breakouts
often spark quick continuation, as momentum
traders pile on.
I kind of prefer the more conservative entry.
Rather than entering signals immediately at
the open of the next candle, I wait for a
retracement back to the midpoint of the opening
5 minute candle, before triggering my entry.
So we enter in the direction of the expected
momentum move at a better price after some
pullback.
This improves our risk-reward ratio.
And we avoid potentially getting stopped out
on wider, more volatile opening candles, if
price whipsaws before the impulse begins.
Essentially, we are refining our execution
using the opening candle range as a guide.
Rather than rushing in at the initial 5-minute
candle breakout, waiting for a modest retracement
often helps manage risk better.
So remember this: overextended openings frequently
pull back within the range.
In this case, tightened entries on a pullback
to the midpoint provides a lower-risk second
chance if momentum stalls, without missing
the trade entirely if it resumes swiftly.
As for stop placement, keeping them near the
open price often offers the best compromise.
It preserves your capital should the setup
fail, without getting stopped prematurely
from temporary fluctuations.
An alternative is, as swings develop, raise
stops proactively to lock profits and capitalize
on extended moves.
But avoid trailed stops that can whip you
out of positions too hastily.
One of the most precise ways I've found to
extract maximum gains from this scalping strategy
is by factoring in anchored VWAP bands around
that first influential 5-minute open candle.
You add the upper and lower bands, anchored
to the opening price, to highlight potential
areas of support and resistance around the
main VWAP line, as the day progresses.
Now when you enter a scalping trade, you initially
target the 2nd or 3rd VWAP band, in the direction
of your entry, for partial profits.
For example if you go long, you target the
upper anchored VWAP bands for the first take
profit.
If you go short, you aim for the lower VWAP
bands for initial gains.
As price reaches the bands, scale out a portion
of the position, while trailing a stop on
the remainder, to lock in further profits
if momentum continues beyond VWAP.
The key benefit of using the anchored VWAP
bands is they objectively highlight profit
areas based on that day's developing value
area.
Using multiple exits using VWAP bands makes
your trading far more dynamic and adaptive.
Aiming blindly for a fixed risk - reward ratio
on every trade can be limiting because price
movements and volatility fluctuate.
Some momentum surges will exhaust quickly
after your entry signal.
Others may continue trending strongly beyond
your static target.
This is where adding adaptive exits like VWAP
bands becomes highly useful.
If momentum fizzles out early, the VWAP bands
can alert you to take profits nearer to your
entry.
If the momentum explodes with thrust, the
bands help you trail stops to capture outsized
gains.
Either way, you are basing exits on the real-time
developing market context, rather than just
assuming a pre-set target will be hit.
Remember, you are scalping, so managing risk
smartly is the foundation to your long-term
success.
Consider reducing position size if entering
on wider opening candles.
And trail stops incrementally to lock in profits
as the momentum wave extends.
Learn to scale out partial profits in pieces
rather than exiting the whole trade at once.
And if you want to discover other scalping
strategies, you might want to watch one of
these videos.