The Anchored VWAP is one of the best
tools for finding potential entry points,
especially in the stock market.
While the traditional VWAP starts
from the beginning of the trading
day to its end, the Anchored VWAP
allows you to choose your starting point.
This flexibility is a game-changer, as it
lets you align the indicator with a significant
market event or at psychological turning points.
So we’ll anchor the VWAP at a high-volume
bar, and this way, you can track how the
market behaves relative to this important level.
High volume often signals strong interest in the
market, and when combined with a price move, it
can indicate momentum in a particular direction.
The core of this strategy revolves around
trading pullbacks to the VWAP lines,
when price temporarily moves against the main
trend, before resuming its original direction.
Selecting the right anchoring
point is crucial for this strategy.
Ideally, you want to choose a point that marks
a clear shift in market structure or psychology.
This could also be a significant swing
high or low, or a major news event.
But a bar with exceptionally
high volume is something special.
The goal is to capture a point where the
market's behavior changed significantly.
So in this chart, we anchored the
VWAP on the highest volume bar.
This high volume shows increased
participation from traders,
often signaling important price
levels or potential trend changes.
When this high volume coincides with a
strong price move, it can be a powerful
indicator of market direction.
Once you've anchored your VWAP,
the strategy involves watching
for price pullbacks to this line.
These pullbacks represent potential entry points
for trades in the direction of the overall trend.
For example, in an uptrend, you might
look for buying opportunities when the
price pulls back to the Anchored line, or
even at the bands below the main line.
This strategy can be applied to all
timeframes, making it versatile for
both day traders, and swing traders.
The principle remains the same:
identify the trend, anchor the VWAP at a
high volume bar, and trade the pullbacks.
To enhance the effectiveness of this
strategy, you can also use the VWAP bands.
These bands are typically set at
one, or two standard deviations,
above and below the VWAP line.
They can help confirm the strength of the trend,
and provide additional support and resistance
levels. When price stays consistently above the
upper VWAP band, it suggests a strong uptrend.
Price consistently below the lower band
indicates a strong downtrend.
These VWAP bands can also help in
identifying potential reversal points.
If the price has been trending strongly,
and suddenly penetrates the opposite VWAP band,
it might signal a potential trend reversal.
The Anchored VWAP strategy aligns well
with the concept of trend following.
By anchoring the VWAP at this
significant point and trading pullbacks,
you're essentially trying to catch waves
in the direction of the overall trend.
But, VWAP, even when anchored,
is still a lagging indicator.
It's based on historical price and volume
data, which means it can't predict future
price movements with certainty.
That’s why, another factor to
consider is the overall market context.
This Anchored VWAP strategy tends to
work best in trending markets.
In sideways or choppy markets,
the pullbacks to VWAP might not be as reliable.
Volume analysis must complement this strategy.
Not only volume is important for selecting the
anchoring point, but it's also key for confirming
the strength of pullbacks and potential breakouts.
When a pullback to the Anchored VWAP occurs on
low volume, it often implies a
weak retracement and a higher
probability that the main trend will continue.
But if the pullback happens on high volume,
it might indicate a stronger move, that
could potentially break the VWAP level.
To further refine your entries using this
strategy, pay attention to price action
around the Anchored VWAP.
Look for rejection candles,
or other signs that the price is respecting
the VWAP as a support or resistance level.
These could include candles with
long wicks or engulfing bars.
You might also use traditional
support and resistance levels,
or even trend lines in conjunction
with the Anchored VWAP.
This approach can provide
additional confirmation.
One approach to setting stop losses with this
strategy, is to place them beyond the recent swing
high or low, on the other side of the VWAP.
For profit targets, you might look at
previous support or resistance
levels, or at the next bands.
The Anchored VWAP strategy can be
particularly effective when combined
with a multiple timeframe analysis.
For instance, you might use a higher
timeframe to determine the overall trend, and
to select your anchoring point for the VWAP.
Then, you could drop down to a lower
timeframe, to fine-tune your entries
based on pullbacks to the VWAP.
We’re looking at an hourly chart
of a stock that has been in a strong uptrend.
You notice this bar with exceptionally high
volume, which coincides with a strong upward move.
This seems like a good place to anchor your VWAP.
Over the next few days, the stock continues
to rise, but then starts to pull back.
As the price approaches the Anchored VWAP
line, you see this previous support level,
suggesting buyers are stepping in at this level.
This could be a good opportunity to enter a long
position, with a stop loss placed
just below the recent swing low.
Now let’s consider a 15-minute
chart of a stock in a downtrend.
You anchor the VWAP at this high-volume bar,
which marked the start of the current leg down.
The price has been consistently trading
below the VWAP, confirming the downtrend.
You notice the price starting to climb back
towards the VWAP line, on decreasing volume.
This could be a good opportunity
to enter a short trade, with a
stop loss just above the recent swing high.
Here, the market has been in a strong uptrend.
You've anchored the VWAP at a significant
high-volume bar, near the recent top.
The price has started to fall and has consistently
traded below the VWAP for several bars.
You notice that each attempt to rally back
to the VWAP is met with selling pressure.
This could be an early sign of a trend reversal.
You might consider entering a short trade on one
of these failed rallies to the VWAP, with
a stop loss above the recent swing high.
In all these examples, the Anchored VWAP serves as
a dynamic support/resistance level and a reference
point for market psychology.
CPR strategy
The Central Pivot Range method taps
into market sentiment and price action.
This particular area shows where the market might
turn, being like a map of support and resistance.
This is the pivot. Above and below are two
more lines. And all of these form a range.
This range tells us a lot about what might
happen today, based on yesterday’s activity.
So when you look at a chart,
you'll see the CPR as three lines.
They might be close together or far apart.
This distance matters, because it
tells us how the market might move.
A wide CPR means the market might stay calm.
Price often bounces between the
lines, and market is taking a rest.
These calm days can lead to big moves later.
A narrow CPR is different. It's like
the market is getting ready to sprint.
When the lines are close, price can break out.
These days often see strong trends. The
market picks a direction and runs with it.
Now, let's talk about how to read the CPR.
It's all about comparing today to yesterday.
If today's CPR is higher than yesterday's,
we're looking up. The market mood is
positive. Buyers are in control. This
is when you want to think about buying.
But if today's CPR is lower than yesterday's,
it's time to look down. Sellers have taken charge.
The market mood has shifted. This
is when you might want to sell.
Here's a key point. The CPR doesn't just tell
us about today. It hints at tomorrow too.
A rising CPR suggests more upside ahead.
A falling CPR warns of possible drops.
Let's see how this plays out. Say you
see the CPR moving up day after day.
This is a strong sign. The market is in
an uptrend. Each new day confirms the
move. This is when you want
to look for chances to buy.
If the CPR keeps stepping down, we're in
a downtrend. The market is showing its
hand. It wants to go lower. This is when
you search for selling opportunities.
But the CPR isn't just about
direction. It's also about strength.
A wide CPR is hard to break.
Price often respects these levels.
They act as strong support or resistance. When
you see a wide CPR, expect the market to pause.
It might bounce around inside the range.
A narrow CPR is weaker. Price can push
through it more easily. But don't ignore it.
A narrow CPR can lead to explosive moves.
The market often builds
energy here before a big run.
Now, let's talk strategy. The CPR
gives you a framework for trading.
It tells you where to look and what to expect.
Here's how you can use it.
First, check the CPR at the start of each day.
Compare it to yesterday. Is it higher or lower?
This sets your bias. Higher means look
to buy. Lower means look to sell.
Next, watch how price interacts with
the CPR. Does it bounce off the lines?
Does it push through? This tells
you about the day's strength. Strong
bounces mean the CPR is working well.
Clean breaks suggest a trending day.
Here's a key tactic. In an uptrend, buy the
pullbacks to the CPR. The CPR acts as support.
Price often bounces here. It's like the market
is taking a breath before the next push up.
In a downtrend, do the opposite. Sell when price
rallies to the CPR. The CPR becomes resistance.
It's where the market often turns back down.
Now, don't just buy or sell blindly at the CPR.
Wait for price to show its hand.
. The more signs you see,
the stronger your trade.
Let's talk about timing.
The CPR works best at certain times.
It's strongest at the market open. This
is when big players make their moves.
They often use the CPR as a reference.
As the day goes on, the CPR can lose some
power. By afternoon, it might not hold as well.
Keep this in mind. Your morning trades might
need different rules than your afternoon ones.
It's all about market psychology. The
CPR shows us where value was yesterday.
Traders remember these levels. And they
often make decisions based on them.
Think about it. If price is above the CPR, traders
feel bullish. They see the market as strong.
This can become a self-fulfilling
prophecy. Buyers step in at support.
Sellers hesitate to go against the trend.
When price is below the CPR, the opposite happens.
Traders turn bearish. They look to sell rallies.
The market develops a downward bias. Again,
this can feed on itself.
This is why the CPR is so
powerful. It taps into mass psychology.
It shows us what the crowd is thinking.
And in trading, understanding the crowd is key.
Consider using the CPR with other indicators.
Trend lines work well. So do moving averages.
The CPR plus a trend line can be a potent combo.
It gives you two reasons to take a trade.
Another pro move is to use multiple timeframes.
The daily CPR is great, but why stop there?
Look at weekly CPRs for bigger moves. Or
zoom in to hourly CPRs for day trading.
Each timeframe adds a layer of insight.
Now, let's talk about market conditions. The
CPR works differently in different markets.
In trending markets, it's a
great tool for riding the waves.
So buy dips to the CPR in uptrends.
And sell rallies to the CPR in downtrends.
In ranging markets, the CPR becomes even more
important. It often defines the range limits.
You can buy at the bottom of
the CPR and sell at the top.
Or look for breakouts when
price finally pushes through.
Here's a subtle point many traders miss. The
CPR can show hidden strength or weakness.
Say price is above the CPR, but struggling to
go higher. This might be a sign of weakness.
The opposite is true too. Price below the CPR
but holding steady might signal hidden strength.
As you use the CPR, you'll develop a feel
for it. You'll start to see patterns.
Some days, the CPR is magnetic.
Price keeps coming back to it.
Other days, it's more of a springboard.
Price touches it and moves away.
But in the end, the CPR is about understanding
market structure. It shows you where the
market thinks value is.
Also, you might want to mark
the Fresh Central Pivot Ranges.
This happens when price doesn't
touch its CPR on a given day.
This untouched CPR becomes a
Fresh CPR for the next few days. This is
similar to supply and demand trading.
Think of the Fresh CPR as a
magnet. It pulls price towards it.
When price doesn't touch the
CPR, it creates an imbalance,
like a gap. And markets don't like gaps.
They try to fill them. This is why Fresh
CPRs are so important. They show
us where price might go next.
On a normal day, price
moves in and out of the CPR.
But sometimes, price makes a big
move. It might go way up or way down.
When this happens, it can miss the CPR
entirely. That's when we get a Fresh CPR.
Now, here's the key. This Fresh
CPR stays important for the next
few days. It's not just a one-day thing.
It keeps its power. That’s why you must
watch it closely, as it could be a
turning point in the next few days.
Say the market drops hard one day.
The next day, price stays
below the CPR. It never touches it.
That CPR is now fresh. It's a target for the
market. Prices often try to climb back to it.
Sometimes, price might get close to the CPR.
It might even have a few wicks that
touch it. But if no full candlesticks
form inside the CPR, it's still fresh.
And why does this matter? Well, because Fresh
CPRs often act as strong support or resistance.
If price is below a Fresh CPR,
that CPR might stop price from going up.
If price is above, the CPR might stop it from
going down. It's like a barrier in the market.
You can use Fresh CPRs in different ways.
Some traders wait for price to reach the Fresh
CPR. Then they look for signs of a bounce or a
reversal. Others use it as a target. If price
is far from the Fresh CPR, they might expect
it to move towards it.
Consecutive candles VSA
The next strategy is based on the concept of
consecutive up or down days in the market.
When a market closes up or down for several
days in a row, it often creates a specific
psychological environment among traders.
There's a natural tendency for people to
believe that a streak can't continue indefinitely.
What goes up must come down, and vice versa.
That’s why many traders use consecutive up or
down days as a basis for their trading decisions.
Now, blindly trading against these
consecutive moves can be risky.
It often means going against the prevailing
trend and momentum, which can lead to
big losses if not done carefully.
That's where this strategy comes in.
Instead of simply betting against any streak of
consecutive up or down days, we focus on those
that occur within a specific market context.
The key to this strategy is understanding
and respecting market structure.
As you probably know, market structure refers
to the overall trend of the market, typically
defined by a series of swing highs and lows.
In an uptrend, you'll see higher highs
and higher lows, while a downtrend is
defined by lower highs and lower lows.
By considering market structure, you can
filter out potentially dangerous trades, and focus
on those with a higher probability of success.
For a long entry, we're looking for
four or more consecutive down days.
These are defined as days where the
closing price is below the opening price.
However, we don't just enter a trade
because we see four red candles in a row.
The key factor is the market structure.
We only consider this setup valid,
if the price hasn't breached the last
swing low in the overall market structure.
This approach essentially turns our strategy
into a trend continuation pullback play.
We're looking for situations where the market
has been in an uptrend, experiences a short-term
pullback (our consecutive down days), but
doesn't break the structure of the uptrend.
This tells us that while there's been
some short-term selling pressure,
the overall bullish trend remains intact.
The entry trigger comes from the next
bullish bar after our streak of down days.
We're looking for a bar that shows momentum,
a relatively large candle body
indicating strong buying pressure.
Low spread candles or those with wicks
on both ends are generally avoided,
as they don't show clear directional momentum.
Volume plays a key role in confirming this setup.
We want to see an
increase in volume on our entry bar.
In fact, the ideal scenario is to see
the highest volume in the past bars.
This high volume tells us that there's
significant interest in the market at this
level, and if it's accompanied by a price rise,
it implies that the buying pressure
is overwhelming the selling pressure.
In Wyckoff analysis terms, this would be
considered a "large effort, large result" day,
indicating strong demand.
For short trades,
the process is essentially reversed.
We look for four or more consecutive up days,
where each day closes above its open.
Again, we consider the market structure.
We only take this setup if the price
hasn't breached the last swing high,
in a downtrend structure.
Our entry trigger is the
next bearish bar, and we want to see it
accompanied by an increase in volume.
The stop loss goes just above the
high of the bearish setup bar.
One of the strengths of this strategy is
its versatility across different timeframes.
While I like to apply it to daily charts, it
can also be effective on shorter timeframes.
However, I would recommend you to stick to
higher timeframes, (4-hour and above).
Another important consideration
is the overall market environment.
This strategy tends to work
best in trending markets.
In choppy markets, the consecutive up or
down pattern may occur more frequently,
but be less meaningful.
Now, here’s an important tip.
When it comes to analyzing volume, understand
that not all volume is created equal.
While we're looking for an increase
in volume on our setup bar,
the context of this volume increase matters.
For example, if you see a large volume spike on
a day with a very small price range, it might
indicate a battle between buyers and sellers,
rather than a clear directional move.
This type of volume is less ideal,
than a volume increase followed by a
decisive price move in our direction.
Another nuance to consider is the relative size
of the consecutive price bars. In an ideal setup,
you'd want to see the magnitude of the moves
diminishing as the consecutive streak continues.
For example, in a downward move, the first
few red candles might be quite large,
but the latter ones should be smaller.
This can indicate that selling pressure is
decreasing, setting up for a potential reversal.
As you gain experience with this strategy,
you might find certain patterns.
For instance, you might notice
that setups that occur near recent support or
resistance levels tend to be more reliable.
Moving averages can be useful
in confirming the overall trend,
and identifying potential
support and resistance levels.
A common approach is to use a combination
of short-term and long-term moving averages.
For instance, you might use a 50-period
and a 200-period moving average.
If the 50-period moving average is above
the 200-period one, it confirms an uptrend,
making long setups more attractive.
Consecutive candles which end up
as a pullback to the moving average
dynamic zone are a great confirmation.
First, you might see a strong trend.
The price is moving up or down steadily.
Then, you start to see candles moving
back toward the moving averages.
These are your consecutive candles. They're
moving against the main trend, but not too far.
As these candles get close to the moving
average, they create what we call a dynamic zone.
This zone is where the price might bounce
off the average, and continue the main trend.
It's dynamic because it moves
as the moving averages move.
When you see several candles in a row
touch this zone without going through it,
that's a strong sign.
It shows the trend is
still strong. The price is respecting the
average as a support or resistance level.
This can be a great time to enter a
trade in the direction of the main trend.