In my experience watching the charts, I noticed
that during a downtrend, the price usually
hits a point where it doesn't want to drop
any more.
And if there's a very high volume bar at this
point of support, it could be a sign that
the decline is ready to reverse.
When I see a huge spike in volume, I know
something important must be happening in the
market.
A lot of volume means many traders are interested
in that part of the chart and are buying or
selling there.
It makes me curious - why are so many people
trading at this price?
I said many times, sometimes analyzing charts
can be confusing if you just look at one thing
like price action or volume alone.
By watching what the price does after that
big volume bar, you can get indications about
what the traders who caused it are trying
to do.
While I was researching about using volume
in combination with price action, I came across
the term "stopping volume."
It's when the volume suddenly spikes really
big and stops the price from going down anymore.
And this is exactly that very big volume bar
I see sometimes after a market has been falling
or increasing for a while.
It seems the big traders are using those moments
to go against the trend and start buying when
the price is low, or start selling when the
price is high.
Signals like this don't happen all the time.
There's lots of ways people combine volume
and price action, but focusing on extreme
volume spikes seems to give one of the best
signals.
When one of those very high volume bars show
up, it changes everything.
The price either levels out instead of keep
falling, or it even starts trending the other
way.
This can be explained by the fact that smart
money saw a chance to buy from everyone who
was selling in a panic.
And watching for signals like this will help
you to recognize when "smart money" is getting
into or out of a market.
One thing I've noticed about volume is that
it often predicts what will happen with the
price better than looking just at the price
alone.
It gives early signs of whether an uptrend
or downtrend is likely to keep going or might
reverse direction soon.
This is related to Wyckoff's law of effort
versus result.
It's the idea that if the volume isn't matching
how much the price is moving, that could mean
momentum is about to change.
So when volume seems high compared to the
little moves in price, it catches my attention.
Sometimes when I see volume changing before
the price, I know a reversal could be near.
Like after a market has gone up a lot, if
the volume stays high while the price just
goes sideways and can't break past old highs,
it makes me think the uptrend might be over.
There's this volume indicator I use to show
if volume is high or low compared to the average.
It's called volume spread for VSA.
With it, I can easily spot the candles that
have very high volume.
When you see red on the volume, something
important is happening under the surface.
When I see one of those huge volume spikes
after prices have been falling, I start wondering
what usually happens next.
In an ideal scenario, it means the downtrend
is over at least for now.
Sometimes that very high volume bar marks
the beginning of an up move.
And I bet a lot of traders who were expecting
the downward to continue were caught on the
wrong side.
Of course, you have to be realist.
Prices don't always turn right away - the
volume spike can also push the market into
moving sideways in a range for a while instead
of continuing down or up.
There's also a chance the declining trend
might keep going even after the big volume
signal.
That would show the sellers still have a lot
of power driving it down.
That's why when I see one of those extreme
volume bars, I draw a channel around it to
see how the price reacts.
Then I only enter if it starts moving higher
or lower from that range.
That helps filter out the bad trades where
price stops moving after the signal.
When I see a candlestick that hasn't moved
prices much but still has regular volume,
that makes sense to me.
But when one of those small range candles
suddenly has super high volume, then it gets
my attention.
Something like a red down candle where the
prices didn't change much from open to close,
but volume spiked way up - that's unusual.
And in a good way.
It's going against common sense because usually
high volume means a big move up or down.
But in this case, even though volume exploded,
prices didn't drop further.
According to Wyckoff's law, the effort (volume)
and result (price movement) aren't matching
up.
To me, that indicates sellers are meeting
more resistance at that level and it's getting
harder for prices to fall below it.
Candlestick patterns like that make me think
the decline could be running out of steam.
It works both ways too - if there's an upwards
green candle with hugely high volume but prices
didn't shoot up that much, it tells me something
different is happening under the surface.
When buyers push volume through the roof but
the range stays small, it looks to me like
sellers are stepping in more at that level
to balance things out.
It's the first hint the upward momentum could
be fading.
Again, just one signal like that isn't enough
- I need to see what prices do after to know
if it really means a trend change is starting.
If the price breaks below that big volume
candle in the future, that would confirm to
me it's time to short sell, since the bulls
aren't in control anymore.
There are 2 ways to trade this very high volume.
To fade the move, or to trade a continuation.
And that depends on the time frame you’re
trading.
I’ve briefly talked about high volume bars
in a past video, and I used to scalp the 1-min
chart with them.
And it’s still a valid approach.
But lately, I’m more inclined to swing trading,
and I had to adjust the method.
The goal is watching how volume interacts
with price and recognizing the early warning
signs like abnormal volume candles before
the trend turns.
So here's how I would explain it from my perspective:
The strategy focuses on capitalizing when
I see one of those massive volume spikes.
It usually works like this:
The price has been falling or rising
Then all of a sudden volume surges way up,
with a huge red volume candle
Then I draw a box around the high and low
of that ultra high volume candle
There are 2 scenarios: that big influx of
trading stops the previous momentum and price
reverses.
Or price continues in the initial direction
more aggressively than before.
If I see prices bounce off that volume candle
and cross back into the box I drew, and breaks
on the other side, that's my signal to jump
in with a buy order.
My stop loss goes below the bottom of the
volume candle box, to protect myself in case
price reverses.
And the first target is to take profits when
I've made at least twice what I risked.
Sometimes these volume signals launch bigger
moves, so there's potential for more gains
too.
So the first strategy is about fading the
move that just happened on the chart using
the volume spike as my guide.
The second strategy is a continuation of that
move.
If I see that price continues in the initial
trend direction, that's my signal to jump
in with a sell order, once price returns to
the box.
I usually don’t sell right after the breakout,
although it’s a valid aggressive strategy.
I usually wait for a retest of the box.
My stop loss goes above box.
And the same first target: at least twice
what I risked.
So the second strategy is about trading a
continuation move, the volume spike adding
fuel to the momentum.
I notice EUR futures has been trading in a
range for a couple of weeks, and then started
dropping again.
Right as it was approaching this demand level,
volume suddenly spiked way up not just once
but twice, second time with a small red candle.
Those very high volume spikes at demand, after
the decline, caught my eye.
Plus the signal price bar had a tight range
even with the high trading.
So I drew a box around that area.
Following the plan we discussed about fading
volume spikes, if EURO price breaks above
the top of my box, that's when I'll hit the
buy button.
My stop goes below demand just in case it
continues falling.
And take profit once it reaches the next major
swing highs.
This was the Daily time frame, so the strategy
is perfect if you have limited time for trading.
If you’re day trading, there will be tons
of huge volume bars that pop up.
But don't try trading each one - focus on
volume spikes that really stand out, especially
near supply and demand levels.
Like this one - we had an up move, then volume
exploded on a small red candle at the high.
If it breaks below the low of our box, a sell
trade with a tight stop, targeting this swing
low looks pretty good.
Here I noticed another potential setup forming.
It looks like a double bottom pattern with
an ultra high volume bar on this candle.
So if it breaks above the top of that candle
after volume surged, I'll take the long entry.
Stop loss under the recent swing low.
And I'll aim to cash out when it hits the
next major high point - that should offer
a very good profit target.
In this example, I noticed a huge spike in
volume with a big green candle.
Since the price range was also large from
open to close, it wasn't displaying the "effort
vs result" imbalance we looked for in the
previous examples.
With high volume matching a strong move up,
my impression was this likely signals a continuation
of the trend rather than reversal potential.
And that is our second approach.
We are trading continuation moves after high
volume spikes.
I drew a box around the signal candle, hoping
for an upward breakout.
As I initially thought, price consolidated
just above the channel I made.
So while this volume spike wasn't an optimal
"stopping volume" setup, observing it helped
reinforce the previous bullish momentum.
As a side note, in case price broke lower,
we could have taken a short trade at the retest
of the box.
Here another trend continuation signal.
Prices had been declining and volume spiked
on a big candle.
With high volume matching the strong down
move, this likely signals a continuation of
the trend.
A box was drawn around the high volume candle.
Since the move down wasn't reversed after
the volume spike, this indeed signaled continuation
of the downtrend.
If prices will retest the bottom of the box
after the initial break lower, a short trade
could be taken aiming for the next swing low.
Another trend continuation signal.
An upward move was underway when volume exploded
on a big green candle.
This suggested buyers were actively testing
that resistance or supply level, indicating
continued buying momentum.
A long trade could be taken after a breakout
above the box drawn around the high volume
candle, with a stop below and profit target
at the next swing high.
Another signal.
A large green candle appeared with matching
high trading volume.
Since effort matched result signaling a strong
move, this pointed to further uptrend continuation
rather than reversal.
So we’re watching for an upward breakout
after price consolidation, and we are betting
that existing bullish momentum will continue,
aiming to ride the trend higher.
Of course, alternatively, a short could be
taken on a retest of the box if prices reversed
its direction.
You just have to be flexible and adaptable.
Now, the market can be noisy, so focusing
on times when trading activity is highest
helps reduce false signals from quiet periods.
Signals seem most reliable for me during key
session overlaps, like London to New York.
Signals formed when volume is normally low,
like overnight, haven't worked as well from
what I've seen.
And for stocks, the first 30 minutes after
open can be choppy.
It helps to wait for volatility to settle
before entering, since that opening surge
of volume can often be misleading
And most importantly, looking for spikes near
evident levels of supply/demand, Fib levels,
VWAP or moving averages.
These areas have the cleanest signals.