Moving averages are among the most popular
and widely used technical tools in trading.
Because they are used by so many traders,
it is worth having them on your charts to
know what other traders are looking at.
Often, in a trend strategy, traders are using
more than one moving average, often a combination
of slow and fast moving averages.
In this video, I will follow this approach
and spin it in a slightly different way to
give you a fresh perspective relating to the
use of moving averages in your trading.
So, a moving average strategy can help you
to not only identify the “average” trend,
but also “trend strength.”
For this reason, you can use more than one
moving average, a slow moving average of 55
period, and a fast moving one, of 21 period.
Why these particular numbers?
Because 21 and 55 are Fibonacci numbers, but
you can backtest and change the values of
the averages as you like.
You just need to learn how to read price action,
using this approach.
So, 21 and 55 moving averages.
This setup will provide a clearer picture
of trend strength on a slower and faster time
frame.
First, let me point out that this is NOT a
crossover strategy.
While such a strategy for moving averages
is perfectly acceptable and valid for some
traders, I prefer to think slightly outside
the box and pay attention to a specific repetitive
pattern when combining a slow and fast period
moving average.
Now, remember that moving averages “indicate”
conditions in the market.
They are not surefire signals that tell you
when to buy or sell, we will use them as a
tactical component within our trading method.
The main goal behind using a shorter period
moving average with a longer one is simple.
We are looking for both perspectives in making
a more informed decision.
While the 21 shorter term moving average will
be located more closely to price resulting
in more touches, the 55 moving average gets
touched less frequently during a normal trending
market.
There exists, however, a different perspective
to following the patterns of slow and fast
moving averages in relation to price action
and I call it the contraction-expansion principle.
The contraction-expansion principle is derived
from the Bollinger bands indicator.
This principle is not based on the moving
averages crossing over, but rather the distance
between the two moving averages as an indication
of the strength of the trend.
When in a strong trend, the price will pull
the 21 MA with it, which in turn will diverge
further away from the 55 MA, causing a larger
gap between the two moving averages.
This is an expansion.
As price pulls back, or transitions into a
sideways pattern, the moving averages will
close in together, often creating a contraction.
We want the price to bounce right off this
dynamic zone, and breakout into a trend.
This example illustrates how the two MAs behave
when the market is trending.
We have a dominant downtrend displaying frequent
but short pullbacks.
Notice how the distance between the two MAs
is fairly consistent to reflect the smoothness
and consistency of the trend itself.
When the market does pull back, it bounces
fairly accurately from the 21 – 55 dynamic
zone, a price action pattern I noticed is
very common during strongly trending conditions.
In this other example, notice this extended
pullback and behavior of the moving averages.
We have here what we call the contraction
of the MAs caused by an extended pullback
into the downtrend.
Essentially, the 21 MA gets pulled back up
with the price near the 50 MA, narrowing the
gap between the MAs.
If the trend is strong enough, and other factors
permit for the trend to continue, we can expect
this pattern of the MAs to release price back
in the direction of the trend.
Keep in mind that like most technical indicators,
moving averages are lagging, which means that
they react to price rather than price reacting
to them.
That also means that the contraction of the
MAs isn’t the cause of the resumption of
the downtrend, but is rather an effect of
price resuming the trend.
Here we’re looking at an uptrend that slowly
transitions into sideways market action.
Each of the pullbacks into the uptrend cause
a slight constriction of the EMAs, resulting
in price shooting back up sharply.
But as we approach potential key resistance
around the round number, an extended pullback
does NOT result in price shooting back up
sharply.
You should note that as price tried to resume
the trend after the last pullback, it stalled
at the crossover point of the two EMAs and
actually reversed back down.
This is usually a very strong indication that
we are either entering a period of sideways
action, preparing for a deeper pullback into
the dominant trend, or entirely reversing
the trend.
So, this is the first step in our strategy.
We analyze price action to find for a contraction
in the moving averages.
Essentially a pullback into the dynamic support
or resistance area, determined by the 2 moving
averages.
By watching how price behaves as it pulls
back to the dynamic zone we can analyze the
momentum present in the current move.
Remember that after a pullback to this area,
we are looking for a sharp move back in the
direction of the trend.
Next, we need to add other aspects into our
analysis.
As said before, when looking for a resumption
of the trend at the dynamic zone, it helps
to analyze if the trend has room to proceed.
Does the dynamic zone also line up with a
round number or a major horizontal support
and resistance zone?
Is the trend headed into a key swing high
/low?
Answering these questions will help you build
an overall understanding of the market and
can help give important signs to fine tune
your entries and exits.
The final step is to trade a breakout, after
the price resumes in the initial direction,
and the price was unable to break below the
dynamic zone of the 2 moving averages.
So we chase a breakout, a momentum move, in
the direction of the trend, after we identified
strength in the market, meaning that the price
found support/resistance at the dynamic zone.
This means we have buying power, in an uptrend,
or selling power, in a downtrend, at the dynamic
zone formed by the 2 moving averages, and
we aim to ride the momentum wave.
But we need a breakout.
We want a trend line breakout or a swing breakout.
In this example we have the dynamic zone,
which basically acts as a magnet, because
when price is too far from it, it tends to
pull price back to this zone.
Then, as the price was unable to go lower,
which is key in our strategy, as we want to
see strength and buying power, we also have
a breakout play here out of the wedge pattern
or triangle pattern indicated by these lines.
So we have a price action based entry.
With this strategy, knowledge of candlestick
patterns and price action is very important.
This is because you will be looking for reversal
candlestick patterns on this area.
Patterns such as engulfing candlesticks and
pin bars are ideal as a trade entry.
Because our strategy is based on a dynamic
zone in the form of the 21 & 55 MA, we will
also use these dynamic areas as our basis
to set our stop loss, below or above it, depending
on the trade we take, in this example, below
it.
This is a conservative stop.
A more aggressive stop is below the most recent
correction.
As for target, I aim for at least 1:1.5 risk
reward ratio.
Here is a short SETUP.
We have the contraction zone here, tested
several times by the price.
Observe that price was unable to go through
this area.
This means we have active sellers in this
zone, ready to push price back down.
We enter short, after the breakout of this
range.
You might ask, why we have to wait for a breakout,
and why not entering short when price was
in the contraction zone.
Well, because in real time, we don’t know
if the price will indeed reject the dynamic
area.
It might push through the zone, and go the
other way.
We need a clear sign or confirmation that
price wants indeed to go lower.
So don’t try to gamble and enter earlier,
without breakout confirmation, because that’s
not the point of this strategy.
So, to be crystal clear, wait for the price
to return to dynamic zone, the 2 moving averages
must not cross each other during this pullback,
and after the price rejects the dynamic zone,
search for a breakout in the direction indicted
by the 2 moving averages.
The best tip I can share with you is to always
pay attention to the slope of the 55 moving
average.
The slope of the 55 moving average can tell
a lot about the strength of a trend.
When the 55 moving average shifts from strongly
pointing upwards during a bull trend, to going
sideways, it can provide early warning signals
about a shift in sentiment.
So pay attention to it.
Here are several examples of valid trades.
This is not a perfect strategy, you will encounter
losing trades and for this reason you could
add your personal spin on it, additional confirmations
or other types of analysis.
Just make sure you don’t overcomplicate
it and stick to the main concepts of this
strategy: rejection of the dynamic zone and
a momentum move in the direction of the trend.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay in touch when we release
new videos.
Until next time.