trading with the trend is one of the
most effective things a trade that
learns and using an engulfing pattern is
one way to get into trending modes just
as momentum is picking up this engulfing
candles indicate a strong shift in
direction and when combined with
observation of the price trending
direction that precedes it
this combination creates the opportunity
for an efficient trading strategy on
engulfed in candle is a candle whose
length completely covers the previous
candle with a close above the high or
below the low of the previous candle if
the closes above the high of the
previous candle then it's a bullish
engulfing candle and the signals buying
pressure while if the closes below the
low of the previous candle
it's a bearish engulfing candle and this
signals a selling pressure in other
words engulfing candle sticks our
reversal patterns a bullish engulfing
candlestick formation implies that
wolves are in full control of bears as
the pattern shows the green body covers
completely the red bodied candle
this shows the readiness of the market
participants to drive the price higher
what about the shadows or the tails do
we include them in our analysis in a
perfect scenario a bullish engulfing
pattern should include the shadows of
the candles a real bullish engulfing
pattern forms when the green body of the
second candle fully engulfed the whole
previous candle including the tails here
the opinions diverge into two schools
one is preaching that the best bullish
engulfing pattern forms when both the
body and the tails are engulfed the
second school believes that for a
bullish engulfing pattern it does not
really matter if the tails are engulfed
or not what matters is only the real
body of the candle my personal style
towards the bullish engulfing pattern is
that the real body is the most important
element it is great if tails are
engulfed but it is not the end of the
world if they are not
sometimes the weeks can offer a degree
of noise in the market that's why I
concentrate on the real bodies I use the
weeks as an indication of where to place
stop losses and potential targets but
for me they are not as important to
validate the bullish engulfing pattern
so here are some great examples of
bullish engulfing patterns I would have
considered as valid as you can see the
red body of the first candle is fully
engulfed by the second green candle the
lower tail of the red candle is not
engulfed by the green candle but for me
this is not important what matters is
the real body of the candle as long as
it's fully engulfed I would classify
this pattern as a bullish engulfing
candle how to read a bullish engulfing
pattern when a bullish engulfing pattern
forms I expect the price to go higher
more market participants are willing to
buy than to sell that particular
instrument that is an indication for
price action traders that more buyers
will join the trend and it will be
extended to new highs here's an
important observation there are many
variations of bullish engulfing patterns
one thing to remember is to learn how to
read the pattern you need to understand
that if you have a red body and then a
series of wind body candles you might
still have a bullish engulfing pattern
what matters is to have the green bodies
engulfing the red body of the previous
candle have a look at this example we
have a two bodied bullish engulfing
pattern so very important it doesn't
matter how many candles you have forming
a bullish engulfing candlestick pattern
what matters is that the body of the red
candle is fully engulfed here we have
multiple candles forming a bullish
engulfing pattern again what matters is
that a red body of the first candle is
covered by one or more consecutive
bullish four green candles if you are a
price action trader don't restrict
yourself to the classic and often
pattern open your eyes and
search for multiple candles forming a
bullish engulfing pattern the beverage
engulfing candlestick pattern is the
complete opposite a bearish engulfing
candlestick this is more bullish candle
followed by a larger red bearish candle
covering or engulfing the small green
candle just like the bullish engulfing
behind the bearish engulfing pattern
stands pure price action what matters is
that a number of sellers outweigh the
number of buyers from a price action
standpoint this means that the balls are
too weak and Bears take control of the
action thus pushing the price down so
bearish engulfing candlestick patterns
are extremely strong continuation
patterns in downtrends the power of the
bearish and bullish engulfing pattern is
in following the trend they are most
powerful when the market takes a break
makes a collection and then forms an
Engel think pattern this is probably the
best place for an engulfing pattern to
form so how to trade using all think
patterns the first step in applying an
engulfing candle strategy is to
determine the dominant trend direction
namely the direction you will trade in
an uptrend is defined by higher highs
and higher lows in price in an uptrend
the advancing waves are larger than the
pullbacks
pushing the market higher during an
uptrend you should take only long
positions buying with the intention of
selling later at the higher price
a downtrend is defined by lower lows and
lower highs in price in a downtrend the
declining waves are larger than the
pullbacks pushing the market lower once
the trend is established you wait for a
pullback waiting for a pullback means
you're getting a better price for the
next wave of the trend when it unfolds
very important if the trend is up watch
for the downward pull back the pullback
should not drop below the low of the
prior pullback as this violates the
rules of an uptrend
if the trend is down watch for an upward
pullback the pullback should not rally
above the high of the prior pullback
this violates the rules of a downtrend
also take note the
fullbacks may move in the opposite
direction of the trend or may just move
sideways so you have to read carefully
the price action with the trend
determined and the pullback occurring
you just wait for the engulfing candle
trade signal during the downtrend wait
until a down candle engulf an up candle
and vice versa for an uptrend no need to
take a bullish engulfing candle in a
downtrend what a bearish engulfing
candle in an uptrend if you do so you're
practically trading against the main
direction once the trade is initiated
losing the engulfed in candle strategy
you could place a stop-loss above the
reason high for a short position and
below the recent low for a long position
Jean coughing candle that occurs after a
pullback in an overall trend is designed
to get you into a trade as the next wave
of the trend is likely to unfold a rule
of thumb is to make sure your winners
are introduced two times bigger than
your losers
therefore measure the distance between
your entry point and where you placed
the stop-loss for example if it's 30
pips or 30 cents that is your risk your
target price should be at least 60 pips
or 60 cents to compensate yourself for
the risk you have taken in technical
analysis there are different tools that
could be used in conjunction with
candlestick patterns the most efficient
ones is the concept of support and
resistance as you can see from this
example the red candle was followed by
two consecutive green bullish candles
forming on top of a major support area
this gives even further confidence to
market participants
and pushes the price higher as you can
see after the bullish engulfing pattern
has formed the next candle is a long
candle and thus marks the bullish bias
of the market in this chart you can see
the opposite scenario there is a
resistance area and the bearish
engulfing pattern as we have already
decided what matters is not the number
of the candles but the ability of the
Bears to engulf the balls thus showing
market participants the readiness of
sellers so trade the pattern when it
occurs at a strong area of support or
resistance that's very important you
cannot just enter a trade every time you
see the engulfing pattern is smart you
support and resistance and trade the
pattern near those levels I also like to
use the 200 EMA in my training analysis
in this example you can see a 200 PMA
and the bullish engulfing pattern that
is a great confluence of factors which
leads to an increased bullish enthusiasm
and here's a tree bodied bearish
engulfing pattern you can see how large
the candle forming the bearish engulfing
is the reason for that is that the
market is indicating a confluence of
bearish factors which lead to a lot of
market participants shorting it after
the completion of the bearish engulfing
pattern there are other tools that could
be used in conjunction with the bullish
engulfing and bearish angles in patterns
like pivot points or Fibonacci levels
don't forget a bullish and bearish
engulfing candle sticks are extremely
powerful when they are used in
conjunction with the existing trend and
are having an extremely strong
connotation especially around support
and resistance areas and moving averages
if you got any value from this make sure
you subscribe click the bell icon so
you'll be notified each time we upload
and give us a like to show your support
until next time