The average true range is a great tool, when
it comes to adapting to the ever-changing
market environment, being a useful indicator
in measuring volatility.
The average true range measures the price
range of an asset – the higher the volatility
the higher the ATR.
The average true range is one of the most
useful indicators because it helps the trader
deciding on where will set a stop loss or
profit target, or if he even should open a
trade in the first place.
The ATR is measured as the greatest of any
of the following 3 metrics:
• the value of the current high minus the
low;
• the distance of the current high minus
the previous close;
• the distance of the current low minus
the previous close
Despite the fact the Average True Range is
not so common among traders, this indicator
can assist them in entering and exiting trades.
The ATR indicator moves up and down as price
movements become larger or smaller.
A new ATR reading is calculated as each time
period passes.
On a one-minute chart, a new ATR reading is
calculated every minute.
On a daily chart, a new ATR is calculated
every day.
All these readings are plotted to form a continuous
line, so traders can see how volatility has
changed over time.
An asset’s range is the difference between
the highest price and lowest price on a given
day.
The Average True Range reveals information
about how volatile the asset actually is.
High ranges reveal high volatility while small
ranges suggest low volatility.
The average true range (ATR) is basically
an exponential moving average of the true
range.
Most common settings of this indicator are
the 14-day ATR.
Depending on their trading objectives or the
time frames, traders can use shorter or longer
inputs of the ATR.
longer ATR will be slower and will generate
fewer trading signals
shorter ATR will generate a higher number
of trading signals and will increase trading
activity
For example:
An average true range of only 5 periods would
not offer a large enough sample to generate
an accurate indication of the true range of
the security
An average true range of 50 periods would
generate a more smooth average true range
on the chart, with fewer and possibly high-quality
signals.
Let’s assume that you are using a swing
trading strategy and you’re using an ATR
with a 50-period input.
You should keep in mind that if you’re trading
on the daily chart, the ATR indicator will
indicate the average volatility over the past
50 days.
However, if you’re trading on the H4 chart,
the ATR indicator will display the average
volatility over the past 50 H4 candles.
So ATR’s value differs from time frame to
time frame, is not a unique value.
How To Read Average True Range Indicator
First, ATR represents a range indicator for
filtering out trades
If you prefer volatile markets or if your
trading strategy is based on huge market moves,
then ATR can filter out markets that are low
in volatility.
Even if you prefer calm, quiet markets the
average true range indicator will help you
to filter out those periods of times that
you would prefer to avoid.
It is important to remember that the ATR does
not measure the market direction.
By tracking the average true range, a trader
cannot identify the prevailing trend on the
market.
The ATR only tracks the magnitude of range,
so it has limited use for generating accurate
trading signals.
It’s a useful indicator only for giving
an idea about how much the price may move
in a defined time frame.
Assume a stock moves $1 a day, on average.
There is no significant news out, but price
has already moved let’s say 30% more than
the average, and now you're getting a buy
signal from a strategy.
The buy signal may be valid but, since the
price has already moved significantly more
than average, betting that the price will
continue to go up and expand the range even
further may not be a prudent decision.
The trade goes against the odds.
Since the price is already up substantially
and has moved more than the average, the price
is more likely to fall and stay within the
price range already established.
While buying once the price is near the top
of the daily range isn't prudent, shorting
is probably a good option, assuming a valid
sell signal occurs.
Now, very important: Entries and exits should
not be based on the ATR alone.
The ATR is a tool that should be used in conjunction
with a strategy to help filtering trades.
For example, in the previous situation, you
shouldn't sell simply because the price has
moved up and the daily range is larger than
usual.
You short only if a valid sell signal occurs,
based on your particular strategy.
Second, the ATR formula will assist you in
setting profit targets
Knowing the average range is extremely useful
since it allows the trader to estimate how
much profit potential there is in the market.
For example, there is no point looking for
200 pips of profit from a trade in a currency
pair, if the average true range for that market
over the last 14 days is only 60 points.
A simpler solution is to halve the 14-day
ATR of the instrument and use this figure
as your profit target.
Thus, after entering a trade in, you could
set yourself a profit target of around 30
points.
How To Trade With Average True Range
ATR Indicator is useful to identify low levels
of volatility
Average True Range doesn’t tell the trader
anything about market direction.
Don’t get confused about its direction.
If the Average True Range is going up on the
chart, that doesn’t mean that the trend
is up.
A viable strategy would be to search for low
volatility levels, in order to find a trade
in the direction of the main trend.
The first thing we need to do is to identify
where the low volatility actually is.
Keep in mind that the low volatility itself
is not enough for a new trend.
This translates into the fact that the current
trend has run out of steam, it doesn’t tell
us that a new trend has begun.
So, we must use the Average True Range in
conjunction with other oscillators or price
action.
For example, in this example we identified
low levels of volatility, but we cannot enter
the market blindly.
A smarter approach would be to wait for the
average true range to exit from that level
and confirm the volatility increase with a
trend line breakout on the chart, or a rising
Stochastic for example, or a divergence on
the RSI or CCI, depending on your strategy.
Second strategy involves using ATR as a trailing
stop loss
A trailing stop loss is a way to exit a trade
if the asset price moves against you but also
enables you to move the exit point if the
price is moving in your favor.
Many day traders use the ATR to figure out
where to put their trailing stop loss.
Here’s how it works: at the time of a trade,
look at the current ATR reading.
A rule of thumb is to multiply the ATR by
two to determine a reasonable stop loss point.
So if you're buying a stock, you might place
a stop loss at a level twice the ATR below
the entry price.
If you're shorting a stock, you would place
a stop loss at a level twice the ATR above
the entry price.
If you're long and the price moves favorably,
continue to move the stop loss to twice the
ATR below the price.
In this scenario, the stop loss only moves
up, not down.
Once it is moved up, it stays there until
it can be moved up again or the trade is closed
as a result of the price dropping to hit the
trailing stop loss level.
The same process works for short trades, only
in that case, the stop loss only moves down.
For example, say you take a long trade at
$10 and the ATR is $0.10.
You would place a stop loss at $9.80 (the
10 cents ATR multiplied by 2).
The price rises to $10.20, and the ATR remains
at $0.10.
The trailing stop loss is now moved up to
$10.
When the price moves up to $10.50, the stop
loss moves up to $10.30, locking in at least
a 30 cent profit on the trade.
This would continue until the price falls
to hit the stop-loss point.
Now, here’s an interesting indicator.
In order to make it easier to visually see
where those stops would be, you could use
the ATR bands.
This indicator will show an upper and lower
band around the price, showing where you can
put your stops (or trail them in open positions).
You can use ATR bands in a number of ways:
• it’s an easy visual way to see where
you can place your stop loss
• you can use a multiple of ATR as your
target
• you can trail your stops alongside the
ATR bands
ATR bands indicator has only 2 variables:
the period and the multiplier.
By default, ATR period is set to 24 with the
rationale that one day has 24 hours so that
way, we’re getting the average price movement
for the past day.
However, if you’re day trading, it could
be useful to have a shorter ATR period, for
example if you want to make recent price volatility
more relevant.
ATR multiplier also depends on your trading
style.
Let’s say your current ATR value is 20 pips
and you use a multiplier of 2, then the bands
will be 40 pips on each side.
If you use a multiplier of 3, the bands will
be 60 pips on each side.
There is no universal rule for setting stops
according to the ATR.
It depends on each trader’s individual risk
tolerance while also allowing the trade “breathing
room” to develop.
So backtest and choose the settings that are
in line with your strategy.
As you probably know, one of the most important
aspects of trading and investing is having
a disciplined risk management process.
Because the ATR does not measure direction
and simply considers the magnitude of range,
it has limited utility as a means for generating
trading signals.
But it is a useful tool for providing an idea
about how much a market may move and will
help you to apply a proper position size and
a proper stop placement.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support, subscribe
to our channel and click the bell icon to
stay notified when we release new videos.
Until next time.