Every trader needs to answer four key questions!
• What direction the price is trending?
• How far is the trend likely to go?
• Where can you enter a trade with the best
risk reward ratio?
• And most importantly, at what point you
are definitely wrong?!
Elliott Wave Theory answers all these questions.
The Wave principle helps to:
• Spot high probability trade opportunities.
• Improve the trade entry.
• With a solid money management, including
stop losses and targets
Today I’m sharing several crucial tips that
will definitely improve your trading, no matter
if you use Elliott method or you simply decide
to use price action.
So, if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
Write down the main Elliot Rules!
Nothing is more important in Elliot Wave analysis
than respecting the Elliott wave rules.
Each wave pattern has a distinct set of rules,
which have to be fulfilled in order to make
the pattern valid.
If certain requirements are not met, some
other pattern must be unfolding… simple
as that.
It is therefore very useful to write down
all Elliott wave rules, so that you can quickly
check and confirm that your wave labeling
is indeed correct.
Wave 2 never pulls back more than 100% of
wave 1, if it does this, the trend cannot
be confirmed.
Wave 3 cannot be the shortest of the 3 impulse
waves, when we see a third wave that is too
short it means that it is not a correct wave
count.
Therefore, the next waves remain part of the
third wave rather than forming waves 4 and
5.
Wave 4 cannot go below the price of Wave 1,
if wave point 4 breaks below the wave point
1 it clearly tells us that this is not part
of the fourth wave, instead it carry’s on
within wave 3.
Trade only in the direction of impulse waves
Prices move in impulsive and corrective waves.
Knowing which kind of wave is likely underway
currently and which type recent waves were,
will help you forecast what the price is likely
to do next.
An impulse wave is a large price move and
has associated trends.
If it’s an uptrend, it keeps reaching higher
prices because the upward moves are larger
than the downward moves that occur in between
the large upward waves.
Corrective waves are the smaller waves that
occur within a trend.
For better results, you should trade in the
direction of the impulse waves because the
price is making the largest moves in that
direction.
Impulse waves provide a better chance of making
a large profit than corrective waves do.
You should use corrective waves to enter into
a trend trade, in an attempt to capture the
next big impulse wave.
Buy during pullbacks or corrective waves during
uptrends, and ride the next impulse wave as
it takes the price higher.
Sell during corrective waves in a downtrend
to profit from the next impulse wave down.
The idea of impulsive and corrective waves
is also used to determine when a trend is
changing direction.
If a market shows big moves upward with small
corrective waves in between and then a much
larger downward move occurs, this signifies
the uptrend may be over.
Since impulses occur in the trending direction,
a big downward move larger than prior corrective
waves and as large as the upward impulse waves
indicates the trend is reversing.
Use PROTECTIVE STOPS below Wave 2 and Wave
The stop loss always been the key to trading,
this is the factor which will make you lose
or make money.
There are 2 particular rules that cannot be
violated within the Elliott wave model.
Wave 2 cannot retrace more than wave 1.
Wave 4 cannot enter the price territory of
wave 1.
Using these rules, Elliott method will help
you placing optimal protective stops.
For instance, when trading Wave 3, you will
know that Wave 2 cannot go below the low of
Wave 1; this means that the best location
to place a stop-loss order will be below the
low of Wave 1.
Or, Wave 4 cannot overlap with Wave 1; this
means that when trading Wave 5, the best point
to place a stop loss would be below the high
of Wave 1.
The process is simple, you identify a possible
Elliot cycle, you immediately check the rules
to be sure all conditions are met, you enter
during an impulsive wave and you place your
protective stops accordingly.
You can eliminate much of the confusion by
applying these rules and you’ll also minimize
your losses to a known amount.
Learn to define the corrective structures
accurately
So, the best trades happen if you can catch
an impulsive Wave early on.
But in order to catch those waves, you need
to define the corrective structures accurately.
According to Elliott, there are 21 corrective
ABC patterns ranging from simple to complex.
You don’t have to memorize all 21 types
of corrective ABC patterns because they are
just made up of three very simple easy-to-understand
formations.
The first one is the Zig-Zag Formation.
Zig-zag formations are very steep moves in
price that go against the predominant trend.
Wave B is typically shortest in length compared
to Waves A and C.
These zig-zag patterns can happen twice or
even three times in a correction.
The second one is The Flat Formation.
Flat formations are simple sideways corrective
waves.
In flats, the lengths of the waves are GENERALLY
equal in length, with wave B reversing the
wave A move and wave C undoing the wave B
move.
And finally, The Triangle Formation.
Triangle formations are corrective patterns
that are bound by either converging or diverging
trend lines.
Triangles are made up of 5-waves that move
against the trend in a sideways fashion.
These triangles can be symmetrical, descending,
ascending, or expanding.
Now, a lot of the pre-trade analysis has to
go into knowing what kind of corrective pattern
is unfolding so that you know when it will
be complete.
This will have a two-fold benefit of protecting
you from entering trades too early, as well
as not missing the boat when price goes into
an impulsive trend continuation.
Look for divergence at the end of corrective
waves
If you followed my channel, you must have
noticed how often I use the word “divergence”,
usually when I’m expecting a trend reversal.
A divergence occurs when the price reaches
a new extreme, while the line of the indicator,
does not.
It means that despite the new high or low,
the current trend is exhausted and might be
about to end soon.
Oscillator indicators are the best tool to
spot a divergence.
I personally prefer to add the Stochastic
or MACD histogram when I’m counting waves.
Now, the easiest point from which you start
a wave count would be at a swing low or at
the end of a correction.
As a clue, corrections usually end in diagonals.
At this point, divergences can be found on
momentum indicators, just like in this example.
Learn the Relationship between Fibonacci Ratios
in Elliott Wave Patterns
The application of Fibonacci ratios are an
integral part of Elliot Wave analysis.
Combining The Elliott Wave structure with
Fibonacci offers high probability turning
points and where the next price move will
likely terminate.
Therefore, counting waves and applying the
appropriate Fibonacci levels is an essential
step for every Elliott Wave trader.
Here are the common relationships between
Elliot Wave and Fibonacci levels.
It is important to write down or print these
levels, so that you know how price action
is most likely play out.
Wave 2 – 50.0%, or 61.8% of Wave 1.
Wave 3 – 161.8%, 261.8% of Wave 1
Wave 4 – 38.2%, 50.0%.
61.8 of Wave 3
Wave 5 – 100% of Wave 1 or 161.8% of Wave
4.
Projecting the end of Wave 3
If you don’t like using Fibonacci, you can
use simple price action to trade and find
projections for Elliot Waves.
To begin with, you can draw a channel as soon
as waves 1 and 2 are finished.
Connect the origin of wave 1 and the end of
wave 2.
Then draw a parallel line from the top of
wave 1.
This channel is considered as an absolute
minimum target for the 3rd wave under development.
If the 3rd wave can’t break through the
upper line or fails to reach it, then the
trend is weak.
Furthermore, the lower trend line of the channel
serves as a stop-loss.
When this baseline gets broken, there is a
strong probability that wave 2 gets more complex,
thus wave 3 has not begun yet.
Keep in mind that wave 3 is normally the strongest
wave and often will go far beyond the upper
trend line.
Projecting the end of Wave 4
As soon as wave 3 has finished you can draw
a channel connecting the end of wave 1 and
wave 3 with a trend line and drawing a parallel
line from the end of wave 2.
By doing this you can project a target for
wave 4.
Keep in mind that normally the baseline from
wave 3 will be broken slightly by the price
action of wave 4.
If wave 4 doesn’t come near the baseline
at all, this is a sign of strong trend.
So you draw a trend line from the beginning
of Wave 2 to the end of Wave 3.
Project a parallel line off the end of Wave
2.
You want to find out the end point of Wave
4, so that you can trade the next impulsive
wave.
Projecting the end of Wave 5 - Method 1
As soon as wave 4 has finished you can draw
a channel connecting the end of wave 2 and
wave 4 with a trend line and draw a parallel
line from the end of wave 3 and project upward
to wave 5.
This is your target for wave 5.
This would be for a normal wave 5.
An extended wave 5 would push higher.
It the price fails to hit the projected trend
line to wave 5 then the market is weak and
you should look for a sell-off.
Projecting the end of Wave 5 - Method 2
Most of the time, wave 3 is the strongest
wave showing a very fast acceleration relative
to wave 1 and 5.
If wave 3 indeed shows a nearly vertical rise
or decline, then draw a trend line-connecting
wave 2 and 4 and draw a parallel line from
wave 1.
This parallel line will cut through wave 3
and will target wave 5.
From my experience, this is a very valuable
channel.
Liquidity is essential for consistent Elliott
Wave behavior
Liquid markets are, by definition, traded
by a large crowd of traders.
Although it is nearly impossible to determine
what a single trader will do, it is possible
to estimate a statistical probability of what
a large crowd of traders will do.
Mass crowd psychology comes into play, the
result of mass human emotion as it swings
from fear to hope to greed, and back again.
Liquidity is essential for consistent Elliott
Wave behavior.
Stocks such as those on the S&P or NASDAQ
and currencies, for example, show strong and
dependable Elliott Wave patterns.
These markets are driven by mass psychology,
or human emotion.
They are truly liquid, driven by supply and
demand.
Conversely, thinly traded markets do not show
consistent Elliott behavior.
This is also the reason why markets that are
manipulated by a few large traders, institutions
or governments are often poor candidates for
Elliott analysis.
So be careful on which markets you decide
to apply your Elliot wave analysis.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.