Developed by Larry Williams, the ultimate
oscillator is a momentum indicator designed
to capture momentum across three different
timeframes.
The multiple timeframe objective seeks to
avoid the pitfalls of other oscillators.
Many momentum oscillators surge at the beginning
of a strong advance, only to form a bearish
divergence as the advance continues.
This is because they are stuck with one timeframe.
The ultimate oscillator attempts to correct
this fault by incorporating longer timeframes
into the basic formula.
The ultimate oscillator combines short-term,
intermediate-term, and long-term price action
into one oscillator and attempts to give overbought
and oversold signals, potential buy and sell
readings, and confirmations of price action
as well as divergences that might warn of
future price reversals.
The default settings of the ultimate oscillator
is 7,14,28.
First, the oscillator calculates buying pressure
to determine the overall direction of price
action.
Second, it measure buying pressure relative
to the true range.
This tells us the true magnitude of a gain
or loss.
Third, it creates averages based on the three
timeframes involved (7,14,28).
Fourth, create a weighted average of the three
averages.
By combining three separate time periods,
short-term (usually 7-period), intermediate-term
(usually 14-period), and long-term (usually
28-period), the ultimate oscillator tends
to peak when price peaks.
The intermediate and long-term also include
the short-term time period; thus, the short-term
period is weighted more heavily in the ultimate
oscillator equation.
How to interpret the ultimate oscillator.
Buying pressure and its relationship to the
true range forms the base for the ultimate
oscillator.
Williams believes that the best way to measure
buying pressure is simply subtracting the
close from the low or the prior close, whichever
of the two is the lowest.
This will reflect the true magnitude of the
advance, and hence, buying pressure.
The ultimate oscillator rises when buying
pressure is strong and falls when buying pressure
is weak.
The ultimate oscillator measures momentum
for three distinct timeframes.
The second timeframe is double compared to
the first, and the third timeframe is double
compared to the second.
Even though the shortest timeframe carries
the most weight, the longest timeframe is
not ignored, which should reduce the number
of false divergences.
This is important because the basic buy signal
is based on a bullish divergence and the basic
sell signal is based on a bearish divergence.
By using the weighted average of three different
timeframes the indicator has less volatility
and fewer trade signals compared to other
oscillators that rely on a single timeframe.
Also, I prefer this indicator because the
ultimately oscillator generates fewer divergence
signals than other oscillators due to its
multi-timeframe construction, so the market
noise is greatly reduced.
The ultimate oscillator is a range-bound indicator
with a value that fluctuates between 0 and
100.
Similar to the relative strength index (RSI),
levels below 30 are deemed to be oversold,
and levels above 70 are deemed to be overbought.
Trading signals are generated when the price
moves in the opposite direction as the indicator,
and are based on a three-step method.
With many momentum oscillators correlating
too heavily to near-term price movements,
Williams developed the ultimate oscillator
to incorporate multiple timeframes to smooth
out the indicator's movements and provide
a more reliable indicator of momentum, with
fewer false divergences.
False divergences are common in oscillators
that only use one timeframe, because when
the price increases the oscillator increases.
Even if the price continues to rise the oscillator
tends to fall forming a divergence even though
the price may still be trending strongly.
Now, how to trade with the ultimate oscillator
In order for the indicator to generate a buy
signal, Williams recommended a three-step
approach.
First, a bullish divergence must form.
This is when the price makes a lower low but
the indicator is at a higher low.
Second, the first low in the divergence (the
lower one) must have been below 30.
This means the divergence started from oversold
territory and is more likely to result in
an upside price reversal.
Third, the ultimate oscillator must rise above
the divergence high.
The divergence high is the high point between
the two lows of the divergence.
Williams created the same three-step method
for sell signals.
First, a bearish divergence must form.
This is when the price makes a higher high
but the indicator is at a lower high.
Second, the first high in the divergence (the
higher one) must be above 70.
This means the divergence started from overbought
territory and is more likely to result in
a downside price reversal.
Third, the ultimate oscillator must drop below
the divergence low.
The divergence low is the low point between
the two highs of the divergence.
In this example, we have classic buy signal,
which met all conditions.
First, we have the bullish divergence forming
between the indicator and security price.
This means the ultimate oscillator formed
a higher low as price recorded a lower low.
The higher low in the oscillator shows less
downside momentum.
Second, the low of the bullish divergence
was below 30.
This is to ensure that prices are somewhat
oversold or at a relative extremity.
Third, the oscillator rose above the high
of the bullish divergence.
Now, technical analysis, requires a little
flexibility and in some cases I don’t like
to wait that much for the oscillator to increase
above the high of the bullish divergence.
An alternative entry I often use is a move
above 50 level.
The chart shows another bullish divergence
signal.
The ultimate oscillator moved to oversold
levels (below 30) as the price fell quite
aggressively.
While the price moved to new lows in, the
indicator held above its prior low and above
30.
The breakout above this high confirmed the
bullish divergence signal.
Also notice that that we have other breakouts
above resistance at a later date.
Even those who missed the initial signal got
a second chance as the price pulled back and
again broke resistance.
Let’s analyze a sell signal.
First, a bearish divergence forms between
the indicator and price.
This means the ultimate oscillator forms a
lower high as price posted a higher high.
The lower high in the oscillator shows less
upside momentum.
Second, the high of the bearish divergence
is above 70.
This is to ensure that prices are somewhat
overbought or at a relative extremity.
Third, the oscillator falls below the low
of the bearish divergence to confirm a reversal.
As in the case of a buy signal, if you want
an earlier entry, pull the trigger when the
ultimate oscillators moves below its 50 level.
And here’s another example.
The stock surged to a new high, but the ultimate
oscillator failed to confirm this high and
formed a lower high.
Also, notice that the indicator became overbought
here.
The breakout below the divergence low confirmed
the bearish signal, and the price declined
sharply afterwards.
Now, I mentioned before that i prefer to skip
the third step, the final confirmation, meaning
the breakout of the divergence high or low,
and use the oscillator’s 50 level as entry.
This approach isn’t always the right decision.
The example shows an unconfirmed bearish signal.
First, the ultimate oscillator became overbought
as the stock moved to new highs, the indicator
posted lower highs.
We have a bearish divergence but the indicator
never broke its divergence low for confirmation.
An entry based on the 50 level would have
brought a loss, because the price reversed
and continued its uptrend.
So, it’s up to you to decide which entry
you prefer.
If you want to be conservative, wait for the
divergence high or low to be broken.
If you want a more aggressive entry, use the
50 level crossover.
Here are some important observations regarding
timeframes.
The ultimate oscillator can be used on intraday,
daily, weekly or even monthly charts.
It is sometimes necessary to adjust its settings
to generate overbought or oversold readings,
which are part of the buy and sell signals.
Some stocks or securities may not generate
overbought or oversold readings with the default
settings (7,14,28).
You need to increase sensitivity with shorter
timeframes.
If you plot the oscillator and there are no
overbought or oversold readings, you could
try shortening the timeframe to (4,8,16) to
increase sensitivity.
The opposite is true for securities and stocks
with high volatility.
It is sometimes necessary to lengthen the
timeframes to reduce sensitivity and the number
of signals.
The ultimate oscillator, like all indicators,
has its own limitations.
While the multiple timeframe trading method
for the indicator may help eliminate some
poor trades, it also eliminates many good
ones.
Second you must take into account the fact
that a divergence is not present at all price
reversal points.
The market can reverse without any divergence.
Also, a reversal won't always occur from overbought
or oversold territory.
Maybe the most important note is that waiting
for the oscillator to move above the divergence
high (bullish divergence) or below the divergence
low (bearish divergence) could mean poor entry
point as the price may have already run significantly
in the reversal direction.
That’s why I told you I try to skip this
step, and enter earlier in my trades.
So, as with all indicators, the ultimate oscillator
shouldn't be used in isolation, but rather
as part of a complete trading plan.
And such a plan must include other forms of
analysis such as price action, other technical
indicators, and even fundamental analysis.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like to show your support and make
sure you subscribe and click the bell icon
to stay notified when we release new videos.
Until next time.