Look at this chart. Every textbook says this
break of structure is a buy signal. So why
did price reverse and wipe out every single
buyer a few bars later? It's because you've
been taught to look at a one-dimensional
model. The market structure you learned
is a lie. Or at least it's only one-third
of the truth. Let's fix this right now.
My market structure analysis is based
on three pillars: technical analysis,
real-time price action reading, and supply-demand
imbalances. The synergy between them is powerful.
Market structure begins with trends. You
have an uptrend when price forms higher
highs and higher lows. You have a downtrend
when it prints lower lows and lower highs.
An uptrend in day trading might last for a
few hours before reversing or stalling. A
small series of bullish candles that surpass
a previous swing high is often labeled as a
break of structure on the upside, affirming
the bullish scenario. On the other hand,
if price consistently fails to make new highs
and eventually breaks under a last critical low,
you conclude that sellers have taken control.
That is the essence of a structural downtrend.
In an uptrend, buyers must be pushing
the market beyond each prior pivot to
maintain upward structure. But structure
can shift quickly on intraday charts. A
single wave of strong selling
might test your assumptions.
Two vital concepts in advanced chart reading
are break of structure and change of character.
A break of structure often occurs when the
market pushes through a prior swing point
that was aligned with the existing trend.
In a bullish scenario, if the price flips
above a prior high and closes convincingly up
there, the structure is broken to the upside,
strengthening the existing uptrend. You might
see these breaks on a 5-minute chart multiple
times in a bullish day. Each time they
confirm that buyers remain in control.
A change of character is more telling
because it signals a potential shift in
balance from buyers to sellers or vice
versa. In an uptrend, the hallmark of
a change of character is a failure to form a
new higher high followed by a decisive break
of a key higher low. This suggests that the
once dominant buyers are losing their grip.
If a price dips below a major low, it
may be flipping from bullish to bearish.
Markets do not always trend. Sometimes they stall
or move sideways in a tight range. This is often
called consolidation or a sideways market.
You might see a zone where for hours price
bounces between a support and a resistance
with no real net progress for either side.
Consolidation can come before a breakout that
resumes the prior trend or sparks a reversal.
It can also happen in the middle of the day when
volume drops or the market waits for a scheduled
event. For day traders, reading consolidation is
crucial, especially if you seek momentum moves.
Price action is the raw record of trades hitting
the market. Some see it as candlesticks with wicks
and real bodies. Others see it in terms of tick
bars or footprint candles. However you visualize
it, price action is the best measuring instrument
of immediate buying or selling pressure.
Many advanced techniques revolve around watching
how price reacts near key supply or demand zones.
If the price snaps up quickly off a demand region,
you know there is healthy buying interest. If
it struggles to push beyond the supply zone on
repeated attempts, that suggests strong sellers.
Price action is about letting the chart speak,
not overshadowing it with lagging indicators.
Identification of advanced price patterns
can refine your skill. For instance, you
might see a short-term wedge forming in a broader
uptrend. The wedge might break to the downside,
generating a quick drop that retests a prior
demand area. Another scenario is a fake breakout
pattern where price runs above a known high, but
then immediately closes below it. These patterns
can be powerful signals for turning points. They
are not guaranteed, but they do highlight areas
where a surge of late buyers or sellers got
trapped, often fueling the upcoming reversal.
Advanced price patterns revolve around tracking
expansions or impulses, and how they fade into
pullbacks or complex corrections. A classic
example is a strong impulse wave up followed
by a three-wave correction, then another impulse
wave up. If you confirm that each wave is printing
new breaks of structure on lower time frames,
you stay confident in the overall direction.
Another intriguing idea is to watch for pockets
of liquidity above old highs or below old lows.
Price might sweep these levels for liquidity, then
reverse swiftly. Such patterns occur regularly
intraday, especially if there are stops placed
behind those pivot points. One approach is to
wait for a break of structure in the direction of
the trend, then trade the retest. Another approach
is to watch for a potential change of character
near a known supply zone. If you see that
a change of character aligns with a cluster of
short-term double tops, that can signal a shift.
Supply and demand revolve around the idea
that major imbalances cause dramatic price
impulses. A supply zone typically forms where
price consolidated briefly before a big drop,
suggesting that large sellers are positioned
there. A demand zone is the mirror image
where price consolidated prior to a rapid
climb. If price later returns to that zone,
you might see the same reaction from participants.
In an intraday context, these zones might appear
on a 15-minute chart or even a 5-minute chart if
the swings were particularly strong.
They are not indefinite. Over time,
the orders that created the reaction
can get absorbed or fully executed,
meaning the zone might lose its potency.
But in many cases, you will see repeated
bounces or rejections at these zones, making
them prime locations for structured trades.
Some traders like to label the zone
with the highest close or open within
the consolidation. Others take the entire range
of the basing candles. The specifics can vary,
but the principle is consistent. Find the
small sideways or subtle area where price
paused before launching a big rally
or decline. If a rally was abrupt,
that implies strong buying committed in that
base. If a drop was abrupt, that suggests intense
selling. When price retests the zone, watch the
raw price action for acceptance or rejection.
Sometimes the retest leads to
another strong bounce in the
original direction. Other times the zone fails,
which can itself be an actionable breakout move
that signals the supply or demand is exhausted.
Supply and demand zones blend seamlessly
with the idea of break of structure and
change of character. If you see a downtrend
with consecutive break of structure events and
now price is approaching a known supply zone,
your bias might be to fade any bullish spikes
into that zone. If you suspect an uptrend is
losing steam and you see price form a change
of character around a previously established
supply zone, it can be a prime short opportunity.
Support and resistance can be more dynamic and
advanced than just drawing a line at a pivot. An
advanced trader notices if support and resistance
lines shift intraday, forming micro channels or
pivot flips. For example, a strong supply zone
can turn into support if price eventually breaks
above it and finds new buyers on a retest.
This shift can be observed from the magnitude
and speed of the breakout. If price soared
from that supply zone, there is a good chance
it might function as support on the retest,
effectively flipping from supply to demand.
A strong demand zone can turn into resistance
if price eventually breaks below it and finds
new sellers on a retest. If price broke
that demand zone, there is a good chance
it might function as resistance on the
retest, flipping from demand to supply.
Trend lines can be a sophisticated lens for day
traders to see dynamic support or resistance,
especially when combined with supply and demand.
Suppose you have a rising channel and inside that
channel is an untested demand zone from a prior
breakout. If price returns to the demand zone,
right where the channel's trend line meets,
you have a confluence of signals that might
yield a strong bounce. That provides a
structured approach for trade planning.
If price slices through that confluence, it
might be a strong sign of a break in structure,
warning you that the uptrend is concluding or
that supply overcame that pocket of demand.
Volume analysis will help you in certain
contexts. For instance, you may watch how
volume spikes at the moment price approaches a
known supply zone. If that spike aligns with a
major wick rejecting the zone, that suggests
a wave of sell orders overcame buyers.
A footprint chart helps us see what is happening
inside those moves by showing the volume that
trades at each price level during each candle.
That way, we do not just see a candle's high
or low. We also see how many orders occur on
the buying side and the selling side at each
tiny step of the candle. This detailed view can
help you understand absorption and imbalances.
Absorption is when large traders soak up orders,
stopping price from moving. Imbalances
happen when there is much stronger
buying or selling at a particular price
range, driving price in a direction.
In a footprint chart, each candle is split into
rows for each price level. You can see how many
contracts were traded on the bid side (the
sellers) and on the ask side (the buyers).
This can paint a vivid picture of whether buyers
or sellers are more aggressive at certain price
increments. When there are large blocks of sellers
at a certain price, you often see a big number on
the bid column at that price. If there is strong
buying, you see a larger number on the ask column.
For day traders, footprint charts can
be a revelation. They add a whole new
layer to market structure. They can
show if there is absorption at a high,
meaning there is a strong group of
sell orders that keeps soaking up buys,
so price cannot break through that same high.
Or perhaps we see an imbalance of eager buyers
stepping in at a certain low, pushing price
upward. By looking inside the candle, you
discover that price is not just a line or a bar.
It is the result of orders at each small step.
If at a critical swing low, we see an
extremely large cluster of buy orders
that appear to stop further drops, that might
warn us that the market is forming a new higher
low and could push up again. Whenever price
approaches a supply or demand zone, you can
look at the footprint structure to see if large
traders are unloading or absorbing positions.
Absorption is when the market tries to move
further in one direction like going up but
meets a large opposing force like big sell orders.
Those big sell orders soak up all the buying that
tries to push price higher, so price cannot really
break up. Sometimes after that we see a reversal.
Imbalances are when one side is heavily stronger
than the other. You might see large numbers on the
buy side (the ask side) with only small numbers
on the bid side at the same price level, or
vice versa. This market order flow can lead to a
swift move in the direction of the stronger force.
You see, markets are always about balancing
out how many are willing to buy and how many
are willing to sell. When that balance is tilted
heavily in one direction, price moves quickly.
On footprints, an imbalance can show up when
you see a big difference in the volume between
the bid and ask at a specific price. That is
a bullish imbalance because it suggests a lot
more people hit the offer. They were
eager to buy. If that keeps happening
across multiple price levels in a single
candle or a short sequence of candles,
you know that buyers are strongly in control.
The price often shoots up. Conversely,
a big imbalance on the bid side is a heavy
wave of sells that can drive price down.
Now, let's connect absorption and
imbalances to the overall structure.
Suppose you have an uptrend. You watch
the footprints near each pullback. This
is where the market dips temporarily
but then tries to continue up. If every
time the price dips you see big
buy imbalances on the footprint,
that signals the path is likely to keep
going upward. The structure remains bullish.
Or suppose price tests a previous swing high.
Now you see heavy absorption from sellers at
that high. Price tries to break but cannot hold
above that level. The footprint reveals that the
market is not accepting higher prices. A normal
chart might just show a candle that poked above
and came back below, but the footprint
confirms that big sellers were standing
in the way. That can hint at a false breakout
or a potential reversal if it keeps happening.
Imagine you see a strong uptrend making higher
highs. Suddenly, it tries to push to a new high
but prints less buy imbalance than before.
Actually, you notice a spike in absorption on
the sell side. If the market fails to hold above
that old high and quickly returns below, forming
a lower swing high, you may have an early sign of
a structure shift. The footprint is telling you
that the imbalance from buyers is not as strong.
Plus, sellers are absorbing attempts to break
upward. That is possibly the start of a downtrend
if the price pushes below a previous swing low.
So, let's recap. You will find that
repeated strong buy imbalances lead
to uptrends. Repeated strong sell
imbalances lead to downtrends,
and absorption near a prior top or bottom
signals a potential turning point. The
advantage is that you do not have to guess. You
see how many trades occurred at each price. So
if a level is truly being defended by big
orders, it becomes obvious on the chart.
The best day trading strategies unify structural
and supply-demand logic with real-time price
action cues. You don't want to rely on a
single pattern or a single zone. Instead,
try to piece together the trend context. Watch
for a break of structure or a retest near a zone.
Confirm on your footprint chart that buyers or
sellers are stepping in. Then pull the trigger.
This market is trending down strongly
overnight. Coming into the London session,
the price forms a small consolidation and
then continues down, showing multiple breaks
of structure to the downside. You then identify
a supply zone that sparked a strong move lower.
When price retests that zone, you watch
your footprints. If you see high levels
of selling aggression at that zone, it
might confirm the continuation short.
While the approach is universal, your personal
plan will depend on how frequently you like to
trade. Some advanced day traders prefer
waiting for quick scalp opportunities
around supply-demand interactions.
Others might hold positions longer,
letting the entire session's trend play
out as multiple break of structure events
reaffirm that they are on the right
side. During a day, the structure can
shift from expansion to consolidation, from
bullish to bearish, so you need to adapt.
Setting up an intraday trade around the
market structure might go like this. First,
you confirm the daily bias from a slightly
higher time frame, such as a 30-minute chart,
to see if there is a dominant bullish or
bearish theme. You identify major supply
and demand levels from that perspective. You
then keenly watch for how price interacts with
those zones on your shorter time frame, maybe
a 5-minute one. If you see an emerging break of
structure aligned with your bias, you look for
confirmation in price action. That might be a
strong bullish candle retesting and rejecting
a prior pivot, or a footprint reading showing
buyers overwhelming sellers. You enter with the
logic being purely structural. Then if you see a
sign that structure might be shifting again, like
a minor change of character, you exit or adjust.
From a purely technical standpoint, you can
manage a trade by letting structure guide stops
and targets. For example, if you go long after a
bullish break of structure, you can place a stop
below the higher low that preceded your entry.
If the market is truly continuing its uptrend,
that low should not be violated. For profit
targets, you might look at the next major
supply zone or the next likely area for a
structural shift. Once price gets there,
you re-evaluate. If you see footprints and
price action still supportive of your thesis,
you might trail the stop. If not,
you can exit, locking in your gains.
In your market structure analysis, one pitfall
is to read too many signals into every micro
swing. You see, intraday charts can be noisy
and you do not want to leap at the first small
break of structure if it is overshadowed by the
larger trend or the possibility of a false break.
So, please resist the urge to jump in after
a massive directional candle. Instead,
wait to see if that move aligns with a
confirmed break of structure or a retest.
Another pitfall is ignoring the bigger
picture. If the market is in a dominant
trend that has shown no true sign of
reversal, a small change of character
on a very low time frame might trick
you into a premature position. Focusing
too narrowly on each wave can cause constant
second-guessing. Instead, you want to keep a
layered approach that spans multiple time frames
aligned with major supply and demand references.
Small refinements matter for day
traders. One approach is to watch a
15-minute chart for structure while using
the 5-minute footprint to refine entries.
You might see the 15-minute chart break
structure for a bullish push, then switch to
the 5-minute to see if footprint volumes confirm
a surge in buyer activity at the retest zone.
Support and resistance can morph as price
moves. A region that was tested multiple
times might weaken or it might accumulate more
orders. You can watch if each subsequent retest
sees smaller or bigger bounces. If bigger bounces
occur, that suggests increased demand or supply
stepping in. If it starts to flatten,
perhaps you are on the verge of a break.
Scaling in or out can be a viable technique
if you regularly trade intraday during strong
trends where you are confident of a continuation.
Rather than entering your full size all at once,
you might start with a partial position at
the initial break of structure. Then if price
retests that break level with footprints
confirming a surge in your direction,
you add more. You can exit part of your position
at the next pivot or supply-demand zone. If the
structure remains strongly with you, you hold
the rest to see if a bigger move develops.
Your framework should revolve around
consistent steps and definitions. For instance,
how exactly do you define a break of structure
for your time frame? Is it a full close beyond
the level or just a wick? How many candles do you
wait to confirm a zone retest? You might require
at least two consecutive closes beyond a swing
high to call it a bullish break, for example.
Or you might say a supply zone is
only valid if price left it with a
strong momentum candle. By clarifying these
definitions, you reduce impulse decisions.
Here are some rules. First, officially define how
you recognize an uptrend or downtrend. Second,
clarify break of structure triggers for bullish or
bearish continuation. Also specify the difference
between potential change of character
patterns and the confirmed reversals,
and try to map out supply-demand
zones in a consistent manner.
So here is a generalized step-by-step approach to
day trade setups using market structure. First is
the pre-market prep. Mark overnight highs
and lows. Identify any high-impact supply
or demand zones left on the chart from the
previous session. Then is the trend check.
Check the bigger time frame, the 30-minute
or 1-hour, to see if you have an established
uptrend or downtrend or if you suspect a new
change of character. Then identify key levels,
evaluate potential breakout points,
pivot lines, or supply-demand zones.
You then monitor price action. Observe how
price reacts near key zones. Look for bullish
or bearish candlestick patterns or specific micro
structure like retests, small head-fake moves,
or partial breaks. Then you use footprint
closely. In a strong bullish scenario,
watch if the footprint bars confirm heavy
ask volume at or above key inflection points.
In a potential top scenario, look for absorption
clusters on the bid side, then execute.
And if you're ready to fit this
into a full A to Z trading system,
that's what our academy is for.
Link is in the description.