Let’s start with the market structure.
Market structure is the
backbone of technical analysis.
It's about figuring out who's in control
– demand or supply, buyers or sellers.
When demand and supply influence
price movement, trends are born.
An uptrend, or a bullish trend, is characterized
by higher swing highs and higher swing lows. This
trend remains intact until a lower low emerges.
A downtrend, or a bearish trend,
shows lower lows and lower highs, and it
continues until a higher high appears.
Markets don't always trend; they can transition
into consolidation phases or a sideways trend.
A sideways trend displays roughly equal highs
and lows, with price consolidating in a range.
To identify the shift from trend to consolidation,
watch for failed tests of recent highs and lows.
To confirm a healthy trend, look for price
to break and close above or below previous
highs or lows. Multiple closes beyond
these levels indicate strong momentum.
A failure to hold above or below
suggests a potential false breakout.
Lastly, keep an eye out for the
breaks in market structure.
In an uptrend, a break in the market structure
occurs when price makes a new lower low,
and a new lower high, indicating
potential weakness or reversal.
Similarly, in a downtrend, a break of structure
happens when price forms a new higher high,
and a new higher low, serving as a warning sign.
Market cycles
All markets move in cycles,
which are: Accumulation,
Mark Up, Distribution, and Mark Down.
Each cycle tells a unique story about
the battle between supply and demand.
Accumulation is when the price has
fallen to a point where the price may
seem stuck in a range. In this phase,
buyers are quietly gaining strength.
In the Mark Up phase, the buyers finally
break free from the range and
start pushing prices higher,
confirming that the buyers are in control.
In the Distribution phase, after the previous
significant price increase, sellers start
to regain control, and the price action
flattens out once again. Lower tops and
flat bottoms characterize this range,
as the sellers prepare to take over.
Finally, the Markdown Phase arrives,
and the sellers steer prices below the
lower level of the distribution phase,
and a strong downtrend emerges.
If you can spot the end of the Accumulation stage,
be ready to buy at the beginning of the
Mark Up, riding the wave of rising prices.
Similarly, if you can identify the end of the
Distribution phase, be ready to sell and profit
from the Markdown's downward momentum.
Support/resistance
Mastering support and resistance is
very important in technical analysis.
Support acts as the floor beneath
the market, an area where the price
has shown a tendency to stop falling.
Buyers might see value at this level
and start buying, creating a demand zone that
prevents the price from dropping further.
Resistance acts like a ceiling above the
market, an area where the price has shown a
tendency to stop rising. It's like an invisible
barrier that keeps prices from moving too high.
Sellers might see it as a fair
price to sell their positions,
creating a supply zone.
This is how you spot these
levels. You need to follow some simple rules.
First, look for the extreme swing highs and lows,
the highest and lowest points
the price has reached recently.
Also, look for at least
two rejections of an area.
The level should be obvious, jumping right
out at you when you glance at the chart.
Also, the move away from the
area should be significant.
Another condition: the level should have
acted as both support and resistance,
respected from both sides.
And finally, the level should
have been recently respected or formed.
You don't need all these conditions
to draw a level, but the more
rules it fulfills, the better.
Now, very important, the more times a
level is tested, the weaker it becomes.
Really strong support and resistance levels
immediately push the price away from them.
If the price can hang around or quickly revisit
the level, it suggests a lack of conviction
from buyers or sellers. Multiple tests of
a level can set the stage for a breakout.
And another tip: when drawing support and
resistance, focus on the significant levels
rather than cluttering your
chart with every possible level.
And very important, treat these levels as zones
rather than exact lines, as the price might break
your line or turn before touching it.
Candlesticks
Candlesticks give you a visual representation
of the battle between buyers and sellers.
Each candlestick reveals the open, high, low,
and close price for a specific time period,
whether it's a minute, an hour, or a day.
The candle body represents the distance
between the opening and closing
price, while the high and low show
the extremes reached during that time period.
The length of the candlestick body and the
wicks are very important in technical analysis,
for revealing the buying and selling pressure.
A long upper wick suggests strong
selling pressure, as sellers drove
the price down from the high.
A long lower wick indicates strong
buying pressure, with buyers pushing
the price back up from the low.
Short wicks imply minimal
buying or selling pressure.
A long body indicates strong
buying or selling pressure,
while a short body suggests
less intense activity.
Sometimes, you might see candlesticks
with no wicks at all, just long bodies.
These are momentum candles, emphasizing
the market sentiment even more strongly.
Also, pay close attention to engulfing
bars (which appear when a larger candle
engulfing a smaller one) and to pin bars,
with their long tails and small bodies.
Also look for inside bars (when one or more
candlesticks that are completely contained
within the range of a larger candle)
The real magic happens when you combine
these candlestick patterns with the right
context, and you analyze a series of candle
within the broader price trend.
So observe how candles form in
relation to previous bars, and look
for engulfing candles, inside bars,
and pin bars at major levels of support and
resistance, or during significant trend phases.
Price patterns
A group or series of
candlesticks form price patterns.
In technical analysis we can have
reversal patterns, which indicate that the
price might be about to change direction,
or continuation patterns, which signal the price
will likely keep moving in its current direction.
Double tops and bottoms are the most
important reversal patterns worth watching.
A double top happens when the price fails to make
a higher high and instead matches the previous
high, hinting at a potential bearish reversal.
A double bottom is the opposite – the price
fails to make a lower low and matches
the previous low, suggesting a bullish
reversal could be on the horizon.
Continuation patterns appear as
consolidations after a period of trending.
Ascending and descending triangles have a
clear directional bias, with buyers
or sellers showing their strength.
Flags and wedges slope in the opposite
direction of the prevailing trend,
hinting at a potential continuation.
Rectangles form when the price
consolidates sideways, bounded by
clear support and resistance levels.
Very important: location and context
of these patterns are crucial. A
continuation pattern is only useful if
there's an existing trend to continue,
and a reversal pattern needs a trend to reverse.
Also, be aware that we can sometimes see what
we want to see, so it's important to stay
objective and don’t rely too much on patterns.
No pattern is foolproof, and they will fail a lot.
It's often easier to spot them after the fact.
Textbook patterns are rare in real life, so be
prepared for price spikes and fake breakouts.
Fibonacci
Fibonacci retracements are one
of the most popular tools in technical analysis
and they work best when the market is trending.
The theory behind this is
that after a trend begins,
the price will often retrace to a previous level
before continuing in the direction of the trend.
To find these Fibonacci levels,
you need to identify recent
significant Swing Highs and Swing Lows.
Then, you use the Fibonacci tool to connect
the Swing High to the Swing Low in a downtrend,
or the Swing Low to the Swing High in an uptrend.
The idea is to buy when the price retraces to
a Fibonacci support level during an uptrend,
and to sell when the price retraces to a
Fibonacci resistance level during a downtrend.
Choosing the correct price swing is crucial
when using Fibonacci retracements.
So focus on larger time frames and avoid using
the tool on very small price moves, as the levels
will be too close together to be reliable.
The best Fibonacci retracements are those
that are easy to spot on a chart
without having to look too hard.
Supply and demand zones
Now let’s talk about supply and demand
zones. These areas are formed when big market
players are placing large quantities of orders.
A demand zone is where buyers are likely to step
in and start buying, causing the price to go up.
A supply zone is where sellers are
likely to step in and start selling,
causing the price to go down.
In theory, if price returns to
certain supply and demand zones, it has a
high probability of rejecting these areas.
This is how to mark supply and
demand zones on your charts.
First things first, you'll need
to identify the overall trend.
Next, look for significant turning points
in the price action. These are the points
where the price made a sharp reversal,
either from a low point or a high point.
To mark a demand zone, find a low point in the
market where the price bounced up strongly.
Locate the last bearish
candle before the price move.
Then draw a horizontal line at the low point of
the candle, and another one at the high point of
the candlestick. This is your demand zone.
To mark a supply zone, you find a high point
where the price fell sharply.
Locate the last bullish
candle before the price move.
Draw a horizontal line at the
high point and another one at the low point of
the candlestick. And this is your supply zone.
When marking zones, focus on the
most recent and significant zones.
Older zones may not be as relevant anymore.
And adjust your zones as needed. If the price
breaks through a zone decisively,
it may no longer be valid.
Volume
Volume is very important
in technical analysis. It basically tells you how
much trading activity there is in a given period.
When volume is high, it means there are a lot
of market participants involved in the move,
including the "smart money" (the big
players who bring the most turnover).
This is a good sign because it confirms that the
market activity is real and not just a fluke.
On the other hand, low volume suggests that
there aren't many traders interested in the
current price levels, which could mean
that the trend is running out of steam.
Volume can also help you evaluate the health of
a trend. In an uptrend, you want to see volume
increasing as the price moves higher, and you
want to see it decreasing during pullbacks.
If volume is decreasing while prices
are rising, it's a warning sign that
the uptrend might be losing momentum.
Another important thing to watch for is
volume spikes at certain price levels.
Look for periods when volume suddenly
jumps up. It means that a lot of traders are
interested in that particular price. If the
spike is really big (like, bigger than any other
recent spikes), it's called a volume climax.
Volume can also help you validate breakouts.
When a market is consolidating and trading
sideways on low volume, a sudden increase in
volume could mean that a breakout is coming.
If the breakout happens with rising volume,
that's a good sign that the breakout it's legit.
But if the breakout happens on low
volume, it might be a fake-out.
Elliott Wave Theory
Elliott Wave Theory is
all about identifying repeating movements
on price charts, which are called waves.
These waves can be either impulsive
(moving with the trend) or
corrective (moving against the trend).
Impulsive waves represent the
direction of the current trend.
Corrective waves work against the prevailing trend
and are usually weaker and less aggressive.
An uptrend typically has three large upward
price impulses and two corrections,
creating a five-wave pattern.
This uptrend is then followed by three waves
lower: an impulse down, a correction to the
upside, and another impulse down.
There are three golden
rules in Elliott Wave Theory:
Wave 2 cannot go past the start of wave 1.
Wave 3 cannot be the shortest wave (so wave
1 or wave 5, or both, must be shorter).
And Wave 4 cannot go into the
price territory of wave 2 (so
waves 2 and 4 must have clear price separation).
It's best to trade in the direction of the impulse
waves, as they represent the largest price moves.
So in an uptrend, buy during pullbacks or at
the end of a corrective wave, and
ride the next impulse wave higher.
In a downtrend, sell at the end of a corrective
wave to profit from the next impulse wave down.
Gaps
Now let's talk about market gaps.
A gap happens when the price jumps higher or
lower from the previous price, leaving an empty
space between the two prices.
Gaps happen because of an
imbalance between supply and demand.
An up gap forms when a candle’s low price
is higher than the previous candle’s high price.
A down gap is the opposite – the high price is
lower than the previous low price.
Gaps show that something significant
has changed in the fundamentals or the
psychology of the market participants.
There are four main types of gaps:
First we have common gaps: These gaps are
normal, small, and happen fairly often. They
usually get filled quickly and don't provide
much insight. A gap fill is when the price
action retraces to the level before the gap.
Breakaway gaps occur when the price breaks
out of a trading range or congestion area.
They need market enthusiasm and a significant
increase in volume to happen. If the volume
increases when the gap occurs, it means the
new trend has a good chance of continuing.
Runaway gaps happen in the middle of a strong
trend and show that the trend is accelerating.
They're a sign of increased enthusiasm
and usually happen with high volume.
Exhaustion gaps occur near the end of a
strong trend and they're often followed by
a sharp reversal in the opposite direction.
Exhaustion gaps are usually filled quickly,
signaling the end of the trend.
Trading indicators
Technical analysis relies heavily
on "trading indicators" to show
various aspects of price activity.
These indicators can be divided into
four main categories: trend-following,
momentum, volume, and volatility.
Trend indicators, like VWAP and moving averages,
measure the strength and direction of a
trend. However, they have a main drawback – they
lag the price and give trading signals after a
trend has already been established, causing you to
potentially miss the initial move of a new trend.
Momentum indicators, also known as oscillators,
measure the relative strength of recent price
moves and plot a value between 0 and 100.
They work well in ranging markets but can
lead to false signals when markets
are trending. RSI, Stochastic, and
MACD are the most popular oscillators.
Volume indicators measure the strength of
a price move using volume information.
You can use the standard volume,
Money Flow Index or On-balance volume.
Volatility indicators, such as Bollinger
Bands and ATR, measure the rate of price
changes regardless of their direction.
These indicators are rising when markets are
fast and falling when markets are slow.
Indicators should confirm your trade
bias, not be followed blindly. Let
them be a tool in your technical analysis
arsenal, but don't rely on them entirely.
And if you liked this guide, you definitely
must watch these next trading tutorials.