Reaching the point of trading consistency
is the ultimate goal of every trader.
And to achieve this milestone, you will need
to incorporate three pillars in your trading,
which will require finding the market direction,
evaluating the strength of the trend and effectively
assessing the volatility.
Most traders apply 3 or 4 indicators to get
this information, but at the same time they
clutter their charts.
One viable solution to this problem is the
Traders Dynamic Index.
In today’s video, we’ll discuss about
the TDI indicator and I will share how to
correctly trade with it and how to incorporate
it in a trading strategy.
Traders Dynamic Index is a hybrid indicator
that can read the market sentiment, market
volatility, and momentum at the same time.
The advantage of combining the qualities of
several indicators into one indicator is what
makes the TDI indicators so special.
The Traders Dynamic Index is based on three
other popular indicators: the RSI, a moving
average and Bollinger Bands.
The standard RSI indicator determines the
strength of the current trend, or if you want,
the rate of change in price.
The moving averages algorithm is used to smooth
the lines and eliminate RSI false signals,
and Bollinger bands are used to estimate the
amplitude of the oscillations, meaning the
volatility.
Now, let’s break down the Traders Dynamic
Index indicator.
As you can see, the TDI has five lines.
The green line represents the RSI indicator
and represents the market sentiment.
It shows you how the market is moving related
to positive and negative expectation.
The red line is simply a moving average of
the green line, meaning a simple moving average
applied on the relative strength index, and
can be used for entries and exits in the market.
The yellow line is what we refer to as the
overall market sentiment.
It’s the middle Bollinger Band and it shows
the overall direction of the market.
The overall market has a tendency to do two
things.
It can turn slowly, or it can continue to
go in the initial direction.
This is because the moving average, usually
of 50 period, is less responsive to quick
market changes and turns slowly.
Last but not least, we have two blue lines,
one above and one below.
Those blue lines represent the volatility
in the market, representing the upper and
lower Bollinger Bands.
They are increasing and decreasing in volatility.
Regarding the calculation procedure, you have
several lookback periods you must tweak and
adjust.
The most important thing you must keep in
mind is the fact that TDI indicator is based
on the RSI − all lines of the indicator
are calculated on the information of the main
RSI oscillator.
RSI forms the overall graphic picture, because
the main task is to assess the rate of the
change in the price.
• A shorter RSI period – below 10 - with
be volatile and will have a lower level of
reliability.
• A longer RSI period – above 20 - smooths
out the plotted line and will generate signals
that are more accurate
I personally would not use a lookback period
below 20 on the RSI.
You can also change period of the moving average
applied to the RSI.
I don’t like using fast moving averages,
below 10, so I would backtest moving averages
with 12 or 21 lookback periods.
The Bollinger Bands periods must not be lower
than the moving average period.
If you choose a period of 20 for the moving
average and 20 for the Bollinger Bands, the
two lines will become one.
I prefer to apply a 50 period on the Bollinger
Bands, and in some cases even a period of
100.
So how to trade with Traders Dynamic Index
and what are the main signals offered by TDI
indicator?
1.
First signal: The crossover of the green and
red lines
The short-term trend is determined by the
relative arrangement of the green line in
relation to the red line:
• the trend is considered ascending, when
the green line, representing the RSI, moves
above the red line, the moving average;
• if the green line is below the red line,
the market is considered bearish.
This is practically an entry trigger.
If the green line crosses the signal red line
from below, it is a signal to buy; if it crosses
the red line from above, this is a signal
to sell.
You enter, place the stop loss behind the
nearest swing high/low and you take the profit
at the channel bands (the blue lines) or after
an inversed crossing of the green and red
lines.
Now, very important.
A crossover of the RSI with the moving average
isn’t necessarily an invitation to enter
a trade.
In some instances, if the price trend isn’t
strong, you have multiple crossovers in a
short period of time, offering many false
signals.
Before acting on the crossover of the green
and red lines, examine price action and make
sure you identified all major support and
resistance points on your chart and take signals
from these key areas.
This is very important, take TDI signals from
major key levels on your chart.
Here are several examples of valid trades.
2.
Second signal involves the crossovers between
the red and yellow lines
The yellow line, the middle Bollinger Band,
indicates a long-term trend and most of the
trading time moves in the range between the
levels of 30-70 − with the exception of
speculative moments.
This line will define key turns for a change
in the trend.
If the yellow line, crosses 30 level downwards,
a new swing low could form in the market.
A breakaway of 30 level upwards signals a
potential reversal or the beginning of an
ascending correction.
If the yellow line rises above 70, a new swing
high could form in the market.
A breakaway of this level downwards signals
the beginning of a descending correction.
The global trend is defined by analyzing the
arrangement of the yellow and red lines.
When the yellow line is pointing down and
the red line is below it − the trend is
considered bearish; for a bullish market you
need a mirror image − the yellow line turns
up and the red line moves above it.
Again, you don’t take crossover signals
blindly, you take them after you identified
the key levels in the market.
Here are other examples of valid crossover
trades.
3.
Another signal is the crossing of 50 level
by the yellow line
This trading signal emerges when the middle
Bollinger Band crosses the 50 of the RSI . This
is a long-term trading signal, especially
if it appears on longer timeframes.
If the yellow line crosses the centerline
from below, this is a signal to buy; if it
crosses the level from above, it’s a signal
to sell.
To make the signal more powerful, use it combination
with breakouts of the support/resistance levels
or lines, the formation of new price patterns.
While many trades focus on the fast moving
average, the red line, I prefer to pay extra
attention to the yellow line, to smooth out
the “noise” of shorter-term price fluctuations.
The slope of yellow line is also important
as it indicates the strength of market trends.
When it points upwards, the market sentiment
is bullish, when it points downwards, the
sentiment is bearish.
4.
The 4th signal is related to trend strength
and the range of volatility
The TDI indicator also signals the current
market strength.
We can analyze the relative location of the
blue Bollinger Bands and RSI line:
If the channel bands diverge or expand and
the green line forms a strong direction (up
or down), then there is active volatility
on the market (and the probability of strong
directional movements or continuation of the
current trend is high);
The greater the angle of the green line, the
stronger the players in this direction;
If the channel lines converge or become narrow,
and the RSI line shows short movements − the
market is ranging, or is preparing for this
state;
The closer the green line to the centerline
(level 50), the less the market is active.
So the expansion of the Bollinger bands signals
an increase in volatility.
The narrowing of the lines, on the contrary,
indicates a decrease in volatility and a weakening
market.
5.
5th signal, involves TDI regular divergences
Many trades concentrate on crossovers, they
but neglect an important signal coming from
the TDI: divergences.
Occasionally, price makes a new (higher) high
and TDI fails to do so (the new high on TDI
is lower than the previous high).
Conversely, sometimes price makes new lower
low, but TDI does not get below its previous
low.
These situations are called TDI divergences.
There is a divergence, or mismatch, between
the information we get from price (the market
continues its trend and makes new extreme)
and RSI line of the TDI indicator (the market
fails to break through the previous extreme
and the trend may be changinf soon).
A high probability signal would be a crossover
between the RSI line and the moving average,
after you spot a divergence.
Of course, this must occur at an important
level of support or resistance.
Here are several examples of divergence TDI
trades.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.