The Schaff trend cycle (STC) is a forward-looking,
leading indicator that generates faster, more
accurate signals than other indicators, such
as the MACD because it considers both time
(through cycles) and moving averages.
The Schaff trend cycle (STC) is commonly used
to identify market trends and provide buy
and sell signals to traders.
Schaff trend cycle is a type of oscillator
and is based on the assumption that, regardless
of time frame, trends accelerate and decelerate
in cyclical patterns.
Many traders are familiar with the MACD charting
tool, which is an indicator that is used to
forecast price action and is notorious for
lagging due to its slow responsive signal
line.
By contrast, STC’s signal line enables it
to detect trends sooner.
In fact, it typically identifies up and downtrends
long before MACD indicator.
While the Schaff trend cycle is computed using
the same exponential moving averages as MACD,
it adds a novel cycle component to improve
accuracy and reliability.
While MACD is simply computed using a series
of moving average, the cycle aspect of STC
is based on time (for example, number of days).
Although STC was developed primarily for currency
markets, it may be effectively employed across
all markets.
It can be applied to intraday charts, such
as five minutes or one hour charts, as well
as daily, weekly, or monthly time frames.
What makes this indicator interesting is that
it is a combination of MACD and fast stochastics
with a cycle component and a smoother to capture
market prices more comprehensively.
It’s basically a combination of leading
and lagging indicators.
So let’s discuss the main problems of MACD
and stochastic.
The MACD follows prices with its 12- and 26-period
exponential moving average (EMA) components
and nine-day EMA signal line.
In this capacity, it is a trend indicator.
Yet it is lagging because it doesn’t always
lead prices and is prone to false signals
especially in fast-moving markets.
So you have to adjust the settings to satisfy
your price and market objectives.
The stochastic is also lagging.
The problem with stochastic is its ability
to generate false signals, while markets can
take off before signals are generated.
Part of the problem with stochastic oscillator
is its concentration on the 3-day simple moving
average as the signal line.
False signals and slow reactions are just
the beginning of problems, especially for
short-term and day traders because the three-day
simple moving average is too short a term
to represent fast markets and act as a true
trigger line.
The Schaff trend cycle (STC) indicator tries
to fix these problems by incorporating a shorter-term
EMA set with a default at 23 with a longer-term
EMA with a default at 50.
This remedies the MACD and fast stochastic
false signal.
This combination can be employed to capture
trends, but it doesn’t incorporate entries
and exits fully.
To fix this, a signal was needed.
The MACD’s nine-day exponential signal line
was not always effective, while fast stochastic
%d signal line was also a failure.
You need a true signal that would capture
a true trend.
This came from cycle theory, a theory never
fully incorporated into an indicator.
This signal line was derived from theories
and practices of 10-, 20-, and 40-day currency
cycles.
The halfway point between the 23- and 50-day
EMA is, in cycle theory, 10 so the cycle default
is set as a standard 10.
But this cycle can also be viewed as a halfway
point of a 20-day cycle as well.
This is the signal line that denotes trends,
ranges, or congestion.
The developer of this indicator considered
that currency cycles generally come in 10-,
20-, and 40-day cycles.
These are measured by daily and weekly candlesticks.
In addition, you must know that not all highs
are cycle highs and not all lows are cycle
lows.
One of the problems with the STC indicator
is that the signal line can get stuck in overbought
or oversold territories for extended periods.
This is because cycles haven’t completed
their time.
But, we’ll discuss these problems later.
So how does it work?
The main idea behind this oscillator is to
combine the benefits of trend and cycle indicators
and minimize their drawbacks such as lags
or false signals.
The main goal of the STC is to identify or
confirm price direction and market turning
points.
Here is how to understand its readings.
There are two thresholds: 25 and 75.
When the indicator crosses above the 25 line,
an uptrend is observed.
When the indicator crosses below the 75 line,
a downtrend is believed to be present.
When the indicator is between the 25 and the
75 lines, the trend is developing in one of
these two directions.
When the indicator turns into a straight line
(which only happens in its uppermost and lowermost
points), the asset is either overbought — when
above the 75 line, or oversold — when below
the 25 line.
In both cases, a trend reversal can be expected,
but no exact time timeline is provided.
How to apply the STC indicator in trading?
The Schaff trend cycle (STC) is a pretty straightforward
indicator, as there are not so many ways in
which it can be used.
And remember, though originally designed for
forex trading, it can be effectively applied
to all asset types and on all time frames.
Here’s how traders usually use Schaff trend
cycle.
When the indicator goes above the 25 line,
the trend is believed to be taking a positive
turn (according to the indicator).
It is when traders consider opening a buy
position, but only if the confirmation is
received.
For example, a candle after current one that
moves in the same direction can be considered
a confirmation.
Readings of other indicators that go in line
with STC can also be treated as a confirmation.
The same rules apply to negative trends.
When the indicator goes below the 75, some
traders consider opening a sell position,
of course with confirmation.
STC is a leading indicator, which means that
it sends a signal before the price move has
occurred.
It also means that it lacks the accuracy of
lagging indicators and should be used in conjunction
with other technical analysis tools, never
on its own.
So, buy and sell signals are generated when
the signal line breaches 25 at the bottom
and 75 at the top.
When the signal line breaches 25 and is heading
up, this is a possible buy, or a long position,
when the signal line breaches 75 and is pointing
down, this is a potential short.
One exit possibility is when the short trade
hits the bottom and breaches the 25 level
and when the long trade hits the top and breaches
75 level.
But if the signal line is pointing in the
right direction, you may choose to stay in
the trade since currencies can easily trend
to the high 90 level at the top and near zero
at the bottom.
It is a good idea to find confirmation through
candles.
Before the long position, make sure you have
an upward candle and a downward candle for
shorts.
Doug Schaff, the developer of the indicator,
recommended a confirmation by entering on
the second candle up for longs and the second
candle down for shorts.
Simple price action, like paying attention
at market swings like higher highs and higher
lows are even better.
Looking at this Tesla chart, we can first
apply the trend filter, in this case an uptrend,
and look to take only buy signals, when the
indicator breaches 25.
We had some decent signals just by paying
attention to the main trend.
The same for a downtrend.
We have lower lows and lower highs, so we
take only shorts when the STC crosses below
75.
Here are a few trade examples using Schaff
trend cycle indicator.
Settings can be adjusted according to various
time frames.
For example, Schaff recommended you try smaller
EMAs for longer time frames and longer EMAs
for shorter time frames.
The smaller the number used for cycles, the
more turns you will witness while the higher
numbers will forecast fewer turns with more
cycle accuracy.
What you want from adjustments is for the
signal line to perfectly follow prices and
candles.
While I find this indicator to be reliable
when the signal is caught correctly, there
is one problem.
The signal can stay in overbought or oversold
conditions for extended periods.
So you need to have an alternative exit plan,
maybe a trailing stop, or a fib target, to
get the most profit out of your trade.
If you and found value and learned something
new, leave us a like to show your support
and make sure you subscribe and hit the bell
icon to stay notified when we upload new videos.
Until next time.