as a day trader or scalper I'm sure you
enjoyed the thrill of the market open
especially during the first hour of the
London and the New York sessions the
rush of adrenaline as we watched the
price move up and down the anticipation
of the next big trade and the fear of
missing out an opportunity are all part
of the experience today I'll talk about
this trading the market open and several
strategies to apply in the first hour of
trading
like subscribe and stick around for the
full video
[Music]
your emotions in Psychology play a
critical role in how you approach the
market during this critical time the
first hour of our trading session is
known to be one of the most volatile
periods of the trading day this creates
an intense activity and movement in the
market which can be both exciting and
intimidating one of the primary emotions
that you may experience during the first
hour of a trading session is fear this
Fear Can arise from a variety of sources
including the fear of missing out on a
big trade the fear of losing money or
the fear of being wrong
another emotion that you may experience
during the market open is great this can
manifest itself in a variety of ways
including the desire to make a quick
profit or a desire to take on more risk
than is appropriate for your trading
strategy
and if you allow gray to drive your
decisions you are more likely to make
mistakes and take unnecessary risks the
point is in order to be successful
during the first hour of the London or
New York session it's important to
approach the market with a clear and
objective mindset this means setting
aside your emotions and focusing on
facts and data presented by the market
[Music]
when it comes to trading during the
market open one of the most important
skills you can have is the ability to
identify key trading levels the main
problem you may face when trading during
the market open is the volatility and
the unpredictability of the market
prices can move rapidly in either
direction and it can be challenging to
know where to enter or exit rates this
is where identifying key trading levels
becomes crucial there are a variety of
different methods that can be used to
identify major trading levels during the
market open including supply and demand
areas trend lines moving averages or
classic support or resistance levels
each of these methods has its own
strengths and weaknesses and it's
important to use a combination of
different tools to get a complete
picture of the market
these tools can give you a good idea of
where prices are likely to bounce or
reverse during a market open
foreign
London or New York session open your
goal is to find some sort of edge that
can help you make better decisions one
approach is to use pivot Points as a
tool to identify key price levels these
are calculated based on the previous
day's price range and they offer you key
levels to watch for potential price
action
during the first hour of the market open
price action is unpredictable however by
using pivot Points you can gain a better
understanding of where price May
potentially move it all starts with a
daily Pivot Point this level can serve
as a reference point for potential price
action
price opens above the daily Pivot Point
you should look for potential buying
opportunities at support levels if price
opens below the daily Pivot Point you
look for potential selling opportunities
at resistance levels
in addition to the Daily Pivot Point you
should also be aware of the S1 and R1
levels this represents the first support
and resistance levels of the day look
for rejection or continuation patterns
at these areas if price breaks above the
R1 level you may look for potential
buying opportunities
if price breaks below the S1 level you
can search for potential selling
opportunities so don't ignore pivots
during the market open
if you are trading indices or stocks
you'll often find gaps at the beginning
of the session Market gaps can be both
exciting and intimidating on one hand
they offer the potential for significant
profit in a short amount of time
on the other hand they can signal a
change in the market Direction and cause
Panic among Traders and it's important
to have a strategy in place for trading
based on these gaps one simple strategy
for trading apps is to wait for the
market to establish a direction after
the Gap has occurred this means you
don't rush and wait for a few minutes
after the market open to see if the Gap
will continue or if the market will
retrace back to fill the Gap if the Gap
continues and finds a key level a pivot
point maybe you can look for
opportunities to enter a trade in the
direction of the gap
if the market retraces to fill the Gap
you can look for opportunities when the
Gap is filled when a gap occurs it can
create a new level of support or
resistance that the market May test by
identifying these levels you can enter
trades in the direction of the gap or
against it depending on a market
reaction to these levels
during the first hour of trading the
market is usually highly volatile with
prices moving rapidly and Traders
scrambling to enter in exit positions
this is where volume can help you when
the volume is high during the first hour
of trading it can be an indication that
there is strong buying or selling
pressure this can confirm the direction
of price movements for example if a
market is experiencing a price increase
during the first hour of trading and
volume is high it can be an indication
that there is strong buying pressure in
the market this can be a sign of a
strong uptrend
on the other hand if the price is rising
but the volume is decreasing this could
indicate that the trend is losing
momentum and a reversal may be imminent
if the price is falling and the volume
is increasing this could indicate a
strong downtrend while a falling price
with decreasing volume could signal a
weakening trend
another way to use volume to identify
potential trades during the first hour
of trading is through volume spikes a
volume spike is a sudden and significant
increase in trading volume that can be
an indication of a potential Market move
in addition to volume analysis and
volume spikes you can also use volume
indicators to help you confirm price
movements during the first hour of
trading
Traders fall victim to liquidity routes
and stop loss hunting time and time
again this can be especially damaging
during Market open when the market is
most volatile liquidity roads occur when
large institutional players enter the
market at the opening bell and take
positions that are significantly larger
than the markets available liquidity
this creates an imbalance in supply and
demand resulting in a sudden and sharp
movement in price
stop loss hunting is another tactic
employed by market players during the
market open this involves intentionally
triggering stop losses of retail traders
in order to create price movements that
will benefit their own positions the key
to protecting yourself from these
practices is to have a solid
understanding of market dynamics and to
be prepared for sudden movements in
price one risk management measure that
you can use is to avoid placing
stop-loss orders at obvious levels
Market players who engage in stop-loss
hunting are often looking for these
obvious levels so by placing a stop loss
at the less obvious level you can reduce
the likelihood of your positions being
liquidated
one indicate
's fall during the market open is the
opening range breakout indicator this
tool will help you identify potential
breakouts at the beginning of a trading
session it works by calculating the high
and the low of the first few minutes of
trading and then using these levels to
identify potential breakouts throughout
the rest of the session
you first need to determine the length
of the opening range this is typically
the first 5 minutes of trading although
it can vary depending on your preference
and the market being traded you can set
it at 15 minutes or even 30 minutes
I prefer to set it for the first 5
minutes after the Market opens once the
opening range has been established you
can then use the high and the low of
this range to identify potential
breakouts throughout the rest of the
trading session when price breaks above
or below the high or low of the opening
range
and of course not all breakouts are
created equal many breakouts may be full
signals and the price May quickly return
inside the opening range you need to be
able to distinguish between genuine
breakouts and full signals and this is
where your ability to read volume
defined Confluence between key levels to
find liquidity clear routes to read
pivots will help you find a trade
my own preference is to watch for the
opening range to develop and allow the
other traders to fight against each
other until one side wins if price
breaks above the high of the opening
range I wait for it to establish itself
above or below the breakout level for
several candles before entering if the
opening range holds I may choose to
enter a long position with the
expectation that the price will continue
to rise
if I see that price is breaking the
upper range and then immediately returns
inside the range and also breaks the
other side I may look too short to
Market if I see that the lower line of
the range is acting as resistance
if you want to learn more about the
opening range breakouts make sure you
watch this video
if your trading currency pairs or
indices and you have access to extended
hours you could also trade the London
open using the Frankfurt session
activity
Frankfurt trading session starts at 7 AM
GMT and a London session starts at 8
o'clock GMT this trading hour between 7
and 8 o'clock GMT will give you many
trade opportunities at the London Market
open
and you don't have to draw this range
yourself
in trading view you add this indicator
FX Market sessions
you'll keep only the London Tab and
you'll hide the rest of the sections
now it displays only the London session
but we want the indicator to draw the
range from the Frankfurt Market open one
hour earlier
if you look at the indicators default
settings at the start of the London
session it shows 8 o'clock GMT we want
to highlight the price action one hour
earlier
so in the first step we'll select the
Frankfurt open Seven o'clock GMT
and you put 8 o'clock the London open
and the second tab
the high and low price of this range are
the first support and the first
resistance of the trading day the trade
plan is to find imbalances in the Market
at the start of the London session
if price goes above the range it's a
sign of strength and you look for buying
opportunities
if price goes below it's a sign of
weakness
and you look for short signals
and you don't trade when price is inside
the channel because there is no
imbalance between buyers and sellers
if you want to trade the New York
session the same process you want the
indicator to draw the range prior to the
New York open
you'll keep only the New York Tab and
you hide the rest of the sessions
and now it displays only the New York
sessions
if you look at the default settings at
the start of the New York session it
shows 1pm GMT we want to highlight the
price action one hour earlier
so in the first step we'll select 12
o'clock
and you select 1 pm GMT then your coupon
at the second tab
and now you have the range prior to the
U.S session again you find imbalances
between buyers and sellers above or
below the channel taking into account
volume pivots liquidity traps and so on
if you want to see an in-depth video
about this strategy you definitely must
watch this video
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time