hey guys in this video I will show you
how I sculpt the markets using a simple
energy setup strategy that helps me to
spot high probability areas on a chart
so scalping is basically a technique
which involves opening and closing the
trades in a very short period of time in
order to obtain quick profits this
trading method is based on opening
trades and closing them with small
profits on lower timeframes my scalping
setup is based on finding confluence the
confluence is an area with multiple
support and resistance levels both
static and dynamic a confluence of
support or resistance is more relevant
to traders as it includes two or more
important focus points on the chart
although it might seem complicated
finding conference on the chart is not
difficult you just have to train your
eyes to spot chart areas where multiple
levels meet finding confluence on your
charts it's very important for scalping
because these areas offer high
probability trade opportunities before
you continue with the scalping setup let
me tell you something important finding
confluence it's a quite subjective and
is dependent on the trader skill
experience and tools used on the chart
my personal role is to find areas with
at least two support and resistance
levels one of them must be a static
level in the other one a dynamic level
so we need three confluence conditions
to be met for our scalping strategy
first we need an obvious area of support
or resistance support and resistance is
practically the foundation of technical
analysis and these levels serve as a
starting point for developing an idea of
what may happen next in what concerns
the price movement so we first look at
recent market swings and try to spot
areas of static support or resistance as
a rule of thumb if the line includes
three or more swing points it means that
the support or resistance level is more
relevant but drawing horizontal lines
around recent market swings can be very
subjective and in most cases we can
usually only approximate
those areas that's why we need to add
something else for our scalping
confluence set up the second conference
condition involves the 200 EMA as a
dynamic area of support and resistance I
prefer to add the 200 EMA because as a
dynamic area of support and resistance
level is constantly changing depending
on recent price action in the case of
esthetic support or resistance level
you already know at the beginning of the
trading day where those levels are you
know in advance where the possible areas
of interest are located on the chart
with dynamic support and resistance you
don't know an exact number as these
levels are changing depending on market
fluctuations this is a good thing for
our scalping setup because we can use
both static and dynamic levels in our
advantage so we add the 200 EMA and
start searching for areas of confluence
between the dynamic support and
resistance and the static support and
resistance our third component in our
scalping setup is the stochastic used to
pinpoint market entries the stochastic
oscillator will help us to spot
divergences on the chart if you are not
familiar with divergences the divergence
occurs when the price for a lower low
while the stochastic forms a higher low
indicating a possible buy or when prices
form a higher high and the oscillator
forms a lower high indicating a possible
sell divergence occurs when the price
action is different from the action of
the stochastic oscillator when a
divergence occurs a potential change in
price direction could be on a course
so now we have the full set up we are
looking for confluence of dynamic and
Static support and resistance levels
respectively recent market swings and
200 EMA and we pull the trigger if we
spot a divergence on the stochastic
oscillator let's see the scalping
strategy in action in this chart we see
this level of static support and
resistance and here is the confluence
area with the 200 EMA the dynamic
support and resistance indicator so we
have this potential area but we cannot
enter the market blindly we need to
confirm it with the stochastic we have a
regular divergence and we also have a
hidden divergence which is a more
powerful set up all our conditions were
met so after the crossover of the
stochastic lines we can enter long on
the market because we trade based on
confluence the stop-loss order would be
placed below the confluence area the
profit target depends on your trading
style and risk aversion you could aim
for a two-to-one ratio or put your stop
to break-even once in profit and write a
risk free trade here's the same setup we
have a confluence area between the
recent market swings and the 200 EMA in
the divergence on a stochastic
oscillator if you incorporate also some
price action techniques the scalping
setup will become even more powerful
look at the flag pattern developed which
is another confirmation that a long
position was the only alternative ensure
positions were out of a question
here we have a short scalping trade we
have a clear resistance area right
around here the 200 EMA serves as a
dynamic area of support and resistance
and around here we have our confluence
area we have a hidden divergence on a
stochastic and once the stochastic lines
crossed we had the conformation we
needed and the high probability trade
was on the short side I know that there
are some of you who are also trading on
crypto markets I personally don't trade
cryptocurrencies because I prefer to
understand the fundamentals behind the
market before I decide to put my money
on it so I've not tested this copy
strategy on crypto markets but you can
back test it on demo account to see if
it has potential on this Bitcoin chart I
found the confluence pattern and the
stochastic entry here but I am not
familiar with the spreads on crypto
markets so I cannot tell for sure if you
can profit from it in the long run why I
am talking about the spreads because of
the nature of the scalping you need to
trade only the instruments with the
lowest spreads as a scalper by default
you will use lower stop losses aiming
for small profits the higher the spread
the lower your stop-loss will become I
personally never sculpt an instrument
that has a spread higher than two points
because the risk reward ratio is not
worth it like I said before scalping may
seem easy but is not if you want to make
money from scalping it's imperative to
have a disciplined approach to trading
keep your price charts clean without
plotting a lot of indicators and focus
also on reading and understanding the
price in order to increase your chances
to sculpt the right way if you got any
value from this please consider
subscribing to our channel share and
like this video as it will help us a lot
in the future
until next time