The Mcginley Dynamic is a little-known yet
highly reliable indicator invented by John
Mcginley, a certified market technician.
Working within the context of moving averages,
Mcginley sought to invent a responsive indicator
that would adjust itself in relation to the
speed of the market.
The indicator itself resembles a lot like
a moving average.
Well, Mcginley found that moving averages
had many problems.
In the first place, they were inappropriately
applied.
Moving averages in different periods operate
with varying degrees in different markets.
For example, how to know when to use a 10-day,
20-day, or a 50-day moving average in a fast
or slow market?
In order to solve the problem of choosing
the right length of the moving average, the
Mcginley Dynamic was built to automatically
adjust to the current speed of the market.
Mcginley believes moving averages should only
be used as a smoothing mechanism rather than
a trading system or signal generator.
It is a monitor of trends.
Further, Mcginley found moving averages failed
to follow prices since large separations frequently
exist between prices and moving average lines.
He sought to eliminate these problems by inventing
an indicator that would hug prices more closely,
avoid price separation and whipsaws, and follow
prices automatically in fast or slow markets.
The Mcginley Dynamic looks like a moving average
line, yet it is actually a smoothing mechanism
for prices, and tracks prices far better than
any moving average.
Because of its calculation, the dynamic line
speeds up in down markets as it follows prices
yet moves more slowly in up markets.
The key principle with this indicator is that
you would want to be quick to sell in a down
market, yet ride an up market as long as possible.
It greatly avoids whipsaws because the dynamic
line automatically follows and stays aligned
to prices in any market—fast or slow—like
a steering mechanism of a car.
That why traders can rely on it to make decisions
and time entrances and exits.
Mcginley invented the dynamic to act as a
market tool rather than as a trading indicator.
But whatever it's used for, the Mcginley Dynamic
is quite a fascinating instrument that is
more responsive to the raw data than simple
or exponential moving averages.
It aims to solve the problem inherent in all
moving averages — their reliance on fixed
time periods.
Here’s the logic behind this indicator:
in order to understand why Mcginley Dynamic
is so special, let’s first take a look at
how conventional moving averages operate.
A 10-period simple moving average takes 10
last closing prices and divides them by 10.
A 20-period SMA will do the same but with
20.
Old and new results receive the exact same
treatment.
An EMA works in a similar fashion but allocates
more weight to recent results, which makes
it perfectly suited for short-term trading.
But how do you know when to use a 10-, 20-
or 50-period moving average?
Mcginley Dynamic aims to solve this problem
as it will automatically adjust itself to
slow and fast markets.
While moving averages tend to lag behind the
actual price performance, displaying dated
information most of the times, Mcginley Dynamic
will follow the prices more closely.
You can think of Mcginley Dynamic as a better
version of a SMA or an EMA.
So let’s compare this tool with a simple
moving average.
We added the Mcginley Dynamic with a 20 period
input and a 20 period simple moving average.
The Mcginley Dynamic reacts to price increases
sooner that the simple moving average whilst
also tracking closer to prices and reducing
whipsaws.
You can see that Mcginley moves faster in
bearish markets and slower in bullish markets
(in order to give the market a chance to develop
necessary dynamics).
Now that you know about the differences between
the moving averages and Mcginley dynamic,
we can take a look at the 3 ways this tool
can be used to help you find trades, ride
trends and exit trades in a reliable way.
First approach, trend direction and filter.
Similar to a moving average approach, you
can use the Mcginley Dynamic to stay on the
right side of the market and to filter out
trades in the wrong direction.
Just this one tip can already make a huge
difference in your trading when you only start
trading with the trend in the right direction.
Mcginley Dynamic will help you to cut down
the amount of "noise" on a price chart.
Look at the direction of the dynamic line
to get a basic idea of which way the price
is moving.
If it is angled up, the price is moving up
(or was recently) overall; angled down, and
the price is moving down overall; moving sideways,
and the price is likely in a range.
As a general guideline, if the price is above
the dynamic line, the trend is up.
If the price is below it, the trend is down.
As always, keep an eye on price action.
Try to read the market and make trading decisions
based on the recent and actual price movements,
rather than relying solely on this tool.
You will have better results when you blend
this indicator into price action.
Here are a few examples of trending markets,
using the Mcginley Dynamic.
The second thing the dynamic line can help
you with is support and resistance trading
and also stop placement.
Because of the self-fulfilling prophecy, you
can often see that the popular moving averages
work perfectly as support and resistance levels.
Because the Mcginley Dynamic is basically
a moving average and because more than anything,
moving averages “work” because they are
a self-fulfilling prophecy, this means that
price action respects moving averages because
so many traders use them in their own trading.
This raises a very important point: you have
to stick to the most commonly used moving
averages to get the best results.
Moving averages work when a lot of traders
use and act on their signals.
Thus, go with the crowd and only use the popular
periods (like 10, 20, 50,100 and 200).
As its name suggests, this indicator may be
used as dynamic areas of support and resistance.
One importane note.
The dynamic line is not perfect, and you can
see that many a times the price may go past
it before moving back into the main trend.
And, there’s no getting around this – it’s
best to think of Mcginley Dynamic as an area
rather than precise point, and as always,
to have a stop loss in place.
In fact, you can keep yourself reminded of
this by using two Mcginley Dynamic instead
of just one, and use the area bounded between
these two lines as a zone of supply (support)
or resistance as the case may be.
Dynamic support and resistance can be found
where the dynamic line intersects with the
current price.
Let’s take a look at this Aussie Dollar
chart.
We’ll look for dynamic support and resistance
supplied by the 10 and 20 dynamic lines.
Notice how the 10 and 20 dynamic lines appear
to be providing support and resistance.
These two lines can be powerful aids, but
only used in combination with the right confluence
factors.
Let’s look at a setup where these dynamic
lines converge with several other factors.
Notice how the pin bar in the chart above
rejected the 10-period Mcginley Dynamic and
at the same time rejected a key price action
level?
We also have an uptrend and no immediate resistance
above this key level.
This was an “a+” setup.
Take note that the 10-period Mcginley Dynamic
was only a fraction of why this was an A+
setup.
Like I said before, price action first, complemented
by this tool.
Here are other examples of trades using Mcginley
Dynamic as a dynamic support and resistance.
The Mcginley Dynamic tool is only as useful
as the other confluence factors that are present
on any given trade setup.
Although it offers several advantages over
classic moving averages, at its core is still
a lagging indicator, because it’s based
on previous price action.
The only thing that isn’t lagging is raw
price action.
But this is okay because we can use this useful
tool as an additional confluence factor to
our price action trading strategies.
Which period for the Mcginley Dynamic should
you use?
The answer is subjective.
There’s no “right” way to use this indicator.
Every trader seems to have their own combination
of periods that works best for them.
I personally use the 50 and 200 Mcginley Dynamic
should.
I have found them to work best with the way
i trade price action.
You can backtest different periods and add
this tool into your trading systems, to fit
your trading style.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave as like to show your support
and make sure you subscribe and hit the bell
icon to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.