Do you have yesterday's high and low marked
on your charts right now?
Chances are, you don’t!
Well let me tell you, those previous day levels
are absolutely crucial to be paying attention
to.
One of the most important factors that influence
price action is the previous day's high and
low.
These two levels serve as crucial reference
points, providing valuable insights into the
current market sentiment.
Whenever I look at the price action, one of
the first things I do is plot the highs and
lows of the previous day.
I use this indicator.
Time and again I'll see price testing that
resistance from last session before getting
rejected.
Or finding support right at the lows and bouncing.
Add them to your charts, and just see for
yourself how often the market respects them.
These levels will give you an edge in spotting
reversals and momentum shifts.
And in combination with the VWAP, the high
and low prices from the day before will offer
amazing low-risk/high-reward trade points
neglected by so many traders.
So Why are Previous Day High and Low Important?
Well, there are several reasons:
1.
First, they represent market memory: These
levels represent the maximum and minimum prices
reached by the market in the previous trading
session.
This information captures the collective sentiment
of traders on that particular day, providing
great insights into the market's current direction.
2.
These levels are also liquidity magnets: They
often attract a high volume of buying or selling
orders, as traders anticipate price movements
around these key points.
This increased liquidity can amplify price
movements, creating both opportunities and
risks for traders.
3.
Previous day high and low can also act as
psychological barriers for traders, influencing
their decision-making.
Many traders may be hesitant to enter trades
outside or inside these levels, adding to
the potential for significant price movements.
So each trading day leaves its mark through
the highs and lows it hits.
And other traders watch these levels closely
as potential battle zones, whether the price
was unable to break through resistance or
found support before falling further.
The memory of a day's action sticks around
in traders' minds even after market close.
That’s’ why these levels carry meaning
based on previous activity.
You know that at that point buyers showed
up there to stop a drop.
And sellers overwhelmed the rally attempts
around this area.
You need to have these levels on your chart,
and be ready to take action if price revisits
that area.
One of the coolest things about using those
previous day levels is how versatile they
are.
It doesn't matter if the market is trending
up, down, or sideways - those highs and lows
from the session before are always providing
clues.
In an uptrend, it's amazing how often that
yesterday's low becomes a rock solid foundation.
Price bounces right back up from it quite
often.
Of course, you’ll often see some liquidity
runs below this level.
Don’t ever expect these levels to be respected
to the pip.
On the contrary, expect liquidity hunts above
or below these levels.
Same thing on the flip side - when we're trending
down, the previous high tends to act like
a magnet, pulling price back down after any
bounce.
But it's not just trends - maybe my favorite
is watching the magic in ranging markets.
You'll see price bouncing between those two
levels like clockwork.
Testing the high as resistance before falling
back to find support at the low.
No matter what kind of action the market is
serving up, those past closing levels make
for reliable areas to find structure.
Scouting for breakouts gets a whole lot easier
when you know the zones the market will likely
run into support or resistance.
But maybe even better, you can find reliable
reversal plays even when things are moving
sideways!
The key is stacking the odds in your favor
as much as possible.
For me, that means looking for confluences
on my charts.
If I see price reacting to a day low AND bounce
from a monthly VWAP line, now we're talking
high probability!
That monthly volume-weighted average price
does a great job showing us those dynamic
support and resistance areas.
And it's always shifting based on how price
has traded recently.
So keeping tabs on how the market interacts
with those VWAP bands is a great way to spot
reversals in the making.
From studying the market over so many years,
I've noticed some repeatable things about
how price interacts with VWAP bands.
In more rangy conditions when there's no obvious
trend pushing' up or down, I've seen time
and again how reliable it is for price to
bounce between that upper and lower band like
a pinball.
Just pinging' off support at the lower line
before stalling against resistance at the
upper bands.
That middle main VWAP line acts as a real
magnet whether pulling price back up or guiding
it down again.
And it also works a charm in trends.
You’ll often spot price sidling along, respecting
the middle VWAP.
So combining the previous day levels with
VWAP - here’s how theory plays out in real
price action.
The way I see it, when those areas overlap,
that's your high probability trade area right
there.
Think about it - if price is bouncing around
a day's low AND finding' support at a VWAP
band?
You got yourself a perfect confluence zone
to be snapping up some trades.
Great odds the move will reverse in your favor.
Same goes for resistance - when the market
tests yesterday's high but then stalls right
at a VWAP line.
Textbook shorting opportunity.
So always be scouting your charts for where
those levels coincide.
You can see this market was in a bit of an
uptrend based on those higher highs and higher
lows.
But also clearly trading' sideways between
these established zones.
So when price comes down and tests right at
that previous day low AND bounces off the
lower VWAP band, to me that’s strong "buy"!
We got two major support levels stacking the
odds in our favor.
And, there's more!
We had this zone that had previously been
acting as resistance, so doubly consolidating
as support.
Three major forces stacking up under the market
– it doesn't get much better than that!
The entry is near that confluence area.
And a protective stop loss right below it
to mitigate against any potential whipsaws.
Here’s a short set up!
First aspect is we're in a clear sideways
trading zone with no momentum.
Then we've marked our key resistance area
between the previous high and upper VWAP band.
Perfect area to short as soon as we got that
touch of the confluence.
This is the aggressive entry.
As soon as price reaches the zone, you enter
a sell trade.
But for those that are more conservative,
you wait for some sort of confirmation, so
waiting for a red candle bearish rejection
is equally valid.
I'm looking at a stock that has been trading
sideways for the past few days, bouncing between
the high and low from the previous day.
Yesterday, it tested the low several times
but bounced each time.
This tells me that level is providing support.
Today, I see the price dipping again and getting
close to the previous day's low.
But this time, it's also lining up right at
the lower VWAP band.
I know from past performance that this stock
likes to find support at the low.
Adding in the fact it's now reaching both
the low and converging on the lower VWAP,
it sets up a lower risk entry point.
If I enter long as it's testing this confluence
zone, I can set my stop loss just below the
VWAP area.
This gives the trade room to bounce without
risk of triggering the stop on small volatility.
This market had been trending lower over the
past week, with each successive day's low
providing a lower low in the downtrend.
And here, we saw a price drop which closed
near the low of its range.
This established a strong support point.
The next day, price spiked up but then rolled
over at a resistance level from the prior
day's high.
It began descending back down from the upper
VWAP band, showing sellers were active on
those rally attempts.
So when it reached the confluence point of
the previous day's high along with the upper
VWAP band, that was the moment to initiate
the short trade.
Knowing we are still in a firm downtrend,
this setup gave a low-risk entry, with a protective
stop placed above both the resistance levels.
I'm looking at Tesla (TSLA).
The stock has been trending down for the past
week, with lower highs and lower lows.
On the previous day's, there is clear resistance
formed right here, with price testing it twice
but rejecting both times.
.
Today, I notice the price is rallying in the
morning and approaching once again this resistance
level from the prior day, as well as the upper
VWAP band.
This confluence of resistance signals to me
that there is a high probability of a reversal
lower if it reaches this zone.
So, the play here is a short position with
a stop loss placed above the lower VWAP band.
In this example, I see the market has bounced
between the previous high and low, forming
a sideways range.
Then price pushes up to retest the high, but
stalls directly at the upper VWAP band.
This confluence of resistance made for a great
short, since both levels were likely to cause
a reversal.
Here we have an uptrend, and I notice price
is hugging the middle VWAP line nicely.
Then it dips to retest the previous low and
bounces perfectly off the lower VWAP band.
This signal at those stacked supports provided
another low-risk long entry.
Now we have down trending conditions, price
was respecting the VWAP very well.
So when it bumped up to tag yesterday's high,
but rolled over at the upper VWAP band, it
was an ideal short setup with converging resistance.
Again, the market started to range between
the high and low, so I watched for opportunities
when it hit those levels in conjunction with
the VWAP.
A retest of the low coinciding with this VWAP
gave a low-risk entry for the next bounce.
As the trend resumed down, I see another great
short after price failed at the high and turned
off the upper VWAP.
Seeing it reverse at that confluence resistance
area led to another price fade.
I hope you see the potential of this trading,
strategy.
It’s not perfect by any means.
Of course you can refine your entries even
more, using volume or even some smart money
concepts.
So drop a like if you want a follow up video,
and in the meantime you can watch these videos.