in less than 20 minutes you'll learn
everything you need to know about Forex
Trading so what is Forex Forex is a
global marketplace where currencies are
traded it's the largest and most liquid
Financial Market in the world with
trillions of dollars Changing Hands
every single day basically it's a
24-hour market driven by economic
political and social factors worldwide
central banks hedge funds and individual
Traders like you and me all participate
in this market buying and selling
currencies in the hopes of turning a
profit at its core Forex Trading is all
about buying and selling currencies it's
like a global Supermarket where instead
of groceries you're trading money a
currency pair is simply two currencies
that are traded against each other it's
like a wrestling match between two
countries money where one currency is
trying to gain value against the other
there are three types of currency pairs
first we have the major ones which are
the most widely traded pairs in the
Forex Market they include combinations
of the world's strongest and most stable
economies these are the seven major
currency pairs next we have minor
currency pairs that don't include the US
dollar they typically involve
combinations of the other major
currencies minor pairs often have less
liquidity compared to Major major pairs
we also have exotic pairs which involve
currencies from emerging or smaller
economies paired with a major currency
usually the US dollar now in the Forex
Market a currency pair represents the
value of one currency relative to
another for example when you see Euro
USD it means you're trading the Euro
against the US dollar in this pair the
euro is the base currency and the US
dollar is the quote currency when you
buy a currency pair like the euro dollar
You're Expecting The Euro to appreciate
while the dollar depreciates when you
sell the currency pair You're Expecting
The Euro to depreciate while the dollar
appreciates in the Forex Market every
currency pair has two prices the bid
price and the ask price let's take the
aie dollar pair as an example the price
on the left side is called the bid price
this is the price at which you can sell
Australian dollars and buy US Dollars
the price on the right side is called
the ask price this is the price at which
you can buy Australian dollars and sell
US dollars in other words when you're
trading a currency pair you're always
buying one currency and selling another
simultaneously the difference between
the bid and ask prices is called the
spread if the bid price is 0. 6635 and
the ask price is 0.66 37 the spread is
two Pips the spread is essentially the
cost of trading as it represents the
difference between the price at which
you can buy and sell the currency pair
spreads can vary depending on the
currency pair market conditions and the
broker you're using so it's very
important to pay attention to the bid
and ask prices as they determine the
potential profit or loss of your trads
when you place a buy order you'll enter
the trade at the ask price and when you
place a sell order you'll enter the
trade at the bid price now let's talk
about two crucial Concepts in Forex
Trading Pips and lots a pip which stands
for percentage in point or Price
interest point is the smallest price
increment that a currency pair can move
for most currency pairs the PIP is
located at the fourth decimal place
let's say the a dollar rate moves from Z
0.
6345 to 0.6
346 that might not seem like a big deal
but in Forex that's a one pip move now
not all currency pairs have their pip at
the fourth decimal place in Yen pairs
the PIP is at the second decimal place
so for US dollar Japanese Yen a move
from 1
1.45 to
1.46 is a one pip move Pips are essenti
IAL because they help you measure the
distance between your entry and exit
points which ultimately determines your
profit or loss Pips go hand inand with
lots a lot is a unit of measurement for
the size of a trade in the Forex Market
there are four common lot sizes standard
lot mini lot micr lot and Nano Lots the
lot size you choose will determine the
monetary value of each bip movement in
your trade for instance if if you're
trading a standard lot of Euro USD each
pip is worth $10 if you're trading a
mini lot each pip is worth $1 it's
crucial to understand the relationship
between lot sizes and pip values as this
will help you manage your risk
effectively a larger lot size means that
each bip movement will have a more
significant impact on your account
balance both positively and negatively
as a beginner it's generally recommended
to start with smaller lot sizes such as
micro or mini lots to minimize risk
while you gain
experience another important concept
related to Lots is leverage leverage
allows you to control larger trade sizes
with a smaller account balance for
example if your broker offers 100 to one
leverage you can trade a standard lot
which is
$100,000 with just $1,000 in your
account while while leverage can amplify
your potential profits it also magnifies
your potential losses so it's essential
to use it wisely and in conjunction with
proper risk management techniques so
Pips measure the price movements of
currency pairs while Lots determine the
size of your trades and the monetary
value of each pip now let's say you want
to make a trade there are several types
of orders in Forex Trading a market
order is the simplest and most common
type of order when you place a market
order you're instructing your broker to
execute the trade immediately at the
best available price if you're buying
the trade will be executed at the
current ask price and if you're selling
it will be executed at the current bid
price a limit order allows you to
specify the exact price at which you
want to buy or sell a currency pair when
you place a bu limit order the trade
will only be executed if the ask price
reaches or drops below your specified
price conversely when you place a sell
limit order the trade will only be
executed if the bid price reaches or
rises above your specified price a stop
order also known as a stop-loss order is
designed to limit your potential losses
or protect your profits when you place a
stop order you specify a price at which
the trade will be closed if the market
moves again against you for example if
you're buying Euro USD and place a stop-
loss order 50 Pips below your entry
price the trade will automatically be
closed if the bid price Falls 50 Pips
below your entry limiting your loss to
that amount a take-profit order is used
to automatically close a trade once it
reaches a specific level of profit for
example if you're buying Euro USD and
set a takeprofit order 100 bips above
your entry price the trade will close
when the bid price reaches that level
locking in your profit one of the most
crucial components is choosing the right
broker a broker is a firm that offers
access to the Forex Market they act as
intermediaries between you and the
interbank market where the big boys
Banks and large financial institutions
trade currencies a broker provides the
platform the tools and the
infrastructure you need to trade
currencies from your own home now here's
the key thing to remember not all
Brokers are created equal some are more
reliable transparent and userfriendly
than others it's essential to choose a
reputable broker that is regulated by a
respected Authority and has a proven
track record of serving traders in order
to place your trads Brokers offer you a
trading platform this is the interface
between you and the market where you can
analyze price movements Place trades and
manage your positions two of the most
popular options are metatrader and
trading view now how do you anticipate
which direction a currency pair might go
well technical analysis is the answer at
its core technical analysis is based on
the idea that history tends to repeat
itself you study what happened in the
past to anticipate where the currency
pair will move in the future in a
trading platform all the ACT happens on
the charts charts are a visual
representation of price movements over
time allowing you to analyze historical
data Candlestick charts are the most
popular way to visualize past price
movements so what exactly is a
Candlestick it's a single bar that
represents the price movement of a
currency pair during a specific time
frame like 5 minutes 1 hour or one day
each Candlestick has a body and two
weeks sticking out from the top and
bottom the body represents the range
between the opening and closing prices
while the Wicks show the highest and
lowest prices reached During the period
if the closing price is higher than the
opening price the body is usually
colored green or white if the closing
price is lower than the opening price
the body is usually colored red or black
now here's the thing the candlesticks
look different depending on the time
frame you're looking at a the time frame
is the interval at which candlesticks
are displayed on the chart each time
frame tells a different story about the
market the lower time frames like 1
minute or 5 minute show more granular
price movements and are often used for
shortterm trading strategies like
scalping or day trading the higher time
frames like daily and weekly show a
bigger picture view and are often used
for longer term position trading or
swing Trading it's like looking at a
city from different altitudes from the
ground level the lower time frames you
see the individual streets and buildings
from a helicopter view the higher time
frames you see the overall layout and
major landmarks of the city in addition
to chart types technical analysis
involves using various indicators and
tools to analyze price action indicators
are simple mathematical calculations
based on historic price and there are a
lot of popular technical indicators to
analyze the Forex Market a moving
average is probably the most common
Forex indicator that will help you
identify Trends relative strength index
is another common one a momentum
oscillator that measures the speed and
change of price movements the May CD is
also popular a trend following momentum
indicator used to capture the trend
Direction Ballinger bands is another
popular one designed to measure Market
volatility these are just a few examples
of the many technical analysis tools
available on any trading platform as you
progress in your trading Journey you'll
likely develop a preference for certain
indicators that align with your trading
style now we need to talk about one of
the most important aspects of Forex
Trading which is Trend analysis a trend
is the general direction in which a
market is moving you can identify three
main types of trend
first is the uptrend also known as
bullish Trend an uptrend is a series of
higher swing highs and higher swing lows
in price in other words each Peak is
higher than the previous Peak and each
trough is higher than the previous
trough this indicates that buyers are in
control pushing prices up over time when
you spot an uptrend you may want to
consider looking for opportunities to
buy as the trend suggests that prices
are likely to continue Rising a
downtrend also known as a bearish trend
is characterized by a series of lower
swing highs and lower swing lows in
price each Peak is lower than the
previous Peak and each trough is lower
than the previous trough this indicates
that sellers are in control pushing
prices down over time when you identify
a downtrend you may want to consider
looking for opportunities to sell as the
trend suggests that prices are likely to
continue continue falling we can also
have sideways Trend also known as a
range-bound market a sideways Trend
occurs when prices are oscillating
between a specific high and low without
forming higher swing highs or lower
swing lows this indicates that neither
buyers nor sellers are in clear control
in a sideways Market you may look for
opportunities to buy near the bottom of
the range and sell near the top taking
advantage of the price o ations support
and resistance are two of the most
fundamental and Powerful Concepts in
Forex Trading think of support and
resistance as invisible floors and
ceilings in the market their price
levels where the market has historically
had a hard time breaking through either
because there's a lot of buying or
selling pressure at those levels support
is like a trampoline it's a level where
prices tend to bounce off and start
heading back up this happens because at
these levels buyers find the prices
attractive and start scooping up the
currency pair pushing prices higher on
the flip side resistance is like a
ceiling that prices have a hard time
breaking through it's a level where
sellers come out in full force this
selling pressure can cause prices to
stall or even start falling back down
now here's the really cool part once
prices do manage to break through a
support or res resistance level that
level can switch roles a broken
resistance level can become a new
support level and a broken support level
can become a new resistance level if
price is at an obvious support level and
you believe the level will hold you
might consider buying as there's a good
chance prices will bounce off that level
and head back up if prices are nearing a
resistance level and you think it will
hold you could look to sell expecting
prices to stall or fall back down now
there's a lot to talk about Forex
Trading but as a beginner practicing on
a demo account is one of the smartest
moves you can make demo trading allows
you to trade in real time with live
market data but with virtual money
instead of your real money this way you
can get a true feel for the market and
the trading platform without the
pressure of potential losses and once
you start trading a live account you
realize there is a psychological
difference between trading with virtual
money and putting your own capital on
the line now I know the Allure of Forex
Trading can be strong the promise of
Financial Freedom The Thrill of the
markets and the stories of big profits
but here's the truth plain and simple
Forex Trading is not a get-rich quick
scheme if someone tells you they became
millionaire in a short period of time
they are simply lying Forex Traders in
is a serious skill that takes time
dedication and discipline to master it's
not about making a quick Buck or hitting
the jackpot with one lucky trade it's
about developing a solid foundation of
knowledge building a robust trading plan
and consistently executing that plan
over time and now that you got
familiarized with the basics it's time
to learn more advanced concepts these
trading courses are the next videos you
should watch