Your entry timing could be the weakest link in
your plan, but you can fix this easily. Here are
some proven entry models that work no matter the
market or strategy. Engulfing candles at supply
or demand levels work because they show you what
matters. Control. Price moves to a key level, then
prints a candle that fully covers the previous
bar. For a bullish entry, a big green candle
eats a red one. For a bearish entry, a big red
candle swallows a green one. This shows a shift in
control. So, why does this entry model work? It's
simple. Markets move because buyers and sellers
fight for control. When price hits a supply or
demand level, everyone watches, waiting for a side
to get on top. The engulfing candle answers that
question in real time. In a bullish engulfing,
the green candle tells you buyers didn't just show
up. They overpowered the sellers and erased all
the selling from the last candle and more. Also, a
supply or demand level isn't just a random price.
It's where lots of trades happened before. It's
where people expect a fight. So when an engulfing
candle forms there, you're not just seeing a
candle, you're seeing the outcome of all that
pressure. The sellers in this case didn't just
win. They crushed the other side and made it clear
who's driving now. This entry works because it's
based on what's happening right now. You don't
need to predict. You just react. When the candle
closes, you enter your trade. That's your signal.
You're not jumping in early. You're not chasing.
You're waiting for proof that the shift already
happened. Waiting for the close of the engulfing
candle is important. This keeps things simple. You
don't have to scroll through lower time frames or
set up complicated triggers. You just wait for the
candle to finish. If it's a bullish engulfing, you
buy at the close. If it's bearish, you sell at the
close. This entry method also gives you a clear
place to set your stop. The low of the engulfing
candle for longs and a high for shorts. The beauty
of this entry model is its simplicity. You aren't
lost in a sea of lines or setups. You watch for
price to test the level, see who wins, and act on
the proof. The engulfing candle is your go signal.
This keeps you from chasing moves or getting
caught in weak levels. Support and resistance flip
is one of the simplest, clearest, most dependable
entry models you'll ever see. It's about seeing
the moment when the crowd changes its mind. So,
picture what happens in a strong uptrend. Price
keeps pushing higher and reaches a resistance
area. Sellers try to stop the move here. You may
see price bounce down a few times, but each bounce
is weaker. Then price finally breaks through
resistance and after the breakout price doesn't
just run non-stop. It often pulls back. The same
thing happens in reverse in a downtrend. Price
falls through a support level and sellers win.
Price keeps dropping but then curls back up to
test the same area. And now the old support acts
like a ceiling. But why does this flip work? It's
about how traders get trapped and how big players
fill their orders. When price breaks out, many
traders are watching the old resistance. Some sold
short there. Others waited to buy until after the
breakout. When price pulls back, those who sold
want to get out with a small loss, so they buy
back at the new support. New buyers who missed the
breakout also enter on the pullback. Big traders
use this spot to fill large buy orders without
moving the price too much. The flip is where old
sellers turn into new buyers. It's the same for
support turning into resistance. Old buyers flip
to sellers. You want to enter at the flip, not at
the first breakout. You know that breakouts can
be tricky. They often fail with price snapping
back into the range and trapping traders. But
when price breaks out, pulls back and holds at
the flip, you see real strength. The market is
showing which side is in control. This is your
entry spot. And a real flip zone is usually wide,
not a thin line. The reality is that markets are
messy. Sometimes price will poke just past the
level, then turn. Sometimes it will fall short.
So draw your support and resistance as bands,
not razor thin lines. This helps you see where the
action really is. If you wait for a perfect touch
every time, you'll miss the best trades. The first
retest is usually the strongest. After the initial
breakout, the first time price comes back to test
the flipped level, the reaction is often fast and
clear. Later retest can still work, but the edge
is strongest on the first or second touch. The
more times a level gets tested, the weaker it
becomes. The more obvious the level, the more
traders are watching and the stronger the reaction
when the flip happens. First pullback after a
market structure shift is another proven and
effective entry. Imagine you spot price going down
for days. Suddenly it flips. It breaks a recent
high, showing buyers finally took control. That's
a market structure shift. Most new traders rush
in right there, scared to miss the move. But the
first move after a shift is often wild and sharp.
It's full of traders bailing out of all trades,
stops triggering, and late chasers piling in. If
you enter right at the shift, you risk getting
caught in this mess. The smarter way is to wait
for the first pullback. After that shift, price
makes its first move in the new direction, then
pauses or retraces, maybe to a moving average,
maybe to a previous level. You don't jump in
during the noise. You wait for price to slow down,
pull back, and then show it's ready to run again.
Enter as soon as you see buyers or sellers step
back in. and price rums the new trend. This way
you're not guessing. You're following proof.
The market reality is that trends don't go in
straight lines. After every strong move, you'll
see a counter move, a pullback. In this case, that
means a short drop as traders take profits or late
sellers try to fight back. But these pullbacks
are weaker than the main move. They don't have
the power to reverse the trend. Instead, they
stall out. The stronger trend steps back in and
price continues. When you trade the first pullback
after a market structure shift, you're getting in
after the dust settles. The wild emotional part
of the reversal is over. Now the market is showing
its real direction. You get a clean entry with
the trend, not against it. Again, let's break
down the entry. Price drops for days, makes a new
higher high. Instead of buying right there, you
wait. Price pulls back to a demand zone. You watch
for signs that selling is drying up, like smaller
candles, lower volume, or even a reversal bar. As
soon as price pushes back up, resuming the trend,
you buy. Your stop goes below the pullback low.
You're in the new trend, but not chasing. This
entry method keeps you out of trouble. Right after
a market shift, things get choppy. The first push
in the new direction is often fast and can snap
back just as quick. If you buy the breakout or
sell the breakdown, you risk getting trapped when
price pulls back. The first pullback gives you a
second chance, an entry with less risk and less
noise. Trading the first pullback gives you a
better risk-to-reward setup. Your stop is close,
just under the pullback low for longs and just
above the pullback high for shorts. Your target
is the next swing high or low or even further if
the trend keeps running because you enter after
some profit taking or counter trend action. You
often get a cheaper price. You're buying low
in an uptrend or selling high in a downtrend.
The first pullback after a shift repeats itself
because price always moves in waves. People buy,
take profit, price pulls back, then the next move
starts. The next entry model involves liquidity
grabs against the main trend. So, picture a
strong uptrend. Price keeps making higher highs
and higher lows. Everyone sees it. Traders want
in. They chase price buying late and footing their
stops just below the last swing low or the nearest
support. Now think about the big traders, the ones
who need a lot of volume to buy. They can't just
buy at any price. If they do, they drive the price
up before they get enough filled. So they hunt for
liquidity. Liquidity is where lots of orders wait
to be triggered. in an uptrend. Think of all those
stop- losses sitting just under the last low.
That's a pool of sell orders. When price drops
into that zone, those stops fire off and sellers
rush in. For the big buyers, this is perfect. They
want to buy and now there's a flood of sell orders
to buy from. This is the liquidity grab. Price
dips under support, grabs all those stops, fills
the big buy orders, and then rockets back up.
The trend keeps going. The weak hands are gone,
and the big traders are in. That's the setup.
So, why does this entry work so well? It's all
about how the market actually moves. Most retail
traders want to buy when price is running up,
but that's the worst time to buy. You risk buying
the very top just as price is about to pull back.
The liquidity grab flips this around. You don't
buy the top. You wait for a sharp drop against
the trend right into the place where everyone
else's stops will trigger. That drop is the grab.
It scares out traders who bought late and set
their stops too close. When they get stopped out,
their sell orders fill the big buyer's orders.
Once the selling is done, there's no one left to
sell. Price snaps back up and the trend continues.
The entry is simple, but it needs patience. You
wait for price to drop below a recent low in an
uptrend or above a recent high in a downtrend.
You know, that's where liquidity pools sit. You
want to see a quick flush, price slices through,
then price snaps right back up. That's your
signal. You enter as soon as price comes back
above the broken support or as soon as the candle
closes back inside the range. Your stop goes just
below the liquidity grab low. You catch the move
right as the trend resumes, not after it's already
run far away. This entry keeps you out of trouble.
Instead of chasing, you wait for price to come to
you. You don't get caught buying the top. You
don't panic and sell when price flushes down.
You know the grab is most likely a trick. A move
to shake out weak hands and fill big orders. One
big advantage of this entry model is that you get
great prices. You're buying near the bottom of the
drop, not the top of the run. This means your stop
is tight. You can put it as below the grab. Your
risk is small and your reward is big if the trend
keeps going. Opening range breakout is a good
entry model for fast trades. It takes the chaos of
the morning and turns it into a simple actionable
plan. Every morning, markets wake up with a bank.
There's a rush of orders, leftover trades from the
night before, and new bets for the day ahead. And
this chaos sets up one of the simplest, sharpest
entries you can use, the opening range breakout.
You start by watching the first stretch after the
open, maybe 5, 15, or 30 minutes. You mark the
highest point and the lowest point price reaches
in that window. That's your opening range. It's
like drawing two lines on a field. Above is buyers
win. Below is sellers win. But you don't trade
yet. You wait. The market is in a fight and you
want to see who wins. Once the opening range is
set, you watch for a clean break above or below. A
breakout tells you that one side just overpowered
the other. If price breaks decisively above the
range, buyers win. If price breaks below, sellers
take control. The breakout isn't just a random
move. It's often the start of a strong trend for
the rest of the day. That's why you enter with a
break, riding the momentum right as it starts.
The entry itself is simple. Set your lines at
the high and low of the opening period. As soon
as price breaks out and trades in the new zone,
you enter in that direction. You're in right at
the start of the move when momentum is strongest.
One big advantage, the opening range breakout
gives you a clear mechanical entry. You know
exactly where to act. The line is drawn and as
soon as price consolidates above or below it,
you go. This keeps you from hesitating or
getting stuck in indecision. With a clean break,
you get in early right as the crowd moves
together. Another edge, the opening range
gives you built-in risk management. your stop
goes at the opposite side of the range. If you
enter on a break above the high, your stop is
at the low. If you go short on a break below,
your stop is at the high. This means your risk
is defined from the start. You know how much you
could lose before you even enter. There are also
downsides. The biggest risk is the false breakout.
Sometimes price pokes above the high or below the
low only to snap right back into the range. This
fake out can trap you, forcing a quick loss.
That's why opening range breakouts don't work
every single time. Some days you get trapped and
stopped out quickly. Another challenge, breakouts
fail more often when the opening range is unclear
or choppy. If the first candles are wild and
overlapping with no clear direction, you're more
likely to get faked out. On those days, it's
better to skip the trade than force an entry. So,
only act when the range is clean and price action
is decisive. Pivot point bounce is a classic
entry, one of my favorite models. You simply mark
the main daily or weekly pivot levels. These lines
are not magic, but they matter. Price reacts to
them again and again. That's because many traders,
big and small, watch the same levels. Their orders
cluster there. That makes pivots like magnets,
pulling price in, then sometimes flipping it away
fast. This entry model works because pivots show
where trades might pile up. When price moves into
a pivot, it's like a test. Will it smash through
or bounce off? You don't try to guess before it
happens. You wait for price to hit the pivot,
then watch for a reaction. If price wakes hard,
prints a reversal bar, or bounces back with
energy, that's your signal. You enter in the
direction of the move away from the pivot. The
entry gets even better with the pivot's direction.
If today's main pivot sits above yesterday's,
it shows buyers control the market. You look for
long trades, buy when price bounces up off the
pivot. If the pivot is lower than yesterday's,
sellers have the edge. So, you look for shorts,
sell when price bounces down. This keeps you
trading with the bigger trend, not against it.
This entry model gives you a clear plan. You know
where to look. You know when to act. There's no
guesswork. The pivot keeps you focused. You avoid
chasing price. You don't have to stare at dozens
of indicators. You just mark your pivots, wait for
price to come to you, then watch for the reaction.
This model repeats day after day. Pivots give you
built-in risk control. If you enter on a bounce,
your stop is close just on the other side of the
pivot. that keeps your losses small. If you're
wrong, if the bounce holds, price can run far,
giving you a strong reward compared to your risk.
This makes the setup clean and efficient. Timing
also matters. Pivots work best when the market is
active, at the open, during big sessions, or when
volume is strong. In slow times, the bounce can
be weak or fizzle out fast. So watching volume and
timing helps you avoid weak trades. Snapback from
overextended move is a high-risk highreward entry.
Price can run far in one direction, sometimes
too far. You see this in big moves that stretch
past normal ranges, break out of channels or
push beyond VWAP bands. At some point it has
to slow down or turn back. These are overextended
moves. When everyone chases the move, price often
gets pushed way past what's normal. This is when
aggressive traders watch for a snapback. Now,
why does this entry work well? Big moves attract
attention. Traders jump in hoping the momentum
will keep going, but the more extended the move
gets, the more likely it is to snap back. There's
a point where buyers or sellers get exhausted. No
one left to push price further. You see the signs,
a reversal candle, a big wick, or a sudden spike
in volume. They show exhaustion. When price snaps
back inside the band or channel range, that's
the entry. You're betting that price will return
closer to its average, not keep running forever.
This is called mean reversion. Price usually moves
around an average. When it goes too far from that
average, it often comes back. The snapback entry
takes advantage of this. You wait for the crowd to
push price to the extreme, then enter when you see
the first sign of reversal. The entry itself is
sharp. You don't guess where the top or bottom is.
You watch for price to move far outside the normal
band, maybe outside a channel, past VWAP lines,
or way above the average range. You wait for
exhaustion, a candle with a long wick and a sudden
spike in volume. As soon as price snaps back
inside the band, you enter. Your stop goes just
past the extreme. This setup works because markets
move in cycles. Big trends get overdone. When they
stretch too far, the move becomes unstable. Weak
hands jump in late hoping for more. But smart
traders know the risk is now high. Profit taking
or stop losses trigger and price snaps back fast.
Because you enter close to the extreme, your stop
is tight. Your risk is small but your reward can
be big if price returns to the average or further
because you enter close to the extreme. Your stop
is tight. Your risk is small but your reward can
be big if price returns to the average or further.
But this model isn't easy. The biggest risk is
trying to call the top or bottom too soon. A
lot of times price will go further than you think,
blowing past your levels and stopping you out. And
that's okay because this entry model works on high
reward ratios. Even if you catch one out of three
reversals, you will still be in profit. This entry
is not for everyone. It's tailored for aggressive
traders. You're going against the current trend,
stepping in as the crowd is still bushing. That
takes nerve. There's always the chance the
move keeps going and you're caught fading a
trend that isn't finished. That's why waiting
for clear exhaustion is key. Range expansion
after compression is a sharp entry because it's
built on pure price action. Price moves in waves.
Sometimes it runs fast and wild. Other times
it gets stuck moving in a tiny box. This is
compression. The market is resting. And this is a
clue. Something big is coming. Compression shows
up as a tight range, candles with small bodies,
and no one really winning. Buyers and sellers
both wait. Volume drops and the chart goes quiet.
But underneath, pressure builds, orders stack up
on both sides. Traders get bored, impatient,
or even trapped. The longer the compression,
the bigger the pressure. You don't jump in during
this quiet period. Most trades fail here. Price
chops sideways and fake outs happen. You let the
compression build. So, you mark the top and bottom
of this zone. Now comes the entry. You wait for
the breakout. A big candle, strong volume. Price
bursts out of the tight box. The expansion must
be sudden and sharp. This is the moment you enter,
right as the market wakes up. Now, why does this
work? Compression is like a market inhale. The
move after the range expansion is the exhale.
All the orders that built up during compression
get triggered at once. Stops fire. Breakout
traders rush in. Trapped traders bail out. Volume
explodes. The first move out of compression is
often the cleanest, fastest move. You catch that
burst by entering right as price expands. This
setup works because it focuses on timing. Most
traders get chopped up in noisy markets, entering
too soon or too late. Compression gives you a
clear signal. The entry is simple. Mark the high
and low of the compression zone. As soon as price
breaks out with a strong candle and increased
volume, you enter in the direction of the move.
You're in right as the market shows its hand.
You get more than just a good entry. You get a
built-in stop. If you go long on a breakout up,
your stop goes just inside the compression zone.
If you go short on a breakdown, your stop goes
just above the range. This keeps your risk tight
and your reward open. The move after compression
often runs far, giving you a strong risk-to-reward
setup. This model also filters out bad trades.
If price never breaks out, you don't enter. If
the breakout is weak, like a small candle and no
volume, again, you skip it. Only the clean, strong
expansions, get your trade. This entry model works
because it's rooted in how markets build energy
and release it. The first move out of compression
is your chance to jump in before the crowd with a
plan and with purpose. You set your lines, wait
for the squeeze, then enter only when price
breaks out for real. You keep your stop tight,
your entry clear, and your edge simple. Now, if
you're ready for more interesting trading guides,
go ahead and watch one of these videos next.