What time frame to use when day trading is
an important choice.
And the right time frame will vary by each
person, the strategy they use, and how they
like to spend their trading time (meaning
a more relaxed trading session versus more
intense one).
In this video we’ll talk about a simple
concept to choose the right time frame for
day trading, in order to make the right decision
right from the beginning.
Professional traders spend little time choosing
a time frame.
Their choice of time frame isn't based on
their trading strategy or the market in which
they're trading.
It's based on their own trading personality.
Before we begin, here is a chart that shows
the difference between a 1, 5, and 15-minute
chart.
They all show 12 hours of price data on the
same day, but, as you notice, there is a significant
difference in detail.
So let’s talk about the benefits and drawbacks
of each day trading time frame so you can
decide which one is right for you.
A 1-minute time frame may work well for someone
who likes seeing detail in the price movements
and potentially getting in and out for short-term
trades that only last a few minutes.
Trading the one-minute requires nearly constant
attention while trading, since candles are
generated every minute and trade signals can
occur often (depending on your strategy, of
course).
Because price bars occur frequently, 1-minute
chart traders typically have the opportunity
to take more trades per day compared to other
time frames.
With a winning system, more trades means more
profit and faster compounding of the account.
But with the potential for more activity,
a trader who doesn’t have a good risk management
strategy can diminish their capital rapidly.
On a 1-min time frame, it’s possible to
make several trades within a two-hour trading
session.
And it’s perfect if you don’t want to
spend too many hours in front of your screen.
With trades based on smaller candles, stop
losses and profit targets tend to be smaller
than those used by higher time frame traders.
This doesn’t have to be the case, though.
A trader could use a small stop loss on the
1-minute chart and aim for large reward:risk
trade.
The main takeaway is that the 1-minute time
frame is for people who want to maximize their
trading time with more trades, typically with
slightly increased position sizes, using small
stop losses and profit targets.
A 5-minute chart may work well for someone
who focuses on bigger intraday trends and
doesn’t need to see the open-high-low-close
price every minute, but would rather get data
over 5-minute periods.
Trading the five-minute requires focus, but
less constant attention than the 1-minute
chart because candles are forming every five
minutes, so there is more time between data
points.
If you wait for the candle to close before
acting, this means no action is taken for
at least 5 minute intervals, and often longer.
Thus, 5-minute chart traders tend to trade
less than 1-minute chart traders because there
are fewer candles to act on.
Depending on your strategy, one or two trades
may develop in a two-hour trading session,
possibly more, but less than on the 1-minute
time frame.
Stop losses and profit targets tend to be
a larger than on the 1-minute chart.
This isn’t good or bad, but it does typically
mean fewer trades per day.
Because candles and price swings are bigger
on the 5-minute chart, this means a greater
distance between the chosen entry and exit.
So the main takeaway is that the 5-minute
chart is for people who want to focus on larger
intra-day movements, recieving fewer signals,
with moderate positions sizes.
A 15-minute time frame is for someone who
wants to see the major trends and movements
throughout the trading day.
Trading on 15 minute chart requires less constant
focus because candles are occurring over a
longer period.
If you wait for candles to close then there
is at least 15 minute period between possible
actions.
Traders on this time frame may only be taking
one or two trades per day.
But if you are only trading during a two-hour
session, many days may have no trade signals.
So trading this time frame may require more
time in front of the screen since it takes
longer to get into and out of trades.
Stop losses and profit targets tend to be
larger than on the 5-minute chart, so this
means fewer trades per day.
Positions sizes are usually smaller than those
on a 5-minute chart because candles and price
swings are bigger, which likely means a greater
stop loss distance.
But because of fewer trades and a smaller
position size, it is easier to have multiple
positions.
The main takeaway is that the 15-minute chart
is for people who want to focus on the large
price movements throughout the day.
If you don’t mind waiting longer for trades
to open and close, if you prefer cleaner movement
and if you plan only one or two trades over
multiple hours of trading, then the 15-min
time frame might work for you.
Some traders only day trade on one time frame,
while others trade multiple time frames to
produce trading opportunities.
A single time frame means you see a trade
on the 1-minute chart (or whatever time frame
you use) and you take that trade.
Multiple time frame trading means you look
at a longer-term chart and use it as a filter
for trades on the lower time frame.
In this case, a trader may check the 15-minute
for the overall trend direction, and then
look for opportunities to enter in that trend
direction on the 1-minute chart, for example.
Most day traders pick one time-frame and then
almost never leave it.
They are so locked into their time frame that
they forget about the bigger picture.
The other extreme are traders that constantly
jump from timeframe to timeframe without much
of a plan.
That’s why the best solution is a top-down
multiple time frame analysis where you start
on the higher timeframe, the 15 min or 30
min time frame, look for the bigger picture
perspective and then slowly build your trading
plan by going lower.
And don’t start your analysis on the lowest
time-frame and then work your way up to the
higher time-frames.
This creates a very narrow and one-dimensional
view and it misses the point of the multiple
time frame analysis.
Now, time frames are often discussed as if
they are the only charting option.
They are not.
There are chart types based on things other
than time and one of them is the range bar
chart.
Range bars are bars that are plotted on a
chart that have the same price increment,
the same height, and each bar closes either
at the high or the low, regardless of the
opening price.
There is no time component as you would see
with candlestick charts or bar charts.
In Tradingview for example, if you want a
range of 10 pips on the Pound Dollar and you
are trading with range bars, set your range
to 100.
Every time the pair moves 10 pips up or down
in total for that bar, it will complete the
current bar and start a new one.
So time has no effect.
Here are the key takeaways to keep in mind
when day trading with range bars:
All range bars are uniform in size because
the range is constant
You can choose any bar size you want, based
on your needs (you can select a 4 pip, a 39
pip or any size you want)
The time period covered by each bar is irrelevant
as range bars are time-independent
For this reason, range bars can help you to
identify ranging price action in a blink of
an eye.
And potential support and resistance levels
are more clearly visible on the chart.
Probably the biggest advantage, especially
for day trading and scalping, is that lot
of the false signals that come with the time-based
charts are eliminated.
Time-based charts will always post the same
number of bars during each trading session
regardless of volume, volatility or any other
factors.
The only time you’ll see more range bars
printed on the chart is when we have periods
of higher volatility.
And even then it’s dependent on the range
bar size selected by the trader.
Inversely, when we have low volatility, you’ll
see fewer range bars printed on the chart.
And this is a huge improvement over classic
time frames.
So if you ever struggled with trade management
strategies when day trading, try using range
bars, because range bars are an effective
tool to time your entry and exit points.
Another day trading and scalping alternative
is the tick chart.
The bars on a tick chart are created based
on a particular number of transactions.
Again, time is irrelevant.
For example, a 200-tick chart creates a new
bar after every 200 transactions.
You can customize tick charts to the number
of transactions you want, for example, 5 ticks
or 500 ticks.
Remember, time does not play a role here.
As tick charts are transaction based and new
bars are formed only when there are enough
trades, the market noise is reduced.
And you know that higher the noise, the more
difficult it becomes to make smart decisions,
especially when day trading, when you need
to act fast.
The main advantage of a tick chart is that
compresses low-activity trading periods.
On a time-based chart, you may see 20-30 useless
candles, while the tick chart may offer you
only 10-15 relevant ones.
Tick charts can help you in placing better
stop-loss orders and take-profit levels on
the chart.
This is especially useful during periods of
high volatility and rapid price movements.
And without the accumulation of small candles
like the ones on the time-based charts, tick
charts make it easier for the trader to spot
price swings.
I will say it once again, there is no best
time frame or a combination of time frames.
A winning strategy can be built on any time
frame, or any combination of time frames.
But understanding the pros and cons of each
time frame will hopefully help you decide
which one works best for YOU.
I’m mainly a swing trader, but when I day
trade, I tend to use a multiple time frame
analysis using range bars.
This works for me, but might not be your style.
One time frame is not better than the other.
But one may be more favorable to you because
it provides more trading opportunities, or
has a cleaner look.
And it’s your job to back test, analyze
and determine which one works best for you.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support and don’t forget to subscribe and
hit the bell icon to get notified every time
we release new videos.
Until next time.