The Ichimoku Cloud is a versatile indicator
that defines support and resistance, identifies
trend direction, shows momentum and provides
trading signals.
Even though the Ichimoku Cloud may seem complicated
when viewed on the price chart, it's actually
a rather straightforward indicator; the concepts
are easy to understand and the signals are
well-defined.
Ichimoku takes multiple averages, plots them
on the chart and uses these figures to compute
a "cloud" which attempts to forecast where
the price may find support or resistance in
the future.
The Ichimoku Cloud consists of five lines.
Conversion Line, Base Line, Lagging Span,
Leading Span A and Leading Span B.
First component: Conversion Line, also known
as Tenkan-Sen
The Conversion Line shows the short-term price
momentum.
On its own, it shows the mid-point price over
the last 9 periods, which is the default value
for this indicator.
Conversion Line signals an area of minor support
or resistance.
• If the market price is above the conversion
line, this indicates a short-term upward momentum,
and you would want to concentrate on buying
signals
• If the price is below conversion line,
this shows a short-term downward momentum,
and you would want to search for selling signals
• An increasing conversion line, meaning
an upward slope, indicates an upward trend
• A decreasing conversion line, meaning
a downward slope, indicates a downward trend
Due to the very short-term nature of the indicator,
it is not typically used on its own but rather
used in conjunction with the other elements
of the Ichimoku Cloud.
Second component is the base line, also known
as the Kijun-sen or the confirmation line.
The base line serves as a signal for support
and resistance levels on medium term.
The base Line is the mid-point of the high
and low price over the last 26 periods.
On its own, the base line can also be used
for analyzing price momentum.
• When the price is above the base line,
it means the price is above 26-period mid-point
and therefore has an upward bias.
• If the price is below the base Line, it
is below the mid-point price, and therefore
has a downward bias.
• An increasing slope of the base line indicates
an upward trend
• A decreasing slope of the base line indicates
a downward trend
Unless there is a very strong trend, the base
line will often appear near the price.
When the base Line is often intersecting or
near the price, it is not as useful for helping
to evaluate the trend direction.
Third component: lagging span, also referred
to as Chikou Span
The lagging span is created by plotting closing
prices 26 periods behind the latest closing
price of an instrument.
This lagging line is designed to allow traders
to visualize the relationship between current
and prior trends, as well as to spot potential
trend reversals.
One of the key ways to use to the indicator
is to view its relationship to the current
price.
• When the price is below the lagging span,
this is usually an indication there is strength
in the price and it is moving higher.
• When the price appears above the lagging
line, this is often an indication there is
weakness in the price.
If it appears that the lagging line is about
to cross above the prior price line, it would
be a bullish confirmation sign, while a span
that is crossing underneath would be a bearish
confirmation sign.
Trading signals based on the Chikou span are
strongest when it doesn’t touch or cross
over any the prior candles.
Any interaction with the past price line is
an indication of a choppy or sideways market.
If a lagging line is descending quickly into
a past price line, it could be a sign of exhaustion
for the asset.
Forth component: Kumo cloud, which is formed
from 2 lines (leading span a and leading span
b)
The Kumo Cloud provides support/resistance
levels that can be projected into the future.
This sets the Ichimoku Cloud apart from many
other technical indicators that only provide
support and resistance levels for the current
date and time.
The uptrend is strengthened when the Leading
Span A (green cloud line) is rising and above
the Leading Span B (red cloud line).
This situation produces a green cloud.
Conversely, a downtrend is reinforced when
the Leading Span A (green cloud line) is falling
and below the Leading Span B (red cloud line).
This situation produces a red cloud.
Because the cloud is shifted forward 26 periods,
it also provides a glimpse of future support
or resistance.
If it is thick, then the support/resistance
is strong (depending on the position of price
in relation to the cloud).
By contrast, if it is thin, then the S/R levels
are considered weak.
Generally, if the price is above the Kumo,
then there is an uptrend in place and/or more
buying opportunities.
If the price is below the Kumo, then it is
under resistance and it is better to be looking
for shorts instead of longs.
The longer price action stays above or below
the Kumo, the stronger the trend and the more
support/resistance the Kumo offers.
The Kumo can be very effective for long term
traders as well as for trend/momentum traders.
This is because price will stay on one side
of the Kumo cloud during a trend.
The farther the price action is from it, the
stronger the trend and more volatile it is.
Generally, you should avoid trading inside
the Kumo cloud, as it signals a period of
indecision.
As a type of moving average system, Ichimoku
signals are generated by crossovers of the
key lines, namely conversion line and base
line.
When the Tenkan/conversion line crosses over
the Kijun/base line, it generates a buying
signal.
A signal to sell appears when the Tenkan/conversion
line crosses below the Kijun/ base line.
But in Ichimoku theory, the signals are not
created equal, and this is where the cloud
comes into play.
If the two lines cross to the downside while
current prices are above the cloud, only a
weak sell signal is generated.
The strongest sell signal appears when the
downside crossover occurs while prices are
below the cloud, essentially signaling that
fresh weakness is now evident within an overall
downtrend.
The same guidelines apply to upside crossovers
generating buy signals and the location of
current prices to the cloud, with the strongest
buy signal coming from an upside crossover
while prices are above the cloud.
Here are several examples of conversion line
- base line crossovers, with Kumo cloud as
filter.
The chikou/lagging span provides yet another
way to evaluate the strength of the crossover
signals given by the tenkan/conversion line
and kijun/base lines.
Remember that the chikou/lagging span is simply
today’s closing price projected 26 days
into the past, providing a clear look at today’s
market level relative to earlier prices.
If a sell signal is generated on a downside
crossover and the chikou/lagging span is below
the price candles, the signal is considered
stronger.
If a crossover to the upside occurs and the
chikou/lagging span is above prices, then
a higher probability is attached to the buy
signal.
Again, the idea is that a crossover in the
direction of the overall trend is considered
more powerful than one that is against the
trend.
The crossover between span lines forming the
Kumo cloud is another trading strategy used
by traders, in a similar fashion to a moving
average crossover.
However, remember that the lines of the cloud
are projected forward by 26 periods.
• when leading span A of the Kumo cloud
crosses above span b, and prices are positioned
above the Kumo cloud, we have a strong buy
signal
• when leading span A of the Kumo cloud
crosses below span b, and prices are positioned
below the Kumo cloud, we have a strong sell
signal
• when leading span A of the Kumo cloud
crosses above span b, but prices are positioned
below the Kumo cloud, we have a weak buy signal
• when leading span A of the Kumo cloud
crosses below span b, but prices are positioned
above the Kumo cloud, we have a weak sell
signal
Another trading technique involves the Kumo
cloud breakout.
This signal occurs when the price cuts through
the Kumo cloud.
• when the price enters the Kumo cloud and
breaks its upper line, we have a bullish signal
• when the price enters the Kumo and breaks
its lower line, we have a bearish signal
If the price is clearly above or below it,
then when price action breaks the kumo, it
can often signal a reversal.
There are several factors which increase the
chances of a reversal, such as:
· The thickness of the Kumo when broken
· The amount of time price action has been
on one side of it
· How far price action has moved before touching/breaking
the Kumo
· and also the time frame
Ichimoku relies on only three different time
periods in its calculations: nine, 26 and
52.
Japanese financial markets used to be open
for trading on Saturdays, meaning that the
trading week was six days long.
As a result, the number nine represents a
week and a half of trading; 26 equals the
number of trading days in a typical month
(30 minus four Sundays); and 52 equals two
months of trading days.
Japanese markets now trade only five days
per week, so some practitioners of Ichimoku
suggest revising the parameters to seven,
22 and 44.
In my experience, however, the traditional
default settings of nine, 26 and 52 have performed
the best.
Ichimoku does have its limitations.
Let’s face it, the indicator can make a
chart look busy with all the lines.
To remedy this, depending on your trading
needs, certain lines can be hidden.
For example, all the lines can be hidden except
for the Leading Span A and B which create
the cloud.
You need to focus on which lines provide the
most information for you, and then consider
hiding the rest if all the lines are distracting.
Another limitation of the Ichimoku Cloud is
that it is based on historical data.
While two of these data points are plotted
in the future, there is nothing in the formula
that is predictive.
Averages are simply being plotted in the future.
The cloud can also become irrelevant for long
periods of time, as the price remains way
above or below it.
At times like these, the conversion line,
base line, and their crossovers become more
important, as they generally stick closer
to the price.
As always, if you found value and learned
something new, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay notified when we release
new videos.
Until next time.