If you have a 9 to 5 job, becoming a trader
in your spare time can be quite a challenge.
Many people have an interest in trading but
don't want to pursue it as a full-time career
or to give up their day job to do it.
And you don’t have to quit your job because
many traders only trade part-time, for one
or 2 hours per day.
So if you have other time commitments but
you still want to trade part-time, the following
strategy can help you to maximize your efforts
in the least amount of time and record consistent
results over the long term.
So let’s get started!
The strategy involves trading price extensions
in 3-wave patterns, using only price action
and the Fibonacci 161.8 level.
Our aim is to trade price action that takes
place primarily in the third wave of a 3-wave
pattern.
A 3-wave pattern is a simplified Elliot wave
cycle.
If you are familiar with Elliot wave theory,
you probably know that trying to trade it
in real time is quite difficult, especially
for beginners.
The major problem is that you cannot really
recognize an Elliot Wave until it has already
passed.
So, I decided to focus only on the first 3
waves of the cycle.
And let me explain how I do this.
Prices within all major financial markets
tend to move in a fairly predictable manner.
Essentially, the market is composed of impulsive
price moves, and corrective price moves.
Elliot wave cycle is a 5-wave pattern.
Three of those waves (1, 3 and 5) move in
the direction of the underlying trend, while
the two waves (2 and 4) act as countertrend
interruptions, or retracements.
Well, because Elliot waves are subjective,
I decided to focus only on the first 3-waves:
an impulsive wave, a corrective price move
and another impulsive move, which is the price
movement we will trade.
The 3-wave pattern is used as a continuation
trading setup that is designed to take advantage
of the second impulsive move of the market.
In any up trending market, there is a pattern
of higher highs and higher lows.
In order for the trend to the upside to remain
active, each successive impulse swing must
take out the point B in the formation.
When price surpasses the price at #2 swing,
you can use this as confirmation that the
3-wave pattern is present.
This is a chart that explains the concept
of the 3-wave trading pattern.
In an uptrend market situation, price will
make 3 points
Point A is the lowest low point, which forms
a support level.
Point B will be the highest point, and forms
a level that we consider as potential resistance
Point C will be the 2nd low point, a support
level (which must be higher than point A).
The breakout of price above point B signals
the continuation of the uptrend.
In a downtrend market, the 3-wave pattern
forms when:
Point A becomes the highest point when price
finds resistance and moves down.
Point B becomes the lowest low point (and
forms a level that we consider as potential
support) and
Then price moves up and finds another resistance
at point C.
When price breaks the point B support level,
it indicates that the market is most likely
to continue downward
The most important variable in this strategy
is the swing size, the first AB wave, because
our risk to reward ratio will depend on the
strength of the first impulse wave.
A swing size that is too small can reduce
profit targets to such narrow margins that
it becomes difficult to execute them.
If the swing size is too big, it could take
weeks or even months to reach the target price.
The trading strategy requires the following
steps:
• Defining a minimum swing size, meaning
the first wave of the 3-wave pattern
• Applying the Fibonacci tool, with a small
twist, to find the 1.618 ratio.
• Taking a trade at the 50% Fib level.
Now, stay with me for the next part because
it’s important.
In order to find the 1.618 ratio, you could
use FIB extentions.
But I like to do it in another way.
The correct way to apply a FIB retracement
is from a swing low to the swing high in an
uptrend (from Point A to Point B), and from
the swing high to the swing low in a downtrend.
To find the 1.618 ratio, I add the FIB retracement
from Point B to point A, so the other way
around.
I know it might seem weird or incorrect, but
this is how I like to find the 1.618 ratio.
Here are the main conditions in order to find
the best signals:
1.
Trend line breakout
A trendline acts as a support for the price
when applied to consecutive higher lows in
an uptrend, and as a resistance when applied
to consecutive lower highs in a downtrend.
Once a rising trendline is broken, that trendline
becomes a resistance for price.
Similarly, once a falling trendline is broken,
that trendline becomes a support for the price.
Basically, the first wave, AB wave must be
the wave that breaks the trendline, like in
this example.
If this sound complicated, don’t worry,
we’ll have plenty of examples later.
2.
Point C must be higher than Point A for an
up move and lower than point A for a down
move
When AB wave ends, it will lead to a price
move lower in BC wave, that will retrace a
portion of the wave one move.
However, the second wave must not fall below
the start of wave one.
This is an extremely important rule.
The second wave must retrace to the 38.2 Fib
level at most.
If it retraces to 23.6 Fib level, I personally
ignore the setup.
The buy or sell zone, depending on the setup,
is the area between 38.2 and 50 Fib level.
3.
If price fails to retrace to the 50% Fib level,
ignore the setup.
In some cases, the trendline will be broken,
but the price action won’t make a decent
retracement.
Sometimes it will retrace to the 61.8 level
and then resume its move.
For this setup, we want price to retrace to
the 50% level.
If it doesn’t, we find other opportunities.
So, trendline breakout, find the AB wave,
apply FIB retracement from point B to point
A, and try to take a trade at around the 50%
Fib level, targeting the 1.618 ratio.
It’s easy, and most important, price-action
based.
Here we have the setup on the pound dollar
on the 4-hour time frame.
We have a clear trendline breakout.
Point A is the lowest point in the chart,
starting the AB wave.
Also the AB wave breaks the trend line.
Point B indicates a possible bullish trend.
A possible, because we don’t know yet, the
price may reverse in the opposite direction.
So we apply the Fib retracement, remember,
the other way around, from point B to point
A.
Point C indicates the pullback, in this case
to the 38.2 Level, which is a valid condition.
If price stalls and rejects the level, you
could switch to a lower time frame to time
your entry
My preference is to enter the trade at the
50% FIB level, with a stop loss below the
23.6 level and targeting the 1.618 ratio.
If price starts moving upwards, then the breakout
of price at point B would add fuel to our
position.
Most trades would enter right here, at the
breakout of point B, but we had a better,
a smarter entry.
At the moment of the breakout, we would be
already in profit.
When price breaks point B, you could move
your stop to break even.
I personally do it every time.
Sometime the prices retraces to the entry
point, leaving us with a breakeven trade and
sometimes goes right to our target.
In this example, the price continued its upward
direction and reached the 1.618 ratio.
Here we have Euro dollar on the daily time
frame.
We have the trendline breakout.
Point A is the highest point in the chart
starting the AB wave and this wave breaks
the trend line.
Point B indicates a possible bearish trend.
Then we apply the Fib retracement from point
B to point A.
Price retraced to the 38.2 Fib Level, forming
a pin bar, a reversal pattern.
We enter the trade at the 50% FIB level, with
a stop loss above the 23.6 level and targeting
the 1.618 ratio.
After the breakout of price at point B, price
came back to retest the level, which then
became a strong resistance area.
When price breaks point B, we moved our stop
to break even
And the price continued its downward direction
and reached the 1.618 ratio.
And look how powerful that level was.
As price reached that level, it immediately
bounced back.
Another long position, this time a continuation
trade.
Here’s the trendline breakout, with AB wave
as the first impulsive move.
Price retraced more that 50%, remember, almost
reaching the 38.2 level.
We enter at the 50% level, with a stop loss
below this area and targeting the 1.618 ratio.
Observe once again, that after price broke
the B point, that level became a support area.
Price retested the level, new traders enter
the market, and took the price to our final
target at the 1.618 ratio.
The reward to risk ratio is maybe the most
important metric in this trading strategy.
By entering at the 50% level and targeting
the 1.618 level, you get at least 3:1 risk
reward ratio, at minimum, in most cases over
4:1 risk to reward ratio.
Remember the rules we discussed before.
If the price retraces all the way to the 23.6
level, ignore the setup.
And if the price doesn’t reach the 50% level,
again, look elsewhere.
We need those conditions, for the highest
probability setups.
IN this example, price retraced and even closed
above the 38.2 level, which invalided the
setup.
And the price did retrace, most likely because
of the initial trendline breakout, another
important condition.
And even if the price managed to close below
the B point, it failed to reach our final
target.
You could try to trade this scenario, and
squeeze some points, maybe to the 100% level.
The best part of this strategy is that you
only have to spend 30 – 60 minutes each
day, which makes it perfect if you have a
busy program and don’t have time to trade.
Make sure you analyze the Daily, 4H and 1H
timeframes and avoid narrow range markets,
with too much or not enough volatility, and
other bad conditions.
And yes, you could also use this strategy
for day trading, on lower timeframes.
Here are other example of valid trades.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support and don’t forget to subscribe and
hit the bell icon to get notified every time
we release new videos.
Until next time.