Tradingview recently introduced a new chart
type, the High Low chart, and for price action
traders, this could be of great help.
Today I’ll show you how to read price action
using High Low charts and you’ll also learn
how to easily find trends and trade with the
current momentum.
You know the drill, like, subscribe, and stick
around for the full video.
High-Low chart
The High-Low chart is located in the chart
type selection menu.
Bars are built based on the value of the maximum
and minimum prices for a given timeframe.
The price values for which the chart was built
are displayed on each bar, below and above
the bar.
This type of chart basically removes the open
and close price, and instead, you see the
range in which the value changed, on your
timeframe.
If you want to customize it, in the Chart
Settings, you can change the color of the
bars and text.
I personally don’t have a problem with the
fact that I don’t see the red and green
color of the candles.
By having the same color on up and down candles,
you’ll actually trade in a neutral/ unbiased
state of mind.
This chart looks weird at first, because you
don’t see the open and close.
You are only seeing a range.
But from a price action perspective, if you
are a trader who is analyzing highs and lows
in price, this is very helpful.
Most traders are looking at major market swings
when they are analyzing highs and lows and
determine trends.
But you can also analyze highs and lows of
individual candlesticks.
With the High Low chart, reading price action
of individual candlesticks is super easy.
When the high and the low of the recent candlestick
is higher than the high and low of the previous
candlestick, market is in a bullish momentum
and buyers are controlling the market.
There is buying pressure.
When the low and high of the recent candlestick
is lower than the low and high of the previous
candlestick, market is in a bearish momentum
and sellers are controlling the market.
You see just how easy it is to read price
action, bar by bar.
Candlestick simplified
Now, using the High low chart presents an
opportunity to simplify candlestick trading.
If you are that type of trader that memorized
dozens of candlestick formations, you’re
in luck, because you don’t have to over-complicate
things.
With this type of chart, there are only 4
candlestick formations.
First candlestick formation is the bullish
candle.
A bullish candle has a higher high and a higher
low compared to the previous bar.
Second formation is the bearish candle.
Bearish candlesticks have a lower high and
a lower low, again, compared to the previous
bar.
Third type is the inside candlestick, which
has a lower high and higher low relative to
the previous bar.
This bar is contained within the range of
the previous candlestick.
Even if the high or the low are equal to the
previous candlestick, it’s still an inside
bar.
Last formation is the engulfing candlestick,
which has higher high and lower low relative
to the previous bar
And even if either the high or the low are
equal to that of the previous bar, it’s
still an engulfing bar.
So this is the foundation of your price action
analysis: bullish and bearish candlesticks,
inside candles and engulfing candles.
It’s time to train your eyes to easily spot
each formation, on a high low chart.
Open any chart, and start reading price action.
We have both highs and lows that are lower
than the previous bar, so this is a bearish
candlestick.
Another bearish candlestick.
And another one.
Another bearish candle.
Here’s the first inside bar, with a lower
high and higher low compared to the previous
bearish candle.
Next is a bearish candle.
Another bearish candle.
Another one.
Again, a bearish candlestick.
Bearish candle once again.
Okey, we have our first engulfing candle,
with a higher high and lower low compared
to the previous bar.
Another bearish candlestick.
Next is a bullish candlestick, with a higher
high and a higher low compared to the previous
bar.
Another bullish bar and now trend seems to
change to the upside.
Bullish candlestick again.
Another bullish candle.
Next is an engulfing candle.
Bearish candlestick.
You see just how easy is to read price action.
I’ll say it again, you don’t need to memorize
other candlestick combinations.
So, to get used to high low charts, the first
thing is to start reading candlesticks until
it becomes very easy to determine which type
is.
6 Price action rules
Now, you might ask, how is this useful to
trade?
It’s simple.
Once you know to recognize these candlesticks,
you’ll then determine the state of the current
trend.
To find the current trend, you follow 6 easy
rules.
1.
If you have consecutive bullish bars, you
are in a minor uptrend.
2.
Consecutive bearish bars indicate a minor
downtrend.
3.
A bullish candle starts an upswing and confirms
the end of a downswing.
4.
A bearish candle starts a downswing and confirms
the end of an upswing.
5.
Inside candlesticks are neutral bars.
They don’t affect the direction of the current
swing, because they do not break the previous
high and low.
So an inside bar after a bullish or bearish
candlestick don’t change the current trend.
6.
Engulfing candlesticks introduce uncertainty
into the market structure, because they break
both the previous high and low.
But, we’ll give the benefit of the doubt
to the current swing.
So, engulfing candlesticks in an upswing continue
the upswing.
Engulfing candlesticks in a downswing continue
the downswing.
Now, let’s look at the previous example
and let’s mark the main swings, based on
the bars that changed the direction of the
market swings.
These bars are inside candlesticks and engulfing
candlesticks and they do not affect the direction
of the market swings.
Let’s change markets and find the market
swings based on this system.
You simply look for bullish candles to start
an upswing and to confirm the end of a downswing.
And for bearish candles to start a downswing
and to confirm the end of an upswing.
And you include the inside candlesticks and
engulfing candlesticks in the respective swing.
First we have a downswing, with many consecutive
bearish candles.
Then, an upswing, this is the candle which
interrupts the previous down leg.
And another downswing, this is the candle
which ends the upswing.
Then market forms an upswing, and another
downswing.
Upswing once again.
Then I see a choppy period, with a small downswing,
a small upswing and another downswing.
And finally, another upswing.
This analysis might seem very simple and unimportant.
But if you understand how the swings are marked
and you see the swings clearly, you will identify
the current direction of the market with ease,
at any point in time.
Support and Resistance trading
I found that high low charts are great to
trade support and resistance, and are also
a good filter to eliminate false breakouts,
when price moves beyond a previously established
price range but then retreats back to within
the range.
As you probably know, one of the classic rules
of support and resistance is that support,
once violated, becomes resistance and conversely,
resistance, once violated, becomes support.
With high low charts, and the previous swing
recognition technique, you can find decent
trades around major levels in the market.
So on this GBP/USD hourly time frame, we see
an uptrend, with price trading around this
resistance level.
We have a candle breaking the previous high,
and a quick retracement below the level.
After a small consolidation, we have a valid
breakout.
So a decent signal would be at the re-test
of the previous level, when the downswing
is ended with a bullish candlestick.
Here’s the signal.
I like to enter when the high of the bullish
candle is broken, but you can also enter immediately
after you see the candle.
Stop goes below the most recent swing and
we’ll be conservative and we’ll set a
risk to reward ratio of 2.
You see how using this type of chart helped
us to avoid the first fake out and allowed
us to enter, in the direction of the main
trend, when a new upswing was forming.
Liquidity clear-outs
Another great way is to trade liquidity clear-outs
in the direction of the main trend.
If you watched my previous smart money manipulation
video, you know I like to join the market
after a false breakout.
Markets hunt for stop orders and activity
beyond significant price levels.
If this breakout occurs and fails, there will
be many trapped traders, which can add momentum
to the opposite direction from that level.
The best trades of this type occur in direction
of the main trend.
In this example, we have a clear downtrend,
with price currently in consolidation.
For a short entry, the market trades above
this resistance area, and immediately reverses
on the following bars and closes back under
the resistance.
There no real continuation beyond the level.
And when the price forms a bearish candlestick,
which ends the previous upswing, we can take
a short trade, after this liquidity clear-out,
in the direction of the main trend.
Stop goes above the previous swing high, and
we’ll target this next swing low in the
price structure.
Here’s another example.
We have a clear support, in an obvious uptrend,
with the price being unable to continue lower.
We then have a small breach below support,
but price immediately closed back above the
support level.
Once the movement was confirmed by a bullish
candle, the wiser trade would be a long trade,
instead of chasing the failed breakout.
Stop loss is placed below the previous swing
low, and we’ll target this next swing high
in the price structure.
In some way, high low charts eliminate some
market noise.
You don’t see the wicks, the red or green
candles.
I can see the market swings and the support
and resistance levels very easy using high
low candles.
You see, many traders follow market swings
in a wrong manner and find them useful only
in hindsight.
They are unable to apply the concept of market
swings in real-time.
With this chart, and following some basic
price action rules you will know exactly the
current price wave you are in, and with a
solid understanding of support and resistance,
you will find good areas to trade from.
Of course, there are lots of other methods
to trade high low charts, involving volume
and even with indicators, divergences in particular
work very well in combination with these candles.
So if you a follow up video about high low
candles, leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.