Bollinger bands are one of the most popular
technical analysis tools implemented in today’s
trading environment.
As the name implies, Bollinger bands refer
to the bands (or price channels) placed on
a chart to represent a volatility range.
Bollinger bands consist of a set of three
bands drawn in relation to price: there is
the 20-period moving average in the middle,
with an upper and lower band of two standard
deviations above and below the simple moving
average.
Bollinger bands use a statistical measure
known as the standard deviation, to establish
where a band of support or resistance levels
might lie.
This concept is also known as a volatility
channel.
A volatility channel plots lines above and
below a central measure of price.
These lines, also known as envelopes or bands,
widen or contract according to how volatile
or non-volatile a market is.
Bollinger bands® measure market volatility
and provide lots of useful information, including:
Trend continuation or reversal
Periods of market consolidation
Periods of upcoming large volatility breakouts
Possible market tops or bottoms, and potential
price targets
Bollinger bands are a trend indicator that
detects the volatility and dynamics of the
price on the market.
The bands contract when the market volatility
is low and expand when volatility increases.
During periods of low volatility, the bands
are narrow, while during periods of high volatility
Bollinger bands expand drastically.
The upper band shows a level that is statistically
high or expensive
The lower band shows a level that is statistically
low or cheap
The Bollinger bandwidth correlates to the
volatility of the market
For a technical point of view, trading near
the outer bands provides an element of confidence
that there is resistance (at upper boundary)
or support (at bottom boundary), however,
this concept alone does not provide relevant
buy or sell signals; all that it determines
is whether the prices are high or low, on
a relative basis.
So, the general consensus is that when the
price reaches the upper band it is considered
as overbought and when price approaches lower
band it is considered oversold.
The Bollinger bands have a default setting
of (20,2) . When using trading bands, it is
the price action as it nears the edges of
the band that should be of particular interest
to us.
Now, regarding standard deviation of the Bollinger
bands.
What is it?
The standard deviation is basically a number
expressing how much the values of the price
differ from the mean value.
Prices will distribute around the simple moving
average:
Around 65% of price action is contained within
a standard deviation of 1 of the Bollinger
bands
Around 95% of price action is contained within
standard deviation of 2 of the Bollinger bands;
Almost 99% of the price action is contained
within standard deviation of 3 of the Bollinger
bands.
Ok, how to use this information?
If you decide to back test Bollinger bands
and play with its inputs, you can adjust the
value of the standard deviation.
If you lower it, you will see the price leaving
the bands often, probably offering a lot of
noise.
However, if you increase it to 3, you will
realize that the price will leave the band
rarely, and might be better to find dynamic
zones of support and resistance.
So, lower settings on the Bollinger bands
will generate more trading signals, but will
also increase the number of false signals,
as the price movement will exit more often
from the bands.
On the other hand, a 2.5 standard deviation
Bollinger bands or even a 3 standard deviation
will generate fewer, but high-probability
signals.
Now, I prefer to trade with the odds in my
favor.
So, if a standard deviation of 3.0 will offer
me around 99% certainty that the price won’t
exit the Bollinger bands, then I will be interested
to trade only with these settings.
How to trade Bollinger bands?
The use of Bollinger bands varies among traders
depending on their overall trading strategies,
styles and goals.
When using Bollinger bands, many define the
lower and upper bands as price targets.
Some buy when the price touches the lower
band and exit when the price touches the moving
average in the center of the bands.
Others prefer to sell when the price falls
below the lower band or buy when price breaks
above the upper band.
The upper and lower bands can act as dynamic
resistance and support levels, as traders
generally avoid buying when the asset price
hits the upper Bollinger band, respectively
avoid selling whenever the price reaches the
lower Bollinger band.
In a sideways market, when there isn’t a
clear trend on the chart, Bollinger bands
provide very good support and resistance,
as most traders believe that there’s high
chance of prices staying within Bollinger
bands.
Studies have shown that the penetration of
Bollinger bands with a standard deviation
of 3 occurs rarely.
The rest of the time prices fluctuate within
the Bollinger bands, and often price returns
to the middle of the bands.
In this way Bollinger bands seem to act like
rubber bands that can only stretch so far
before snapping back to the middle.
The upper and lower ranges of the Bollinger
bands, which are created by the 2 or 3 standard
deviation lines, create the boundaries of
price.
Since there are greater odds that price will
be contained within the bands instead of penetrating
them, one of the surest and most common ways
of trading the bands is to buy when prices
near the lower band and sell when prices near
the upper range band.
But not blindly.
We talked before about price action.
This strategy is suited in non-trending markets,
when there isn’t a clear direction.
Even more, when the bands are parallel, the
signal is even more powerful.
So we want to sell at the upper bb and buy
at the lower bb, when the bands are parallel,
and preferably, if we see addition confirmation
of a support or resistance.
Here are a few examples of Bollinger bands
signals during ranges……
Also, you could take signals during trends,
but only in the direction of the main trend.
Why is that?
Just because prices hit the upper or lower
Bollinger does not necessarily mean that it
is a good time to sell or buy.
Strong trends will “ride” these bands
and wipe out any trader attempting to buy
on the “low” prices in a downtrend or
sell on the “high” prices of an uptrend.
In fact, price will be making new highs in
an uptrend and new lows in a downtrend, hitting
and exceeding the bands, quickly taking out
the stops on trades taken directly on the
bands.
So, instead, we look to sell the upper bb
during downtrends, meaning when the price
is making lower lows and lower highs, and
buy the lower bb in uptrends, when the price
is making higher highs and higher lows.
Practically we look for pullbacks or corrections,
but in the direction of the trend, we don’t
chase reversals.
Here are a few examples of Bollinger bands
signals during trends…..
As we previously mentioned, Bollinger bands
indicator measures the volatility on the market.
The wider the band, the more volatility it
has.
A narrow band means indecision on price movement
and when this happens, it is almost always
guaranteed that markets are about to move
either up or down.
Also, if the market has recently experienced
a lot of volatility and the bands are far
apart, this is a sign that the market will
settle down and trade into a range in the
near future.
Another Bollinger bands strategy that is relatively
simple to implement is known as a squeeze
strategy.
Squeeze refers to the narrowing of the trading
range and implies a potential breakout.
It happens when the price starts shifting
sideways in a tight consolidation.
You can visually identify when the price is
consolidating as the lower and upper bands
get closer together on the chart.
It means the volatility of the particular
asset has decreased.
After a period of consolidation, the price
usually tends to make a larger move in either
direction, ideally on higher volume.
Expanding volume on a breakout is a sign that
traders are expecting that the price will
continue to move in the breakout direction.
The longer it moves within this narrow band,
the more likely the market is eventually going
to penetrate these bands and continue on in
the direction of the breakout, especially
if this event occurs in the direction of the
previously established longer-term trend.
Timing is everything, however, and just we
don’t know how long the squeeze will last.
How to identify the breakout?
Look at the hooks of Bollinger bands.
We want to see the upper band pointing up
and lower band pointing down.
If the bands remain flat or just one band
hooks while the other does not, the breakout
isn’t there yet.
However, if upper band is rising while the
lower band is falling, after a period of consolidation
and tight range, this signifies that a potential
explosion in price action is about to occur,
in the direction of the candlestick pushing
against the band.
The more vertical, the stronger the potential
move.
Here are other examples of valid Bollinger
bands breakouts.
If you got any value from this, make sure
you subscribe, hit the bell icon so you’ll
be notified each time we upload and leave
us a like to show your support.
Until next time.