If you look at any price chart and you will
notice that price does not move in a straight
line.
It does not move up or down vertically.
It moves in waves, and these waves are called
market swings.
In a bull market, price rises with a series
of up and downswings.
Naturally, the upswings generally exceed the
downswings in length.
The reverse is true in a bear market.
By observing market swings, you will be able
to notice the structure of the market and
get clues on whether the market will move
up or down.
And following market swings must be your first
step to read the market bias.
Another way to look at market swings is to
think of them as a higher time frame perspective.
Each swing is equivalent to a bar in a higher
time frame.
This is why some traders use a higher time
frame to evaluate market bias.
There are two challenges with the higher time
frame approach.
First, the higher time frame is usually chosen
arbitrarily.
Common choices are multiples of three and
five.
For instance, if your trading time frame is
1-minute, using a multiple of five, you will
use the 5-minute chart for determining the
market bias.
However, there is often no sound basis for
the choice of the higher time frame.
Next, by using a higher time frame, you must
split your attention between two time frames.
While some traders might find that manageable,
some try to keep trading as simple as possible
and focus on one chart only.
By analyzing market swings, you will be able
to factor in the price action of a higher
order into your analysis without a second
chart showing a higher time frame.
The advantage of this approach is that you
will be able to evaluate the ongoing price
action within its larger context on the same
chart.
So, we will focus on reading market swings
to deduce the market bias using a single time
frame.
So how to define market swings.
The first step is to classify every price
bar into one of the following four types:
up bars, down bars, inside bars and outside
bars.
These labels describe the relationship of
each bar high/low relative to the previous
bar.
1.
Up bars have the following characteristics
– Higher high, higher low compared to the
previous bar
2.
Down bars have lower high, lower low compared
to the previous bar
3.
Inside bars have lower high, higher low relative
to the previous bar
If the high or the low or both are equal to
that of the previous bar, it is still considered
an inside bar.
4.
Outside bars have higher high, lower low relative
to the previous bar
If either the high or the low are equal to
that of the previous bar, it is still an outside
bar.
So, by using this approach, the closing price
of a price bar does not matter in the classification.
An up bar might close lower than it opened.
A down bar might close higher than it opened.
For a bar that closes higher, we will use
the term “bullish bar”.
For a bar that closes lower, we will use the
term “bearish bar”.
Let’s identify the candles in this example.
We have 4 up bars, followed by an inside bar,
another 3 up bars, and another up bar, despite
being a red candle, because the high and low
were higher relative to previous bar… we
then have a down bar, 3 up bars, 2 down bars
and an inside bar, up bar, then outside bar
because the high and the low are equal to
that of the previous bar, so it is still an
outside bar.
Then an up bar, an outside bar, followed by
an inside bar, and another inside bar, 2 down
bars, 4 up bars, inside bar, down bar, an
inside bar, down bar, an inside bar and finally
an outside bar.
With this approach, you don’t need to memorize
tens of candlestick combinations, you just
need this 4 types of candles.
I recommend opening a chart and start reading
candlesticks until it becomes very easy to
determine which type is.
Do this until you will be able to recognize
the type of the candle almost instantly.
Once you have mastered the different bar types,
you will be able to identify market swings
with ease, with these four rules.
1.
An up bar starts an upswing and confirms the
end of a downswing.
2.
A down bar starts a downswing and confirms
the end of an upswing.
3.
Inside bars do not affect the direction of
the current swing because they do not break
the previous high and low
4.
Outside bars break both the previous high
and low so it introduces uncertainty into
the market structure.
However, as each swing is a minor trend itself
and trends tend to continue, we give the benefit
of the doubt to the current swing.
Thus, outside bars in an upswing continues
the upswing.
Similarly, outside bars in a downswing continues
the downswing.
Now, we took the previous example and we marked
out the market swings, based on the bars that
changed the direction of the market swings.
The circled bars are inside bars and outside
bars and they do not affect the direction
of the market swings.
So most swings are confirmed by an up bar
or a down bar.
However, under exceptional circumstances,
it is possible for a swing to form without
either an up bar or a down bar.
An upswing can be formed when the market rises
above the last swing high without forming
an up bar.
Similarly, a downswing can be formed when
the market falls below the last swing low
without forming a down bar.
An outside bar is always involved in such
cases.
This is example of the market forming a new
downswing without a down bar.
And this is an example of the market forming
a new upswing without an up bar.
1.
The market has been forming regular swings
with up bars and down bars.
2.
This bullish outside bar broke above the last
swing high.
There was no up bar.
However, as the last swing high has been broken,
despite the lack of an up bar, we must recognise
that a new upswing has been formed.
And here is an outside bearish bar marking
a new swing.
Let’s take a look at another price swing
example and see which shows the correct price
swings?
Is it A or B?
Example B is the correct one.
Although this point might seem like a swing
low, it is not.
Typically, an outside bar doesn’t end or
start a price swing.
Without a down bar or a break below the last
swing low, an upswing will continue.
So why is this analysis important?
Well, if you understand how the swings are
marked and you have learned to identify market
swings clearly, you can confidently state
the current direction of the market wave at
any point in time.
This is an important first step to uncovering
the market bias.
The next step to determine market bias is
determining swing pivots.
Swing pivots are the turning points of each
market swing.
The point where an upswing turns down is a
swing high.
The point where a downswing turns up is a
swing low.
Why are swing pivots important?
Swing pivots are price points that turned
the tide of the market.
These points are not random.
They represent a momentary change in demand
and supply forces.
In this example, bulls could not move the
market above this swing high, not even for
one tick.
This means that at that point in time, no
one was willing to offer a price higher than
the swing high.
Traders saw no value above the swing high
and didn’t want to buy above the swing high.
Hence, when prices move close to or above
a swing high, we must remember that traders
saw no value in buying above that point previously.
Assuming that most traders have not changed
their opinions, prices are unlikely to move
above the swing high.
So, the swing high marks a price area that
resists the market from moving up.
This is what we call a resistance area.
In the case of a swing low, the bears could
not push prices below it.
This occurrence implies that no trader was
willing to sell below that particular price
point.
The reason was that traders perceived value
below the swing low.
They want to buy value and not sell it.
So when everyone wants to buy and no one wants
to sell, price goes up and we get a swing
low.
The logic we applied to analyzing swing highs
works for swing lows.
When the market falls near a swing low, assuming
that traders still see value in buying below
the swing low, prices are unlikely to fall
below it.
The swing low supports the market and is a
support area.
The failure of swing highs and lows to hold
up at resistance and support respectively
leads us into another concept.
• Failed resistance turns into support
• Failed support turns into resistance
When a resistance level projected from a swing
high fails to block a market from rising higher,
it turns into a support area.
This is because, despite its failure, the
price point remains memorable to market participants.
A price point that has failed decisively as
a resistance will then serve as a reliable
support.
You can apply the same logic to failed support.
After failing to hold prices up, they serve
as potential resistance.
`
Here we have an example of a failed resistance
turning into support.
1.
We used swing highs to project possible resistance
levels.
2.
The market rose above with ease, crushing
the resistance.
3.
The failed resistance then became a powerful
support zone.
In a nutshell, there are two key skills in
reading price action.
1.
Evaluate how likely a swing pivot will hold
up as support/resistance.
2.
Understand the implication of a swing pivot
not holding up as support/resistance.
This might seem very easy and basic, but is
one of the most important concepts in trading.
Tracking market swings and understanding what
they are telling you about the market are
foundational price action trading skills.
Many traders follow market swings in a wrong
manner and find them useful only in hindsight.
They are unable to apply the concept of market
swings in real-time.
With this simple approach, you will know exactly
the current price wave you are in, and with
a solid understanding of support and resistance,
and confluence of swing pivots, you will find
the best areas on a chart to trade from.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.