Chaikin Money Flow is a technical indicator
which determines if an instrument is under
accumulation or distribution.
The Chaikin Money Flow compares the closing
price to the high-low range of the trading
session.
• if the price closes near the high of the
session with increased volume, the Chaikin
Money Flow increases in value
• if the price closes near the low of the
session with increased volume, the Chaikin
Money Flow decreases in value.
Chaikin Money Flow measures buying and selling
pressure over a set period of time and is
a popular indicator among the traders who
use volume technical analysis.
Along with the On Balance Volume, the Chaikin
Money Flow is tracking the Money Flow on a
market.
What are the setting of this volume indicator?
Traders generally use 20-periods or 21-periods
for calculating the Chaikin Money Flow indicator.
Some traders also use the 50-period Chaikin
Money Flow to determine the accumulation /distribution
on the longer term.
• Chaikin Money Flow settings with values
over 30 make the indicator less sensitive.
This will result in fewer, but better quality
signals
• Chaikin Money Flow settings with values
below 20 make the indicator over-sensitive.
This will result in more market noise.
Lower settings on the Chaikin Money Flow indicator
should be carefully traded, as it can lead
to many false signals
How To Read Chaikin Money Flow
Chaikin Money Flow is used by traders to confirm
the market trend.
CMF values above zero indicate an uptrend
while CMF values below zero suggest a downtrend.
• when the Chaikin Money Flow indicator
is above 0-level this is a bullish signal
is below 0-level this is a bearish signal
The Chaikin Money Flow usually stays between
-0.5 and 0.5 levels and rarely reaches its
maximum/minimum values of -1 and 1.
A movement of the Chaikin Money Flow oscillator
from negative to positive or vice versa does
not suggest a change in trend.
So remember this observation because in choppy
markets the CMF generates many false signals.
The Chaikin Money Flow is also used by traders
to confirm the strength behind an uptrend
or a downtrend.
In this regard, the indicator resembles the
Average Directional Movement (ADX), which
also measures trend strength.
Chaikin Money Flow confirms the breakouts
of support and resistance levels.
During an uptrend, if a breakout of a resistance
occurs while the CMF reaches new highs, this
suggests that the bulls are taking control
of the market.
This is a signal of an uptrend continuation
During a downtrend, if a breakout of a support
occurs while the CMF reaches new lows, this
suggests that the bears are taking control
of the market.
This is a signal of a downtrend continuation
However, the Chaikin Money Flow has a flaw.
The CMF is not handling gaps very well.
For example, if a gap occurs on the upside
and closes at a lower price, the money flow
would give you a negative figure, despite
the bullish price increase.
How to Read Market Conditions with Chaikin
Money Flow
• values between 0.05 – 0.25 indicate
buying pressures from the bulls.
This is a sign of accumulation and that the
market trades in an uptrend.
• values between 0.25 – 0.4 indicate that
the bulls are in control of the market.
This indicates that the market is in a strong
uptrend
• values between 0.4 – 1 indicate that
the bulls are in full control of the market.
This indicates that the market is in a very
strong uptrend
• values between -0.05 – -0.25 indicate
selling pressures from the bears.
This is a sign of distribution and that the
market trades in a downtrend.
• values between -0.25 – -0.4 indicate
that the bears are in control of the market.
This indicates that the market is in a strong
downtrend
• values between -0.4 – -1 indicate that
the bears are in full control of the market.
This indicates that the market is in a very
strong downtrend
• values between -0.05 – 0.05 signals
a decision-making period.
When the CMF trades between these levels,
the bulls and bears are putting pressure to
take control of the market.
This area is often marked by choppiness and
is better to be avoided.
How To Trade With Chaikin Money Flow
One of the most common ways in which traders
use the Chaikin Money Flow indicator is to
take signals when the oscillator crosses the
zero level.
• when CMF indicator crosses above zero,
a buy signal is generated
• when CMF indicator crosses below zero,
a sell signal occurs
If we analyze this chart, we can observe some
decent signals offered by the Chaikin Money
Flow indicator.
But being a volume indicator, by itself, the
CMF is not so reliable and it will offer many
false signals.
It’s better to confirm the trend with another
indicator.
In this case, I like to use my old reliable
200-period moving average in order to determine
the prevailing trend.
• When the price trades above the 200-period
exponential moving average, we consider taking
only long entries.
• When the price trades below the 200-period
exponential moving average we consider taking
only short entries.
Now, entering the market is much simpler.
We wait for the Chaikin Money Flow indicator
to cross above the 0-level, above 200-EMA
for a long entry and we wait Chaikin Money
Flow indicator to cross below the 0-level,
below 200-EMA for a short entry.
And here an even better entry.
A smarter way to trade the Chaikin Money Flow
would be to plot the 0.05 and -0.05 levels.
In this way, you filter the choppiness around
the 0 level.
• Take short entries below -0.05 level
• Take long positions above the 0.05 level
Here are a few examples of valid CMF trades.
Another strategy involves applying a moving
average on the indicator.
By adding a moving average on the Chaikin
Money Flow’s chart window, you can take
crossover signals,
Now, when you want to trade a crossover between
the Chaikin Money Flow oscillator and a moving
average, you should be aware of an important
thing.
A crossover will catch good movements when
markets are trending.
When markets are trading in a range, this
system is subject to false signals, which
will lead to losing trades.
A longer-term moving average added on Chaikin
Money Flow will work better than short-term
moving average.
A longer-term moving average will produce
fewer signals.
Also, this is not enough.
This approach will generate many false signals
if you don’t confirm the trend with other
indicators.
You cannot take a crossover signal without
knowing the market trend.
That’s why I prefer to determine the prevailing
trend in the market with Ichimoku indicator.
For this setup, I plot only the Kumo cloud.
So we plotted the Kumo cloud and we added
a 200-period moving average on the Chaikin
Money Flow indicator with a 21-period input.
And the setup is simple:
• Buy only signals above the Kumo cloud,
when the Chaikin Money Flow crosses above
the 200-period moving average
• Sell only signals below the Kumo cloud,
when the Chaikin Money Flow crosses below
200-period moving average
Also, very important…We don’t take entries
when the price is inside the Kumo cloud.
If a crossover between Chaikin Money Flow
and the 200 EMA occurs when the market price
is inside the Kumo cloud, we ignore the setup.
We could enter a trade once the price closes
above or below the cloud, in the direction
indicated by the crossover.
But never when the price is inside.
Here are some examples of valid trades, with
the Kumo cloud as trend filter.
Chaikin Money Flow is a very useful indicator
for confirming the direction of the main trend.
It works well during trending market conditions
and is very good at confirming the strength
of the main trend.
In what concerns its limitations, in a choppy
market, many false signals are generated around
the zero level, so be aware of this.
Also, CMF value is not accurate when big gaps
occur on the market so when you spot larger
gaps, maybe you should re-analyze the setup.
I also found the Chaikin Money Flow quite
unreliable on smaller time frames like M1
or M5, so I would pay extra attention when
using it for scalping.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like to show your support and make
sure you subscribe and hit the bell icon to
stay notified when we upload new videos.
Until next time.