Whether you want to believe it or not, Fibonacci
levels play a critical role in defining support
and resistance levels when day trading.
And determining support and resistance levels
is common problem faced by most traders.
Some of the common methods to determine support
and resistance include trend lines, moving
averages, pivot points, Fibonacci retracement
etc.
Today, you will learn how to determine hidden
support and resistance levels using Fibonacci
extensions.
Fibonacci series incorporates several analysis
tools on the basis of Fibonacci ratios and
sequences showing geometrical law of human
behavior and nature which is also applied
to financial markets.
The Fibonacci study can be applied to identify
probable support and resistance levels by
studying Fibonacci numbers in various timeframes.
Fibonacci extensions, also referred to as
Fibonacci expansions, or Fibonacci projections,
are external levels that go beyond the 100%
Fibonacci level.
You may already be familiar with these important
Fibonacci levels – 23.6%, 38.2%, 50.0%,
and 61.8%.
These are considered internal retracements
that are measured inside of a specific swing
being analyzed.
But there are important Fibonacci levels that
extend beyond the 100% level and where price
action tends to react often.
And these are what we call Fibonacci extension
levels.
Fibonacci extension is drawn by joining three
points unlike Fibonacci retracement which
has just two points by joining the lowest
and the highest points of a pre-defined trend
and vice versa.
Let’s understand how we can draw Fibonacci
extension in case of an uptrend.
You need to join the lowest and the highest
point and then after a retracement or a correction,
and the price continues in the direction of
the original trend, the low of the retracement
or a pullback would be our third point.
For example, looking at this chart, the price
moved from here to here and after this the
stock moves in the direction of the original
trend.
So the first point to draw Fibonacci extension
would be at point a, the point b will be here
and the third point will be here, at the low
of the retracement.
This will give you probable resistance levels
where the price may face resistance in the
near future.
Let’s now consider a downtrend.
In this example you can see that we have a
bearish swing in price from point A to point
B before price retraces part of this decline.
Once price has corrected to point C and then
begun selling off again we can go ahead and
apply our extension tool, mapping the swing
from point A to point B and then back up to
point C.
The most common Fibonacci extension levels
are 161.8%, 261.8% and 423.6%.
Other important resistance levels using Fibonacci
extension come at 50%, 61.8%, 78.6% and 100%.
Fibonacci extensions are a way to establish
price targets or find projected areas of support
or resistance when the price is moving into
an area where other methods of finding support
or resistance are not applicable or evident.
If the price moves through one extension level,
it may continue moving toward the next.
That said, Fibonacci extensions are areas
of possible interest.
The price may not stop and/or reverse right
at the level, but the area around it may be
important.
For example, the price may move just past
the 1.618 level, or pull up just shy of it,
before changing directions.
If you are long on a stock and a new high
occurs, you can use the Fibonacci extension
levels for an idea of where the stock may
go.
The same is true if you’re short.
Fibonacci extension levels can be calculated
to give you an idea on profit target placement.
You have the option to decide whether to cover
the position at that level.
It’s important not to confuse Fibonacci
extensions with Fibonacci retracements.
What is the difference between Fibonacci extensions
and Fibonacci retracements?
While extensions show where the price will
go following a retracement, Fibonacci retracement
levels indicate how deep a retracement could
be.
In other words, Fibonacci retracements measure
the pullbacks within a trend, while Fibonacci
extensions measure the impulse waves in the
direction of the trend.
Let’s look at some of the practical examples
to gain more clarity about the concept of
Fibonacci extension.
This is crude oil in the weekly timeframe
with one Fibonacci extensions drawn on the
above chart to show number of resistance identified
using the above logic.
At first we noticed that, the price faced
resistance at 38.2% extension and saw an immediate
selloff.
Next 50% extension acted as a strong resistance,
and you can see how the price rejected that
area, almost to the pip.
We then have a double top at the 61.8% extension
level, again, almost to the pip.
On its way down, observe how to price stopped
at the previous extension levels.
This is powerful stuff, and it’s a shame
that not many traders use this tool in their
analysis.
Let’s move on the stock market and analyze
a downtrend on Exxon mobile chart.
Here is the weekly time frame.
We have the starting point here, point b here
and the correction point here.
The extension levels are respected almost
religiously.
We have rejection at 38.2% extension level,
at 50% level, at 61.8% extension and finally
at 78.6% level.
Also, don’t neglect the fact that after
the price rejected those extension levels,
it stopped at previous levels, offering short
opportunities for those who wanted to trade
in the direction of the main downtrend.
Here are other examples of Fibonacci extension
levels on different markets.
So, how to use the fib extensions
You can consider entering the market on fib
extensions when the price reacts to a level.
This could be a bounce or a breakout.
If the price bounces from a Fibonacci extension
level, it is possible that price may be stalling
or changing direction.
In this manner, you might be able to pursue
a price move to the previous fib level.
In some cases, you will see the price clearly
breaking thru a Fibonacci extension level.
In this case, you may consider a trade in
the direction of the breakout and target the
next extension level.
Essentially, you would trade Fibonacci levels
in a similar manner to other support and resistance
levels.
The main difference is that fib levels are
considered hidden levels of support and resistance
that are not clearly recognizable to non-Fibonacci
based traders.
Stop loss order
As a general rule, you can place your stop
loss order at the next level beyond the one
that you are trading.
In the case when this distance may be too
far away from your entry point, then you can
simply use a swing top/bottom that is closer
to your entry point.
Take profit level
In trading, there are no certainties.
We are dealing with possibilities and probabilities.
And so it is important to understand that
there is no such thing as knowing exactly
how far a price move will go.
You can always set a minimum target at the
next Fibonacci extension.
However, you will see that price will very
often move farther than this, so you have
to evaluate the market condition at each level
and act accordingly.
You do this by taking into account other factors
such as volatility and average daily range,
which can help in setting logical take profit
targets.
The more volatile the market you are trading
is, the more likely it is to generate bigger
moves.
Though Fibonacci is one of the useful methods
to analyze your chart but it doesn’t provide
an exact entry point rather an estimated area
of entry.
Moreover, there is a no guarantee that the
price will reverse from any specified fib
level and hence you should combine it with
other technical parameters as a confirmation.
So use complementary indicators or patterns
when looking to determine one or multiple
price targets because we don’t always know
which level the price will reverse from.
However, this tool gives us levels to monitor.
It is then down to you to use other elements
such as confluence with other technical elements
(trend lines, moving averages, indicator readings
or price action) to decide whether to trade
the level.
Traders may differ in identifying the swing
high and swing low points from which the extension
levels are drawn, so there is some subjectivity
involved here.
But the best way around these problems is
to practice and practice!
The point is that there is no one right way
to do it, but with a lot of practice, you’ll
make better decisions of picking swing points.
Gradually you will get a feel for the trend
and the overall technical picture.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new leave us a like to show your
support and also don’t forget to subscribe
and click the bell icon to stay in touch with
new uploads.
Until next time.