Hey guys, in this video I will show you how
I read the price action in order to determine
if the bulls or the bears are in control of
the market and we’ll also try to establish
the momentum of the market by analyzing the
bull and the bear candles during a trend.
So, what is price action?
Price action is a representation of a price
movement on a given chart and in its core
it’s basically a representation of the behavior
of the market participants, namely the bulls
and the bears.
The bulls want to move the market up, and
their strength is represented by upward bars
and the bears want to move the market down,
and their strength is represented by downward
bars.
Every bar on a given chart is basically a
battle between bulls and bears.
When we read the price action on a chart,
we don’t have to over analyze and complicate
our trading, we just have to determine whether
the bulls or the bears are in control of the
market.
How we do that?
By analyzing the bull bars- the green ones,
and the bear bars – the red ones.
Before we begin, let me be clear on something,
we will not look at candlestick patterns yet,
we will look at much simpler and clearer clues.
So, a market controlled by bulls is often
characterized by the following bar patterns:
First, then obvious one is that we have more
bull bars than bears bars.
When he see this on our charts, this means
that the bulls have more power and are increasingly
moving the market upwards
Also, we will see consecutive bull bars.
Consecutive bull bars is a clear indication
of a bullish momentum
In a bull market, the green bodies are bigger
than the red bodies.
When he see this on our charts that’s a
signal that the bulls have more strength than
the bears.
Also, during a bull controlled market, we
will see the green bars closing near their
highs.
This suggests a good momentum on the upside,
because the bulls are trying to maintain the
prices higher.
We will also see a lot of wicks below the
green bars.
This also represents a good signal that the
bulls are in control of the market and that
are trying to push the prices upwards.
When we see the green bodies getting bigger
this signals a clear bullish momentum.
This kind of price action suggests that the
bears are unable to compete with the strength
of the bulls.
Also, during a market controlled by bulls,
the red bars are getting smaller, as the bears
can’t drive the prices down.
Now, let’s look at the bar patterns for
a market controlled by the bears.
First, we have more bear bars than bull bars.
This means that the bears have more power
and are moving the market downwards.
Also, we will see consecutive bear bars.
Consecutive bear bars is an obvious indication
of a bearish momentum.
In a bear market, the red bodies are bigger
than the green bodies.
This kind of price action suggests that that
the bears have more strength than the bulls.
Also, during a bear controlled market, we
will see the closing red bars near their lows.
This price action suggests a good momentum
on the downside.
We will also see a lot of wicks above the
red bars.
This represents a good signal that the bears
are in control of the market and that are
successfully push the prices downwards, despite
the initial reaction of the bulls.
Also, when we see the red bodies getting bigger
this signals a clear bearish momentum.
This is a good indication that the bulls are
unable to compete with the strength of the
bears.
Also, during a market controlled by bears,
the green bars are getting smaller and smaller.
This price action indicates that the bulls
can’t drive the prices upward.
Now that we know what to look at when we analyze
a chart, let’s take a couple of examples.
Here’s a bull controlled market on the EUR/USD
on the daily chart.
For a better overview, we added a 50-period
exponential moving average to gain a better
perspective on the market.
Once the price action started to move in higher
highs and higher lows, and the price stabilized
above the moving average, the bulls took control
of the market.
We see consecutive bull bars, big body candles,
green bars closing near their highs, wicks
below the bars, green bars becoming bigger.
As long as the price continues to record higher
highs and higher lows this should be considered
a bull controlled market and the only trading
scenario will involve buying positions.
So only long positions during this kind of
price action.
Here’s a similar example on the pound/yen.
The same price action: market starts to record
higher highs and higher lows, price action
above the 50-period moving average, consecutive
bull bars, big body candles, green bars closing
near their highs, wicks below the bars, green
bars becoming bigger, red bars getting smaller
and smaller.
Here’s a bear controlled market on the EUR/USD.
First we see the price action making lower
highs and lower lows, as the price closes
below the moving average.
At this moment, the bears took control of
the market.
Observe the consecutive red bars, big red
candles, bear bars closing near their lows,
wicks above the bars, red bars becoming bigger.
As long as the price continues to record lower
highs and lower lows this should be considered
a bear controlled market and the only trading
scenario will involve short positions.
In this example, after a strong move downwards,
the bulls gained some strength and push the
market above the moving average.
At this point, this is no longer a bear controlled
market.
I hope you learned a few things from this
that will improve your approach when you trade
the market.
Price action is about simplicity and by analyzing
the market this way, you’ll have more clarity
about the general outlook of the market.
If you got any value from this, please consider
subscribing to our channel and leave us a
like as it would help us a lot in the future.
Until next time.