traitors face all kind of problems when
they trade some traders struggle with
establishing the main trend other have
problems with their market entries but
what if you developed a trading strategy
that would solve both problems
hey traders this is marios and if you
stick with me a couple of minutes I will
share with you a great day trading
strategy that will keep you on the right
side of the market the corrupt strategy
relies on a leading indicator pivot
points and accumulation and distribution
line an underrated volume based
indicator not used by many traders let's
dive right into the strategy and see how
it works here's the first rule of this
strategy we aim to buy at the central
pivot point in an uptrend and sell at
the central pivot point in a downtrend
the central pivot point is the most
important part of the whole setup the
location of the main pivot point on the
chart represents an important
information to be aware of because there
is a high probability that it will be
reached have you ever wondered why pivot
points are so popular among traders well
that's because the what points are an
accurate indicator and most market
participants are watching and trading
these key levels part of what makes the
pivot point so reliable is the fact that
they are based purely on the price in
our strategy we'll consider the central
pivot point as the intraday point of
balance between the buyers and the
sellers in this area will assume that
the largest amount of trading volume
takes place now this is how I read the
central pivot point in our setup if the
price is above the central pivot point I
consider the outlook as being bullish
and considered taking only long
positions if the price is below the
central pivot point I consider the
outlook as being bearish and I only look
to short the market if the price
decreases below the pivot the first
target will be s1 and if the price
continues to decrease the next target
will be s2 if the price rises above the
but the first target is r1 and if the
price continues to increase the next
target is r2 this strategy is very
simple what is one of the most powerful
ways that you can use the pivot points
by using the central pivot point at the
beginning of the day we already know at
what price we will enter the market we
just need to type the market and enter
in the direction of the main trend but
how do we establish the main trend with
the accumulation and distribution line
here comes the second rule of this
strategy we establish the main trend
with the crossover of the ad line and
the 200 exponential moving average we
added a moving average on the indicator
in order to eliminate the noise offered
by the eddy line you can test other
moving averages but from my experience
longer term moving average added on the
ad line will work better than a short
term moving average now here's how we
take the signals we aim to buy at the
center of pivot point if the crossover
of the ad line and the 200 EMA indicates
an uptrend this means that the 200 EMA
is below the ad line and we also aim to
sell at the center pivot point if the
crossover of the ad line and the 200 EMA
indicates a downtrend this means that
the 200 EMA is above the ad line very
important we only take signals around
the pivot point that's the main rule of
our system here's the euro USD on the
15-minute chart
in this chart we have four trading days
during which we had a downtrend a small
range and an uptrend during the first
day we had a buy signal generated in the
first part of the day as the price
rejected the central pivot point and the
crossover between the ad line and the
200 EMA indicated an uptrend during the
New York session we had a sell signal as
the price broke below the central pivot
point and a 200 EMA crossed above the 80
line
the second day the price didn't retrace
to the central pivot point so we didn't
open my new position the third day
offered a short signal during the London
session you can see the price closing
below the central pivot point move
confirmed by the ad line and the 200 EMA
crossover in the last part of the day
this system generated a buy opportunity
as the price breached above the central
pivot point and AD line crossed above
the 200 EMA during the fourth day we had
two opportunities to enter long on the
market when the price retraced to the
central pivot point the first signal was
generated at the end of the Tokyo
trading session and the next one during
the London trading session here's
another example the pound USD this time
we have five trading days during which
at least three days are trading in a
range please keep in mind that you have
to adjust the time frame if in the
previous chart we used a 15-minute time
frame on this pair we used a 30-minute
chart you have to back test and see
which time frame offers the higher
probability setups now as you can see
despite the fact that during first two
days the price action was extremely
choppy this setup offered a few short
signals below the central pivot point
this was due to the fact that the ad
line was below the 200 EMA suggesting a
downtrend the third day we had two good
signals as the price retraced to the
central pivot point observe how the ad
line is moving lower and lower
confirming the downtrend the fourth day
started with a short signal below the
central pivot point offering on
excellent trade the end of the New York
session brought a buy signal above the
central pivot point confirmed also by
the ad line in the 200 EMA
the fifth day was a no-trade day as the
price reached new highs and failed to
retrace to the by area meaning around
the central pivot point by now I hope
you are convinced by the power of this
setup you will be on the right side of
the market most of the times of course
you will take some losses but if you
stick to the rules at the end of the
week you will be in profit remember to
take the trades only around a central
pivot point stick to this important role
as it will benefit you in the longer
term you will be tempted to take your
trades in other areas of the chart but
my advice is to be disciplined and enter
the market at the central pivot point
take a part of your profits at s1 or r1
levels and leave the trade run to its
full potential by moving your stop-loss
to break-even backtest other currency
pairs commodity or even cryptocurrencies
and see which time frame is suited for
them and very important don't trade
stocks with this system because the ad
line does not include gaps in its
calculation and the signals will not be
100% reliable test the strategy for a
couple of weeks and come back here and
share your results if you have any other
filters or tools to improve this setup I
look forward to hear from you in the
comment section if you got any value
from this video please consider
subscribing to our channel and give us a
like as it will help us to grow our
channel in the future until next time
[Music]
you