Hello and welcome.
Today I’m sharing how to find high probability
bullish and bearish pressure areas using simple
price action, and I will reveal how to day
trade these zones, in multiple market scenarios.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
Candlesticks shadows can tell you a lot about
the psychology of market participants and
should play an important role in your analysis.
Long upper shadows are considered bearish
shadows.
The presence of one or more bearish shadows
after a price advance demonstrates that the
market could possible reaching a top.
There is not enough demand at higher prices
to continue to move the price upward, at least
for the short term.
Long lower shadows are considered bullish
shadows.
The formation of one or more bullish shadows
after a price decline, especially near support,
shows us visually that the market could be
reaching a bottom.
In this case, the wick indicates that lower
prices are being rejected.
The Psychology Behind A Wick
I’ve said it a previous video.
Markets are traders making trading decisions.
If you really want to succeed at day trading,
when you look at a chart, don’t see it as
price movement.
See it as traders making decisions.
So let’s analyze three stages of a Pin Bar,
from the perspective of other traders.
How do traders react to this bar, during and
after its formation?
The best way to examine this price bar is
to consider the perspective of traders who
transacted at the extremes of the bar.
• Group 1 – Sold at the bar high
• Group 2 – Bought at the bar high
• Group 3 – Sold at the bar low
• Group 4 – Bought at the bar low
Traders who sold at the high of the bar (Stage
One) felt like geniuses in Stage Two.
Then, they quickly became frustrated as the
market moved higher and erased their profits.
Traders who bought at the high of the bar
(Stage One) were constantly watching the bar
erode their trading account.
Stage Two was the worst time for them.
In stage 3 they felt extremely relieved when
the bar ended the way it did.
Traders who sold at the low of the bar (Stage
Two) are in the worst case scenario.
The market did not move a single tick in their
favor.
Traders who bought at the low of the Bar (Stage
Two) are the happiest.
They did not suffer a single tick against
them.
So, in the case of a large wick candle, we
have 4 types of traders.
1.
Sellers who are scared (likely to cover shorts)
2.
Buyers who are optimistic (likely to hold
longs)
3.
Sellers who are demoralized (likely to cover
shorts)
4.
Buyers who are confident (likely to hold longs
or even add more)
Why is this important?
Well, together, they are likely to produce
buying pressure.
The traders who are short want to cover, so
they are creating demand.
The buyers want to hold, so they are not supplying,
at least not without demanding higher prices.
The result is a pressure on the market to
move up.
So, the lower shadow reflects the amount of
buying pressure.
You job is to locate the buying and selling
pressure zones implied by the lower and upper
shadows of price bars.
Although in the previous case, I used a Pin
Bar as an example, a strong Pressure Zone
is not defined just by one Pin Bar.
To find high probability Pressure Zones, you
must not be particularly interested in how
a single bar looks.
You must pay more attention to the appearance
of a group of price bars.
7.2 - Identifying the Pressure Zone
So the buying or selling pressure found on
a single price bar might not be sufficiently
reliable for a trading setup.
Therefore, instead of a single bar, look for
at least three consecutive bars with overlapping
upper or lower shadows.
Remember, shadows indicate potential buying
or selling pressure.
When shadows overlap, they create a price
zone that is more likely to exhibit the buying
or selling pressure you anticipate.
Consider the perspectives of the four groups
of traders again.
When we have three consecutive bars with overlapping
lower shadows, the traders undergo the same
emotional cycle three times, all within a
compact price range.
That price range is the Pressure Zone we are
looking for.
A bullish Pressure Zone is easy to identify.
You can mark it out as a zone on your charts
1.
Find three consecutive bars with overlapping
lower shadows.
2.
Mark out the lowest low among the three bars.
3.
Mark out the lowest closing price of the three
candle bodies (exclude the shadows).
4.
The area between these two price levels is
the bullish Pressure Zone.
To find a bearish Pressure Zone
1.
Find three consecutive bars with overlapping
upper shadows.
2.
Mark out the highest high among the three
bars.
3.
Mark out the highest close of the three candle
bodies (exclude the shadows).
4.
The area between these two price levels is
the bearish Pressure Zone.
Very important.
Small overlaps of shadows can create unreliable
Pressure Zones.
To avoid them, ignore overlaps below a certain
threshold.
For trading higher time frames (1 hour and
above), consider increasing the threshold
as necessary.
Here’s the Long Pressure Zone Trading Plan
1.
Find a Bullish Pressure Zone
2.
Buy above the next bullish bar that overlaps
with the Pressure Zone and closes above it
(The third bar of the Pressure Zone is acceptable
if it is bullish.)
If the price returns once again to the bullish
pressure zone and forms another signal candle,
you can re-enter.
This is similar to supply and demand trading.
3.
If price breaks below the Pressure Zone, the
setup becomes invalid.
And here’s the Short Pressure Zone Trading
Plan
1.
Find a Bearish Pressure Zone
2.
Sell below the next bearish bar that overlaps
with the Pressure Zone and closes below it.
(The third bar of the Pressure Zone is acceptable
if it is bearish.)
If the price returns once again to the bearish
pressure zone and forms another signal candle,
you can re-enter.
3.
If price breaks above the Pressure Zone, the
setup becomes invalid.
Here we have an uptrend.
This swing high maintained the excellent bullish
momentum by moving above the previous swing
high.
After such a bullish move, expect the market
to react with some bearish or sideways action.
This low that formed could not close below
the previous pivot low, implying that uptrend
is still intact.
And here’s our bullish Pressure Zone.
These consecutive wicks signify that sellers
were able to push the price down.
Bulls drove price back up, showing strength.
Since bulls overpowered the selling pressure
by bears, there is the potential that their
strength will carry forward leading to an
upwards movement in price.
This is the signal candle, which overlaps
with our pressure zone, so we buy above it.
The low of this extended wick provides a very
prudent level for you to place your stop.
The rationale for that stop placement being
that sellers pushed price to the low of that
wick but could not push it beyond that point.
Hence, placing the stop just below that wick
is a level that has a lower likelihood of
getting hit.
How Do You Know When to Exit?
This is probably the most difficult question
to answer; it will depend based upon your
risk tolerance.
Sometimes it’s best to take your profit
quickly and walk away.
Other times you want to take some money off
the table, move the stop to breakeven and
let the trade run.
This discretion will be up to you.
This example shows a bearish Pressure Zone
setup.
These three bars formed the Pressure Zone
and gave us an opportunity to short the market.
This was the setup bar, as it overlapped the
area and was also bearish.
The short trade had decent follow-through.
And as the market pulled back upwards once
again, this was an excellent option, especially
for traders who missed the first bearish Pressure
Zone setup.
The advantage of this strategy is that the
Pressure Zone places less emphasis on the
length of a single shadow and instead focuses
on multiple shadows to find reliable signs
of bullish or bearish pressure.
But, this price pattern has an important drawback.
Consecutive bars with overlapping shadows
also occur frequently within congested markets.
Instead of taking signals and trades all over
the place, the better trades usually happen
at key price levels and when you also take
volume into account.
So location of the pressure zones and volume
are very important to filter those bad zones,
that are offering false signals.
A good filter would be a common moving average.
200, 100, 50 period moving averages or even
VWAP are worth having on your charts when
it comes to finding key pressure zones.
During ranges, moving averages lose some of
their validity, but during trending markets,
you’ll see that those moving averages will
work very accurately.
So try to buy bullish pressure zones, above
a common moving average and sell a bearish
pressure zone below a common moving average.
Higher timeframe support and resistance levels
and zones add a great layer of additional
confirmation and confluence to these pressure
zones.
I especially look for strong and impulsive
turning points where price has previously
shown a strong reaction because it implies
that there is a lot of buyer and seller interest
in such an area and price is likely to show
another reaction as well.
Trendlines and channels are also great confluence
areas.
Trendlines are especially valuable if you
are looking for potential pressure zones during
trending markets, when it comes to finding
re-entry opportunities during pullbacks.
When it comes to drawing trendlines, go for
the most obvious ones with the most touches.
My favorite dynamic support and resistance
levels are pivot points.
Pivot points are based on previous day’s
high, low and close so they don’t change
throughout the current day.
I mostly pay attention to the central pivot
point and S1 and R1 levels.
So when you spot a pressure zone that forms
at a pivot level, that’s a high probability
trade.
Also, the take profit aspect becomes much
easier.
You exit a part of your position at the next
pivot levels.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.