Hello and welcome.
Today we'll look at volume, based on Wyckoff
theory, as well as discuss how to read volume
in combination with price, and additionally
we'll showcase several strategies you could
apply for day trading, swing trading and even
scalping.
So if you could… like, subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full video.
Volume is the ultimate leading indicator.
When there is unusually high volume in any
given time period (which could be 5 minutes,
an hour, a day, or a week), then the price
tends to continue in the same direction in
the future.
This principle applies to all financial markets.
When prices are rising, the market will not
decrease purely as a result of low volume
but will simply move sideways as it takes
a breather.
Conversely any reversal from a falling market
cannot occur without an increase in volume,
and is sometimes also referred to as a volume
climax.
Volume confirms the strength of a trend or
suggests its weakness.
Because if the market is rising, and volume
increasing, then this suggests that we have
a strong trend supported by an increasing
number of buyers.
Think about it, if this was selling volume
coming into the market, then prices would
fall, or perhaps move into sideways congestion
before falling.
As this is not the case, we can therefore
conclude that the volume is BUYING volume,
and you expect the trend to continue.
Conversely, if you have a rising trend but
falling volume, then this is WEAK.
It’s logic, if the buyers are still in the
market, then this would be represented by
RISING volume, and in this example we have
FALLING volume, so we can assume here that
the buyers are NO LONGER INTERESTED.
The trend is running out of steam and becoming
exhausted.
This is the first sign of a POSSIBLE change
in trend.
The buyers have left the market, and MAY now
be replaced with SELLERS.
In a trend, the volume will go with the trend,
so expect to see the volume fall away in the
pullback of the trend.
This is NORMAL volume behavior.
The buyers are taking a rest, before re-entering
the market to buy once more.
WHY? - because there has been NO SELLING CLIMAX
to signal a change in trend.
If we see the following in an uptrend, with
an ultra-high volume bar appearing, then this
is a signal that the trend is about to reverse,
as volume climaxes OFTEN highlight price reversals.
This is particularly true if the extreme volume
is associated with no equivalent reaction
in the price.
According to Wyckoff’s third law, if the
market requires effort (VOLUME) to rise and
fall, the if the market has failed to rise
with significant volume, then clearly the
market is resistant to any further increase,
and this volume must therefore be considered
to be SELLING volume.
If it were BUYING volume then the market would
have risen strongly.
Here we can see that the market has been rising
strongly, with increasing volume, a positive
sign.
However, on the last bar, the volume has been
ultra-high, but the market has fallen with
a narrow spread price bar.
What’s happening here?
In simple terms the buyers are no longer interested
at this price and a trend reversal is imminent.
If the volume bar was BUYING volume then the
market would have continued to rise as in
the previous bar.
Instead it has failed to rise and the price
spread of the bar is narrow, so this MUST
be selling volume coming into the market.
Points where the market trades on high volume
are the points of strong support and resistance,
and are the first signs of a change in trend
or a breakout.
Volume helps us to confirm the potential breakout
from an area of price congestion.
In this example, we can see that we have high
volume at the bottom of each market reversal,
which is suggesting BUYING or ACCUMULATION
at these points.
The support area confirms this view, so that
when we FINALLY see the breakout we have a
GREAT signal from our volume bars, that this
is a GENUINE breakout and therefore a LOW
RISK TRADE.
In this example, the high volume is at the
TOP of each trend, so in this case we can
assume that this is SELLING volume with the
market creating a region of price resistance
in this case.
As this is selling volume, then when we see
the breakout to the down side, VOLUME once
again VALIDATES this breakout, as we have
seen the HIGH volume bars on each FAILED attempt
to move higher.
Once again we have a low risk entry, confirmed
by our volume.
Breakouts and market spikes can be validated
or voided with the help of volume.
Without volume, we are merely guessing at
the future direction of the market.
With volume, we have an insight into the market,
and whether the interest is buying or selling.
However, just like price, volume in isolation
tells us very little about the market’s
future direction.
All it can signal on its own is interest in
a market or event.
For this we need to combine price and volume
together to give us the most powerful analytical
tool available, which will reveal the market’s
future direction.
As Wyckoff said: “all you need to know can
be found in price and volume.”
From Wyckoff I learnt that price alone can
only tell you what is a market’s present
technical position and where the trend is
probably headed.
That volume determines the trend with more
accuracy and detects turning points.
But together, they form a complete picture.
Volume expresses interest and enthusiasm.
Volume is the fuel of the market, it is what
drives the market, and without it, the market
will simply drift.
Volume exposes the truth of the market.
Volume reveals conviction in the market.
If the market is moving higher, but with falling
or low volume, then this is simply telling
us that this is not a genuine move.
Equally, if the market is falling with falling
volume, then once again this is not a genuine
move.
I know I’m repeating myself, but this is
so simple and powerful.
On their own, price and volume only reveal
a part of market information.
After all, price tells you a number.
Volume on its own only tells us there is interest,
and nothing else.
However, when combined, the true market intent
is revealed giving clear signals of both buying
and selling interest, something that would
not be revealed by either on their own.
In simple terms, the more people that participate
in a price move, or in our case the more volume
associated with a price move, the more that
price move is validated.
When there is low volume, few buyers, then
our price is simply not validated.
It really is that simple.
Let’s talk about volume and news announcements.
The markets, as we know, are always full with
news of every type, from the daily release
of fundamental and economic data, to the political
statements from governments, to the latest
announcement from a central bank.
All of these pieces of news are absorbed by
the markets and built into the latest price
action.
Now, as this new information is released into
the public domain, volume reveals the effect
of this information on price.
By watching the change in volume, as this
information is released, we can instantly
see how the markets are reacting to the news,
and how quickly the latest piece of news is
being absorbed by the various market participants.
What this means in simple terms is that the
volume substantiates the importance of the
release.
If the volume rises on the news and the price
rises in tandem, then the market is placing
significant emphasis on this piece of news.
Clearly in this case the price is being validated
by the volume surge.
Conversely, if the volume fails to rise on
the news, then the market and the market participants
have clearly discounted this item, and consider
it to be unimportant or irrelevant, as they
now wait for the next release to arrive.
Let’s look at a few more examples of how
volume plays a key part in the current AND
future direction of a market.
VOLUME HIGH OR LOW
As we have seen volume is the second most
valuable item of data after the price itself.
Large volume confirms market activity and
that market participants are involved in the
move, including smart money, who bring the
highest turnover to the market.
When the smart money are trading, it means
they are interested in price at certain levels
and they literally push the price up or down.
Low volume tells us that there are very few
participants in the market, and that neither
buyers nor sellers have any significant interest
in the price.
In this scenario no smart money will be involved,
and therefore any moves from individual traders
will be weak.
VOLUME AND TREND
Volume helps us to determine the health of
a trend.
An uptrend is strong and healthy if volume
increases as price moves with the trend and
decreases when price goes counter trend (correction
periods or ‘pull backs’).
When prices are rising and volume is decreasing,
it tells traders that a trend is unlikely
to continue.
Price may still attempt to rise at a slower
pace, and once sellers take control (which
is usually signified by an increase in volume
on a down bar or candle), prices will fall.
A downtrend is strong and healthy if volume
increases as prices move lower and decreases
when the price begins to re-trace (pull back)
upwards.
When price is falling and volume is decreasing,
the downtrend is unlikely to continue.
The price will either continue to decrease,
but at a slower pace or start to rise.
VOLUME AND REVERSALS
When volume spikes at certain price levels,
traders know that this was an area of high
interest at that price level.
If there is a great deal of interest, it means
the level is a key one.
This simple observation of volume allows traders
to identify important support and resistance
levels which could play a significant role
in the future.
Where volume spikes are extreme (in other
words larger than any historical spikes nearby),
this is generally known as a volume climax.
When this occurs traders should look for clues
for the future direction of the move from
the price itself, and this is often followed
by particular candle or price bar pattern.
Single volume spikes can bring price to a
halt temporarily and these are often seen
during fundamental and economic announcements
on a daily basis.
Reversals, however, happen not over a single
day, but over a series of days.
If higher than average volume stays in the
market for several days a huge volume spike
- volume climax - will crown a point of market
reversal.
VOLUME AND BREAKOUTS
Volume can help to validate all kinds of breakouts.
When the market is consolidating on low volume,
a pick up in volume can signify that a breakout
is due.
A breakout occurring on rising volume is a
valid breakout, while a breakout that attracted
no interest from traders occurring on low
volume, is likely to be false.
If you’re learned something new, please
hit the like button, since it really helps
us out, and subscribe, to stay up to date
with our latest releases.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.