be honest how many days and nights you
spent on the charts looking for the
perfect setup or the perfect pattern the
one that would bring constant gains over
time have you found it yet if not I want
to show you a simple and effective for
strategy I have developed over months of
research and study and I will
demonstrate how to profit consistently
by taking advantage of the Dynamics of
price and
time this Forex strategy is based on two
fundamental factors two elements that
leave no room for discretion price and
time the main advantage of this sculping
strategy is the fact that you don't have
to spend hours in front of the charts to
try to find all the various patterns
like Flags head and shoulders and so on
and you don't have to jump from one time
frame to another looking for the
conviction that the pattern you have
identified is really worth trading and
it doesn't matter if you like trading
with indicators or your a price action
Trader both approaches will work with
this strategy because will be analyzing
markets based on objective and
non-subjective criteria established with
Clarity and precision if this sounds
good let's dive right into the
strategy first let's talk about the time
component Forex is the world's largest
financial market and is open 24 hours a
day 5 days a week however depending on
where you are in the world days and
times May differ due to time zone and
daylight savings time generally the
opening and closing times of the markets
are indicated considering the GMT
meaning the green witch meantime and you
have to pay attention to the fact that
in the various periods of the Year each
country can have different time zones
these Concepts may seem obvious to some
but it's very important regardless of
the platform you use to know the exact
time shown by your charts compared to
the GMT in London so very important you
should pay close attention to the time
displayed on the charts because it's not
always the same as the GMT time since
for this strategy it's essential to know
the opening and closing times of the
various Forex sessions that make up the
day if we are misled by the wrong time
on the platform our analysis would be
wrong the trading day consists of
several sessions the European session
the American session and the Asian
session also known as London New York
and the sessions in Tokyo or Sydney for
those who trade Forex and specifically
trade intraday it is therefore essential
to know that times at which currency
exchanges take place on various markets
and especially the times at which
multiple sessions are opened at the same
time I have summarized the start in the
end times of the main trading sessions
in the London GMT time in this
[Music]
diagram for the strategy we're
interested in the European session for
Europe the session starts at 7 GMT with
the opening of The Frankfurt session but
the main opportunity start at 8 GMT with
the opening of the London session while
Tokyo is in the last hour of trading at
this time a large number of Traders are
participating in the market this results
in larger price movements than in the
Asian session which often also Prov to
be of great impact on the sentiment for
the day we can therefore say that the
opening moments of the London session
are a good starting point to trade in a
highly liquid Market as well as finding
the best
opportunities with the opening of Europe
Frankfurt before and London and our
later the movements that are generated
often create the trend for the day
giving us the opportunity to take
advantage and capture a part of it the
trend of the day generated by London
doesn't always remain that way at the
opening of New York session the high
volume of trade that shi combined with
the publication of important economic
data can cause large reversal moments
that can also re observe the entire
movement triggered by London session it
goes without saying that even these
reversals offer us the opportunity to
see is another trading
opportunity now let's talk about the
importance of the opening price here's
what you need to know when sculping and
day trading Forex the opening of the
European session can cause large price
movements that often result in important
intraday Trends and the first factor to
take into account in order to take
advantage of these movements is the
opening price of the European session
the opening price is the point from
which all daily activities originate
it's a very important price level
according to to which big Traders move
from a long Vision to a short vision and
vice versa we can therefore consider the
opening price as the crossing point
representing the sentiment of the
day here's the key point of this
strategy most Traders focus on the
London open but smart Traders know there
is another important Focus Point prior
to the London open and that is the
Frankfurt open the opening of The
Frankfurt occurs at 7 GMT and the
opening of London at 8 GMT during this
period there is an increase in volumes
but it's still not enough to generate
real Trends now pay attention the price
distance that is formed in this 1H hour
interval from 7 GMT to 8 GMT determines
the range that goes to form the opening
channel the opening Channel contains the
open price of the Frankfurt session and
the open price of the London session and
very important the opening channel is
the area within which you never have to
enter the market for the rest of the
trading day the No Man's
Land This example shows the opening
channel from 7 GMT the opening of
Frankfurt to 8 GMT the opening of London
these lines represent the low price and
the high price formed within this hour
thus determining the opening
channel the high and low price of the
opening channel are two very important
levels because they are the first
support and the first resistance for the
trading day remember remember we don't
trade inside the channel if the price
goes above it it creates an imbalance
that triggers supports from the buyers
and vice versa if the price goes below
the strength of the sellers is triggered
if the price is inside the channel since
there is no imbalance between buyers and
sellers you cannot know which direction
to expect either long or short this
concept remains valid throughout the
trading day during European session and
even in the first part of the New York
session
as we have seen the opening Channel
which has the opening of the European
session within it acts as a neutral
Price Zone between buyers and sellers
when price breaks upwards we'll have a
long entry signal while when it breaks
downwards we'll have a short entry
signal obviously the entry signal is
triggered after 8 GMT the opening of
London when the price breaks the channel
upwards or
downwards here's an example of a long
entry we have identified the opening
Channel and soon after the London open
we had an upward breakout after London
session opened we can see the market
traded within the opening Channel and
then immediately changed Direction and
started upwards with a strong
Trend and here's a short entry after
withdrew the opening channel the market
immediately started a strong downward
intraday Trend a short trade under the
channel would have allowed us to capture
a nice profit for the
day when where to place the stop loss
stop loss which is mandatory must be
positioned on the opposite side of the
opening channel for a long entry stop
loss goes a few Pips below the opening
Channel low and for a short entry stop
loss is placed a few Pips above the
opening Channel High the stop loss is
positioned in this way because once
entered in the market in a short trade
for example and during the session the
price goes back and breaks the opening
Channel upwards remaining in a trade
will no longer be sensible because the
sentiment of the big Market players
those who move the markets passed from
short to long with the high probability
that the trend of the day will change at
this point it's clear that it no longer
makes sense to insist on remaining in
the
market where to set take profit levels
once you have identified the channel
enter the market after a breakout and
placed your stop loss you must proceed
to identify the future price levels at
which you will take profits to Define
these levels the best thing to do is to
measure the range of the opening Channel
and project it from the breakout of the
Channel's high price for the long Target
levels and from the breakout of the
Channel's low price for the short Target
levels and you have to do it multiple
times just like adding pivot Points you
determine the first Target by projecting
the channel and then the second target
by projecting the channel once again and
once again for the third target for the
to
day when setting price targets the
opening channel is a measure of
volatility if the channel is narrow you
will have to add multiple price targets
if the channel is wide you will have to
add just a few you can close 50% of your
position once the price reaches the
first Target and then let the trade run
until the next Target is reached it's up
to you you decide which money and risk
management you want to
use now that you know the right ways to
determine the takeprofit levels it's
important to mention that you will have
to plot them immediately on the chart as
soon as the opening channel has been
formed you should know that this price
levels that you will add to the chart at
the beginning of the session in addition
to being the ones on which we will place
our take profits they will also be the
levels of future support and resistance
you'll notice how these levels will be
used by institutions during the trading
day as real levels of support and
resistance in this chart I have traced
upwards and downwards levels of take
profit and it's evident how the price
reacts when it approaches these
levels it's really unbelievable how
accurate these levels are the price
bounces several times reverses breaks
and retest them these price targets are
very important knowing the support and
resistance levels for the day in advance
right at the beginning of the London
session will certainly be a great
advantage over the
market the great thing about this Strat
stry is that it has a precise set of
rules you can back test this strategy
easily and you can Implement other types
of analysis to confirm the breakout if
you are a price action Trader you can
analyze swing highs and lows and trade
breakouts in the direction of the trend
during an uptrend you will have higher
highs because buyers push the price
higher and lows are also higher because
buyers keep buying the dips earlier
during a downtrend lows are lower and
Highs are also lower because sellers
sell earlier and buyers are not as
interested so if you spot an uptrend and
you see an upside breakout of the
opening Channel that's a high
probability trade a downward breakout of
the opening Channel when the price is
making lower lows and lower highs is
also a strong sell signal
[Music]
is
if you prefer confirmation from
indicators moving averages are perfect
for this strategy because are great to
identify the market direction as well if
you want to use moving averages as
filter you can apply the 200 EMA and
then only look for trades in the
direction of the moving average in this
example we can see that we had a long
signal above the opening Channel and
that that during this uptrend price
always stayed well above the moving
average
[Music]
as always if you learn something new and
F value and you want a followup video
about this topic leave us a like to
showare support subscribe to our Channel
and hit the Bell icon to stay notified
when we upload new
videos until next time