Classic patterns like triangles, wedges or head
and shoulders are just bait for retail traders.
And the market is built to trap those
who follow the same old chart setups.
Today it’s time to learn the
patterns the pros actually chase!
Over-and-Under – Quasimodo pattern
The Over-and-Under pattern, also called
Quasimodo, is one of smart money’s favorite
setups. It’s about sudden changes and traps.
It all starts with a strong move up.
Price makes a high. It pulls back,
then pushes higher, making a new
high. After that, price falls sharply,
breaking below the low of the last dip.
This is the key moment! Price makes a lower low,
taking out stops placed by traders who went long
earlier. This dip below the last low is fast,
almost like someone grabs liquidity and runs.
The move is deep enough to scare holders out. But
instead of rolling over, price snaps back up right
away. Sellers who chased the low get trapped.
Now, the market shifts. Price climbs,
but this time, it doesn’t reach the old
high. It stalls and starts to turn down
earlier. This creates a “lower high.”
The Over-and-Under pattern gets its name from
this exact sequence: a fake-out higher high,
a fake-out lower low, followed by a lower
high. The pattern is about the trap. Big
money creates the lower low to pull in sellers
and force out buyers, then reverses back up so
quickly that most can’t react. The new lower
high is the spot where the trap closes.
Here’s how to trade it. When you see price drop
below support and snap back, mark that low as
the “liquidity grab.” Watch as price rises
again. If it fails to reach the old high and
starts to fall, this is the “over-and-under.”
The lower high is your entry zone. Sell short
as price turns down from this area.
Your stop goes just above the lower
high. If price returns above that, the pattern
failed. If not, you’re in for the ride down.
This pattern works because many traders put their
stops under the old low. When price drops and
breaks that level, those stops trigger, giving big
players the liquidity they need to enter or exit
quietly. After the trap, the market structure
changes. It’s no longer making higher highs.
Instead, it prints a lower low and then a lower
high. This switch signals that the uptrend is
likely over, and a downtrend may be starting.
The best Over-and-Under patterns happen after
a clear uptrend, when lots of traders are
caught off guard. Volume often spikes during
the liquidity grab, showing that big players
are active. The lower high forms quickly,
often with less energy than the earlier
moves up. The rejection is sharp.
So to spot this in real time, watch for three
things. First, a strong move up with a clear high
and a clear low. Second, a sudden break below the
low, followed by a quick reversal back up. Third,
a lower high forming as price fails to
reach the old high. When you see this,
get ready. The lower high is your short entry.
Set your stop above it, and look for price to
make new lows as the trend shifts down.
Wyckoff “Spring” (after Accumulation)
Wyckoff Spring is one of the most common fake
breakout patterns, to shake out weak traders.
Picture a price chart with sideways movement.
The price bounces up and down between two
lines, a top and a bottom.
Traders call this a range.
They buy at the bottom, sell at the top. But the
market has a trick up its sleeve. This is where
the Wyckoff “Spring” pattern comes in.
The “Spring” happens after a time of
sideways trading, near the bottom of that range.
Price slowly drops right through the support line,
just enough to make everyone think the range is
broken. Traders panic. Some who bought at the
bottom sell fast to cut their losses. Others go
short, betting the market will keep falling. This
is what big players want. They set the trap.
Here’s the key: the drop below support doesn’t
last. It’s quick, sharp, and then, just as
suddenly, price snaps straight back inside
the range. The bounce is hard and fast.
The market shakes out the “weak hands”,
traders who panic and sell at the worst time.
This flush is not random. The large players,
the ones with deep pockets, use this moment to buy
what the weak hands are selling. They want to buy
big, but they want to do it quietly. If they just
buy in the range, the price would rise too soon,
so they use the “Spring” to buy from scared
sellers without tipping off the crowd.
You can spot the Spring by watching for a dip
below the lowest point of the range, followed by a
fast return inside the range. Volume often spikes.
It shows big players are active. When price comes
back inside the range, that’s the signal. Now,
you want to buy! Place your stop just under the
lowest tick of the Spring. If price returns
below that point, the pattern failed. If not,
you ride the next move up, when the market finally
breaks out for real and price runs higher.
On the flip side, after an uptrend and a period
of distribution (where big players sell to late
buyers), you get the opposite pattern: the
Up-Thrust After Distribution. The price sneaks
above the top of the range, often in a sharp move.
Traders think this is a breakout. They pile in,
buying the “new high.” But then, price slams back
below the range top. That breakout was a fake.
The big players used it to dump their
inventory on eager buyers. The market
can’t hold the higher price. The reversal is fast
and deep. This is the last bull trap before the
markdown phase, where price drops hard.
Both the Spring and Up-Thrust show how big
players use traps. They create fake breakouts to
shake out weak traders and fill their own orders.
These patterns show up every day, on all
markets and time frames, and they offer
strong entries. That’s how you know the big
players are moving and the pattern is real.
Volume-Climax + Tight Coil
Volume-Climax followed by a tight Coil
is a pattern that tells you when the big players
just made their move, finished their business,
and are getting ready for the next big swing.
Here’s how it works. First, you’ll spot a giant
candle. It’s much bigger than all the
candles before it. The price shoots up
or down, covering more ground in a few
minutes or hours than it did all day.
The volume on this candle is huge, maybe the
highest you’ve seen in days or even weeks. This
isn’t normal trading. This is when big money is
at work. They’re either dumping a huge position
(unloading) or snapping up shares (loading up).
This giant candle is the climax. It’s the end
of one story and the start of another.
Right after this, everything goes quiet.
Price stops moving fast. Instead, you get
a group of tiny candles. They barely move
up or down. They sit in a small box, trapped
between two tight lines. This is the coil.
It’s like the market is holding its breath.
Volatility drops. Traders get bored or nervous.
This is where the big players finished their
work. They bought or sold what they needed,
and now they’re waiting for the next move.
So why does this pattern matter? Because big
money doesn’t just smash the market for fun.
They move size when they’re ready for a change.
That giant volume candle means they needed
to get in or out, fast. The tight coil that
follows means the rest of the market is stuck,
waiting, not sure what will happen next. But
volatility always comes back. The market can’t
stay quiet forever. Sooner or later, price will
break out of that coil. When it does, it’s usually
fast and sharp and the next big move is here.
The trick is watching which way to trade. The
direction of the giant volume candle tells you
which way the big money moved. If the climax
candle is up, it means they bought in a rush.
If it’s down, they sold hard. After the coil, you
want to trade in the same direction as the climax,
because that’s where the force is most likely
to come back. The break from the coil is your
entry. The stop goes just outside the coil,
if the breakout fails, you’re out quick.
Volume is the key to this setup. If
the big candle happens with low volume,
it’s a fake. Only the real, heavy volume bars
matter. You want to see the spike, the kind of
volume that stands out on your chart, way above
normal. That’s when you know the big players are
active. The coil should have low volume, too.
That means all the excitement is gone, and the
market is quiet, waiting for the next jolt.
Some traders call this pattern a volatility
squeeze. But the combination of a volume climax
followed by a tight coil is special. It tells you
the market just had all the noise, and now it’s
setting up for the next big burst. The breakout
that follows is often fast, with price moving
quickly and cleanly. You won’t have to wait long.
This pattern works on all timeframes. You can
spot it on a one-minute chart, a daily chart,
even weekly bars. The story is always the same:
big spike, then silence, then explosion. The key
is to wait for the breakout. When price busts out
of the coil in the direction of the volume spike,
that’s your trade.
Gap-and-Go
Gap-and-Go pattern is loud, fast, and
full of energy. Most traders freeze.
Some try to fade the move, thinking the
gap will fill. But in the Gap-and-Go,
the market leaves those traders behind.
When the market opens, price isn’t where
it closed last night. It’s far above resistance
or below support. This isn’t a small gap. It’s
big enough to wake up momentum traders everywhere.
They see it and get ready to trade. Shorts panic.
They rush to cover. Buyers want in before the move
gets away. The first minutes of trading are wild.
This gap matters because it’s not random. It comes
after a long range or a clear area where price
kept bouncing. The gap blasts right past that.
It doesn’t pause. Buyers rush in and push price
even higher. Sellers who bet against the gap can’t
get out fast enough. The market never comes back
to fill the gap. That’s the key. Most gaps fill
later. But not this one. The move holds strong.
This pattern is all about momentum. You see a
small range in the first one to five minutes
after the open. Price chops up and down, setting
its boundaries. Traders watch this range closely.
As soon as price breaks out, either above
the high of this mini-range for an up gap,
or below the low for a down gap, they jump
in. That’s the entry. The stop goes just under
the low of the small range if you’re long. If
you’re short, put the stop just above the high.
Volume is huge. This isn’t like other days. It’s
a sign that big money is moving. The crowd wants
in. The move feeds on itself. People who
missed the first entry chase. Shorts who
didn’t cover at the open now scramble. Each
new high pulls in more buyers. Each new low
for a down gap brings in more panic sellers.
Most traders think: “The gap will fill. It always
fills!” They try to fade it. But the Gap-and-Go
pattern is different. The news is too strong,
or the surprise is too big. The market moves fast.
The gap becomes the new base. Price almost never
comes back to fill it, at least not right away.
Sometimes, you see a series of gaps like this
in a strong trend. These are called runaway or
measuring gaps. They show up when a trend gets
even stronger and momentum explodes. Each
new gap is a sign that buyers (or sellers)
are even more eager than before. The chart
looks like a staircase, jumping from one
level to the next without looking back.
To catch the Gap-and-Go, you need to act
fast. Watch for the big gap at the open. Check
that it’s above clear resistance or below clear
support. Watch the first one to five minutes.
Wait for the range to break. Enter with the
direction of the gap. Use a tight stop. If the
move fails and price falls back into the gap,
get out. But if the move holds, you’re in the
flow with the strongest traders of the day.
So momentum, volume and speed. That’s
what the Gap-and-Go is all about.
Rounded Bottom with Volume Divergence
is one of the best reversal patterns.
In this chart, sellers control the market.
The chart has a clear downward slope. But then,
the speed slows. The drops get smaller. The
bounces start to last longer. Price stops making
sharp new lows and instead drifts sideways. The
curve starts to look round, almost like a bowl.
This is the early sign of a rounded bottom.
At the start of the rounded bottom, volume
is still strong. People are still selling.
But as price sinks lower, the volume falls too.
Each wave down has fewer sellers than before.
Buyers are not rushing in yet. They’re waiting,
watching. The market feels quiet. This tells you
supply is drying up. Sellers are tired. Big
money might be stepping in, but they don’t
want to show their hand yet. Price keeps moving
sideways and slowly curling upwards. It’s not a
sharp reversal. It’s slow, gentle, and calm.
Now, here’s the interesting part. The price
starts to rise, but volume stays low. Most
people think that rising prices mean buyers
are strong. But here, the rise is soft. It’s not
about enthusiasm. It’s about no one left to sell.
The big players are quietly buying. They want
to keep the price low while they collect shares.
If they bought fast, the price would
jump and everyone would notice. But
they want to buy cheap and unnoticed.
As the bottom of the curve forms, you notice
something else. Each little dip has less volume
than before. Each bounce up is a bit stronger,
but still mostly on low volume. This is volume
divergence. Price is starting to move up,
but volume hasn’t picked up yet. That’s
the clue. It’s not the crowd driving
the price. It’s smart money buying slow
and careful, soaking up all the supply.
At some point, things change fast. Suddenly
more big candles appear. Volume increases.
The price shoots up, breaking above the top of
the bowl. This is the signal. It’s the moment
when the big players have finished buying. Now,
they want the price to move. They push hard and
everyone else sees the move. This is when the
new trend begins. The burst in volume confirms
the shift. It isn’t just a slow drift anymore.
This is a real move, with force behind it.
The rounded bottom with volume divergence is a
strong sign that the market has changed. Supply
is gone. Demand is building. Control has shifted
from sellers to buyers. The new trend is here,
and it’s not just a bounce. It’s
a move backed by big money.
If you want to trade it, you wait for
the slow curve at the bottom. Watch for
price to rise while volume stays weak. When
the big candle appears and volume bursts,
that’s your entry. The trend is ready to go. Place
your stop under the lowest point of the curve.
Most traders miss this pattern because it’s slow.
It doesn’t look exciting. But that’s the point.
The slow, rounded shape and the quiet volume tell
you big players are at work. The sudden burst in
volume is their signal that the game has changed.
If you spot the pattern and act on the breakout,
you’re with the money that matters.
Inside-Outside-Inside
The Inside-Outside-Inside pattern is not common.
Most traders miss it. But when it shows up,
it means something big might be coming.
First, price prints an inside bar. This
candle sits inside the range of the one
before. It’s small. It shows the market
is quiet. Buyers and sellers are holding
back. Some call this a pause or a squeeze.
Then comes the outside bar. This candle is
wide. It breaks above the high and drops
below the low of the last bar. It engulfs both
sides. The market wakes up. This outside bar
means there’s a fight. Volume often jumps.
Both buyers and sellers try to take control.
The range expands fast. Anyone with tight
stops gets hit. The outside bar is noisy,
messy, and full of action. This
is the wide part of the pattern.
Right after, another inside bar forms. This
candle is tight again, sitting inside the high
and low of the outside bar that just happened.
The market settles down. The burst of energy
is gone, but tension is still there. People are
waiting. No one wants to make the first move.
This whole sequence means pressure is building up.
The first inside bar shows the market is waiting.
The outside bar is the spark. The final inside
bar shows the waiting isn’t over. Something is
about to break loose. This is what traders call
a “pending breakout.” Price is about to move,
but nobody knows which way.
But when price breaks out,
you follow. If the upper range is broken, you go
long. If the lower one triggers, you go short.
This pattern works because it traps traders on
both sides. The first inside bar makes people
think nothing will happen. The outside bar shakes
them up, but it’s over so fast, they don’t trust
it. The last inside bar makes most give up. Then,
when price finally breaks, it’s strong. There’s no
resistance left. The move can be fast and clean.
You see this most on lower timeframes, but it can
show up anywhere. It means the same thing: the
market is ready to move big. Patterns like this
highlight points in market structure where buying
and selling pressure is about to tip over.
Most traders ignore the inside-outside-inside
pattern. But it works! If you learn to spot it,
you can catch eruptions
before the crowd even notices.
The pattern gives you tight levels for entry
and stops. If the move fails and reverses,
you’re out quick. If it works, you’re
in when the move is just starting.
Three-Line Strike
The Three-Line Strike pattern makes it easy
to spot when the market is about to move fast.
First you see price moving in a clear trend,
but it’s slow. Each candle is small, and they line
up in the direction of the trend, maybe three tiny
green bars in a slow uptrend, or three red ones in
a slow downtrend. These candles show the move is
still going, but it’s not strong. People trading
with the trend are getting tired. Some might
even start to think about trading the other way.
That’s when the big move happens. Out of nowhere,
a huge candle appears. This one is fast and
strong, and it moves in the opposite direction
to the three before. If you were looking at three
green candles, now you have a big red candle. If
you were watching three reds, now a green one
appears. This candle doesn’t just close over
one or two of the small bars, it swallows all
three. The body of this big candle completely
covers the bodies of the three smaller trend
bars. This is the Three-Line Strike pattern.
The pattern is more than just a reversal.
It’s a small shock. The market was drifting,
and then someone stepped in with force. The big
candle shows a sudden change in control. Buyers
or sellers who tried to fight the trend are
now wiped out. The pattern tells you there’s
energy building up. The trend looked weak,
then got hit by a big move the other way.
Now you simply mark the high
and low of the engulfing candle.
These two prices are now your channel.
And you wait and focus on the breakout.
Watch for price to push above the high of the
big candle, or drop below its low. That’s your
trigger. If price breaks out above the high, you
enter a long trade. If it breaks below the low,
you go short. Don’t guess which way it will
go. Let the market show you. As soon as the
breakout happens, you enter with the move.
Your stop is simple. Place it just on the
other side of the channel. If you buy the
breakout above the high, put your stop just
under the low of the big candle. If you sell
the breakout below the low, your stop goes
just above the high. This keeps your risk tight.
The Three-Line Strike pattern tells a story. Small
candles mean the trend is running out of steam.
The big candle means a fight for control. This
strategy works because the big engulfing candle
is a signal that something important has changed.
Big traders just made their move, and now the
rest of the market reacts. The channel gives you
clear levels to watch. You don’t need to guess or
hope, you just wait for price to show its hand.
Hidden Divergence
Hidden divergence is a pattern
that most people miss. This pattern happens when
price and an indicator, like RSI or MACD don’t
agree. This is not regular divergence, which
usually signals a reversal. Hidden divergence
points to the trend continuing, even when
price action looks tricky. It’s a pattern pros
use to spot real momentum before everyone else.
A Bullish hidden divergence happens in an uptrend.
Price pulls back and makes a higher low,
but it doesn’t drop as far as before. But
the indicator makes a lower low. This
means that, even though price held up,
the indicator dipped more. The hidden divergence
says the uptrend will likely continue. You look
for this when price is near support in an uptrend.
If you spot it, you can plan to enter long trades,
betting the trend will keep going.
Bearish hidden divergence shows up in
a downtrend. Price bounces, making a lower
high. But the indicator makes a higher high.
The indicator shows more force, even though
price couldn’t break past the last high. This
is a sign the downtrend wants to continue. You
look for this when price is near resistance in
a downtrend. If you find it, you can plan to
enter short trades, following the main trend.
The steps to spot hidden divergence
are simple. First, mark the trend:
look for clear up or down moves. Second, wait
for price to make a swing high or low. Third,
compare these points to your indicator and see
if price and the indicator disagree. So price
makes a higher low, but the indicator makes
a lower low; or price makes a lower high,
and the indicator makes a higher high.
Hidden divergence tells you something
about the market that price alone won’t reveal.
It shows when the crowd tries to fight the trend
but fails. The indicator exposes this hidden
strength. You don’t see it on price bars,
but the oscillator drops important clues.
The market might look weak, but hidden
divergence says the trend is still alive.
You can trade hidden divergence by entering
in the direction of the main trend. For bullish
setups, go long when price starts to rise after
the divergence. For bearish setups, go
short when price starts to fall. Use
the last swing high or low for your stop. This
keeps your risk small, in case the setup fails.
This pattern works on any market. But it’s best
on clear trends, not in choppy sideways action.
Now, if you’re ready for more
interesting trading guides,
go ahead and watch one of these videos next!