what do you think moves price action in
the market from one value area to
another
is the unfilled orders of the smart
money
today i'm showing you how to take
advantage of these orders and how to
combine supply and demand zones with
trading indicators to find the best
signals
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
by analyzing supply and demand you
basically try to anticipate where the
unfilled orders of the smart money are
located in the market
the plan is to enter the market where
the smart money have their unfilled
orders and be a participant along with
them
knowing when the smart money liquidity
providers are moving the markets is
critical so you can be there to ride
along with them
so this is the mindset you must have you
enter where and when the liquidity
providers the smart money are providing
liquidity
everything you see on the chart to the
left has already taken place
the only thing that matters is where
those unfilled orders are resting in the
market because that is where price
action goes to and takes off from
let us start with different methods of
identifying and plotting areas of supply
and demand
the easiest zone to spot is when you
have an obvious change in the direction
of the trend
for a supply zone you need two points
first the exact point the market dropped
quickly out of a small range i use the
price open of the last bullish candle
before the drop
and the second one uses the highest
candle wick of the range
for a demand zone you find a point the
market rose quickly out of a small range
meaning the open price of the last
bearish candle before the price increase
and the second point is the lowest
candle wake of the range
in both cases
you look for a large candle body or a
gap away from the zone as a future
indication of how strong the price
action is in that value area
the next method of identifying zones is
to look for an area where price has been
trading sideways and in a narrow range
for several bars and then dramatically
shoots away from that range
on the left side of the chart we see
price trading in a narrow range for
several bars and then drops dramatically
the next time price came into the zone
the trend reversed giving us a short
opportunity
the third method is to look for areas of
indecision
ranging periods or small corrections
during a strong downtrend for a supply
zone
or ranging periods or small corrections
during a strong uptrend for a demand
zone
these are the rally-based rally and the
drop based drop structures
[Music]
the last method is by looking for gaps
when a stock gaps either up or down
there has been a sudden change in the
balance of supply and demand
the price it gapped from is very likely
to be a strong supply or demand zone
watch this video if you want to learn
more about market structures and supply
demand trading
when price action comes back and
revisits the value area again in the
future you will be there waiting for a
reaction
you must anticipate several things
who is in control right now how do trend
waves relate to each other
is momentum gaining or losing strength
how is the price reacting around
previous highs and lows
these are important clues that will help
you understand the buyer and the seller
dynamics
after you identify the zone watch for
how far price action breaks into the
value area on the first retracement
if price action doesn't quite reach the
value area there may be more unfilled
orders left at the value area and price
could come back here to fill more orders
very important the first retrace back to
the value area is the highest
probability of a trade working out
on the second or the third retest the
probability of the trade working out
decreases
a supply and demand level becomes
invalid once price action breaks through
and closes above or below the tested
level this is because all orders that
were left at that level have been
absorbed
thus the candle can close above the
value area
what happens when a value area is not
fresh and price has been back to it one
or more times
chances are price will trade through the
value area because all of the previous
orders that were placed there have been
filled or absorbed
one of the most interesting aspects of
trading is that there are so many
different approaches
some traders prefer to focus on supply
and demand and price action
while other traders prefer to focus on
technical indicators
as price action traders we basically
have two ways to trade
with or without a confirmation signal
when trading supply and demand you have
two choices
to enter when price returns to the zone
or to confirm the setup with another
signal
it's important to understand that each
trait in its supply and demand zone is
unique
there will never be two trading
situations that are exactly the same in
the market
so whether you enter on a confirmation
signal or without one is going to be
determined on a case-by-case basis
you might choose to wait for a
confirmation signal at a supply or
demand level
or you might just enter blindly at this
key level
i prefer to have a confirmation from an
indicator
and one of the best ways of doing this
is through establishing confluence
first confirmation comes from the macd
a trade confluence simply refers to the
overlapping of two technical elements at
the same price and time point giving the
same signal
in this case a supply or demand zone and
a signal from the macd indicator
after all if we have two or more
non-correlated signals or studies giving
us a trade signal the chances of it
working are increased
now macd can be used to confirm the
trend strength direction and momentum
you can receive a lot of different
signals from it i've talked about the
macd signals in this video for supply
and demand trading i found that macd
divergences are perfect leading signals
to confirm our setups
macd as a momentum indicator shows the
movement of price over time and how
strong those movements are or will be
regardless of the direction of the price
moves up or down a divergence refers to
any instance where the price reaches a
new high or new low but momentum as
illustrated by the macd doesn't reflect
the same extreme
when price and momentum diverge it
typically indicates that the market is
primed for a reversal
here we have a demand zone on the euro
yen on a daily time frame
when using macd divergences with supply
and demand zones i use a multiple time
frame approach
there are two major rules for a multiple
timeframe analysis
larger time frames establish and
dominate the trend
and reversals start from the smaller
time frames and continue upwards
so you find your supply and demand zones
on the higher time frames the daily
chart then you move to a lower time
frame in this case the 30 minute chart
to find the macd entry signal
this is very important you watch for
price action to turn on a lower time
frame but at a higher time frame supply
or demand area and when trend is
changing
you look at the higher time frame to see
where the previous value area was
because price should go there on the
lower time frame chart
on the 30 minute chart we noticed that
the macd as a momentum indicator turned
to the upside or no longer continued to
follow the downward price movement
it means that the indicator diverged
from the price movement and shows that
the momentum of the current price
movement was failing
we also had an engulfing candle
rejecting the area which is the third
confluence factor in the setup
this was a valid trait and we entered
right after the rejection with a stop
loss below the engulfing bar
here we have another demand zone on the
pound dollar on the daily time frame
again we'll use a multiple time frame
approach the daily chart on the right
the larger time frame will establish the
trend and reversals start from the
smaller time frames first and continue
upwards
on the 30 minute chart here's the macd
divergence inside the demand zone which
means that momentum of the current price
movement was failing
to make the histogram turned positive
another bullish confirmation
price then started to make higher highs
and higher lows another bullish sign
as it checked many confluence factors an
entry inside the demand area turned out
to be a great trait
it goes without saying you can replace
the macd with any other momentum
indicator if you don't like it use the
rsi instead for spotting the emergencies
for example
[Music]
second confirmation comes from the
stochastic
stochastic also measures the momentum of
price
although i don't rely much on overbought
and oversold conditions these signals
tend to work in combination with supply
and demand zones
now when stochastic isn't overbought and
oversold it has absolutely nothing to do
with the market getting ready for a
reversal not even in the slightest way
trading with these levels without price
action is a guaranteed way to lose money
trading
so because i don't trust these levels
much i increased the parameters for
overbought and oversold from 20 and 80
to 10 and 90 and i also increased the
length of the stochastic to 15 5 and 3.
this way the indicator won't reach the
levels as often
here we see an example of stochastic
confirmation by signal at the demand
area
we'll use the same multiple timeframe
approach
we'll trade in the direction of the
higher time frame especially for a trade
like this
that would be considered against the
previous downtrend leading up to it i
like to see a confirmation signal before
entering
we can see a nice up move which followed
this oversold stochastic signal
you could also wait for this trendline
breakout if you really want to be sure
that the bulls are taking full control
here's another example
we found the supply zone on the four
hour time frame on the right side
on the 30 minute time frame on the first
re-test of the supply zone stochastic
was well over 90 and price found new
sellers in this area
we had a nice swing to the downside we
even had the third and the fourth
re-test of the area
if you want to trade the supply area
make sure the zone is still fresh which
means that after the initial creation of
the zone price has not come back to it
yet each time price revisits a supply
zone more and more previously unfilled
orders are filled and the level is
weakened continuously
but if you have confidence that the
supply area will hold you could re-enter
with a lower position
the fourth retest came with a massive
move to the downside
[Music]
if you learned something new please hit
the like button since it really helps us
out and subscribe to stay up to date
with our latest releases
and check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time