Many traders use moving averages to follow
the trend and to identify changes in market
direction.
While moving averages are a useful tool to
have in your toolbox, they can provide false
signals quite a lot.
One method to filter market noise and remove
a part of those false signals is to use moving
average envelopes.
In today’s video, you’ll discover how
to trade using envelopes and I’ll share
several strategies using this indicator.
The Envelopes is a tool that attempts to identify
the upper and lower bands of a trading range.
It does this by plotting two moving average
envelopes on a price chart, one shifted up
to a certain distance above, and one shifted
below.
The idea behind this indicator is that the
price has the tendency to remain within a
certain range during normal market conditions.
However, when these conditions are changing
the price has the potential to move above
or below the envelope bands, which is signaling
possible trading positions.
Moving Average Envelopes consist of a moving
average plus and minus a percentage deviation.
When you apply the envelope indicator, you
will notice two lines or bands which appear
above and below the price and these lines
are called upper and lower envelopes.
Also, the area between the bands represents
the channel.
The line within the channel is moving average.
You can see that the bands move in parallel
with the moving average because the distance
away from the moving average is constant.
Each envelope is set the same percentage above
or below the moving average.
This creates the parallel bands that follow
price action.
Now, the selection of period of the moving
average and the percentage of envelopes is
what makes or breaks your trading strategy.
The parameters for the Moving Average Envelopes
depend on your trading or investing objectives
and the characteristics of the market you
are trading.
Day traders and scalpers will likely use shorter
(faster) moving averages and relatively tight
envelopes.
Swing traders and investors will likely prefer
longer (slower) moving averages with wider
envelopes.
The market volatility will also influence
the parameters.
When you plot the envelopes on your chart,
you probably see the resemblance with Bollinger
Bands and Keltner Channel.
Well, these indicators will adjust by themselves
to market volatility.
Bollinger Bands use the standard deviation
to set bandwidth.
Keltner Channels use the Average True Range
(ATR) to set channel width.
Well, with envelopes, you must independently
account for volatility when setting the Moving
Average Envelopes.
Stocks with high volatility will require wider
bands to encompass most price action, while
markets with low volatility can use narrower
bands.
In choosing the right parameters, it often
helps to overlay a few different Moving Average
Envelopes and compare.
For example, this chart contains 2 Moving
Average Envelopes based on the 21-day SMA.
The 3% envelopes were touched several times,
while the 5% envelopes were only touched rarely.
A swing trader might use the 5% envelopes,
while a short-term trader could use the 3%
envelopes.
So how to read the envelopes?
With a moving average as the base, Moving
Average Envelopes can be used as a trend following
indicator.
Beyond simply trend following, the envelopes
can also be used to identify overbought and
oversold levels when the trend is relatively
flat and also to provide dynamic support and
resistance.
The moving average envelopes smooths out price
fluctuations and allows us to see the bigger
picture of the market.
With the Envelopes, you can look at the direction
of the bands to get an idea about the trend.
If the bands are sloping upward, then it confirms
an uptrend.
If the bands are sloping downward, it confirms
a downtrend.
When the envelopes are moving sideways, price
is neither in an uptrend or downtrend.
Although different traders have their own
way in which they use the envelope and try
to identify specific patterns, the common
application of the indicator is to provide
certain alerts such as overbought or oversold,
sell and buy signals or as a trend confirmation.
If you use narrow envelopes, when prices are
done resting and consolidating, they will
break out of envelopes, in one direction or
the other.
A trader might view prices breaking above
the upper envelope as a potential buy opportunity.
And when prices break below the lower envelope,
a trader might view that as a selling opportunity.
Basically, Moving Average Envelopes can be
used to identify strong moves that signal
the start of an extended trend.
The trick, as always, is picking the correct
parameters, which takes practice, trial and
error.
In this example notice how the price broke
above the upper envelope and continued moving
above this band.
This shows buying strength.
The inverse logic can be applied for a downtrend.
A strong move below the lower envelope signals
weakness that can foreshadow an extended downtrend.
Remember, if you want to chase breakout moves,
use narrow envelopes.
Now, the majority of price breakouts do not
go on to form new trends.
They will instead more frequently revert back
into the previous price range.
If you are familiar with Bollinger Bands,
you probably now that a common strategy is
to sell near the upper band and to buy near
the lower band.
This could also be applied to envelopes.
Moving Average Envelopes make great overbought
and oversold indicators, when using higher
parameters.
Using the concept of range trading, you could
buy when the price penetrates the lower envelope
and closes back inside the envelope.
Likewise, you might sell when the price penetrates
the upper envelope and then closes back down
inside the envelope.
In this example, notice there are times when
price initially moves above or below an envelope
but turns back around.
This usually happens when the moving average
slope is FLAT.
When this happens, moving average envelopes
can be used to identify overbought and oversold
levels.
When price moves above the upper envelope,
this can be considered overbought.
When price moves below the lower envelope,
this can be considered oversold.
However, identifying overbought and oversold
levels isn’t easy.
Remember, price can become overbought and
remain overbought when the bullish trend is
strong.
The same goes for being oversold.
This is why it’s best to pay attention to
the slope of the moving average and make sure
it’s flat.
Here, notice how the 20 MA and the upper and
lower envelopes are flat…almost horizontal
even.
Basically, the price is directionless here.
There is no strong bullish trend, nor is there
a strong bearish trend.
Observe how the upper envelope acts as a strong
resistance level.
Whenever price traded near the upper envelope,
price would fall back down.
The same with the lower envelope.
Observe how it acts as a strong support level.
Whenever price traded near the lower envelope,
price would bounce back up.
Envelopes are also great for buying or selling
pullbacks.
If the last high was let’s say five percent
above the moving average, keep the upper envelope
line set at five percent—the next high will
often reflect the same extreme.
Conversely, if the last significant downswing
low was five percent below the moving average,
keep this figure as the lower envelope setting
until market action dictates otherwise.
In this example, notice this great entry at
the lower envelope.
The market made a swing low here, and respected
the dynamic support offered by the lower envelopes
the second time the price reached the area.
The envelopes also serve as dynamic support
and resistance areas.
If prices cross above the moving average,
assume that this line will act as support
on pullbacks and the next rally will have
the potential to advance to the upper envelope
line.
If the price is in an uptrend, the upper envelope
line may act as a rising dynamic line of resistance.
The rally tops will hug the upper envelope
line, but prices will tend to keep going up.
So, in an uptrend, the upper envelope is a
great take profit zone.
If prices cross below the center moving average,
assume that this line will act as resistance
on any rebounds and that downside potential
is to the lower envelope line.
If the trend is down, the lower envelope line
may act as a falling dynamic support line.
The lower envelope is a potential take profit
zone.
In an uptrend, price could decline to the
lower envelope line.
This area will define where the price is both
oversold and the specific price area that
offers a potential buying opportunity.
In a downtrend, price could advance to the
upper envelope line.
This area will help define where the market
is both overbought and the specific price
area that may be most opportune as a selling
point.
Remember that moving averages are lagging
indicators.
This is because the price data always incorporates
periods of the past, so the inflexions in
the market's direction will always be reflected
more slowly by a moving average, rather than
by the price itself.
How much more slowly, is a function of the
size of the period you choose.
In some cases, you may find that using a combination
of more than one set of envelopes (say, one
with a longer period and one with a shorter
period) may paint a fuller picture.
Really the best way to establish what works
with your own trading style is to go ahead
and back test different periods in different
time frames.
Also, it goes without saying, building a complete
Envelope strategy is not just about signals
informing you when to buy and sell.
Envelopes are just a part of the full story.
Price action, support and resistance and a
solid risk management are also needed to get
the best out of envelopes.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay in touch when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.