Renko charts are one of the most valuable
and underrated instruments, which offer a
great value to patient traders.
Although Renko trading is not as popular and
not as well-known as normal candlestick or
bar charts, you’ll be surprised about how
profitable it can be if used correctly.
In this video, i’ll explain you the concept
of Renko trading, I’ll show you the advantages
of using this type of chart and you’ll also
discover a simple Renko strategy to trade
the stock market.
Before we continue, if you’re new to our
channel, make sure you subscribe, hit the
notification bell and leave a like to show
your support.
So, what is a Renko chart.
A Renko chart is a graphical display that
only involves the price movement, because
the time and volume are not included.
The construction of a Renko chart is simple:
a brick (or better said, the “body” of
a Renko bar) is formed in the next column
once the price exceeds the top or bottom of
the previous brick by a predefined amount,
in this case i use a 100 brick, but you could
use any brick size you want, 10, 20, it all
depends on your trading style.
The difference between common charts and Renko
is noticeable.
The conventional charts like candlestick charts
or bar charts are plotting a new candlestick,
bar based on time.
The uniqueness of Renko charts is that this
technique plots a brick only when the price
moves a certain amount of pips /ticks in one
direction or the other.
Now you might wonder, how is this better than
a classic candlestick chart.
Here are the main advantages of Renko trading.
First, Renko charts are very effective for
traders to identify key support/resistance
levels
In this chart, we notice how simple it is
to plot the support and resistance levels.
And most interestingly, notice how price reacts
to these support/resistance levels from the
left side of the chart.
By using Renko chart for support and resistance,
we can see price action being more responsive.
Second, Renko charts offer a simpler look
of the market and indicate trends in a more
clean way
Here we have the evolution of the price during
the past 7 months.
Look how OBVious is for you to identify the
trends.
Since December to January, we have 2 months
of downward price action, and after that we
have a clear uptrend, with the price making
higher highs and higher lows.
Another important advantage is the fact that
it removes the “market noise” seen on
typical candlestick charts or bar charts,
including wicks, false breakouts and price
volatility.
In addition, Renko charts are suitable for
scalping and short-term trading.
So, if you want to scalp the market, I would
say it’s better to use a Renko chart than
trading on the 1-min timeframe.
Also, it allow traders to catch larger moves
by filtering out minor price fluctuations
One of the most important advantages of Renko
charts is a better determination of stop losses
and take profit targets.
With Renko charts, is very easy to place your
orders, based on the previous bricks.
You just have to time your entry and make
sure your orders are placed accordingly.
Also, what I’ve noticed over the years,
is the fact that Renko trading minimize overtrading
and increase patience, which will make a better
trader overall
Now enough with the theory and let’s dive
right into a simple Renko strategy.
For this strategy, I use a 100 Renko brick.
How is a 100 Renko brick formed?
A new green Renko bar forms only after the
current price exceeds the top of the previous
Renko bar by 100 points.
The closing price of a green Renko bar is
also the high for the green Renko bar.
A new red Renko bar forms only after the current
price surpasses the bottom of the previous
Renko bar by 100 pips
The closing price of a red Renko bar is also
the low for the red Renko bar.
Besides the 100 brick I also prefer to add
a 10 moving average in order to determine
the trend and the OBV.
So Renko bars are based only on price, but
I don’t want to neglect the volume.
The on balance volume (OBV), is a momentum
indicator that relates volume to price change
and shows if market’s volume is flowing
into or out of a stock.
In other words, the OBV offers information
regarding the strength of price movements.
OBV increases or decreases during each day
in correlation on whether the price closes
higher or lower compared to the close during
the previous period.
The main assumption is that on balance volume
movements precede price changes.
As the volume is the main fuel behind the
market, OBV is designed to anticipate when
major moves in the markets would occur.
For this reason, the OBV will play an important
part in the strategy.
Here are the main rules of this strategy:
We use the 100 Renko brick to identify key
support/resistance levels, to determine the
market trends and to place our stop-loss and
take-profit targets
We use 10 simple moving average to determine
the short-term trend
We confirm our bias with the on balance volume
(OBV) to determine if market’s volume is
flowing into or out of the traded instrument
Here is the setup for a long signal:
1.
A new green Renko bar forms above the SMA10
2.
We only take trades in the direction of the
SMA.
When the Renko bars are traded above SMA10,
we look for long entries
3.
We filter the signal with the on balance volume.
We look for a new high in the OBV, which indicates
that buyers are stronger than sellers, and
the price is likely to increase.
When OBV increases in correlation with the
price, the upward trend is confirmed.
4.
Stop loss will be placed 2 Renko bars below
the entry point.
5.
We can exit the position manually if the price
falls below the simple moving average.
6.
Minimum take profit should be 3 Renko bars
into the future, to cover the spread and commissions.
When the price reach this target, we can move
our stop loss to break even and let the trade
ride, or we can use a trailing stop to capture
a larger part of the move.
In this example, we have 4 valid buy entries,
all of them bringing decent returns.
And here we have another chart during which
we had 5 signals.
Remember to always look at the OBV to confirm
the entry.
Also, here’s another tip to reduce your
losses.
Take a closer look at the slope of the 10
SMA.
For better quality signals, try to enter the
market when the ma is pointing upward.
In our case, the first 2 signals appeared
when the 10 SMA was flat, so a conservative
trader would have ignored these entries and
focused on the last ones, when the slope was
clearly pointing upward.
And here is the setup for a short signal:
1.
A new red Renko bar forms below the SMA10
2.
We only take trades in the direction of the
SMA.
When the Renko bars are traded below SMA10,
we look for short entries only
3.
We filter the signal with the on balance volume.
We look for a new low in the OBV, which indicates
that sellers are stronger than buyers, and
the price is likely to decrease.
When OBV decreases in correlation with the
price, the downward trend is confirmed.
4.
Stop loss will be placed 2 Renko bars above
the entry point.
5.
We can exit the position manually if the price
increases above the simple moving average.
6.
Minimum take profit should be 3 Renko bars
into the future.
As in the case of a buy signal, when the price
reaches this target, we can move our stop
loss to break even and let the trade ride,
or we can use a trailing stop to capture a
larger part of the move.
On our example, we had 4 signals.
First one was a losing trade, but we could
easily avoided if we looked at the slope of
the SMA, which was flat.
The next 3 signals were successful, as the
price and OBV went head to head, the price
making lower lows and lower highs.
And in this example we have 3 entries.
The first entry here, with some risk because
the SMA slope was pointing upward, the second
one here, with the perfect setup, from the
SMA and OBV, and the third one here, also
riskier because the SMA was flat.
The price consolidated for a few days below
the SMA, before it finally continued its downward
direction.
So, for you to record better results, pay
attention to the slope of the 10 SMA and try
to enter when you see the slope in correlation
with the market trend.
Also, pay attention to the recent market swings,
try to enter long during long term upward
trends and go short during long-term downtrends.
Now, if you found value and enjoyed this type
of content make sure you subscribe, hit the
notification bell and leave a like to show
your support.
Until next time.