Financial markets have price movements that
repeat over and over again.
These movements are called waves.
Elliott Wave Theory is a comprehensive and
complex topic, taking practitioners months
and even years to master.
Despite its complexity, there are some elements
of Elliott Wave that can be incorporated and
may help improve your trade timing.
So I’ll try to keep this very simple and
I will break down the Wave Theory into small
pieces.
First concept: Impulsive and Corrective Waves
Ralph Nelson Elliott, the trader who developed
the Elliott Wave Theory, proposed that trends
in financial prices resulted from investors'
predominant psychology.
He found that swings in mass psychology always
showed up in the same recurring fractal patterns,
or "waves".
Elliott discovered that stock index price
patterns were structured in the same way.
He then began to look at how these repeating
patterns could be used as predictive indicators
of future market moves.
Now, prices move in impulsive and corrective
waves.
Knowing which wave is likely underway, and
what recent waves were, will help you to forecast
what the price is likely to do next.
An impulse wave is a large price move and
has associated trends.
An uptrend keeps reaching higher prices because
the moves up are larger than the moves down
which occur between those large up waves.
Corrective waves are the smaller waves that
occur within a trend.
So, knowing this, it’s advised to trade
in the direction of the impulse waves, because
the price is making the largest moves in that
direction.
Impulse waves provide a better chance of making
a large profit than corrective waves do.
You can use corrective waves to enter into
a trend trade, in an attempt to capture the
next bigger impulse wave.
The ideal way to trade is to buy during pullbacks
or corrective waves during uptrends, and ride
the next impulse wave as it takes the price
higher.
Also, you sell during corrective waves in
a downtrend to profit from the next impulse
wave down.
The idea of impulsive and corrective waves
is also used to determine when a trend is
changing direction.
If a price chart shows big moves to the upside,
with small corrective waves in between, and
then a much larger down move occurs, that
is a signal the uptrend may be over.
Since impulses occur in the trending direction,
a big move to the downside—which is bigger
than prior corrective waves, and as large
as the upward impulse waves—indicates the
trend is now down.
If the trend is down, and a big up wave occurs—that
is as big as the prior down waves during the
downtrend—then the trend is now up and you
should look to buy during the next corrective
waves.
Second concept: Trend and Pullback Price Structures
Elliot found that when an uptrend is underway
it typically has three large upward price
moves, with two corrections.
This creates a five-wave pattern: impulse,
correction, impulse, correction, and another
impulse.
These five waves are labeled wave one through
wave five, respectively.
The uptrend is then followed by three waves
lower: an impulse down, a correction to the
upside, and then another impulse down.
These waves are labeled A, B, and C.
Elliot also found that these movements are
fractal, meaning the pattern occurs on small
and large time frames.
For example, the first impulse wave higher
within an uptrend on a daily chart is composed
of five waves on an hourly chart.
Also, corrective waves are composed of three
smaller waves if viewed on a smaller chart
time frame.
Just as impulsive and corrective waves help
determine when to enter trades, and in which
direction the trend is moving, the price structure
can do the same.
Assume there was a big move to the upside—an
impulsive wave—then a correction is likely
to follow.
That correction to the downside will often
unfold in three waves: a drop, a small rally,
and then another drop.
You can use this to improve trade timing by
waiting for that second drop.
Getting it right when the price starts to
drop the first time is too early, as another
drop is likely coming.
Also, once there have been three big moves
to the upside, the uptrend may be nearing
completion.
An impulse wave to the downside would then
confirm that the price is likely to head lower
and the uptrend is indeed over.
Third concept is the correction size
So your trading plan should be to buy on corrections
during an uptrend or selling on corrections
in a downtrend.
And it is helpful to know how large the typical
correction is.
Based on the five wave pattern, wave one is
the first impulse wave of a trend and wave
two is the first correction.
Wave three is the next impulse, followed by
corrective wave four and impulse wave five.
Based on the research of Nelson, wave two
is typically 60 percent the length of wave
one.
If wave one advances $1, then wave two will
likely see the price drop by about 60 cents.
Wave two is followed by impulse wave three.
The third wave of a trend is often the largest,
usually much bigger than wave one.
Wave four comes next and is typically 30 to
40 percent the size of wave three.
For example, if wave three rallied $2, the
price is likely to drop 60 to 80 cents during
wave four.
The same concept holds true for a downtrend.
These are averages seen over many trades and
trends.
Corrections may be smaller or larger than
average on any single trade.
Yet, even having an approximate idea of how
big a correction is likely to be can help
improve you trade timing significantly.
The 3 Golden Rules Of Elliott Wave Theory
There are THREE important rules in labeling
waves.
Rule Number #1: Wave 3 can NEVER be the shortest
impulse wave.
So wave 3 should be the longest of the impulse
waves but it cannot be the shortest which
means that waves 1 or 5 CANNOT BE longer than
wave 3.
Also the high of wave 3 must be higher than
that of wave 1 and if it’s not higher, you
have to start your re-count.
You need to remember that impulse waves are
meant to be making progress not slowing down.
Therefore if price does not exceed the high
of wave 2, then that means there’s no progress
therefore you have to start the re-count.
Rule Number #2: Wave 2 can NEVER go beyond
the start of Wave 1.
In other words, Wave 2 shall not retrace more
than 100 % of wave 1.
If a break occurs below this low, you need
to start your re-count.
Rule Number #3: Wave 4 can NEVER cross in
the same price area as Wave 1, meaning that
Wave 4 can never overlap wave 1.
So the LOW OF WAVE 4 cannot go BELOW THE HIGH
OF WAVE 1.
If that happens, you need a re-count.
3 Elliott Wave guidelines
Now, we got 3 golden rules but we also have
3 Elliott Wave guidelines.
First guideline: when the wave 3 is the longer
impulse wave, wave 5 will be almost/approximately
equal to wave 1
Second guideline: the structure for wave 2
and wave 4 will alternate…if wave 2 is a
sharp correction, wave 4 will be a flat correction.
If wave 2 is flat, wave 4 will be sharp.
And the last guideline: after a 5 wave impulse
advance, ABC corrections usually end in the
area of prior wave 4 low.
Elliott wave trading is not that easy to understand…at
first.
As a matter of fact, the easiest part is the
theory part.
The hardest part is the application part!
That’s why I advise you, at first, to utilize
the concepts I’ve talked in the beginning
of the video: Impulsive and Corrective Waves,
trend and Pullback Price Structures and correction
size.
The most important thing to remember is to
only take trades in the direction of the impulse
waves and take trades during the corrective
waves.
Look for trade entry signals once the price
has corrected the average amount.
The correction isn't likely to stop exactly
at the percentage levels discussed before,
so taking trades slightly above or below the
described percentage levels is fine.
Also, consider keeping track of each wave
in the overall price structure.
For example, after a five wave pattern to
the upside, a bigger three wave decline usually
follows.
Watching the direction of the impulse waves
will signal potential trend changes, and that
signal is stronger if combined by a five-wave
impulse pattern or three-wave correction pattern
ending.
These Elliott Wave concepts will improve your
analysis skills and improve your trade timing,
but it is not without its own problems.
As I said before, the theory can be complex
to apply, as it isn't always easy isolating
the five wave and three wave patterns.
Elliott Wave is not a trading technique.
There are no specific rules of entry or exit,
nor is there one “right” way to use it
in trading.
As a result, the use of Elliott Wave has been
avoided by many traders, not due to a lack
of understanding but because of the apparently
subjective nature of how it may be applied.
Nonetheless, there are many traders who have
successfully used Elliott Wave patterns in
their trading.
This video was basically an introduction to
Elliot Waves and I tried not to complicate
things, but in future videos we’ll go deeper
and we’ll talk about some advanced Elliot
wave concepts that can be applied to day trading
and swing trading.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.