Here’s what I’ve learned after 1 full
month of studying and back testing the Elliot
Wave Theory.
The key to using the Elliot method successfully
lies in counting the waves correctly and identifying
the wave in which the market is currently
trading in. That’s it. Identify the wave
and you will profit from it.
Today, I will try to help you better understand
the general characteristics of the different
waves within the overall market structure.
Learn this, and Elliot Wave theory will become
much simpler.
Before we begin, if you want more videos,
more often, please drop a like to help us
with Youtube algorithm and turn on the bell,
so you don’t miss when new content is released.
One of the key points within the Elliott wave
theory is the concept of the fractal nature
of the markets. This means price patterns
repeat themselves over and over again on all
time frames.
Under the Elliott wave theory, there are two
types of price progressions.
The first are those price movements or waves
that are aligned with the larger trend. These
price movements are referred to as motive
waves.
The second are those price movements are waves
that are contrary to the larger trend. These
price movements are referred to as corrective
waves.
Motive waves can be classified further as
impulse waves or diagonal waves depending
on the form and location within the overall
structure.
Impulse waves are the most common form of
motive waves and the easiest to spot in a
market
A diagonal wave also moves the market in the
direction of the trend. The difference is
that the diagonal wave looks like a wedge
- either expanding or contracting.
Corrective waves are generally classified
as either flat structures, zigzag structures,
triangle structures, or double or triple combinations.
The basic form of the entire Elliott wave
sequence is comprised of five waves that make
up the motive wave, which are labeled waves
one through five.
Following the completion of wave five within
the motive sequence, the market will develop
into a three wave retracement that moves contrary
to this motive wave sequence.
This retracement move consists of three waves
labeled as waves A, B and C.
If you’re just starting, there are only
three unbreakable rules as it relates to the
Elliott wave principle.
The first rule is that wave two cannot retrace
more than 100% of wave one.
The second rule is that wave four cannot move
into the territory of wave one.
And finally, wave three cannot be the shortest
wave amongst waves one, three, and five.
So, like I said in the beginning of the video,
if you learn to recognize the current wave
of the market, you will be ahead of most traders.
Now let’s me share the characteristics of
the various waves within the Elliott wave
structure, in the context of a bull market.
Pay attention to each description, and by
the end of the video Elliot wave theory will
no longer appear complicated.
Wave one begins the impulse sequence.
During this wave prices began to bounce higher
after a long sustained downtrend.
The sentiment in the market is very bearish
at the start of wave one.
As wave one moves higher, most people see
this upside price movement as just a bear
market rally, and many investors and traders
consider wave one as a good opportunity to
initiate a new short position or add to their
existing short positions.
Wave one is generally the least predictive
wave within the entire Elliott wave structure.
There is really no way to know how long the
wave will last.
However, at some point it will become clearly
apparent that wave one has ended, as a significant
swing high is reached, and prices begin to
move lower in a bearish direction once again.
Wave one generally subdivides into five smaller
waves and can sometimes appear as a leading
diagonal structure.
After wave one completes, the next one in
the sequence will be wave two.
Wave two will move counter to wave one, and
will retrace a large portion of wave one.
Often wave two will retrace wave one by either
a 50% retracement, 61% retracement, or even
78% retracement.
During wave two investors and traders begin
to feel assured once again that the downtrend
has continued. However, the market will fail
to break below the wave one low.
Remember, one of the unbreakable rules within
the Elliott wave theory, which is, that wave
two cannot retrace below the start of wave
one.
Informed traders will begin to recognize this
pattern and start to position to the long
side of the market.
Wave two will generally take the form of a
zigzag correction, or a flat correction.
In either case the retracement will be fairly
deep.
Additionally, since wave two is a corrective
structure, it will develop as an ABC pattern
comprised of three waves.
Wave three offers the largest potential for
profit as it is usually the biggest and most
powerful wave within the overall Elliott wave
structure.
The psychology of traders during wave three
is generally one of growing optimism.
Although many of the earlier sellers will
still resist the optimistic outlook during
the early stages of wave three, it will become
increasingly evident to most traders that
the trend has shifted, and the markets are
poised to move higher.
After the break of the swing high of wave
one, prices will begin to accelerate upward
as more and more traders recognize the bullish
sentiment and start taking long positions.
Additionally, many sellers will have their
stops triggered at the wave one swing high,
which adds further fuel to the upper price
momentum.
If you identify the 3rd wave, you need to
join the trend as quickly as possible in order
to take advantage of the explosive moves that
are characteristic of wave three.
Those that wait for a pullback or retracement
to get in, will often miss the entire move,
as wave three offers very little in the way
of pullbacks, and when they are present, they
tend to be quite shallow.
Wave three will often travel 1.618 times the
length of wave one measured from the end of
wave two. The second most common projection
for wave three is for it to travel 2.618 times
the length of wave one measured from the end
of wave two.
One of the guidelines within the Elliott wave
principle is that among waves 1,3 and 5 of
the impulse sequence, there will be one extended
wave which is quite larger than the other
two.
In most cases, wave 3 will be that extended
wave.
Wave four will follow wave three and will
retrace a portion of wave three.
Typically, wave four will be a shallower retracement,
and will often terminate at 38% or 50% of
wave three.
Since wave three is often the longest wave
within the overall sequence, we can expect
wave four to be less aggressive in percentage
terms than wave two.
Also, we need to keep in mind one of the core
rules within the Elliott wave theory during
wave four. That is wave four should not overlap
into the territory of wave one.
If it does, then you need to relabel your
wave count as this is an unbreakable rule.
Wave four is also often seen as a profit-taking
wave.
Because those traders that bought early in
wave three are sitting on a healthy amount
of profits, many of these traders will begin
to liquidate their positions and lock in their
profits.
This creates a sideways price movement that
is often prolonged in nature.
Wave four often takes the form of a triangle.
However, wave four can also be a flat formation,
and sometimes it forms as a zigzag pattern
or some combination.
The price action often appears range bound,
with prices moving back and forth without
any clear direction.
Wave four brings with it whipsawing price
action that often generates false breakout
on either side of the market.
You need to be very careful when taking new
positions during wave four as you are more
likely to lose money during these directionless
market conditions.
Wave five is the final leg within the Elliott
wave impulse sequence.
It moves in the direction of the overall trend
similarly to waves one, and wave three.
During the progression of wave five, almost
everyone is bullish.
Wave five is often considered a retail wave,
because it is during this time when most retail
investors are driving prices higher, often
to extreme valuations.
The momentum behind the bullish activity in
wave five will be less dynamic than that during
the wave three progression.
This basically means that the velocity of
the price movement will be more subdued than
that seen during wave three.
During the late stages of wave five we will
also see technical divergence patterns form
between the price action and many momentum
indicators such as RSI, Stochastics, and MACD.
These momentum divergence signals are telling
us is that the velocity of the price movement
higher is diminishing, and we should expect
the upside trend to reverse its course soon.
Along with momentum divergences, wave five
will often register lower volume compared
to wave three. This is another indication
that the trend is weakening and that profits
should be locked in, as a potential reversal
is imminent.
In terms of how far wave five will travel,
well…wave five will terminate upon reaching
a length that is equivalent to the length
seen in wave one.
The next most likely projection for wave five
is for it to travel a distance of 61% the
length of wave one. Both of these projections
for wave five are measured from the end of
wave four.
The end of wave five brings with it the completion
of the impulse sequence.
More specifically, the impulse sequence consists
of waves one through five, and thus, at the
end of wave five, we can expect a corrective
structure to follow which will often be a
three wave pattern, waves A, B, and C.
Wave A starts the corrective sequence and
during this phase, most traders are still
very bullish, and consider the wave A pullback
as just another minor retracement.
Wave A is somewhat similar to wave one in
its structure.
During both of these wave progressions, the
market participants are heavily positioned
on one side of the market, depending on the
direction of the larger trend.
However, just as in wave one, some experienced
traders begin to recognize the overbought
market condition during wave five.
Wave A is often a sharp move and may subdivide
as either a five wave pattern or a three wave
pattern.
Wave B is the second leg of the corrective
structure and follows wave A.
Wave B is often considered a bull trap, because
it tends to draw in a lot of traders, believing
that the existing trend is still healthy.
However, this is far from the case. Wave B
will be a fairly short-lived pattern and will
often fail to surpass the wave five swing
high.
Wave B will often create a double top formation
in which it will try to test the wave five
extreme and fail to breach it.
This doesn’t always happen; however, it
is quite characteristic for wave B to terminate
just short of the wave five extreme.
Wave B is often a fairly deep retracement
and will retrace wave A by either 50%, 61%,
or 78%.
The subdivision within Wave B itself is often
seen as a zigzag pattern, but sometimes it
will form as a triangle as well.
One of the best trades within the Elliott
wave sequence is to fade the wave B price
move as it nears its terminal point.
After wave B completes, wave C will begin
and this wave marks the final leg within the
entire corrective structure.
When the wave B swing low is breached, that
event will mark a turning point where more
and more traders will become convinced that
the uptrend has actually ended, and the market
is poised for lower prices.
Wave
C is often equivalent to the length of wave
A.
Wave C will travel a distance of 1.27 times
the length of wave A.
After this distance, the next most likely
area for wave C to terminate would be when
it has traveled the distance of 1.61 times
the length the wave A.
Now that you know the characteristics of each
wave, let me share a simple checklist to apply
to the sequence. Print it or write it down,
and use it every time you are unsure about
the current wave of the market.
• Wave 1, wave 3 and wave 5 are trending.
• Wave 2 and wave 4 are corrections.
• Of wave 1, wave 3 and wave 5, wave 3 must
not be the shortest, but it does not have
to be the longest
• Wave 2 can retrace up to 99 percent of
wave 1.
• Wave 4 should not go into the price area
of wave 2.
• Wave 4 never enters the price territory
of wave 1
• Wave 2 and wave 4 must display alternation
in as many ways as possible. That is, wave
2 and wave 4 must be different in as many
ways as possible.
Alternation occurs between wave 2 and wave
4 as either price, time or pattern type.
• Price: Wave 2 when compared to wave 4
may be obviously smaller/larger in price.
• Time: Wave 2 when compared to wave 4 may
take much more/less time.
• Pattern: Wave 2 may be a simple ABC. Wave
4 could be a more complex A B C or even a
triangle. Wave 2 could be a flat formation.
Wave 4 could be a zigzag or vice versa.
If you enjoyed this type of content and want
more Elliot waves videos, leave us a like
to show your support and to help us with Youtube
algorithm and in future videos we’ll go
even deeper with more advanced strategies
that can be applied to day trading and swing
trading. Until next time.