If you are tired to study charts with overloaded
indicators, and just want to trade price action
with less stress and guessing, then this video
might help you do that.
I don’t know if you are familiar with Renko
charts or with Ichimoku cloud, but let me
tell you, those 2 techniques combined will
give you some decent entries and will filter
a lot of market noise.
So, in the following minutes, we’ll go full
Japanese mode and we’ll discuss about Renko
and Ichimoku, and how you can combine these
2 approaches in a trading strategy.
Before we continue, if you are new to the
channel, make sure you subscribe, turn on
the notification bell and leave a like to
show your support.
Renko and Ichimoku are one of the many traditional
Japanese forms of analysis.
Renko charts are an overlooked way of analyzing
price data and charting markets.
Renko charts eliminate the time component
of trading and only focus on the price itself.
Potentially, Renko charts can filter out a
lot of the market noise and display the price
in a much more organized way that is simpler
to interpret.
Conventional candlestick charts generate a
new candlestick every hour, 4 hours, day,
week or another time interval the trader chooses
as his period setting.
Renko charts, on the other hand, are not time-based
and they don’t use candlesticks, but “bricks.”
A trader might set 1 Renko brick equal to
10 points which mean that the Renko chart
will show a new brick every time price has
moved 10 points in one direction.
For this strategy, we’ll use 100 points
for one brick, because i want to eliminate
the noise as much as possible.
The second component of our strategy is the
Ichimoku indicator.
An Ichimoku chart is a trend-following system
with an indicator similar to moving averages,
which offers a unique perspective of support
and resistance.
I don’t like to plot all the components
of Ichimoku, because it’s messy and a quite
confusing, so i only focus on the cloud and
on the lagging span.
The lagging span allows us to visualize the
relationship between current and prior trends,
as well as to spot potential trend reversals.
When lagging span is above the current price,
this indicates that current prices are higher
than previously, and indicates a bullish bias
• When lagging span is below the current
price, this indicates that current prices
are lower than previously, suggesting a bearish
bias
• When lagging span is near the current
price, this indicates a trading range
The most important component of Ichimoku is
the Kumo cloud, formed from 2 lines (span
A and span B), which act as major areas of
dynamic support and resistance.
Here are the main 4 rules we will apply later
in our strategy
• the longer the price stays below/above
the Kumo cloud, the stronger the trend is(
so for strong and reliable trends, we want
the price to stay above or below the cloud
for long periods of time and we don’t want
to see the price cutting through the cloud
multiple times in a short period of time
• When the cloud is wide, the expected support
or resistance is strong.
• When the cloud is thin, the expected support/resistance
is weak.
• The last important rule is that you should
never trade inside the Kumo cloud.
So when the price trades inside the Kumo,
no matter if you anticipate that it will break
in one direction, you must stay disciplined
and wait for the price to exit the cloud.
Now, when we apply Renko charts with the Ichimoku
cloud, we get a very clean, clear and simple
way to analyze markets.
Applying the Ichimoku to the Renko charts
but only using the 2 components that we discussed,
Ichimoku cloud and the lagging span, will
offer you a simple and effective trend following
strategy.
Here are the basic rules of this trading approach:
• We use the 100 Renko brick to identify
key support/resistance levels, to determine
the market trends and to place our stop-loss
and take-profit targets
• We use Kumo cloud to determine the main
trend
• When the price enters the Kumo cloud and
breaks its upper wall upward, we have a bullish
trend
• When the price enters the Kumo and breaks
its lower wall downward, we have a bearish
trend)
• We can confirm our bias with lagging span,
by following its position above or below the
Kumo cloud.
The most reliable opportunities appear when
3 conditions are met simultaneously:
For buy entries a new green Renko bar appears
above the Kumo could
The Kumo cloud is green and wide
And the lagging span is above the Kumo cloud
And for sell positions
A new red Renko bar appears below the Kumo
could
The Kumo cloud is red and preferably wide
And the lagging span is below the Kumo cloud
So let’s analyze this chart.
These are the perfect market conditions, with
green Renko bars above the green Ichimoku
cloud, and the lagging span above the Kumo
cloud.
Look how easy you spot the upward trend.
Now, I don’t know about you, but when I
look at this chart, I have zero temptation
to short the market.
I can see so clearly that the trend is up,
with greens everywhere, and all I have to
do is to go with the flow and enter long.
There are many long opportunities here: a
possible buy around here, another one here,
riskier because the market hasn’t corrected
much, another one here, right about the previous
support level, also confirmed by the lagging
span, another entry here, after the market
found support from the previous breakout level,
and another one here after a small pullback.
Remember that these are 100 point bricks,
so this is similar to a swing trading style.
Here is another example.
Do you buy here?
No, because the Kumo cloud is red.
So don’t try to jump early in the trade.
Do you buy here or here?
Also, no.
The cloud is still red.
Here is when the first buy entry occurs.
And yes, it was a losing trade, or a breakeven
trade at most, because the market formed another
green brick and reversed.
Another long appeared here, and this one was
a great one.
Pay attention to the lagging span, which stayed
above the Kumo cloud, confirming our bias.
We have another buy opportunity here, riskier
because the market didn’t record a significant
correction.
I personally like to see a correction of at
least 2 or 3 bricks before re-entering.
Here was another opportunity to buy, and the
market indeed continued its direction.
Let’s see how a short signal works on a
tesla chart.
So here, the downtrend begun, but the Kumo
was still green, so you might say we waited
a little bit longer to join the downward move.
Here is when we had the green light to short
the market and from now all you have to do
is to manage the trend accordingly.
We had another chance to reenter after a small
pullback, and another one here.
Other 2 short trades appeared here and here.
All this time, the lagging span remained below
the cloud and confirmed the trend.
In real time, we have contradicting signals.
So the price broke through the cloud, which
is still red, and the lagging span also made
its way on the other side of the cloud.
So, at the time being, no short here for now.
Now, let’s see how we deal with choppy and
ranging markets.
This looks…ugly and not tradable.
First, here is my most important rule.
If I see the lagging span that is going up
and down though the cloud, I read this as
market indecision, and I ignore the setup
and search for better entries.
Pay attention at the lagging span here, it
broke up, broke down, stayed inside the cloud.
It’s all a big mess, and this is not what
a trend looks like.
So, no trades here.
Another clue is the Kumo cloud.
I want to see consistent red, or consisted
green.
I don’t want to see the cloud changing its
color often.
Look here, we have red, green, red, green.
Clearly the market is in indecision and if
I see the cloud that is changing its color,
then maybe it’s better not to trade this
market at all.
Also, the Renko bars.
Look how choppy the market seems.
First the Renko bars are unable to record
higher highs or higher lows, or lower lows
and lower highs, the ultimate definition of
a trend.
But they also cut though the cloud easily.
So no signs of dynamic support or resistance
from the cloud or from the Renko bars.
So, pay attention to these filters because
they can make the difference between a bad
trade and a good one.
Now, if you found value and learned something
new, make sure you subscribe to our channel,
turn on the notifications so you don’t miss
future uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.