The VWAP is one of the best trading indicators
for determining intraday momentum.
VWAP, meaning the Volume-Weighted-Average-Price,
tells you a very important piece of information:
the average price at which an instrument is
traded over a given period of time.
Basically, is the total amount of money transacted
during some period divided by the total amount
of volume that traded over the same time frame.
While VWAP is no holy grail, it is an effective
instrument for differentiating between random
(meaning choppy price action) and non-random
(meaning trending behaviour).
That why, in today’s video I will share
how I use the VWAP to time my entries and
I’ll show you the precise pattern I search
for when I’m day trading stocks.
VWAP represents the market's True Average
Price over the plotted length of time, most
commonly a trading day.
While the other popular technical indicators
are displaying data based on a recent number
of candles, the VWAP has a cumulative nature.
That’s the problem with periodic indicators,
like moving averages for example.
Let’s say you selected a 10ema or a 20sma
to trade with.
Data from beyond the look-back period you’ve
selected is no longer factored into the calculation,
leaving you with an incomplete picture of
the market.
VWAP’s cumulative nature allows you to see
the full picture develop over the course of
the day while factoring in each candle.
No piece of data gets left behind, as each
transaction that has occurred should factor
into how you interpret the current state of
the market and what's most likely to happen
next.
Unlike traditional moving averages which simply
sum up the closing price of an instrument
traded and divide it by a number of predetermined
periods, the VWAP gives you the true average
price of the instrument by additionally considering
the transaction volume at a specific price.
In addition to providing increased context,
the cumulative calculation of VWAP prevents
confusion regarding selected chart time frames
and indicator settings that exist in nearly
every other piece of technical analysis.
It doesn’t matter if you use a 1-minute
chart, a 30-min chart, or anything in between.
There is only one intraday VWAP.
Flipping between time frames will affect only
the display of the VWAP behavior, but the
calculation remains constant.
The same can’t be said for periodic indicators,
where a 20-period moving average on a 1-minute
chart will often look drastically different
than it would with any other period, like
the 5-minute chart.
The reason why VWAP is highly effective is
because it acts like a magnet, either attracting
or repelling the price.
For this reason, VWAP indicator can help you
to identify support and resistance levels.
Since the indicator averages the total periods
for the day, it has psychological meaning
on the chart.
If the price approaches the VWAP from below
and starts hesitating in the area, then the
VWAP may be considered resistance.
If this happens in the opposite direction,
then the indicator might be able to support
the price, creating a bullish movement.
Now that we covered the basics of VWAP, let’s
see how we can apply it to day trading and
scalping.
Considering that the VWAP offers dynamic support
or resistance through the day, the trading
plan would be:
• to identify a probable trend that's expected
to continue
• and to enter the trade around VWAP area
with defined risk
If you analyze any chart, you will notice
that when stocks go on strong trends and get
extended from the VWAP, they will at some
point pullback before the continuing trend.
Waiting for this pullback takes patience.
Most novice traders chase the stock when it
is going up, and then sell for a loss because
they bought when it was extended.
The stock almost always pulls back to its
VWAP at some point during the trading day.
That’s why it’s better to wait for the
pullback and don’t chase the market.
This gives you better Reward vs Risk on your
trades and helps you time your entries and
exits.
So the idea is to buy a retracement to VWAP
after a strong upward move and to sell the
retracement after a strong downward move.
But this strategy alone isn’t enough to
record consistent results.
Often times, the price will cut though the
VWAP with ease.
It’s not about taking a signal, it’s about
filtering and trading only the high quality
setups.
The greatest value of a trading setup is not
the entry it offers, but the stop-loss it
implies.
For VWAP setups, our stop-loss is always on
the other side of it.
A high quality setup offers a reliable stop-loss
point that the market is unlikely to hit in
the near future.
The stop-loss of a high quality VWAP setup
is often a solid support point in a bullish
market or a resistance point in a bearish
market.
Remember this: a high quality VWAP setup usually
occurs at a key support or resistance level.
A long trading setup at a support area is
superior to one that is located in “no man’s
land”.
A short trading setup is more promising if
it appears as the market tests a resistance
area.
So there are 2 factors you should consider
in assessing the quality of a VWAP trading
setup.
First is the VWAP line on your chart and second,
as we target a pullback of a stock, the 50%
Fibonacci retracement.
What I’ve found out when I was analyzing
trends is that most major moves, and many
minor ones, will eventually retrace to around
the 50% level of the move.
That’s why I started to pay extra attention
to these areas.
To draw effective support/resistance levels
using the concept of 50% retracement, the
key is the price move you choose.
The price move must be a strong one that has
momentum on its side.
I primarily only use the 50% level, but for
me it is an ‘approximate’ 50% retrace,
and that means if a valid signal forms near
the 50% level, say anywhere from a 50% retrace
to a 60% retrace, I will also count that as
a valid retrace.
Now, the strategy is all about finding confluence
between VWAP and the 50% FIB level.
For a long signal:
We look for a bullish price move that clears
above a previous swing high with strong momentum.
We mark out a “retracement zone” between
50% and 61.8% of the price move.
If price falls down to the retracement zone
and the VWAP offers additional support, we
aim to buy a possible rejection of that area.
In this example, we have a first strong upswing.
We have consecutive bullish bars which rose
above the last swing high
We drew the 50% and 61.8% retracement levels
of the bullish move.
The area between them is the retracement zone.
This sharp retracement down found support
at the VWAP, right in the retracement zone.
The candlesticks that followed had lower shadows
implying bullish pressure.
Thus, the confluence area between VWAP and
50% zone was a valid signal and offered a
high probability trade.
Stop loss below the confluence area and ideally,
aim for at least 1:1.5 risk reward ratio.
Please bear in mind that you should evaluate
the market bias before assessing individual
trading setups.
The market bias trumps any individual VWAP
trading setup.
If you get the market bias wrong, regardless
of the quality of the trading setup, it will
not work out over the long run.
For a short signal:
Look for a bearish price move that clears
below the previous swing low with strong momentum.
Mark out a “retracement zone” between
50% and 61.8% of the price move.
If price rises up to the retracement zone
and the VWAP offers additional resistance,
we aim to sell a possible rejection of that
area.
Here we have a bearish move that brought the
market to a new low for the day.
With this bearish move, we drew a 50% retracement
zone, which also aligned with the VWAP
As the price reached the confluence area,
we had a trendline breakout which offered
additional confirmation that the bears are
in control of that area.
Given the confluence of resistance levels
and VWAP, this trading signal was valid.
More specifically, the entry timing offered
by the setup was appealing.
The advantage here is that VWAP is more responsive
to price movements on significant volume versus
those with less money behind them.
As VWAP absorbs more price and volume data
over time, it becomes more resistant to random
oscillations and sudden shifts
Here are other examples of valid VWAP trades.
One of the reasons I prefer trading with VWAP
is its ability to eliminate the noise that
occurs throughout the trading session.
Knowing the price at which a majority of the
volume has traded makes it easier to evaluate
a good level to buy or sell.
Also, remember that the best setups often
appear together or close to one another.
By looking for a confluence of patterns, we
are able to identify the high quality setups.
The point is that when you find clusters of
trading setups pointing in the same direction,
you find quality.
An additional tip is to focus trading this
setup on large-cap equities with sufficient
average daily volume, typically familiar names
that move smoothly and follow VWAP levels.
Also avoid pre and post market and the first
15 minutes after the open.
VWAP tends to be jumpy and unreliable during
those periods while it establishes itself.
Remember to apply money management rules when
trading based on the VWAP indicator, and it
would hurt to look for additional confirmation
signals from candlestick patterns, chart patterns,
or other price action signals.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.