One of the more common price analysis tools
used by traders is Fibonacci.
In today’s video, we’ll talk about the
most practical 10 uses of retracements, the
best practices for building a trading strategy
around Fibonacci and other trading tips to
find high-probability signals using this tool.
1.
There must be a visible trend otherwise FIB
levels won’t have a meaningful impact on
price movement
No matter how often you use Fibonacci, what's
most important is to use it correctly every
time.
And choosing the correct price swing for placing
your Fibs is one of the main problems when
using it.
Fibonacci is an effective method but you must
place it on the swing that makes the most
sense for current market conditions.
The most important aspect when using Fibs
is the presence of a trend.
There are two primary ways to solve the problems
with drawing Fibs on the chart:
1.
Focus on trend and momentum.
2.
Using the logic price swings for placing the
Fibonacci tool.
Please remember this: Fibs do not work well
in consolidations, corrections, ranges and
sideways moves.
2.
Don’t use the Fibonacci retracement tool
on very small price moves or shorter time
frames
Applying Fibonacci retracements over a short
timeframe is ineffective.
The shorter the timeframe, the less reliable
the retracement levels, making it very difficult
for the trader to really pick and choose what
levels can be traded.
Not to mention in the short term, spikes and
false breakouts are very common.
These dynamics can make it especially difficult
to place stops or take profit points as retracements
can create narrow and small confluences.
So try to focus on larger time frames when
you apply FIB levels.
By keeping tabs on the long-term trend, you
can apply Fibonacci retracements in the correct
direction.
Further, if you use the Fibonacci retracement
tool on very small price moves, it may not
provide much insight.
The levels will be so close together that
almost every price level appears important.
3.
Apply Fibonacci retracement levels on the
correct price swings
Using a Fibonacci retracement tool is subjective.
There are multiple price swings during a trading
day, so not everyone will be connecting the
same two points.
The two points you connect may not be the
two points others connect.
Here’s how you correctly apply FIB retracements.
– you determine the dominant trend
– you identify the swing high and swing
low before drawing the Fibonacci lines
– in a bullish trend, draw the Fibonacci
from the swing low to the swing high.
– in a bearish trend, draw the Fibonacci
from the swing high to the swing low.
– you will be drawing the Fibonacci tool
from the wicks of the swing highs and lows
At the very basics, the clearer the swing
low, the clearer the swing high and the clearer
the “trend” between these 2 points, the
more accurate a Fibonacci Retracement will
be.
Also, very important: don’t try to force
FIB levels.
The best and most helpful Fibonacci retracements
are those where you don’t have to look long
on a chart.
4.
Shallow vs Deep Retracements
In trending or impulsive markets, the Fib
levels indicate precise levels where there
is a high chance of the market turning back
in the direction of the trend.
Basically, FIB levels provide areas of interest
to watch on pullbacks.
There are 2 main types of pullbacks using
Fibonacci: shallow and deep retracements.
If you correctly analyze the strength of the
trend, you will have high-probability areas
to take trades
Once a trend has clearly established itself
then you will often see shallow pullbacks
to 23.6, 38.2 and 50% FIB levels, which are
very typical before the trend continues.
So when the trend is strong, pay attention
to these FIB levels.
Price will make a deep pullback when a trend
is not yet clearly established.
In those cases price can make multiple ups
and downs which will test the bottom (in an
uptrend) or the top (in a downtrend) but without
breaking those levels (which would invalidate
the trend).
You will see deep pullbacks to the 61.8, 78.6
and 88.6 Fib levels.
If the price retraces 100% of the last price
wave, that may mean the trend has failed.
5.
The Golden Ratio Retreat Strategy
The 61.8 level is called the Golden ratio.
Here’s how the Golden Ratio Retreat Strategy
works.
In this example, we found this downtrend and
applied the Fibs.
• If the price moves up above the 50% retracement,
but does not close above the 61.8 Golden Ratio,
look for a bearish entry.
• It is OK for the wick of the candle to
break the 61.8 line as long as the price closes
below it.
• As the price bounces from the 61.8 Golden
Ratio, look for a possible reversal move back
down to the 38.2 level.
• If the price breaks the 38.2 level, the
23.6 may be its next hesitation point.
• If that doesn’t hold, expect a possible
100% retracement back to the 0 line.
• These levels are good potential places
to consider scaling out of the trade.
• If the price never gets higher than the
61.8 then you can set your initial stop just
above that line.
• If the price went higher than the 61.8
then you could set a stop above the high of
the candle that broke the level.
• If scaling out of the trade, consider
moving the stops to the next Fib line as the
targets are met.
6.
Combine multiple FIB Retracements to create
confluence
Fibonacci Confluence is essentially combining
multiple Fibonacci levels to find clusters
where these levels align around the same area.
This example reveals an area of confluence
formed by the 50 percent retracement of AC
wave and the 78.6 percent retracement of BC
wave.
In this other example, price found support
at this area of confluence formed by the 50
percent retracement of AC wave and the 78.6
percent retracement of BC wave in this daily
chart.
This is one of my favorite trading strategies
using Fibonacci because it leads to high probability
setups.
7.
Confluence with moving averages
Fibonacci can provide reliable trade setups,
but not without confirmation.
Applying additional technical tools like moving
averages will support the trade opportunity
and increase the likelihood of a good trade.
Fibonacci and moving averages work well together
because both tools are most effective in a
trending environment.
First of all, using moving average will help
you determine if there is a trend.
Second of all, moving averages also act as
dynamic support and resistance in a trend,
which means that a moving average adds confluence
to a Fib level.
For instance, if a 50% Fibonacci retracement
and the 200 EMA align at one spot on the chart,
then this is called a trading confluence.
There is a combination of elements joining
together at one point on the chart.
When a FIB level and a moving average are
confirming a spot on the chart to be of importance,
then the likelihood of price reacting to this
level increases.
Again, this is very effective, because by
combining FIBS with moving averages, you remove
the weaknesses of each tool when used separately.
8.
Confirm Fibonacci levels with Volume
As a trader when you see the price coming
into a Fibonacci support area, the biggest
clue you can look for is the volume, to see
if that support will hold.
Notice how the stock had a number of spikes
higher in volume on the move up, but the pullback
to support at the retracement saw volume decreasing.
This does not mean people are not interested
in the stock, it means that there are fewer
sellers pushing the price lower.
This is where buyers come in and accumulate
shares in anticipation for the rally higher.
High volume after the rejection of a FIB level
represents a very good sign.
9.
Look for divergences at FIB levels using RSI,
MACD or Stochastic
Now, rather than blindly entering into a trade
because it hit a particular retracement ratio,
you need a confirmation signal that the price
is likely to turn.
I prefer adding a momentum oscillator, like
the RSI, Stochastic or MACD, and look for
a divergence signal, forming around FIB levels.
These are leading signals, by the way.
Here we have a downtrend with the FIB levels
added to the chart.
The first level, the 38.2% level was broken
with ease.
However, we can now see that the 50% level
is providing some resistance.
We can confirm the slowing momentum with the
RSI.
The RSI is showing a divergence which is a
bearish signal as well.
Price makes higher highs, but the oscillator
makes lower highs.
This means that momentum is slowing.
And slowing momentum into a resistance level
is a good recipe for a trading opportunity.
In this example we have an up trend, with
the MACD indicator showing a hidden divergence.
Here, when the MACD hidden divergence appeared
on the price chart, the price reached the
38.2 Fib level.
When price tested this Fibonacci retracement
level - this would have been a good level
to enter in the direction of the main trend.
10.
Analyze candlestick formations around FIB
levels
Analyzing price action at Fib levels represents
another effective way to take signals.
In this case, traders wait for a candle stick
pattern to occur at the Fibonacci level instead
of “only” anticipating a price reaction
at the Fib.
In this way, the candle pattern confirms the
response of the market at the Fib level.
Generally speaking, these candlestick patterns
combined with Fibonacci levels tend to work
better on longer-term time frames.
When price reaches a FIB level, you look for
a rejection candlestick that has formed at
or near the level.
The three types that are of most interest
will be the hammer candlestick, which is often
seen after a bearish price move, the shooting
star candlestick, which is often seen after
a bullish price move, and the Engulfing pattern,
which can either be of a bullish or bearish
variety.
These candlestick reversal patterns are quite
powerful and can foretell the end of a retracement
move.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay in touch when we release
new videos.
Until next time.