If you stay, I’ll teach you the best swing
trading strategies that work on any market,
whether it’s Forex, stocks or crypto.
Monthly pivot
The first strategy involves the monthly pivots,
which are the secret weapon of swing trading.
They are based on the previous month's
high, low, and close, and will give you
a rough idea of where the market might find
support & resistance in the coming weeks.
Monthly pivots are like the big boss of
support and resistance levels. They carry
a lot more weight than your average daily pivot.
That’s because they represent a whole month's
worth of price action, not
just a snapshot in time.
This levels acts as a magnet, attracting
the price on higher time frames.
The big market players are watching these levels,
and when the price interacts with a monthly pivot,
it can trigger some serious fireworks.
The more time the price spends above the pivot,
the more reliable it becomes as a support level.
And, the more time the price spends below
the pivot, the more reliable it
becomes as a resistance level.
The strategy here is to look for confluences
between the monthly pivot and supply/demand areas.
It doesn't happen every day, but when it
does, it can be a sign of something special!
Let's say you're looking at a chart and you
notice that the price is approaching a key
demand area that lines up with a monthly pivot.
That's a confluence perfect for a swing trade.
If the price bounces off that area, it could
be the start of a beautiful uptrend that you
can ride for weeks or even months.
On the flip side, if you see the
price approaching a major supply area
that coincides with the monthly pivot,
it could be a sign that the buyers
are about to run out of steam.
If the price gets rejected at that level, it might
be time to start hunting for short opportunities.
Of course, these confluences between
monthly pivots and supply/demand areas
aren't the only thing you should be looking for.
You'll also want to keep an eye on candlestick
patterns, like pin bars and engulfing bars.
When you find a candlestick with a long wick,
rejecting the monthly pivot,
that’s a really good signal.
Now, what if the price blows right
through the monthly pivot. It will happen,
because no level is unbreakable, and
sometimes the market will just keep
moving with momentum, even on higher time frames.
Even if the price does break through the monthly
pivot, it can still give you valuable information
about the strength and direction of the trend.
For example, if the price breaks above
the monthly pivot, it could be a sign
that the buyers are in control and that
the trend has momentum to continue.
The pivot that once acted as
resistance now becomes a new support,
helping the price to reach new heights!
On the other hand, if the price breaks below the
monthly pivot and starts to accelerate, it might
be time to start looking for short opportunities.
The sellers have taken control of the market,
and they'll do everything in their power to
keep the price from rising back above the pivot.
Now the pivot has become a resistance, pushing the
price down when it tries to break through.
3 BB
The second swing trading strategy
involves using Bollinger Bands indicator.
It might look a bit strange at first, because
you're going to use three Bollinger Bands.
First add Bollinger Band with a Period
of 50 and a Standard Deviation of 1.
Then add the Second Bollinger Band with a
Period of 50 and a Standard Deviation of 2.
The Third Bollinger Band will have a Period
of 50 and a Standard Deviation of 3.
With this setup, the trend is pretty clear to see.
Let’s consider an uptrend, with different stages.
When price is between the middle line, the 50 E
MA, and the first band, that's a weak uptrend.
In this area, there's no strong momentum.
Price is likely to bounce around in a range
and might even dip below the middle line.
You can buy in this area, but only if you
have other factors lining up.
When price is between the first
and second Bollinger Bands above the
50 E MA, that's a strong uptrend.
There's a better chance that
price will keep going up.
As long as candles keep closing in this buy
zone, the odds are in favor of holding current
long positions or even opening new ones.
When price is between the second and third
Bollinger Bands, above the middle
line, that's a very strong uptrend.
Price is stretched and I would avoid
buying if price goes outside the bands.
Looking for overlaps of major support and
resistance levels with Bollinger Bands is
a great way to find swing trading setups.
These confluence areas tend to attract
more buyers or sellers, leading to
a reversal or a trend continuation.
With this confluence, you're basically
finding pullbacks in a strong trend.
When a market is in an uptrend (meaning price is
above the middle Bollinger Band) and you find a
confluence between a recent support or resistance
level and one of the standard deviation bands,
you can trade a bounce off that area.
On the flip side, when price is in a downtrend
(below the middle band) and a recent support or
resistance lines up with one of the lower bands,
a decent pullback trade might be setting up.
Looking at this chart, it's obvious how much price
respects the bands. Even when price was below the
middle band, it found support at the lower bands.
And here, price broke above the middle band and
also broke this resistance level, which could
potentially now act as support.
Here's our value area.
The first band above the middle line and
this level are lining up at the same point.
This is a solid trend continuation opportunity.
Finding profit targets is very easy. You just
aim for the next bands. The first
take profit is at the second band,
and the next target is the last band.
As a tip, always expect momentum to slow
down when price reaches the next set of
bands. That’s why it’s best to take some
of your profits at these levels.
21 EMA channel at round numbers
The third swing trading strategy involves
taking advantage of round numbers. And we’ll
confirm the signals using 2 moving averages.
First, you plot two 50-period Exponential Moving
Averages on your chart - one applied to the
high price and the other to the low price.
These lines will act like dynamic
support and resistance levels.
The beauty of this channel lies in its simplicity.
When the price is trading above the channel, it's
a bullish signal, suggesting that the trend is up,
and it's time to look for buying opportunities.
When the price is below the channel, it's a
bearish signal, indicating that the trend is
down and it's time to consider selling.
When you combine this channel with the
psychological significance of round numbers,
you've got a really good swing trading strategy.
Round numbers are those big, juicy price
levels that end in double or triple zeros.
These levels hold a special place in the minds of
traders, often acting as key areas of interest.
Round numbers are not just some arbitrary figures
on a chart. They are psychological anchors and
catalysts for market movements.
There's a deep psychological
aspect to round numbers that makes them so
powerful. We are naturally drawn to whole numbers,
and we tend to assign more significance to them.
When the price approaches a round number,
it's like a magnet, drawing in all sorts of
attention and potential trading activity.
Here’s how you find signals.
First, you look at the moving
average channel to determine whether the
market is in an uptrend or a downtrend.
Then you locate the closest round numbers
that the price is approaching. This will
be your key levels to watch.
If the price is in an uptrend,
supported by the moving averages, and
approaching a round number from below,
you look to buy a breakout ABOVE the level.
If the price is in a downtrend and approaching
a round number from above, you look to sell
a breakout BELOW the psychological level.
This channel acts a as a trampoline. When
the price breaks it and then returns to hit
the upper or lower EMA, it's like a test bounce.
If the channel holds and the price bounces off it,
it's a confirmation that the
channel is indeed valid.
This first bounce is crucial because
it validates the channel as a
significant level of support or resistance.
When you have an initial bounce, be ready to
trade the next bounces, near round numbers.
So very important: an initial rejection of
the channel is a good sign that the
channel is holding firm and that the
price is likely to respect it in the future.
This second or third bounce is like a green light,
signaling that it's time to pay attention
and prepare for a potential trade.
Here another crucial tip. When the
price is caught inside the channel
for more than three candles, and is located
near a round number, avoid taking a trade.
In this situation, the market is experiencing
consolidation. It's a time of uncertainty,
where the price is searching for
direction, inside the 2 EMAs.
Trying to trade during this period
is like trying to predict the outcome
of a coin toss, it's like a gamble.
So, when the price is trapped inside
the channel for more than three candles, simply
stay on the sidelines and wait for clarity.
You want to see an immediate reaction around
the channel, a quick rejection of the area,
like in this example.
Now, if you want to
learn other trading techniques, you
definitely must watch our next videos.