Let me share my biggest struggles when I first
started trading: I had very little self-control
and I was unable to resist the temptation
to over-trade and over-leverage.
If you’re in your first years, you’re
probably facing the same issues.
So today I want to reveal the several tweaks
I’ve made to save my trading.
So, like, subscribe, and stick around for
the full video.
“High" tends to indicate even higher and
"low" usually means even lower
There is a special appeal to trade against
the trend or against a big momentum price
move.
The main reason is the illusion of an "attractive"
price.
A market that has been going down for many
days, by definition is going to have a relatively
"low" price.
And you’re tempted to buy it, at this low
price.
The danger of these seemingly attractive prices
is an important law of trading: continuation
is more likely than change.
From my experience and many losing trades,
"high" tends to indicate even higher and "low"
usually means even lower.
This was one of my biggest mistakes: I took
far too many trades against a powerful price
move.
I haven’t kept records from the beginning,
but I’ve definitively lost far more money
on these trades than I’ve made.
And it’s probably true for you.
But, even more damaging than the amount lost
against these momentum moves were the profits
not realized, because I’ve missed several
good trades with-the-trend.
Trading against the trend will misdirect your
focus, and as a result you’ll miss many
entry points for profitable trades in the
direction of the main trend.
Against-the-trend trading has a tendency to
be addictive.
And this will bring other problems.
When a trade against-the-trend goes against
you, you’ll initally say: I was a little
"early" with my timing.
And, there is a strong temptation to try again
and buy or sell more at what now has become
an even "more attractive" price.
So never add to a loser if it is against the
trend.
My mentor had a funny saying: if you think
you reached the bottom of the ocean, and you
can’t go lower, remember that you can always
dig the ground.
The same with trading.
If you think the market reached an absolute
high and it can’t go any higher, you’ll
have a big surprise.
Your time span and your level of patience
When you trade, you need to know what the
"time span" you will most often act upon.
If you are a short-term trader and find it
difficult or impossible to hold positions
for several days and instead get in and out
frequently, then you have to adjust your trading
style accordingly.
If you are swing trader and hold trades for
longer periods, regardless of short-term price
movement, then you need to use a trading strategy
to capitalize on these tendencies.
You need to know your patience level.
If you know you are patient, then you’ll
be able to endure the inevitable fluctuations
in your swing trades.
If you know you are impatient, you’ll end
up trading shorter timeframes.
The shorter the timeframe you decide to trade,
the more intense concentration you will need
to sustain.
So, if we consider once again trading against
the trend, the only possible way to succeed
is to be a short-term trader, as well as be
very selective (I mean only entering when
momentum is clearly in your favor).
And one of the worst trading styles is to
be a long-term swing trader who trades against
strong trends.
This combination will inevitably result in
consistent, big losses.
So know your time span and your level of patience.
Become a market specialist
The first decision to make when designing
your strategy is to decide which currency
pairs, cryptocurrencies or stocks you will
be trading, because, I said it many times
before, not all strategies will work on every
market.
Trading price action on Tesla is very different
compared to Bitcoin’s price action.
If you’re in your first years, it’s better
to become a market specialist.
And as a specialist, you will concentrate
on one market.
I have a friend which trades only one market,
GBPUSD.
I know him for 10 years, and he never traded
anything else.
It sounds radical, and but this works for
him, trading just one currency pair.
This comes with the understanding of the market,
knowing the factors that affect the market,
and, of course, a solid strategy for different
phases of the market.
When you are focusing on one market, you’ll
also learn the correlations associated with
that market, when the market is reacting in
an unusual way, when is trending or not.
If it’s too radical for you, monitoring
just one market, have a maximum of 3 markets
and make them your focus.
If you have a hard time trading, try narrowing
down.
It might help you.
Weekly maximum drawdown – best tool to avoid
overtrading
Do you have a weekly maximum drawdown?
You should!
This is the amount you are willing to lose
over a period of time.
An easy way to measure the maximum drawdown
is to look at it during one trading week.
You may risk 1 percent of your account on
each trade.
If you set your weekly maximum drawdown to
5 percent, then you can withstand five losing
trades in a row.
After five losing trades, you have hit your
maximum drawdown for the week.
This is when you stop trading for that week
because you reached your maximum drawdown.
This is the best way to avoid over trading,
revenge trading and over leveraging.
Now, how you decide to apply the maximum drawdown
rule may depend on the timeframe you decide
to trade.
If you are a scalper or an active day trader,
you may need a maximum drawdown amount for
one day.
That maximum drawdown will affect how many
trades you’ll be able to take at any given
time.
For example, you may decide to have a maximum
drawdown of 5 percent for each trading week.
But If you have six daily signals on the first
trading day of the week, and you risk 1 percent
on each trade, you could have a drawdown of
6 percent in your first day!
So to avoid reaching your maximum weekly drawdown
on your first day, you should reduce your
risk.
Instead of risking 1 percent per trade, you
risk 0.5 percent per trade, or even lower.
Find the balance between anticipation and
confirmation
A popular concept in trading is to wait for
confirmation before entering a trade.
This means you have a signal, for example,
a price action pattern, and you wait for the
markets to confirm that pattern before you
enter.
The idea, of course, is to filter out bad
trades and to gain confidence before entering
the trade.
When planning a trade, there are two basic
approaches.
You can anticipate a move or you can wait
for confirmation.
Both methods have their pros and cons.
Anticipation can provide better entries with
less certainty.
Waiting for confirmation provides higher certainty
at the expense of a later entry.
Let’s say you’re monitoring this specific
support level.
Price is aggressively moving towards it and
closed in this area with a big momentum red
candle.
You wanted to buy here, you patiently waited
for price to reach this area.
But with this big red candle, do you enter?
The risk to buy into a support level while
the market is in free fall is risky.
But that's precisely why these trades offer
you great profit potential.
You anticipated the move and you were rewarded
for the risk you took.
The conservative traders would have waited
for a confirmation.
They would have entered after a rejection
candle.
But, they already missed the initial price
move.
That move may be over …and those who took
the risk and bought at the support level are
now potentially taking their profits.
The point to consider is that whenever you
wait for confirmation you give up potential
profits.
And there’s the other side of the coin,
where price broke that support level with
ease, and all traders anticipating a bounce
are now at a loss, while the conservative
traders are the winners in this situation.
Your job here is to find a good compromise
between getting in too early due to a signal
coming from market noise and getting in too
late due to a signal that misses most of the
opportunity.
It’s a hard task, I know, and it will take
you some time to find the balance.
But when you’ll find it, trading will become
a lot easier.
A smaller stop loss doesn’t mean a smaller
risk
You have a tool on your side to assist you
in giving trades the time they require to
turn into winners.
That tool is stop loss placement and more
specifically, using wider stop losses.
Many traders are naturally tempted to place
a small stop loss on their trades.
They think that a smaller stop loss distance
means a smaller risk, and that wider stop
losses means they are risking more.
But, it is obvious that it is the contract
size (or number of lots) that determines the
risk per trade, not the stop loss distance.
The stop loss distance is nowhere near as
important as the position size you are trading.
The position size determines how much MONEY
is risked per trade, not the stop loss distance.
The fact is many traders don’t take into
account market noise.
Market noise is simply the price data that
distorts the picture of the current trend.
This includes small corrections and intraday
volatility.
You say you’re minimizing risk and use a
small stop loss, but you don’t take into
account random price spikes that may occur.
Giving a trade even another 30 pips for example,
can significantly improve the chances of that
trade flipping from a loser to a winner.
Ask yourself, what’s better: Placing 10
trades with small stops and losing on most
of them or placing 2 trades with wide stops,
winning big on one and taking a loss on the
other?
The second strategy is the one you should
follow.
Remember, wider stops will keep you in the
game longer and improve your chances over
a series of trades.
Give the market the time to move in your favor
Trades do not often turn out exactly as we
want them to.
This affects our emotions because, we are
wired to want instant results.
There’s a difference between what we expect
from a trade and what a trade actually gives
us.
A common mistake is to expect some unrealistically
big profit on nearly every trade you take.
You are a day trader, but you place profit
targets that are 200 pips away from your entry.
And then when this target doesn’t get hit,
you experience emotional pain and distress.
And here’s another bad mindset.
You often have unrealistic expectations of
how long a trade will take to play out.
I’m also guilty of this.
I want every trade I enter to immediately
go into profit territory.
I’m mostly a swing trader now, and I would
love a 100 pip move in my favor in my first
day, but if the average daily range is only
60 pips, what would be unrealistic.
A trade can sometimes take several hours or
days to play out, depending on your time frame,
and you need to keep this in mind because
you will never make money if you don’t give
the market the time to move in your favor.
Next time you place a trade, you should be
prepared to see it out and let it run for
days or weeks if it needs to.
If you’re a swing trader, don’t get scared
by an intra-day fluctuations against your
position and don’t exit too early, as you
may miss out on a potentially strong trend
move.
It’s also very important that you understand
that each day and each week the market can
only move so far, so don’t have unrealistic
expectations of how far your trade might move
in a certain period of time.
Now, these are only a part of the measures
I took to improve my trading.
If you want to learn other tips and tricks
to be ahead of the game, make sure you watch
this video.
And also check out our academy program, if
you want to further level up your trading.
Until next time.