when a breakout in the market occurs and
the market moves in the direction of the
break commonly you'll see the market
returns to the point of the breakout
then proceed to go in the direction of
the breakout
trading the retest of a breakout point
is not a new strategy and is quite a
popular method in the trading community
but i bet you are trading retests in the
wrong way because the rules provided to
you by most trading books and websites
are not aligned with how the smart money
operate in the financial markets
today i'll show you how to trade retests
of breakouts properly we'll begin by
looking at the actual reason why a
retest occurs after a breakout i'll show
you how to trade retests using price
action and i'll reveal to you the secret
ingredient in order to trade the retests
effectively
so if you could like subscribe the
channel and stick around for the full
video
a retest at a breakout level means the
market breaks a high or a low returns to
the breakout point and moves back in the
direction of which the breakout occurred
this market action is down to the smart
money needing to fill more buy or sell
orders in the market before the market
breaks out from a high or a low
there are many breakout traders that
have pending orders placed at the levels
ready to profit from the breakout
when the breakout finally comes their
orders are filled
breakout traders spend a little time in
profit on their trades as typically the
market will continue in the direction of
the break for a small amount of time
the turning point comes when smart money
begins to take profits off their own
trades because very important they
entered early way before we retail
traders saw the actual breakout
this profit taking is what will cause
the market to move back to the breakout
point the retest
if you are the breakout trader you will
watch your profits steadily decrease as
the market gets closer and closer to the
breakout point where you had your trade
placed
so seeing your profit gets smaller and
smaller you will most likely get scared
of potentially coming out of the trade
with no profit at all
so you will close your trade while there
is still a small amount of profit left
different traders will decide to close
their trades at different times the
closer the market gets to the breakout
point the higher the number of breakout
traders will be closing their trades
and when the breakout traders close
their trades opposite orders will be put
into the market which the smart money
will use to get more buy or sell
positions placed in the market
[Music]
start thinking at retests as the
market's way of resetting itself or
flushing out the weak positions
the term weak position refers to any
group of traders usually retail who are
not comfortable holding a position
through the increased volatility for the
opportunity to make larger gains these
are usually the traders who are very
risk averse
and therefore get stopped out
prematurely before a larger move ever
gets going
of course there are also those who trade
the lower time frames and therefore
aren't looking for the larger
opportunity
these traders are happy to take their
profits early and often
this area on the chart is the point
where breakout traders will have pending
orders to sell placed in anticipation of
the market breaking out
you can see how the market continues to
advance lower after the breakout has
took place
smart money begins their profit taking
after the breakout occurs
and the market begins to rise back to
the breakout point
causing a re-test
now beside breakout traders there are
also reactive traders in the market who
would have placed sale trades after the
candle which caused the breakout
these traders will also add a
significant number of orders in the
market which the banks will use to fill
more orders when their profit
pushes the market higher
[Music]
most traders when looking to trade the
retest will mark the point where a
breakout has occurred using horizontal
lines
and this is one of the reasons why you
fail at trading re-tests
a far better way of marking the points
is using areas
by marking the breakout point as an area
instead of a line you give yourself the
benefit of not having to guess the
breakout point
if there are several highs for example
and you mark the level using a line
then you won't be able to know which
highs the market is going to return to
by having a zone you can cover multiple
highs and include them in your total
risk when trading the retest
in this example you can see there are
two highs which breakout traders could
have used to enter long trades
in real time you wouldn't know which one
of these highs the market is going to
retest
if you mark an area including both highs
then you are able to remove some
discretion from your decision making
process
and also give yourself a point where you
know the trait is likely to be wrong
when trading retests of breakout it all
comes down to judgment experience and
the market or the instrument because
very important
each will have its own unique price
behavior and risk profile also there
needs to be a clearly visible gap in
terms of the closing price of the candle
which finally breaches the support or
resistance level
this is the first signal that the
breakout is in progress the second is of
course volume
as we can see in this example the
initial move higher up and through the
resistance level has to be followed by
strong and rising volume
it takes effort for the market to move
away the same applies here and you
should see this move reflected in the
associated volume of the next few bars
if you don't see this then you know it's
either a trap said by the smart money or
there is simply no interest from market
participants to take the market higher
at this stage
if it's a valid move then the volumes on
the initial break will be well above
average and rising
at this stage you want to see the market
pull back to test the formal resistance
level but very important this should be
followed with low or decreasing volume
since we are now developing a bullish
trend higher and expect to see a rising
market with rising volume
so very important you want to see strong
and rising volume on the breakout
and low volume on the pullback
then at the retest level you want to see
another increase in volume
[Music]
exactly the same principles apply when
the breakout is into a bearish move
once again it makes no difference
whether this is a continuation of a
bearish trend or a reversal from bullish
to bearish the only difference is that
this time we are breaking through the
support of price congestion
as before this breakout should be clean
and well developed and followed by a
well above average volume to reflect the
effort required to break away
again we want to see the market move
back higher to test the previous support
area
but this should happen on low volume
and as the market pulls away rising
volume should reflect the new downwards
move
remember falling markets should also see
rising volume reflecting a genuine move
lower
[Music]
it isn't enough to simply see the market
touch a broken level as a new support or
resistance
and if you think about it that doesn't
actually qualify as a retest
when the market revisits a level after
breaking it we want to see some sort of
confirmation that the previous support
level turned into resistance and vice
versa a previous resistance level turned
into support
my preferred method to enter into traits
at the retest of a breakout level is by
using price action more specifically
using candlestick patterns such as
engulfing candles or pin bars
[Music]
i trade on higher time frames mostly on
hourly 4-hour and the daily charts
when i see a market breaking a support i
like to watch the breakout on a lower
time frame to see if there are any
candlestick patterns i can use as an
entry into the trade
here we have the breakout area here we
can see when the market reached the area
a bearish engulfing candle formed
volume confirmed the move high volume on
the breakout
and low volume during the pullback
seeing the engulfing candle at the
retest with volume confirmation
you could have entered into a short
trade with your stop above the high of
the breakout zone
now you could also decide to put your
stop above the high of the engulfing bar
but be careful
if you use the signal candle to place
your stops you'll tend to find you'll
unnecessarily lose money because if the
market breaks the high of the engulfing
bar and you take the loss and then the
market moves deeper into the zone before
reversing again
then you have basically taking a loss
which could have been avoided if you
would just put your stop at the high of
the zone in the first place
[Music]
the pinbar is one of the most powerful
and reliable price action trading
signals during re-tests and the signal i
rely the most in my trading
a pin bar is a price action pattern
which signals that the reversal may be
about to take place in the price action
trading pinbar signals with support and
resistance and volume confirmation is
perhaps one of the most effective ways
to trade
the very best pin bars stick out at the
right test level
the bigger the rejection and the bigger
the pin bar the more powerful the signal
a high probability pin bar at the right
test level needs to have the wick
sticking out from all other candles and
above average volume to confirm an
active participation in the retest
whether you are trading a key horizontal
level a wedge pattern or a channel it's
important to always wait for a re-test
of the broken level
this involves waiting for the re-test
analyzing the volume during the breakout
and during the pullback period
as well as confirming price action
before putting any capital at risk
you will be tempted to enter right after
the breakout and many times you won't
get a chance of a re-test
and you have to accept that you will
miss many moves by being somewhat
conservative
but remember by waiting for a re-test
you are essentially waiting for any weak
positions to exit the market before
placing a position
this is a stronger foundation from which
you buy or sell which leads to a higher
probability of a successful outcome
[Music]
one of my own rules is that the first
retest is the most important one
what i mean is that if you have a zone
marked on your charts and you see the
market return to the breakout zone and
proceed to move back in the direction of
the breakout i consider this first
retest as having the highest probability
of succeeding
one of the primary concepts of order
flow analysis is the idea that when a
technical level has been hit once its
significance in the market decreases
dramatically and the chances of the
market reacting to the level in the same
way again is low
you may not agree with this but here's
how i view the situation
in a breakout retail scenario if the
price returns to the breakout zone once
again after already being touched the
breakout traders went long on the
breakout will not be in their trades
anymore
so a second reaction at the breakout
level has a lower chance of succeeding
less stops are being hunted less orders
are being put on the market
you can see here the breakout area which
turns the market on the first retest
but on the second touch the market
breaks the area easily and returns to a
lower technical level
[Music]
if you found value and learned something
new leave us a like this way we'll know
if you'd like to see more videos like
this one and check out our academy
program if you want to further level up
your trading
until next time