The human behavior in relation to money is
always dominated by fear; greed, and hope.
Well, candlestick analysis will help you to
understand these changing psychological factors
by showing you how buyers and
sellers interact with each other’s.
Candlesticks are basically a visual
representation of what is going on in the market.
By looking at a candlestick, you can get
valuable information about the open, high,
low and the close of price, which will
give you an idea about the price movement.
In today’s video, you will discover how to
recognize the most important candlestick patterns,
the psychology behind their formation, and what
do they indicate when they form in the market.
First pattern is the engulfing candlestick.
This candlestick formation consists of two bodies,
the first body being smaller than the second
one, in other words, the second body engulfs
the previous one. Here we can have a bearish
engulfing bar and a bullish engulfing bar.
In case of a bearish engulfing bar,
this pattern tells us that sellers
are in control of the market.
When this pattern occurs at the end of an uptrend,
this indicates that buyers are engulfed by sellers
which signals a potential trend reversal.
Why is that? Because buyers are losing
control of the market, and sellers are
trying to push the market to go down.
The bullish engulfing bar pattern tells us that
the market is no longer under control of sellers,
and buyers are gaining strength.
When a bullish engulfing candle
forms in the context of an uptrend,
it indicates a continuation signal.
When a bullish engulfing candle forms at the end
of a downtrend, it signals a potential reversal.
This example shows clearly how the market
changes direction after the formation of a
bullish engulfing pattern. The smaller
body that represents the selling power
was covered by the second body
that represents the buying power.
Very important: don’t try to trade the
market using this price action setup alone,
because you will need other factors of confluence
to decide whether the pattern is worth trading or
not. What I want you to do for now is to
get the skill of identifying bearish and
bullish engulfing bar on your charts. This
is the most important step for the moment.
Second pattern is the Doji Candlestick pattern.
Doji is one of the most important Japanese
candlestick patterns, when this candlestick
forms, it tells us that the market opens
and closes at the same price which means that
there is indecision between buyers and sellers,
there is no one in control of the market.
The opening price is the same as the closing
price, this signal means that the market
didn’t decide which direction will take.
A doji could anticipate a reversal, or
it can be a sign of consolidation.
This example shows how the
market changed direction
after the formation of the Doji candlestick.
The market was trending up, meaning that buyers
had more strength. The formation of the Doji
candlestick indicates that buyers are unable
to keep price higher, and sellers push prices
back to the opening price. This is an indication
that a trend reversal is might be on the cards.
However, always remember that a Doji indicates
indecision in the market, and you will
often find it during periods of resting
after big moves higher or lower.
Third pattern is the morning star.
The morning star pattern is considered
as a bullish reversal pattern,
it often occurs at the bottom of a downtrend
and it consists of three candlesticks:
-The first candlestick is bearish which
indicates that sellers are still in charge.
-The second candle is a small one which
represents that sellers are in control,
but they don’t push the market much lower,
and this candle can be bullish or bearish.
-The third candle is a bullish candlestick
that gapped up on the open and closed above the
midpoint of the candle, and this candlestick
holds a significant trend reversal signal.
The morning star pattern shows us how buyers
took control of the market from sellers.
When this pattern occurs at the bottom
of downtrend near a support level,
it signals a potential trend reversal.
Here, the pattern occurred during an obvious
bearish trend. The first candle confirmed
the seller’s domination, and the second
one produces indecision in the market.
Basically, the second candle indicated that
sellers were struggling to push the market lower.
The third bullish candle indicates
that buyers took control from sellers,
and the market is likely to move upward.
Next is the evening star pattern
The evening star pattern is considered
as a bearish reversal pattern that
usually occurs at the top of an uptrend.
The pattern also consists of three candlesticks:
-The first candle is a bullish candle
-The second candle is a small candlestick,
it can be bullish or bearish
-The third candle is a large bearish candle.
In general, the evening star pattern is the
bearish version of the morning star pattern.
Here, the market was trending up, the first candle
in the pattern indicating a trend continuation.
The second one is a short candle indicating
price consolidation and indecision.
In other words, the trend that created the first
long bullish candlestick is losing momentum.
The final candlestick moving lower than
the previous candlestick indicates a
potential beginning of a new down move.
Another important candlestick
formation is the hammer.
The Hammer candlestick is created when the
open high and close are roughly the same price;
it is also characterized by a long lower shadow
that indicates a bullish rejection from buyers
and their intention to push the market higher.
The hammer is a reversal candlestick pattern
when it occurs at the bottom of a downtrend.
This candle forms when sellers push
the market lower after the open,
but they get rejected by buyers so the market
closes higher than the lowest price.
Here the market was trending down,
and the formation of the hammer
represented a significant reversal pattern.
The long shadow represents the high buying
pressure from this point. Sellers were trying
to push the market lower, but at that level,
the buying pressure was more
powerful than the selling pressure
which resulted in a price reversal.
The most important to understand is
the psychology behind the formation of this
pattern. If you can understand how and why
it was created, you will be able to anticipate
the market direction with a higher accuracy.
The shooting star is another important
reversal candlestick pattern.
The shooting formation is
formed when the open low,
and close are roughly the same price. This
candle is characterized by a small body
and a long upper shadow. It’s basically
the bearish version of the hammer.
Very important: the shadow of the shooting star
should be twice the length of the real body.
This example shows a perfect shooting star with
a real small body and an upper long shadow.
When this pattern occurs in an uptrend;
it indicates a bearish reversal signal.
The psychology behind the formation
of this pattern is that buyers tried
to push the market higher, but they
got rejected by the selling pressure.
When this candlestick forms
near a key resistance level,
it should be taken as a high probability setup.
Another important formation is the inside bar.
The inside bar is a two bar candlestick
pattern, which indicates price consolidation.
In order to confirm this pattern you need to see
a candle on the chart, which is fully contained
within the previous bar. In this manner, the
inside bar candle should have a higher low
and a lower high than the previous candle.
This candlestick is considered a bearish
reversal signal when it occurs at the top of
an uptrend, and it is a bullish signal when
it occurs at the bottom of a downtrend.
In this example, you can see how the trend
direction changes after the inside bar formation.
The bullish inside bar pattern occurred at the
bottom of a downtrend. Here, sellers were pushing
the market lower, price starts consolidating,
and this indicates that the selling power
is no longer in control of the market.
The bearish inside bar is the opposite
of the bullish one, this one occurring
at the top of an uptrend indicating that
buyer’s domination is losing strength
and the beginning of a downtrend is possible.
For me, since the inside candle has a lower high
and a higher low than the previous candlestick
on the chart, this indicates consolidation. Bulls
cannot manage to create a higher high and at the
same time the bears fail to create a lower low.
As such, there is not sufficient buying or selling
pressure to break the previous bar’s high or low.
When this candlestick pattern happens during
an uptrend or a downtrend, it’s probably
better to see it as a continuation pattern which
offers a good opportunity to join the trend.
Tweezer top or bottom is another useful pattern.
Tweezers are reversal candlestick patterns that
signal a potential change in the price direction.
The tweezer bottom candlestick pattern is a
bullish reversal pattern that can be spotted
at the bottom of a downtrend. It consists of
two candles, where the first candle is in line
with the bearish trend, while the second candle
reflects more bullish market sentiment as the
price moves higher, in the opposite direction.
If this price action happens near a key support
level, it indicates that a bullish
reversal is likely to happen.
The tweezer top candlestick pattern is of the same
structure as the tweezer bottom, except for the
fact that it happens at the end of an uptrend, and
therefore, it is a bearish reversal pattern. The
first candle is bullish, and it continues in the
same direction, while the second bearish candle
indicates that the trend may be changing soon.
The tweezers top occurs when buyers push the
price higher, this gave us the impression
that the market is still going up, but sellers
surprised buyers by pushing the market lower
and close down the open of the bullish candle.
These 2 patterns signal price reversals
and we can trade them more efficient
if we can combine them with other technical tools.
Both the bottom and top tweezers are only valid
when they occur during uptrends and downtrends.
Their appearance during choppy trading conditions
is practically meaningless, and it signals the
market indecision to move in either direction.
Candlesticks are flexible, but they shouldn’t
be used alone in your analysis. You don’t open
a buy position every time you spot a bullish
engulfing candle and you don’t short the market
every time you see a shooting star. Candlestick
patterns are best used in combination with support
and resistance, trend lines, and other technical
tools such as the moving averages or pivot points.
Also, the time frame is very important. But we’ll
discuss about these concepts in future videos.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like to show your support, subscribe
to our channel and hit the bell icon to be in
touch when we upload new videos. Until next time.