If you are not using AI in your trades,
you risk falling behind while others
find their edge. AI is leaving old
methods in the past, and only traders
who adapt will win. So, copy my
blueprint and catch up before you are
left behind.
Chart analysis is where you see the
power of AI right away. So, start with a
raw price chart and take a screenshot.
Then simply upload that image to your AI
tool. Use a simple prompt like, "Show me
the key levels, trend structure, and
tell me where I should consider trades."
Then see if the AI analysis makes sense
to you. In this case, the AI spots the
main trend first, a clear downtrend from
the left side, making lower highs and
lower lows until that sharp spike near
184.5 level. The AI marked this as a
major demand zone. This isn't just
another bounce. This is where big money
stepped in hard, creating a liquidity
grab before pushing price higher. If
price returns here, the AI suggests
watching for long trades, but only after
seeing real buying pressure. The AI then
identified resistance around 189 level.
It's where sellers consistently showed
up. The AI flagged this as a key supply
zone. If you're thinking about shorts,
this is where you watch for rejection
signals.
Here's where AI gets smart about trade
location. That messy, choppy area
between 186 and 188 was marked as a no
trade zone. Small candles, overlapping
moves, no clear direction. This is where
traders lose money fighting noise. The
AI advised to skip these areas and wait
for price to hit the real levels where
big players fight. The AI also reads the
trend shift. After that spike from 184.5
level, price stops making new lows. The
trend structure changes from straight
down to sideways. This tells you to
adapt. No more blind selling. The market
is ranging now. For trading bias, the AI
showed the early trend was bearish, but
now we are neutral. For a beginner, this
is power at your fingertips. Instead of
guessing at levels or drawing random
lines, you feed the chart to AI. It
finds the zones where real money moves,
where trends change, where you should
trade, and where you should stay out.
The big edge comes from speed and
clarity. You don't spend hours
analyzing. You grab your screenshot, ask
AI, and get a clear map. Key levels
marked, trend structure defined,
dangerous zones identified, and now you
have a plan. You know exactly where to
watch for setups and where to avoid the
noise. AI can analyze different time
frames and combine insights into a
single recommendation. This is one of
the most common problems of traders.
It's when you look at the hourly chart
and see a strong uptrend. Then you drop
down to a 5-minute chart and see a messy
sideways chop. That's the reality of
multiple time frames. Each time frame
tells a different part of the story.
This is where AI helps. Again, you feed
it the daily chart, the 4hour chart, or
any other intervals you like. and AI
scans each time frame, identifies the
main trend, the key levels, and then
combines them into a single
recommendation.
So, let's try this. Let's take another
screenshot with the 4hour and 30 minute
and 5 minute charts of pound yen, upload
it to the AI, and say, "Give me a
complete analysis across all time
frames." Then simply watch how AI
connects the dots that many traders
miss. So the AI starts with the 4hour
chart, the biggest time frame. It spots
a strong uptrend with higher highs and
higher lows. The recent candles are big
and green showing buyers in control. No
reversal signs yet. This is pure bullish
momentum on the larger scale. Moving to
the 30inut chart, AI sees price
stairstepping up. After some sideways
chop, buyers took charge and started
making steady progress. Each push higher
leads to a small pause, then another
push up. The AI notes price might be
getting overextended here as it's moved
up a lot without much rest. On the
5-minut chart, the smallest time frame
AI confirms the uptrend but adds a
warning. While price is climbing, these
small time frames can see quick
pullbacks even in strong trends. The
most recent move shows a sharp rally,
possibly after breaking out of a tight
range. Then the AI combined all three
time frames into one clear picture. All
charts point up. The momentum is strong
across the board with no major reversal
signals. But on those smaller charts,
price looks like it needs a breather. So
AI suggests waiting for small dips to
buy rather than chasing the highs. For
actual trading, the AI mapped out a
simple plan. You wait for a pullback on
the 5-minut or 30inut chart. The AI also
spots danger zones. Don't try selling
just because price has gone up a lot.
When all time frames align like this,
fighting the trend usually ends badly.
Instead, he advised to use those small
pullbacks as chances to join the
uptrend. This is how AI transforms
multi-time frame analysis. No more
confusion.
Now, if you're like me, you probably
have dozens of ideas for a special
indicator, but you're not a coder. This
is when you call on AI. It can help
write code for your own custom
indicators. You can describe what you
want and AI can generate the code for
you. So, I was thinking about creating
an indicator focusing on volume spikes,
something that could spot what the big
money players are doing. You see,
regular indicators miss this. But I had
an idea for something that could catch
these major players in action. So, I
asked AI to create me an indicator that
spots volume spikes above average
levels. I wanted to make it show when
big players step in. I've asked it to
compare current volume to a moving
average of volume and to color the bar
differently when it exceeds a certain
threshold. After you get your code, you
open your trading view chart and look
down at the bottom of your screen for
the pine editor button. Now look for the
new button and click it. Then choose
indicator from the drop-own menu that
appears. This creates a fresh pine
script file for us to work with. You'll
probably see some template code in
there. So you just delete all of that.
Then simply paste the code. After saving
it, look for the add to chart button and
click it. This is where you'll see if
everything works properly. If all goes
well, you'll see your indicator appear
on your chart right away. If you see any
error messages pop up, don't worry.
That's totally normal when coding. Just
grab a screenshot of the error or copy
the error message text and simply ask
the AI to fix any issues. Now, when we
look at this British pound futures
chart, we see that this indicator works
beautifully. The volume spikes often
come right before major moves. That's
because volume reveals supply and demand
imbalances, something most technical
indicators completely miss. The real
power shows up in the price action after
the signals. Notice how some uptrends
started right after those volume spikes.
That's not random. It's showing you
exactly what professional floor traders
watch. They know where the big money
moves. And now this simple AI indicator
spots it too. And the beauty is you
don't need to understand complex coding
or market mechanics. AI builds the tool
and you watch for the signals. Just
describe what you want to track and AI
will create professionalgrade indicators
in just a few minutes. Stock analysis is
another clever use of AI in trading. You
simply take screenshots of stocks
fundamentals you're analyzing or upload
full documents and ask AI to point out
key findings about financial ratios. AI
can also summarize earnings reports,
highlighting key findings faster than
reading the full document. So, let's say
you are looking at Apple's stock and you
want to understand its financials
quickly rather than spending hours
analyzing numbers. You turn to AI for
instant clarity. So paste Apple's
fundamentals, the revenue, earnings,
main ratios, market cap, and even price
movements. The beauty of AI analysis is
its speed and precision. Instead of
manually comparing dozens of metrics, AI
processed everything in seconds. You
simply fed the numbers into AI and it
will immediately spot key patterns that
matter. The real advantage comes from
AI's unbiased view. While humans might
get emotional about a company, AI sticks
to pure numbers and facts. Ask him to
and it will quickly point out both
strengths and potential concerns. Think
about how this speeds up your research.
What used to take hours of reading
financial statements now takes minutes.
AI acts like your personal financial
advisor, but faster and without bias.
You feed it the numbers and it tells you
what matters most. For newer traders,
this removes the confusion of
fundamental analysis. Instead of
drowning in financial terms and ratios,
AI translates everything into clear
insights. It's like having a smart
friend explain complex numbers in simple
terms. For Apple, AI quickly showed its
healthy profits, reasonable PE ratio,
and current price discount from recent
highs. This approach can give you a
trading edge, an accurate analysis of
any stocks fundamentals combined with a
decent trading strategy. More
importantly, AI helps you understand why
these numbers matter for trading
decisions. The AI process catches things
humans might miss. Looking at Apple's
data, it immediately connected the lower
forward PE ratio with analyst growth
expectations, showing potential future
value that might not be obvious at first
glance. For newer traders, this means
you can understand company fundamentals
without being a Wall Street expert.
The next smart use is to have AI review
your trading strategy to identify
potential blind spots or market
conditions where your strategy might
underperform.
So I asked AI to analyze my trading
approach and give me straight answers
about what works and what needs fixing.
First, I told AI my exact trading rules,
when I enter trades, how I manage them,
and where I place my exits. The AI
immediately spotted patterns in my
approach that I hadn't noticed. The
process opened my eyes. AI pointed out
that a lot of my trading errors came
from mental perception, not market
conditions. While I was hunting for the
perfect signals, AI showed me that
optimization should focus on improving
my decision-making process. You can do
this, too. Simply tell AI about your
trading rules and watch it uncover blind
spots you never noticed. For example,
when I shared my entry criteria, AI
showed me I didn't have a solid way of
telling if market is trending or
rangebound. When I described my momentum
based entries, AI pointed out that I
needed to compare multiple price swings
to confirm true strength or weakness.
When I described my riskmanagement
rules, it quickly spotted
inconsistencies between my goals and my
actual trading behavior. The power of
this approach is its brutal honesty. AI
can sometimes be a yes man agreeing with
most things you say. So tell it you
don't need a sugarcoat feedback. Ask it
to analyze your strategy purely on
merit. It will then show you exactly if
your trading edge exists and where
you're just gambling. This modern
approach beats traditional strategy
review. Try this and you'll see yourself
how AI will shift your perspective on
strategy analysis.
Stock and crypto scanning becomes a
whole new game with AI at your side.
Think of scanning as searching through
thousands of stocks. But now you have a
smart assistant who sees patterns you
might miss. Let's say you start with
Trading Views stock screener, a tool
that shows you tons of stocks at once.
AI can analyze your Trading View
screener to spot hidden patterns. Just
share a screenshot and ask something
like, "What trends do you notice in
today's market? Any sector standing
out?" The AI will quickly identify
sector rotations, performance clusters,
and stand out stocks that you might miss
on your own. When looking at your
trading view data, AI can be your second
set of eyes for spotting the weird stuff
that doesn't quite fit. So, simply
request AI to identify any unusual
metrics in the screener.
It can also help you with sector
analysis. Just ask AI to group and
analyze performance by sector based on
what's showing in your screener.
Filter optimization is another use. You
send AI your current screener setup and
ask for suggestions on additional
filters that might improve your results.
You can also ask AI to suggest
additional useful columns to add to your
screener based on your trading style.
Finding the sweet spot for your stock
filters can be frustrating guesswork.
Instead of blindly adjusting numbers,
show AI your trading view screener and
ask something like, "What PE ratio range
would make sense for finding undervalued
tech stocks in this market?" The AI can
suggest practical parameter ranges based
on current market conditions. Instead of
starting from scratch every time market
conditions shift, let AI design your
custom trading view templates. Just
share your current setup and ask AI to
create three screener templates. One for
finding opportunities in a bullish
market. One for protecting capital
during bearish periods and one for
volatile conditions. The AI will suggest
specific filters, columns, and
parameters tailored to each market
environment, saving you hours of
configuration time, and ensuring you're
looking at the right metrics when market
conditions change. When earning season
hits, finding the best setups among
hundreds of reports can be overwhelming.
Just share your Trading View screener
and ask which stocks here have upcoming
earnings that might be worth playing.
The AI will identify the most promising
candidates. This instantly narrows your
focus to the handful of earnings plays
with the highest probability of success.
Let's say you find two similar setups.
When trying to choose between similar
stocks, AI can give you a sidebyside
breakdown. Just highlight a few tickers
and asked to compare them based on
several metrics. The AI will instantly
analyze the key differences in
valuation, growth rates, and technical
setup. In just a few seconds, you'll
know which stock might be the better
opportunity.
AI can also help you with a valuation
perspective. have AI explain whether
certain stocks appear overvalued or
undervalued based on the metrics
displayed. It can spot stocks where
certain ratios suggest growth isn't
properly priced in or find companies
where recent sell-offs have created
opportunity.
And remember, for best results, be
specific about what you're looking for
when using AI to analyze your Trading
View screener. Now, I'm sure you have an
indicator you love. It might give decent
signals, but it's not yet a full trading
system, and you want to see how it would
perform if traded systematically.
Well, AI can help you convert your
indicator into a back testable strategy.
You simply hand over the code or the
logic to the AI and it transforms it
into a strategy script. So, here I have
the chandelier exit code on my screen.
It's a solid indicator that many traders
use. The chandelier exit uses average
true range to set stop- losses that
trail behind the price. It's smart, but
as an indicator alone, it just sits
there. We need to make it act. So, I'll
copy the pine script code and paste it
into clawed AI. And I've asked it to
turn the indicator into a strategy.
We'll keep it very simple. So, I've
requested it to always stay in the
market, either long or short. When the
chandelier exit shows a buy signal, we
go long. When it shows a sell signal, we
go short. So, the strategy always keeps
a position. If it exits a long trade, it
enters a short trade right away. After
the AI wrote the code, I then copied it
into the Pine editor. The settings we
used are pretty straightforward. We set
the ATR period to 50, which means the
strategy calculates volatility based on
the last 50 bars. The ATR multiplier is
set to one, which determines how
sensitive our exits will be. We are also
using close prices. This back test runs
on the 1 hour time frame for Tesla. You
can see all those trade signals marked
on the chart. The strategy flips between
positions rather than ever sitting flat,
which was exactly what we wanted when we
built it. What jumps out immediately is
the equity curve at the bottom. I see a
steady climb and a return of over 60%.
That's a solid performance for a simple
strategy. The draw down stats show a
maximum equity drawd down of around 4%.
That's remarkably small for a strategy
that's constantly in the market. Many
trend following systems have draw downs
of 20% or more. So, this is really
promising. Look at the total number of
trades. We have over 1,000 signals.
That's plenty of data to judge if our
system works. The profitable trades
column shows that around 25% of our
trades made money. That might seem low
at first glance, but remember this is an
always in strategy that flips positions
frequently. Many of those trades are
quick exits to switch direction. What
matters more is the profit factor, which
sits at around 1.7.
Anything above 1.5 is considered decent
for an automated strategy. This confirms
what I hoped. The chandelier exit works
well as a trend following system. It
gives trades room to breathe while still
protecting profits when the trend
reverses. Of course, I will test this on
other time frames and symbols to see if
the results hold up. My biggest concern
is whether we could actually stick with
this strategy during choppy periods. But
overall, this looks like a solid
foundation. For a strategy that took
less than 5 minutes to create, these
results are promising. Once the AI sets
up your own strategy, you can then ask
the AI for improvements. If the draw
down is too high, can we add a trailing
stop? If the average loss is bigger than
the average win, can we modify our exit
logic? The AI will then modify the code
or the logic. You keep doing this until
you find a version that suits your
style. Maybe you discover your indicator
works best only when aligned with the
larger trend. So, you need to add a
trend filter. The AI will merge that
filter into the strategy code. And this
simple process reveals the truth about
your indicator. Sometimes you discover
that your favorite tool underperforms
during choppy markets. AI ensures you
see the actual raw numbers, not
illusions. Once you have a tested
strategy, you can forward test it in a
live or demo account. AI makes creating
a personal trading journal simple. Start
by asking AI to build your trading
journal. Be clear about what you want to
track. Your spreadsheet template must
include the date, trading market,
position type, entry price, exit price,
position size, stop-loss level, risk
percentage, profit or loss, and note
sections for strategy used, and lessons
learned. AI will give you the structure
in seconds, and this saves you hours of
setup time. Also, you could ask AI to
add calculation fields. Ask it to add
formulas to calculate your win rate,
average win, average loss, and
risk-to-reward ratio. These numbers tell
you if your strategy works or needs
fixing. The spreadsheet now does the
math automatically as you add trades.
Next, customize your journal for your
trading style. If you're a swing trader,
maybe ask AI to add columns for market
conditions or sector performance. Your
journal should match how you trade. You
can also tell AI to add a screenshot
link column. After each trade, take a
picture of your chart setup and save it.
Then paste the link in your journal.
Looking at these images later shows
patterns you missed. Visual records are
powerful learning tools. The most
valuable part of your journal is the
lesson section. Ask AI to create a
template for the notes section with
prompts for strategy used, rules
followed or broken, emotional state, and
lessons learned. This structure forces
you to reflect on each trait. Ask AI to
suggest a routine for updating your
journal. The best time is right after
closing a position. Make this a habit.
No trade is complete until it's in your
journal. AI can even help you create
reminders to maintain this discipline.
For review purposes, ask AI to create a
weekly review template. This helps you
spot trends in your trading. The real
magic happens when you have enough data.
After a month of consistent journaling,
ask AI to analyze your trading patterns.
What are the things you're doing well?
Where are the mistakes you're constantly
making? AI finds patterns you might
miss, like trading poorly on certain
days or taking too much risk when you're
down. A good journal doesn't need to be
complex. It just needs to be used
consistently, and AI helps with both.
This might be one of the most important
trading tools you'll create. Now, if
you're curious about mastering other
trading techniques, go ahead and watch
one of these videos next.
[Music]