If you want to increase your chances to succeed
at trading, you must align yourself with big
players in the market.
And how you do that?
Using supply and demand.
Supply zones are found when the market makes
a large move down from either a single candle
or small consolidation structure, also known
as a base.
Demand zones are found when the market makes
a large move up, again, from a single candle
or a base.
Drawing the supply and demand zones is simple.
For a supply zone, you want to mark the area
from the OPEN of the LAST bullish candle before
the drop which created the supply zone, up
to the most recent high before the drop.
For a demand zone, you mark the area from
the OPEN of the LAST bearish candle before
the drop which created the demand zone, down
to the most recent low before the up move.
If you want to know more about how to find
and draw supply and demand zones make sure
you watch this video first.
Now, there are 4 types of supply and demand,
defined by how the price approaches the supply
and demand zone and how it leaves the zone
again.
I’ve grouped them into continuation structures
and reversal structures.
Continuation price structures include Drop-base-Drop
and Rally-base-Rally patterns.
Reversal price structures are Drop-base-Rally
and Rally-base-Drop patterns.
So let’s analyze each of those structures,
one by one.
Rally – Base – Rally
The rally-base-rally is a type of demand zone
which forms during an up-move, being a continuation
pattern.
The market structure is very simple.
In this example, you can see we first have
a rally, then a consolidation (or the base)
and finally another rally, which creates the
demand zone.
A rally-base-rally will always form a demand
zone; it can never create a supply zone.
Drop – Base – Drop
The drop-base-drop is the exact opposite of
a rally-base-rally, with the only similarity
being they both form during trending movements.
A drop-base-drop will always form a supply
zone, a zone which if the market returns to,
should push the price back in the direction
of the movement that created the zone.
In this example a drop lower created the supply
zone so if the market will return to this
zone it should push the market lower.
Now the big question: what creates drop – base
– drop/rally – base – rally structures?
Both zones form in the market because of bank
traders taking profits off existing trading
positions.
In this example, during the first rally we
had bank traders placing long trades.
When the bank traders are in profitable trades,
they’ll want to secure some of their profits.
When they decide to do this, they consume
all of the buy orders coming into the market
from retail traders who are have begun entering
long trades due to size of the rally.
This consumption of buy orders means the market
makes a small move lower, and creates the
base of the potential demand zone.
The move lower causes a large number of retail
traders who went long on the rally higher
to close their trades at a loss which puts
a lot of sell orders into the market.
In addition to this, there will be a small
number of retail traders thinking the move
down is a trend reversal, meaning they’ll
place sell trades with the expectation that
the market is going to move lower.
With these two sets of retail traders putting
sell order in the market, the banks now begin
buying again knowing they’ll make the market
move higher, and in the process cause anybody
who sold the move to close their trades at
a loss, which ends up being the bank traders
profit.
For the drop-base-drop structure, the exact
same process takes place only the other way
around.
The banks take profits from sell positions,
which stops the market from falling, then
as the market begins to retrace against the
trend, the retail traders who sold late into
the down-move close their trades at a loss,
and reversal traders begin placing buy trades
because they think the trend is changing.
Both of these traders are putting buy orders
into the market, the banks start selling again
at the supply zone, and all the traders who
placed buy trades are now losing money.
Drop – Base – Rally
The drop -base-rally is a structure which
always forms a demand zone in the market.
These zones differ from the first 2 price
structures, mainly because of their location
in the market.
If rally-base-rally and drop-base-drop zones
only form during trending movements, drop-base-rally
zones will only be found when the market changes
from moving down to moving up.
So, it’s a reversal pattern.
Rally – Base – Drop
On the opposite side of the scale we have
rally-base-drop zones.
These zones form when the market reverses
from moving higher to moving lower, and when
their construction is complete, a supply zone
will have formed in the market which should
cause the market to fall.
Again, a reversal structure.
What Creates Rally – Base – Drop/Drop
– Base – Rally structure?
The drop-base-rally and rally-base-drop zones
are created by bank traders either placing
trades to make the market reverse or by taking
profits off existing trading positions.
Very important: The rally-base-drop/ drop-base-rally
zones which form when bank traders taking
profits have a lower probability of resulting
in successful trades than zones that are created
because of bank traders placing trades, wanting
the market to reverse.
To understand why, we must analyze and try
to find the intentions of the bank traders
when they are placing trades.
If a bank is placing trades in order to make
other traders lose money, the area at which
they have placed their trades is important,
as they have an interest in keeping the market
price from breaking the area.
In supply and demand trading this means when
a rally-base-drop or drop-base-rally zone
is created by bank traders placing trades,
wanting a reverse the market, the banks must
keep the market from moving past the point
where they have entered their positions, in
order to protect the trades they have placed.
In this example, we can see a drop-base-rally
zone after the market has been falling.
When the banks enter into their long trades,
they consume all the sell orders coming into
the market and the price begins to rise, breaking
the swing high found at the top of the last
move lower.
Soon after the break of the high we see a
large drop taking place, this drop causes
a lot of retail traders to start shorting,
thinking the move higher was simply just a
pullback to the downtrend.
When the market comes into contact with the
demand zone which was created by the first
phase of buying, the banks buy again.
If the banks didn’t buy and the market fell
below the demand zone, then they would be
put at a loss on their positions and would
have to liquidate their buy trades.
Of course it’s highly unlikely for this
to happen because the banks always make sure
to plan their trades in advance.
The main problem with drop-base-rally/rally
-base-drop zones is determining if the zone
has been created by banks placing trades to
make people lose money or by taking profits
off their own positions.
To find out whether the zone you’re looking
at has been created due to profit taking or
from bank traders placing trades, this requires
you to be able to understand the mechanics
of where the supply or demand zone has formed
in relation to the current trend on the time-frame
you’re observing.
The first piece of market structure in a rally-base-drop
is a rally.
The analysis of the rally is what will give
us clues in figuring out for the reason why
the zone has been created.
The size of the candlesticks which form the
rally/drop along with understanding where
the wicks are on the candles, can give us
the majority of the information needed to
find out why the zone has been created.
Check out the rally which took place at the
end of this down-move.
This move up most likely occurred due to professional
traders placing buy traders, the way I can
determine this is by looking at the previous
moves up in the downtrend.
It’s all about previous price action.
None of the previous up-moves, against the
trend, moved up in a strong manner.
The bullish candles were either small or had
wicks present on the top of the candle which
shows us someone was selling even though market
was moving higher, each one of these up-moves
were created by bank traders taking profits
off sell positions.
Now if we look at the final up-move we can
see the rally was much greater in size than
the previous up-moves.
These candles were far greater in size than
the bull candles from the previous upswings.
Remember this: the banks will only cause a
reversal when there are enough retail traders
for them to make a lot of money off.
The appearance of a supply or demand zone
when the market has only been moving in the
same direction for a short length of time,
means there won’t be many retail traders
entering trades.
Therefore, the banks will not be able to make
a lot of money if they cause the market to
reverse, because only a small amount of traders
will be liquidating their losing positions.
Here’s another drop-base-rally zone.
There are two clues which made this structure
an important area on the chart.
The first was the rally out of the zone, the
candles which made up the rally were large
bullish candles which pushed the market a
large distance against the previous down-move.
These bull candles contained very little selling
meaning its unlikely the banks where placing
sell trades as the market rallied higher.
The second clue was the fact the rally managed
to break the most recent swing high.
If you plan to trade rally-base-drop/drop-base-rally
zones the best piece of advice I can give
you is make sure the zone your trading breaks
a recent swing high for drop-base-rally zones
or a recent swing low for rally-base-drop
zones.
If the rally in a drop-base-rally breaks an
old swing high there is a much higher chance
the zone will result in you having a successful
trade than if no swing high was broken.
The same is true for rally-base-drop zones.
If the drop pushes the market below a recently
formed swing low there is a high probability
of the zone working out profitably.
Now you know what to look for when drawing
your supply and demand zones.
In future videos, I plan to show you how to
spot the best supply and demand areas, the
high probability ones, and I will reveal how
to trade the bounce or the retest of these
areas.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.