hey guys in this video I will show you
the correct way of using the stochastic
RSI indicator for day trading and swing
trading the stochastic RSI is one of my
favorite indicators because it combines
the features of the stochastic
oscillator and the relative strength
index the indicator increases the
sensitivity and the reliability of the
regular RSI indicator as it applies the
stochastic formula to the RSI values
instead of the price value so the
stochastic RSI is basically an indicator
of an indicator but also meaning that
this is a lagging oscillator by itself
the stochastic RSI is not a reliable
indicator if you want to swing trade or
day trade only with this indicator it
will be a very hard task to find valid
signals now you might wonder what are
the differences between the stochastic
indicator the RSI and the stochastic RSI
let's look at this Bitcoin chart to see
if we can spot some visual differences
between the simple RSI the stochastic
and the stochastic RSI indicator from a
simple glance we immediately see that
the stochastic RSI indicator is more
volatile compared to the other two
indicators what this means is that it
will generate a lot of noise also we can
observe that the stochastic RSI just
generates more overbought and overs
signals than the simple stochastic
oscillator if we look closely at the
chart there are more false signals
offered by the stochastic RSI compared
to the other two indicators we can
safely say that during trending
conditions the stochastic RSI is not a
reliable indicator for spotting
overbought or oval Sal entry points on
the
market in what concerns Trading
divergencies
the stochastic RSI also lacks I don't
know about you but I can spot the
divergencies more clearly on the simple
stochastic oscillator and the
RSI so how do we trade with a stochastic
RSI first we forget about overbought and
overso signals as many Traders use the
RSI in a wrong way there is a high
chance that they will also use the
stochastic RSI in a similar manner
entering counter Trend positions
whenever the sto IC RSI indicates
overbought or oversold conditions will
only lead to losing positions being a
lagging indicator my advice is to forget
about using stochastic RSI for trading
overb and oversaw conditions in a non-
trending Market this indicator will
generate a lot of false signals tell me
do you see any clear entries on the
Bitcoin chart cuz I don't the smarter
use of the stochastic RSI is to look for
divergencies between the indicator and
the price of the traded instrument but
here's the trick if you want to search
for divergencies we only need to display
the d% on the chart the reason I only
display the d%c is simple I like Clean
and Clear charts and the stochastic RSI
could be quite
confusing here's another Bitcoin chart
with the 200 exponential moving average
and the Deep % of the stochastic RSI
added what we need to do is to search
for divergencies between the stochastic
RSI and the prise but only in the
direction of the main Trend indicated by
the exponential moving average so we
never take counter Trend entries when
trading the stochastic RSI divergencies
we just stick with the main trend on the
market in this example as we are in a
clear downtrend we only only look for
divergencies that allow us to short the
market here is my favorite way of using
the stochastic RSI what I prefer to do
in order to make the indicator more
reliable is to smooth it while using
longer periods for this setup to be
profitable I prefer to use the 100
period for the RSI and the 100 period
for the stochastic the trick here is to
add a 50 level and watch for bullish and
bearish periods remember how I said to
ignore the overbought and oversaw levels
While most Traders seek to enter counter
Trend positions when they see stochastic
RSI in overbought and oversold
areas I prefer to look for continuation
movements but that isn't enough even
with this setup the stochastic RSI will
also offer a lot of noise that's why we
have to adjust our entry points my
preference is to add a macd indicator
with 10 101 settings basically these
macd settings are tracking the crossover
between the 10 EMA and the 100 EMA so
when the stochastic RSI indicator is
above 50 this signals bullish pressure
and when the indicator is below 50 this
trend translates into bearish pressure I
prefer to confirm the entries with the
macd macd above zero level suggests a
bullish Outlook while macd below zero
level indicates a bearish
scenario the setup is simple we look for
Market strength with the stochastic RSI
and the macd
aligned now let's look at this down
Jones index chart we simply search for
buy entries when the stochastic RSI is
above its 50 level only if the macd
confirms the move also we aim to short
the market when the stochastic RSI is
below 50 and the macd is in negative
territory here's another chart this time
the Dex index we look for buy signals
when the stochastic RSI is over over 50
and the macd above zero and we look for
short opportunities when the stochastic
RSI is below 50 and the macd below zero
by using the stochastic RSI this way we
gain an important Advantage by looking
differently at this indicator we don't
trade overbought and oversold levels and
we don't chase tops and bottoms as much
most Traders do we are searching for
Market
strength as I was saying before when day
trading or swing trading with a
stochastic RSI we must use it in
conjunction with other technical
indicators or chart patterns in order to
maximize its
Effectiveness if you got any value from
this please consider subscribing to our
Channel and leave us a like as it will
help us massively in the future until
next time