If you are searching for a smarter way
to trade, then you definitely must see
what AI can do for you. In this video,
I'm revealing exactly how I'm trading
with AI and save thousands of dollars.
Stay till the end and you'll learn how
to transform your own ideas into
professional AI indicators in minutes,
even if you've never written a single
line of code. Here's your exact path.
Today, we'll use AI to create a momentum
candle detector that catches explosive
moves. Then, we'll make a pattern
recognition indicator that highlights
reversal trades. Then, a custom 5-minut
range breakout detector. Then, a pin bar
scanner and a gap fill detector, perfect
for day traders and scalpers.
So, I had this idea for catching
explosive candles the moment they
appear. No lag, no repainting, just pure
momentum detection. Most people get
momentum wrong. They see a big candle
and assume it means something. But size
is relative. A momentum candle isn't
just big, it's abnormally big compared
to recent price action. Here's my idea.
The logic behind a momentum candle is
simple. The spread is the high minus the
low of the bar. Compare it to the
average spread of the last 10 candles.
If the bar spread is at least 1.5 times
that average, it's considered a momentum
candle. That means the range is
significantly bigger than usual. This is
perfect for scalping and day trading
because volatility surges often lead to
breakout continuations. When the market
suddenly expands its range, something
important is happening. Whatever the
cause, you want to know immediately.
Now, here's where AI changes everything.
Instead of learning Pine Script, you
just describe what you want. This is the
exact prompt I use. I wanted a momentum
candle detector that calculates average
spread of last 10 bars. Then it
highlights the candles that are 1.5
higher than the average. I also asked
for optional inputs for look back length
and multiplier. Within seconds, I got my
code. Here's how you implement it. Open
Trading View. Click Pine Editor at the
bottom. Delete the default code. Then
simply paste your generated code. Click
add to chart.
And now momentum candles glow on screen.
Now let's make a quick visual
validation. See those colored candles?
Each marks a volatility explosion.
You can combine it with your existing
strategy. If you trade breakouts, wait
for momentum candles at key levels. If
you prefer reversals, watch for momentum
exhaustion. The indicator adapts to your
style. The best momentum candles appear
at key support and resistance levels.
you want to see rejection wicks or
continuation patterns forming right as
the momentum signal triggers. I can
optimize it even further. I can adjust
the multiplier. Maybe 1.5x is too
sensitive for crypto.
I can also add time filters. In the
future, I may ask the AI to only
highlight momentum candles during market
hours. This removes overnight noise.
You might wonder about accuracy. In my
testing, roughly 60% of momentum candles
led to continued movement in that
direction. Not perfect, but strong
enough for an edge.
This next indicator was born from
frustration. I kept seeing these massive
reversal candles that completely
destroyed the previous trend, but I'd
spot them too late. So, I had this idea
for an indicator that highlights big
candles, wiping out the last three bars
completely. The threeline strike pattern
would became a solid reversal weapon.
When everyone's leaning one direction
and a single candle erases multiple bars
of progress, it signals violent
rejection. Markets don't reverse gently,
they slam the brakes. Here's the anatomy
of the indicator we'll build using AI.
You need three consecutive same color
candles moving in one direction. Think
three bullish closes in a row, each one
pushing higher. Then the fourth candle
completely engulfing all three previous
bars. That fourth candle just erased
three bars of progress in the opposite
direction. It's like the market saying,
"Just kidding to everyone who bought
that trend." For a bullish strike, you
reverse the logic. Three bearish candles
followed by one massive bullish
engulfing bar.
Why does this pattern work so well?
Well, it signals potential sharp
reversals at exactly the right moment.
So, let's build this using AI, a pattern
recognition indicator. Here's my exact
prompt. We want AI to check candle
direction, to measure body sizes, and to
confirm the engulfing action. Most
importantly, to place clear visual
signals right where the pattern
completes. I'm thinking a box to easily
see it and trade the breakout.
Now, let's import the code into trading
view.
We'll save it.
Then, we add it to the chart.
Look at those boxes highlighting our
pattern. No more staring at the charts.
The best part is that this simple AI
indicator will eliminate any human error
in pattern recognition. We can even
optimize the indicator. In the future, I
will add a volume confirmation filter.
Large volume on the fourth candle
strengthens the signal. I will tell AI
to only show patterns where the fourth
candle volume exceeds the 20 period
average. This filters out weak signals
in thin markets.
As you can see from this quick back
test, not every strike leads to full
reversal, but most provide profitable
scalps. You can even trade a
continuation of the previous trend if
the box is broken to the upside.
Here's an advanced tip. Layer this with
support and resistance. A bullish strike
at major support represents a strong
signal.
A bearish strike at resistance is a
decent short. This indicator will help
me a lot. Instead of guessing when
trends end, I wait for the market to
show me. Another modification that could
improve my results, timebased filtering.
Some patterns work better during active
sessions. So, I might request the AI to
only show strikes during London and New
York sessions.
If you skip this next concept, you'll
regret it because it can make or break
your intraday results. Most traders
ignore the micro opening ranges that
form every single hour. But trading with
AI can automate this powerful scalping
technique. So I had an idea about an
indicator that helps me to trade the
micro opening range of every hour in any
market. This sounds complex but the
logic is simple. At the start of each
hour, you take the first 5-minut bar,
plot its high and low as your range
boundaries. Then watch for price to
close outside that box before the hour
ends. Perfect for day trading. Every 60
minutes, the market establishes a new
micro range. A break above could mean
potential continuation in the right
conditions.
With this indicator, you have multiple
opening ranges per day instead of just
one. That first 5-minute bar represents
the market's initial judgment about fair
value for the new hour. When price
breaks outside that range, it signals
institutional money-making directional
bets.
So, let's ask AI to transform this
manual process into automated signals.
The first 5-minute candle creates a
range. The high and low become my
reference levels for that hour. If price
closes outside this box before the next
hour begins, we have a signal. I've
asked AI to extend lines until the next
hour begins. Okay, we have our code.
Let's paste it into trading view.
The visual result is powerful. The
indicator draws fresh boxes every hour.
High and low lines extend right until
the next hour starts. Then new lines
appear. The chart stays organized
automatically. Each hour gets its own
range box. When price breaks out, I see
it immediately.
No manual drawing, no missing levels,
just clean objective ranges updating
like clockwork.
There are multiple strategies starting
from here. Entry happens on the close
outside the range, not just a wick. Stop
goes inside the box, usually at the
midpoint. target equals 1.5 times the
box height.
Now, a big mistake would be to trust
every break signal without considering
market context. In the future, I plan to
use Trading View's bar replay feature to
test this across several hours and see
how price actually behaves around these
ranges.
From a quick glance, I immediately see
that during quiet Asian sessions, price
often chops around the range without
clear direction.
One enhancement that could boost the win
rate is once again volume confirmation.
I may request AI to only signal breaks
where volume exceeds a certain
threshold. This filters out fake breaks
in dead zones. The beauty of trading
with AI is the consistency. Your
indicator never misses an hour, never
forgets to draw the lines, and never
gets distracted by other chart patterns.
It just works hour after hour.
Strategy-wise, I want to enter on the
close outside the range and place my
stop inside the box and target 1.5 times
the box height. This gives me favorable
riskreward ratios while capitalizing on
institutional flow patterns.
I'll be honest, I wasted months using
terrible pin bar indicators. They'd mark
every candle with a tiny wick. Useless
noise. I didn't find a reliable
indicator anywhere. So, I decided to
build my own. I wanted AI to make me an
indicator that only flags true rejection
candles without squinting at charts for
hours. Let's bust a myth about pin bars.
Everyone thinks long wick equals pin
bar. Wrong. True pin bars show violent
rejection with specific proportions. The
wick must be at least three times the
body. Anything less is just normal price
action. Why do these proportions matter?
Because they reveal genuine rejection,
not just the volatility.
When price explores one direction, then
snaps back, leaving a tiny body, that's
institutions defending levels. Retail
traders got trapped. Smart money won.
Here's the exact logic. for a bullish
bin bar. We see a long lower wick
showing sellers pushed price down and a
tiny body near the top showing buyers
won by the close of the candle. For
bearish pins, long upper wick showing
buyers failed and small body near the
bottom showing sellers took control.
Time to build it using AI. I want the
indicator to analyze several key factors
that make pin bars more reliable. First,
it measures the wick size as a
percentage of the total candle range. I
want to set this threshold anywhere from
10% to 90%. With 50% being the default,
this means the wick must be at least
half the size of the entire candle to
qualify. I also want a comparison
feature. I want the indicator to look
back at the previous candles and only
triggers when the current wick is
significantly larger than recent wicks.
I want to set how much larger it needs
to be with the default being 1.5 times
bigger. This prevents false signals in
choppy markets where every candle has
medium-sized wicks. I also asked AI to
include a filtering mechanism. The
candle must be a minimum size relative
to the average true range. This will
eliminate tiny pin bars that don't have
enough significance to matter.
Okay, after a few iterations and
debugging, we have our code. So, let's
import it.
As you can see, green triangles appear
below bullish pins, red triangles above
bearish pins. each marks a potential
reversal point. Instead of searching for
pins manually, they jump off the screen.
Of course, context matters. A pin bar in
empty space means little. But a pin at a
moving average or previous days high or
round number. At support levels, bullish
pins become buy signals.
At resistance, bearish pins trigger
shorts.
From a quick back test, not every pin
starts a new trend, but most produce
profitable bounces.
One pattern I look for, pins in the same
area. This is a massive rejection
signal. Don't ignore pin bars in trends.
Counter trend pins at moving averages
often mark perfect pullback entries.
Trend following pins at breakout points
confirm continuation.
The key is patience. Not every pin
deserves a trade. But when location,
volume, and context align, pin bars
offer incredible riskreward.
The beauty of this indicator is that it
eliminates the guesswork in pin bar
identification.
Instead of manually scanning charts and
debating whether a week is long enough,
the AI does the heavy lifting and only
highlights the pin bars that meet your
specific criteria for size, comparison,
and market context.
I had another idea to exploit one of the
markets most reliable patterns. Gaps
fascinate me because they are pure. No
indicators needed, just empty space on a
chart that acts like a magnet. And once
again, AI will help me to automate the
entire gap detection and the monitoring
process. The concept seems almost too
simple. When today opens way above
yesterday's high, that's a gap up. When
today opens below yesterday's low,
that's a gap down. And the market loves
filling that empty space on the chart.
Some say 70% of gaps fill eventually.
This is a classic scalping and day
trading method. Price has this magnetic
tendency to trade back into the previous
day's range, filling that empty space on
the chart. It's like the market needs to
revisit those abandoned price levels to
confirm their significance. Each gap
creates a potential scalping opportunity
if you can track them properly. So, I
want an indicator to show the unfilled
area visually, so I can see exactly when
price approaches fill levels. Manual gap
tracking is impossible at scale, but
trading with AI makes it effortless.
Here's the prompt for the AI. Basically,
I've asked it to check for gaps versus
prior sessions to draw shaded boxes
between the open and prior extreme and
to remove shading when price trades into
the gap area. Okay, I ran into several
errors, but nothing AI couldn't handle.
Let's import the code and add it to
charts.
So green boxes mark gap up zones. Red
boxes show gap downs. As price fills
each gap, boxes disappear. Clean,
visual, and effective. The strategy
becomes obvious. When gaps appear,
consider fading them. Buy gap downs near
support.
Short gap ups near resistance.
And I'll use the box edges as targets.
Gap fills often happen faster than you
expect. Morning gaps frequently fill
before launch, especially in high volume
stocks. That's why I wanted this
indicator to ensure I won't miss these
quick scalping opportunities. So, the
strategy is simple. I will enter trades
in the direction of the gap fill with my
stop beyond the gap extreme and the
target at the fill completion.
For bigger gaps, I could also add a
modification. I could request AI to add
a 50% fill line and alert me when
reached. Many traders exit half at 50%
fill, keeping half for complete fill.
This balances profit taking with runner
potential.
Gaps are very underrated for scalping.
You see, gaps up trap late buyers who
chase. Gaps down trap panic sellers. As
gaps fill, these trapped traders exit,
accelerating the fill. So, I'm planning
to profit from their mistakes. The
indicator also helps with gap and go
setups. Sometimes gaps don't fill
immediately, but continue in the gap
direction. I might watch for the first
hour action. If price holds above below
the gap after 60 minutes, I will
consider trading the continuation.
So, I will incorporate this into the
code. Of course, I can combine this
indicator with the other ones I've
created. A gap up with a bearish pin bar
represents a strong fade signal. Trading
with AI lets you merge these concepts
effortlessly.
I hope you see how simple is to turn
your own trading ideas into custom
indicators and full strategies. Few
years ago, this required years of
programming knowledge. But now, in a few
hours, you can build something really
special. Here's the thing most people
never realize. Every profitable trading
strategy started as a simple observation
about market behavior. Maybe you noticed
price tends to bounce off certain moving
average combinations. Or perhaps you
spotted that volume spikes predict
direction changes. These observations
are gold mines waiting to be automated.
Maybe you had some brilliant trading
ideas, but you couldn't turn them into
actionable signals. That's why trading
with AI will change everything. It will
transform your random thoughts into
precise indicator code. The secret sauce
lies in breaking down your idea into
clear logical rules that any AI can
understand. You don't need to think like
a programmer. You just need to think
like a trader who can explain their
edge. Let me walk you through the exact
framework I use to transform any trading
concept into an indicator. This process
works whether your idea involves price
patterns, volume analysis, timebased
signals, or multi-time frame setups.
Step one, capture your core observation.
What exactly did you notice about market
behavior? Be specific about the
conditions that create your edge. For
example, I noticed that when price makes
a new 20-day high, but volume is below
the 10-day average, it often reverses.
Step two, define your entry and exit
criteria. What triggers your signal?
What confirms it? What invalidates it?
Using our example, the trigger is new
highs with low volume. Confirmation
might be a bearish engulfing candle and
invalidation could be volume expanding
above average.
Step three, specify your visual
requirements. How should the indicator
display signals on your chart? Arrows,
colored bars, background highlights,
text labels. The clearer your vision,
the better your AI assistant can execute
it. The AI will understand your trading
logic and will convert it into
executable code. But don't stop here.
Don't take the first version and assume
it's perfect. Test it, refine it, and
further optimize it. Your first prompt
might produce basic code. That's fine.
Test it. Find weaknesses. Request
improvements. Make the lines thicker.
Add percentage labels. Include multiple
time frames. Then back test your new
indicator across different market
conditions. Does it work in trending
markets, rangebound conditions, and high
volatility periods? What about low
volume sessions? This testing reveals
the true edge behind your original
observation. You can then test new
variations in minutes, change the look
back period, adjust the threshold
values, and add confirmation filters.
And another key tip, you might think
complex indicators and strategies are
always better, but that's exactly why
they fail at practical application. The
best AI indicators solve one specific
problem really well rather than trying
to predict everything.
Focus your ideas on single observable
market behaviors. So here's the workflow
that unlocks unlimited AI tools. First,
crystallize your idea. No coding terms,
just clear logic. Then structure a
specific prompt with inputs, conditions,
and outputs. Then feed it to an AI
model. Paste the generated code into
trading view. Visually verify the
indicator works correctly and then
refine by requesting modifications
and don't stop at indicators. AI builds
complete strategies. If you can describe
it clearly, AI can build it. Your next
move is obvious. Pick one idea that you
think has potential. Write your prompt.
Within minutes, you'll have your first
custom indicator running. Then build
another. and another. If you learned
something new today, would appreciate a
like. And if you want more AI trading
tips, check out these other videos next.