today I'm revealing several key steps to
double your trading performance we'll
cover a variety of topics including
common trading mistakes to avoid
psychology hacks and some risk and money
management tips to be ahead of the game
so like subscribe and stick around for
the full video
if you're planning to trade and actually
stay in the game for longer you're going
to lose money at some point and if you
want a good trading experience you must
have a somewhat high tolerance for risk
some people just don't have it the idea
of losing money doesn't sit well with
them
fear of losing money is a good emotion
to have in many areas of life we have to
be protective with our wealth however in
trading this tendency to be defensive
and emotional with money needs to be
transformed and refocused into a
different mental state
I had this in my first years the fear of
losing money can break you as a Trader
causing you to miss out on winning
setups and to second guess yourself
constantly but if you want to succeed at
trading you have to conquer this fear
instead of being fearful of losing your
money when trading embrace the control
you have on each trade with the help of
risk management manage your money employ
a solid risk management and in time
you'll diminish those negative thoughts
some people love math because typically
there is just one right answer the
answer in trading always changes that's
because short-term trading is often
driven by human emotions
so many times people want the formula if
I do this can I expect this result if
the RSI goes to 30 I buy right if I see
a doji that's indecision right
but the market is too Dynamic for that
and here's another thing you can have a
great idea in trading but if your
execution sucks you will end up losing
money
or you can have the right strategy but
you decide to trade a different Market
because you really want to trade today
again you probably end up losing money
you are only as disciplined as the
quality of your method and your belief
in that method
thank you
[Music]
no one has a magical crystal ball that
can foresee the future trading is not
about predicting the future it's about
calculating the odds of possible
scenarios right
prices can continue to go Way Beyond
what you anticipate and calling tops and
bottoms without any real method can
therefore be very dangerous
let me repeat no method can detect
exactly where prices will stop and
that's a very common mistake you have a
losing position and you say it will stop
there then it will reverse and you lose
and then you blame your discipline but
it's not your lack of discipline but a
lack of understanding of the basics of
the supply and demand of prices and the
action mechanism of the marketplace
sadly some Traders will never understand
this
[Music]
some may say that the exit is less
important than the entry which is a big
misunderstanding of how trading works
a trading strategy is more than a method
of identifying entry signals or finding
a more accurate indicator to time your
entries more effectively exits are
equally as important as entries this is
where you decide when to get out and cut
your loss or under which circumstances
you realize a profit
without a clear plan you are more likely
to become unfocused and you have no
chance in a game dominated by
professionals
an Exit Plan deciding whether you take a
profit or a loss should not be random
you can put your stop at 50 100 or 200
but if it was decided based on your
tolerance its randomness
using reasonable price levels based on
technicals price action in particular
for your stops and profits can often
help you to make better decisions
stops and targets based on what you're
happy with will not cut in in trading
you need to wait certain odds prior to
executing a trade thus you can decide
ahead of time whether you want to be in
a trade or stand aside
and keep in mind standing aside and not
taking a trade is a valid option
based on your own risk tolerance you
should only take traits that suit your
personality and your parameters
stress during a losing trade is often a
sign that your position is too big
[Music]
you must know how to differentiate
between scenarios where you take a
profit at a certain point or when it's
better to be patient as prices go more
and more in your favor
the common problem is taking random
profits as soon as you see them
just to regret later that you didn't
wait it out
or maybe you're waiting too long and
giving back profits again this is not
where you want to find yourself either
and you blame your lack of discipline or
grit which is oftentimes not true rather
it's your lack of ability to decide how
far the price will extend because
periodically prices do rest and extend
contract and expand
your intuition cannot and shouldn't
dictate how far you think prices will
extend
so let's say you are analyzing Euro USD
you have your bias you know you want to
be long on the market and you're just
waiting for some confirmation
then you read several articles saying
that the short trade is the right play
and you start to question your plan
and instead of going long you short the
market
and you guessed it you are right in the
first place
the market went up
chances are you are a technical Trader
so stick with your technical system and
be aware of the fundamental environment
surrounding your Market
YouTube videos Reddit posts or Twitter
rumors will easily distract you from
your technicals in the end your system
is what you determine your trades others
opinions shouldn't matter
right
I get asked every day what is the best
time frame what are the best settings
for the macd or the RSI you won't
appreciate my answer which is it depends
the problem is that many new Traders
don't understand context
day trading or swing trading without
understanding context can and will be
fatal to your account
you see amateurs place the same
importance on every scenario
professionals always adjust their
thinking and positions because the
market is always changing it changes
volatility ranges Direction and bias you
may get into a trade with odds in your
favor while one hour later the odds
change demanding an exit you don't just
sit there and wait for your profits to
turn into a loss you have to be flexible
and understand that you need to exit
where conditions change
the context of the market will dictate
the size of the move and how long a move
will last
so you need to be flexible and to adjust
to the new situations on the market
[Music]
it's not how much you know that matters
but how well you know the few things
that work for you
of course learning is always encouraged
but on learning what's not necessary
practical or effective may be just as
helpful
for example in my first years I relied
100 on indicators and it was very hard
for me to unlearn the way I analyzed the
market
I was used to look at indicators to know
the trend and to enter only when three
of them were aligned and so on
seeing too much data can hamper your
decisions whereas having a narrower
approach with strong money management
may increase your odds of success
quality of knowledge is more important
than quantity of knowledge and knowing
what not to do may be more important
than accumulating a clutter of knowledge
[Music]
one of the most brutal aspects about the
market is its volatile nature the market
can be smooth and trend for a period of
time and then without warning run into a
volatile sideways and choppy movement
that can make trading very difficult
well at least for Trend Traders
another group of Traders might just be
waiting for that sideways movement and
that's exactly the point I'm trying to
make always know the market you are
going to be trading in the market
conditions a trading system will always
Define the market it is best suited for
for example you could be relying on a
moving average strategy that calls for
entering on minor pullbacks within a
dominant Trend or you could be a scalper
who benefits from short-term price
movements within a wide range
or maybe you try to catch reversals
which means you're looking out for
larger swing trades the point is they
are going to be phases when you will be
enjoying the action from the sidelines
make sure your trading strategy allows
that a good way of ensuring this is
having a strict entry criteria that
allows you to stick to certain market
conditions for the most part
[Music]
you often hear words like Intuition or a
gut feeling but it's very important to
distinguish between real intuition and
what Traders must take as intuition
a common mistake is when Traders use
intuition to justify trades where they
prematurely entered the market and broke
their trading rules they will then say
that they had a feeling that price was
going to take off and that they didn't
want to miss the trade but let's be
honest how often does that really happen
don't confuse intuition with
undisciplined trading because that's
what causes major losses the more room
for interpretation in a trading
methodology the more often Traders will
use the word intuition to justify traits
which could have been avoided in the
first place
intuition doesn't only play a role when
it comes to trade entries but it goes
much deeper
intuition is also used to justify
staying and losing trades much longer
than anticipated you start sensing that
price is about to turn around and you
wait and wait and that's when the
disaster usually starts
although Traders might call it intuition
once you are in a losing trade your
brain starts looking for reasons to
avoid the negative feedback from closing
out a losing position
real intuition only comes with years of
experience is a form of subconscious
pattern recognition
after you've spent hundreds or thousands
of hours in front of your charts being
exposed to tens of thousands of Market
moves and patterns it will become a part
of you you may call it intuition but in
fact it's nothing but a subconscious
recognition of a market pattern you have
seen so many times before especially new
Traders should stay away from using the
term intuition when it comes to making
trading decisions because what they
mistake has got feel is just a form of
undisciplined and unstructured trading
foreign
let me tell you something logical and
more rational persons have problems when
trading
why because markets are irrational most
of the time a logical person often looks
for answers to why certain movements
happen but the market is often driven by
emotions like fear and greed
I'm a logical person and it was very
hard for me to accept this
trading is not like school when you can
study hard and know you'll do well on a
test being too logical in an irrational
Market can be a detriment in trading you
can't know the outcome of the events
before they happen only the
probabilities
if you want to see more videos like this
one leave us a like And subscribe and
check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time