Many traders adopt a single screen or indicator
that they apply to each and every trade.
In principle, there is nothing wrong with
adopting and adhering to a single indicator
for decision making.
In fact, the discipline involved in maintaining
a focus on a single measure is related to
the trader's discipline and is, perhaps, one
of the main determinants of achieving success
as a trader.
But what if your chosen indicator is fundamentally
flawed?
What if conditions in the market change so
that your single screen can no longer account
for all of the eventual outcomes operating
outside of its measurement?
The point is, because the market is very complex,
even the most advanced indicators can't work
all of the time and under every market condition.
For example, in a market uptrend, trend-following
indicators rise and issue "buy" signals while
oscillators suggest that the market is overbought
and issue "sell" signals.
In downtrends, trend-following indicators
suggest selling short, but oscillators become
oversold and issue signals to buy.
In a market moving strongly higher or lower,
trend-following indicators are ideal, but
they are prone to rapid and abrupt changes
when markets trade in ranges.
Within trading ranges, oscillators are the
best choice, but when the markets begin to
follow a trend, oscillators issue premature
signals.
This is why alexander elder came up with the
triple screen system.
The triple screen system was first proposed
by elder as a stock trading strategy – but
it’s regularly used in forex and other markets
as well.
So, what is the triple screen?
Triple screen is essentially a trend following
system, but the main characteristic, is that
it works by analyzing charts at multiple timeframes.
The root of elder’s triple screen is that
it tries to time trade entries to coincide
with market corrections or pullbacks.
These can happen in both bull trends and bear
trends.
The strategy only buys or sells when the signals
between different screens at different timeframes
are in agreement.
Here are the steps you should follow if you
want to implement the triple screen:
The first step is to choose which charts to
use.
Most traders who use triple screen choose
a time ratio of between 3 and 5.
This means that the period of each chart reduces
by a factor of 3, 4 or 5 from the longest
duration chart to the shortest duration chart.
If the long range chart is the weekly, we
divide by 5 to get the tactical chart, then
by 5 again to for the executional chart.
If the exact period chart doesn’t exist
on applying this rule, the closest one is
used.
If you prefer to hold your trades longer,
you might use the weekly, daily and h4.
For swing traders, the daily chart, the 4h
and 1 hour charts are best suited.
The 4 hour, 1 hour and 15 minutes are perfect
if you prefer day trading.
Choosing the right chart set depends on your
trading goals.
If you are a buy and hold, or sell and wait
trader, then a longer range setup is perhaps
going to be the best choice.
If you trade intraday on the other hand, you
might prefer short range set of charts.
Now, how to read the triple screen.
In order to identify the entries, elder’s
original system used a combination of MACD
and the force index, which are types of momentum
oscillators.
In practice though, there are a variety of
other indicators that will do the same job,
and work equally well or better.
I personally use the hull ma on the longer
term chart, the RSI on the intermediate chart
and I use price action on the short term chart,
to pinpoint the entry.
Timing is everything with most strategies,
and this one is no exception.
Triple screen doesn’t have a definitive
buy or sell signal.
It works as a system of confirmations from
one time frame to the next.
This is done in order to find a suitable time
to enter a trend in the likely direction the
market is moving.
This can be both a good thing and a bad thing.
Because while there are no rigid criteria,
this does mean you can incorporate your own
thinking into the strategy.
It also means you can make it simpler by using
fewer indicators.
So when to enter the market?
The time to buy in the triple screen is when
a bull trend has just undergone a correction
and is beginning to turn up again.
Conversely, the time to sell in the triple
screen is when a bear trend has just undergone
a correction and is beginning to turn down
again.
Here’s how it works: to identify this, first
pull up the longest range screen – in this
example we’ll use the daily chart.
First step: determine the trend: I use the
100 hull moving average line to confirm the
trend.
In this particular chart we see the general
direction of the trend is bearish.
Keep in mind that you can use any other tool
to determine the trend, elder used the MACD,
I use the 100 Hull ma, you can use your favorite
trend indicator.
Next we need to check the middle chart, and
in this example it is the h4 chart.
We use this chart to determine the market
momentum.
Using the RSI, I look at the chart to confirm
if a correction is completing.
What we are trying to determine here is that
the upward buying pressure from the correction
is reducing.
This means the flow of profit taking and other
buy orders has hit a peak.
It’s essential here as well that we check
to confirm this isn’t the start of a new
bull market.
If the upward correction is particularly strong,
you need to wait.
So we know that the daily trend is down, and
we also identified an upward correction on
the h4.
I’m also interested in the RSI value, I
want it to below 50 and stay below it.
Now, we add the execution chart, the 1 hour
chart.
On this chart we’re looking for the optimum
time to execute the sell order.
That means we look for evidence that the pullback
is completing and the market is reaching an
overbought point on this time scale.
I prefer to use simple price action, most
of the times i search for trendline breakouts.
In this case we see this upslope trendline,
which was broken to the downside, after a
correction, in the direction of the primary
trend on the daily chart.
When to exit the trade?
Normally there isn’t any take profit defined
for each order.
I prefer to use a trailing stop loss.
For this sell order, the exit stop loss is
gradually moved downwards as the market makes
lower lows.
This is done to lock in the profit.
The loss amount and the order sizes are set
according to your desired risk limits.
Let’s take another example.
The first screen – we analyze this time
frame to identify the direction of the larger
trend with a trend indicator.
Again, I use the 100 Hull ma.
Once the first screen identifies the direction
of the tide, this is the only direction in
which you will be allowed to trade when looking
at your intermediate chart.
So if your trend indicator signals that it
is an uptrend, like in this example, you can
only buy.
Second screen: once we know the direction
of the trend, we are looking for a wave in
the contrary direction on our intermediate
chart that will give us a beneficial entry.
So you are looking at the h4 chart as your
intermediate time frame, as the daily chart
showed that the larger trend is upward.
You are now looking for an h4 decline which
would provide you with an advantageous opportunity
to buy the market.
You would do this by searching for a buy signal
from your oscillator.
In this example, I use the RSI.
I want to see the RSI above 50.
Any sell signals in this case would be ignored
because the uptrend from the first screen
has already filtered those out.
We move to the third screen once we get an
agreement from the first and second screen:
that is, when the larger trend is up, and
an intermediate decline has generated a buy
signal from our oscillator.
In the third screen you determine the specific
entry point.
So you are aiming to go long in the market
with a h4 chart used in the second screen.
Like in the previous example, i prefer to
rely on price action to enter the market,
as I don’t like to use many indicators.
We have a nice trend line breakout on the
h1 chart, which gave us the green light to
enter long.
Here are other examples of triple screen trades.
The triple screen system can serve as a very
good basis for building your own trading strategy.
Its big advantage is the confluence of time
frames, with following only a long-term trend.
It’s not a perfect system by any means,
but it surely reduces the risk of entering
at wrong times in the market.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, don’t forget to subscribe,
click the bell icon to stay in touch with
new uploads and leave us a like to show your
support.
Until next time.