If you are a fan of trading with moving averages
and unfamiliar with the alligator technical
tool, get ready for an interesting strategy.
The Alligator is trading indicator created
by famous trader Bill Williams, which, just
like moving averages, is used to confirm ongoing
trends and their primary direction.
In addition to identifying existing trends,
you can also use the alligator indicator to
enter counter trend moves.
Alligator is a trend-following tool which
follows the premise that financial markets
and individual stocks trend just 15% to 30%
of the time while grinding through sideways
ranges the other 70% to 85% of the time.
The indicator has a funny name: it comes from
the head of an alligator.
As part of it, there are three averages.
Each average has a name related to an alligator’s
mouth: jaws, teeth and lips.
The alligator analogy is designed to help
describe some of the behaviors of the market
as it goes from non-trending to trending.
The idea is that the absence of a trend in
the market — meaning periods of sideways
movement — is like a sleeping alligator.
Eventually the alligator wakens and the longer
it has slept, the hungrier will be — in
other words, the more pronounced the trend
will be.
I know this analogy might seem funny, but
don’t exit the video yet and let me explain
further the usefulness of this indicator.
Bill Williams was insistent that a successful
trader will know the structure of the market.
In keeping with this line of thinking, the
Alligator indicator consists of three moving
averages, each smoothed over different time-frames,
which he called 'balance lines'.
By looking at the behavior of the balance
lines, we can determine the structure of the
market — in other words, whether we are
dealing with a sleeping alligator or not.
So Alligator uses three smoothed moving averages,
set at five, eight and 13 periods, which are
all Fibonacci numbers.
The three moving averages comprise the Jaw,
Teeth, and Lips of the Alligator, opening
and closing in reaction to evolving trends
and trading ranges:
Green moving average represents the lips of
the Alligator and is set to 5 and displaced
into the future by 3 periods
Red moving average is the Alligator teeth
and is set to 8 periods and is pushed 5 periods
into the future
Blue represents the jaws of the Alligator
and is set to 13 periods and displaced 8 periods
into the future
Now, How to Use the Alligator Indicator in
Trading
There are three key pieces of information
shown by the Alligator indicator: the absence
of a trend, the formation of a trend, and
the direction of the trend.
Let's discuss each of these, and see how we
can use them with Alligator indicator:
First.
The Absence of a Trend.
This is a common state and it's indicated
by those times when the three lines of the
Alligator indicator are close together or
intersected.
We can see it in this example, where the green,
the red, and the blue lines all stick close
together.
This means that the alligator is dormant — and
that the market is not really doing anything,
and that we are awaiting a change in state.
So when the 3 lines are intersected, we do
not have a trend.
This is generally a time of low volatility
and you may want to find another instrument
to trade.
Next.
The Formation of a Trend
A successful awakening of the alligator is
a crossover of the fast green line through
the slower lines, plus the slower lines following
that direction, and all three lines spreading
apart.
When the moving averages move wide apart like
in this example, the alligator is woke and
eating.
The longer the alligator has lain dormant,
the hungrier it is.
I know is cringey, but think of a market that
is ranging… we know it will break out and
the longer the range continues, the more violent
the breakout can be.
These periods of persistent trends are when
the indicator tends to be more effective.
So, the lips of the Alligator, the green line,
the fastest moving average, will be the first
one you will want to monitor.
You want to see the green line cross both
of the slower moving averages.
You will also see the lips and the jaw start
to turn in the direction of the green line.
As an entry point, many traders will enter
the market following a candle close above/below
all 3 lines.
Third phase.
Direction of the Trend
The direction is indicated by the movement
of the balance lines.
The green line is our fastest moving average,
and we expect this to move first, followed
by the red line, and then the blue line.
The green line crossing above the slower lines
represents a buy signal.
Crossing below represents a sell signal.
If all three move higher and widen, it confirms
an uptrend.
If the balance lines move downward and widen
after a sell signal, it confirms a downtrend.
As the trend comes to an end, the balance
lines draw closer together.
The fast green line crossing back over the
slower lines is the signal to take your profit.
The key strength of the indicator is the way
that it helps you to stick with a persistent
trend.
One of the drawbacks is the difficulty in
successfully reading the opening signals in
a timely manner.
During sleeping period, when the lines are
closed and intersected, you will see many
crossovers that look like trading signals.
The trouble is the timing — because if the
indicator lags at the start of a down trend
for example, and the fall was steep, you could
potentially miss the move.
The classical way to use The Alligator is
to look for “the perfect order”.
The three moving averages should NOT cross.
When doing that, the perfect order forms.
Moreover, this signals a strong trend.
But this isn’t the only way to use it.
Remember that this indicator shifts the moving
averages further in time.
This shifting allows for a greater flexibility.
In a way, it resembles the Ichimoku Cloud.
Traders familiar with cloud strategies know
the cloud, or “kumo” is shifted on the
right side of the chart!
Therefore, future support and resistance levels
appear at the present time.
A useful Alligator trading approach deals
with support and resistance levels.
And these levels are NOT horizontal.
You see, traders sometimes make a fatal mistake
believing that support and resistance can
only be horizontal.
But there are also dynamic levels.
Dynamic support and resistance move along
with the price.
Therefore, they offer more value.
The three moving averages that make the Alligator
indicator do exactly that.
They follow the price.
If the price rises, the three lines follow.
The bigger the distance between the lines,
the stronger the support and resistance area.
The bigger the time frame, the more difficult
for the price to break through.
In this way, the area between the first line
(the green one – lips) and the last one
(the blue one – jaws) is dynamic support
or resistance.
For example, in a bullish trend, it shows
support.
In a downtrend, it show resistance.
When the Alligator is feeding, watch for pullbacks
against the main trend direction and trade
those moves with a pullback strategy.
So here we have a bullish trend, with the
Alligator offering dynamic support.
It starts from the green line and ends with
the blue line.
The lips offer weak support.
If bears push stronger, they might reach the
teeth.
Jaws represent the final support.
Any move beyond and the trend is in danger.
Another useful Alligator approach consists
of analyzing the crossovers.
That means, the crosses between the three
lines that make the indicator.
A typical approach is to use the faster average
(the green line) for spotting fake crosses.
When the green line crosses the red one and
then turns again without reaching the blue
line, a fake move just forms.
Hence, in a bullish trend, you can search
for long entries after this crossover.
Or, in a bearish trend, go short when the
perfect order gets back in place.
Probably you’re familiar with the golden
and death crosses concept.
It calls for two big moving averages crossing.
When the fast one moves above the slow one,
a golden cross forms.
This is bullish.
When a death cross appears, the opposite is
true.
Bears are in control.
The Alligator could offer a similar interpretation.
The secret is to use the bigger averages in
the same way.
Therefore, use the red and blue lines as the
faster and slower averages.
A cross like this shows you the type of the
market: bullish or bearish.
Furthermore, use the green line of the Alligator
indicator as a confirmation.
Alligator indicator provides a useful visual
tool for trend recognition and trade entry
timing, but it has limited usefulness during
choppy and trendless periods.
Alternatively, you could try using a different
tool, such as a Momentum Indicator or a different
oscillator to look for price/momentum divergence,
as a way of confirming your trading signal.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.