Let me tell you a secret: price action and
candlestick psychology is what separates
the true market masters from the rest.
You see, every candlestick on your chart is
a visual representation of the decisions made
by thousands of traders, each acting on their
own beliefs, fears, and expectations.
Well, candlestick psychology is about
understanding that the market is
not just a series of random candles,
but a reflection of human behavior.
So let’s talk about it. This is
how I personally read each candle!
A long candlestick, also called a trend candle,
whether bullish or bearish, represents a
significant imbalance between buyers and
sellers during that time period.
The length of the candle body
reflects the intensity of this imbalance.
A long bullish candlestick forms when the
closing price is significantly
higher than the opening price.
In terms of supply and demand, this indicates
that buyers were in complete control during
this period. They aggressively bid up
prices, absorbing any available supply.
The lack of upper wick suggests that buyers
remained in control until the very end of the
candle, with the closing price near the high.
This type of candle often signals strong
bullish sentiment.
Buyers are confident
and willing to push prices higher.
It can potentially indicate the start of a new
uptrend or the continuation of an existing one.
The psychology here is one of optimism
and aggression from the buyers.
On the flip side, a long bearish
candlestick forms when the closing price is
significantly lower than the opening price.
This indicates that sellers dominated the
session, aggressively pushing prices lower.
The lack of lower wick suggests that
sellers remained in control until the close,
with the price ending near the low.
This type of candle signals strong
bearish sentiment. Sellers are confident and in
control, potentially indicating the start of a new
downtrend or the continuation of an existing one.
The psychology here is one of pessimism and
aggression from the sellers.
A short candlestick, whether
bullish or bearish, represents a period of
relative balance between buyers and sellers.
The small size of the candle body indicates
that neither side was able to gain a significant
advantage during that time frame.
From a supply and demand perspective,
a short candlestick suggests that the forces of
buying and selling were largely in equilibrium.
This type of candle often indicates a period
of indecision or consolidation in the market.
Neither buyers nor sellers have a clear advantage,
leading to a relatively narrow trading range.
The psychology here is one of uncertainty
and caution from both sides of the market.
When a series of short candlesticks appear,
it may show declining momentum in the current
trend or be a symptom of sideways movement.
A doji candle forms when the opening
and closing prices are virtually equal.
This means that despite any price
fluctuations during the period,
buyers and sellers were ultimately in balance,
neither side being able to gain the upper hand.
From a supply and demand perspective, a doji
represents a moment of indecision, a pause
in the ongoing war between buyers and sellers.
As the candle opens, buyers attempt to bid prices
higher, while sellers attempt to drive prices
lower. Over the course of the period, neither
side is able to maintain a significant advantage.
Every advance by the buyers is met with equal
selling pressure, and every decline instigated
by the sellers is met with equal buying support.
This back-and-forth results in the price
oscillating around the open, ultimately
closing at or very near the same level.
From a psychological standpoint,
a doji suggests that the market is
at a crossroads. The previous trend,
whether bullish or bearish, has lost momentum.
Market participants are reassessing their
positions, reevaluating their convictions in light
of new information or shifting market dynamics.
This moment of collective hesitation can be
a precursor to significant market moves.
Candlesticks with long upper and lower wicks
on both sides of the real body represent a
period of significant volatility and indecision.
As the candle opens, buyers push prices higher,
as indicated by the long upper wick.
This shows that there was significant
buying pressure during this period.
However, at the higher prices, sellers
stepped in aggressively, driving prices back down.
The long lower wick shows that sellers were able
to push prices significantly lower.
But here they meet strong opposition.
Buyers re-entered the market at these
lower prices, bidding prices back up.
This back-and-forth between buyers and
sellers continues throughout the period,
resulting in a relatively small real body (which
is the difference between the open and close),
compared to the total range of the candle
(the distance from the high to the low).
From a psychological perspective, these
candles indicate a market in a state of
high uncertainty and indecision.
Neither buyers nor sellers are
able to maintain control for long.
The long wicks on both sides suggest
that both bullish and bearish sentiment is
present, but neither side has a clear advantage.
This type of price action often occurs
at key turning points in the market,
or after a prolonged trend.
It signifies that the previous
trend is losing momentum and that a shift
in market sentiment may be underway.
Candlesticks with long upper wicks and little
to no lower wick can signal a potential shift
in market sentiment and supply/demand dynamics.
As the candle opens, buyers are in control. They
aggressively push prices higher, extending the
uptrend or rally from the previous periods.
This buying pressure is reflected in
the long upper wick, which shows the
highest price reached during the period.
As prices reach these levels sellers begin
to emerge, stepping in to take advantage of
what they perceive as overextended prices.
They start to outweigh the buyers, creating
selling pressure that drives prices back down.
From a supply and demand perspective,
these candles indicate a potential
exhaustion point in an uptrend.
At the higher prices, supply begins
to outweigh demand as more participants view
the price as overextended and look to sell.
This shift in the supply/demand balance is what
causes the price to fall back from the highs.
Psychologically, these candles can signal
a potential change in market sentiment.
The long upper wick suggests that the bullish
momentum that drove prices higher is decreasing.
It's a visual representation of a
"buying exhaustion" - the point at
which the upward trend loses steam as fewer
buyers are willing to push prices higher.
The candlestick with only a long lower wick can
also signal a potential shift in market sentiment.
As the period begins, sellers are firmly
in control. They aggressively push prices
lower, extending the downtrend or
decline from the previous periods.
This selling pressure is reflected
in the long lower wick, which shows
the lowest price reached during the timeframe.
However, buyers are sensing an opportunity in the
oversold conditions, and they start to step in.
They begin to outweigh the sellers, creating a
buying pressure that drives prices back up.
From a supply and demand perspective,
these candles indicate a potential
exhaustion point in a downtrend.
At the lower prices, demand
begins to outweigh supply
as more participants view the price
as undervalued and looked to buy.
This shift in the supply/demand balance is what
caused the price to rebound from the lows.
Psychologically, these candles can signal
a potential change in market sentiment.
It's a visual representation of a "selling
climax" - the point at which the downward
trend loses steam as fewer sellers
are willing to drive prices lower.
Gap candles reflect dramatic shifts in
overnight sentiment and supply/demand dynamics.
An up gap candle occurs when the lowest price
of a candle is higher than the highest price
of the previous candle.
Visually, this leaves a
blank space or "gap" on the chart.
Psychologically, an up gap candle
suggests a significant shift in sentiment in
favor of the buyers. It indicates that buying
pressure has intensified dramatically, to the
point where sellers were unable to drive the
price down to the level of the previous close.
It could reflect a more gradual shift in market
psychology, where a critical mass of buyers has
decided that the current price is undervalued.
Either way, the up gap signals that
demand has suddenly outpaced supply,
and that the balance of power has shifted
decisively in favor of the buyers.
This can serve as a powerful signal to look for
buying opportunities, as the increased buying
pressure could lead to further upside momentum.
A down gap candle occurs when the highest price
of a candle is lower than the
lowest price of the previous one.
Psychologically, this suggests a significant
shift in sentiment in favor of the sellers.
Selling pressure has intensified dramatically,
to the point where buyers were unable to drive
the price up to the level of the previous close.
It could reflect a more gradual shift in market
psychology, where a critical mass of sellers has
decided that the current price is overvalued.
This increased selling pressure could
lead to further downside momentum.
Also, gap candles don't always lead to
continued movement in the direction of the gap.
Sometimes, a gap candle can be a signal
of exhaustion, where the move has
pushed the price to an unsustainable
level, leading to a rapid reversal.
This is why many traders pay close attention
to gap fills - instances where the price moves
back to fill the blank space left by the gap.
Now, very important: we're often tempted to react
immediately to a single dramatic candle.
For example, you're watching a market
that's been in a steady uptrend, and
suddenly, a massive candle appears,
much bigger than the previous candles.
It's a bearish, compelling pattern, no doubt!
But here's the thing: the market is a
complex, noisy place. At any given moment,
there are many factors influencing price action.
A single candle, no matter how dramatic,
is just a snapshot of a very brief period
of time. It doesn't tell the whole story.
That single dramatic candle it's
worth noting, but it's not enough
on its own to base a conviction on.
You need to gather more evidence.
This is a critical lesson for all traders to
learn, but especially for beginners. The market
has a way of generating all sorts of dramatic,
compelling signals on a minute-by-minute basis.
It's easy to get caught up in the excitement,
to feel like you need to react to every candle.
But the successful traders, the ones
who last in this game, know better.
They know that the real edge comes not from
reacting to every signal, but from patiently
waiting for the high-quality setups.
That’s why in the future videos,
I plan to talk about the psychology of support
and resistance levels, and how to combine them
with candlestick analysis. And in the meantime, go
ahead and watch one of these price action videos.