how do you know if a market is about to
switch from a consolidation to a full
trend
this may be obvious in hindsight when
you look at the previous charts
but in real time this is a major
challenge for all traders
you know the situation you've got a
setup that you like on a market that you
follow
but the market looks like it's in a
range what do you do
you take the signal or wait luckily for
us there's an interesting tool that can
help to detect when such a switch from
consolidation to trend might be near
in today's video we'll discuss about the
ttm squeeze indicator
and i will share how to use it and how
to trade with it to find the best setups
ttm squeeze is a volatility and momentum
indicator
which is based on the tendency for price
to break out strongly after
consolidating in a small price action
range
trading price action is a pretty
straightforward idea of understanding
support and resistance levels
however understanding momentum and the
direction of price at these levels is
probably
one of the most difficult concepts for
many traders
being able to spot momentum increasing
or decreasing at these levels
makes the difference between success and
failure when entering trades
that's why ttm squeeze makes spotting
momentum changes
and incoming volatility much easier
the ttm squeeze indicator visualize the
relationship between the bollinger bands
and the kelvin channels which helps to
identify when an asset is consolidating
meaning squeezing and signals when
prices are poised to break out
if the bollinger bands are completely
enclosed within the keltner channel
that indicates a period of very low
volatility
this state is known as the squeeze when
the bollinger bands expand
and move back outside of the keltner
channel volatility increases
and prices are likely to break out of
that trading range
in one direction or the other the ttm
squeeze is comprised of two main
components
first is the momentum oscillator this is
the vertical histogram which indicates
the direction of momentum
the green vertical lines is positive
momentum and the red vertical lines is
negative momentum
in relationship to their positions above
or below the horizontal zero line
the zero line is the second component
this horizontal line is where the
squeeze is visualized by a series of
green and red dots
green dots are a condition of no squeeze
and the red dots
are when the price is squeezing the
squeeze signal
meaning the red dots appears when the
bollinger bands are squeezed into the
keltner channel
now let's actually add the bollinger
bands and the keltner channel to the
charts
as seen these squeeze conditions
represent the consolidation of price
with bollinger bands within the keltner
channel which corresponds to a series of
red dots
appearing along with the zero line on
the ttm
increase in momentum is represented by
higher bars on the momentum histogram on
the ttm
and the expanding of the bollinger bands
with the release of the squeeze seeing
the red dots turning green
the ttm squeeze indicator helps to take
a lot of the guesswork
out of the momentum equation with a
simplified representation
of what's happening when the bollinger
bands and the keltner channel
enter a consolidation phase and you have
a much simpler and cleaner
chart so how to read and how to trade
with the ttm squeeze
i said before the ttm squeeze has both
volatility and momentum components
the squeeze dots signal volatility
conditions while the momentum histogram
indicates the direction long or short in
which to trade
in the ttm squeeze we have a horizontal
line that changes color between green
and red
this represents the situation of the
market in the current moment
if we happen to found that the dtm
squeeze horizontal line is red
it means that the market is in a
consolidation period and is not ready to
move just yet
however if we finally spot the green dot
after
a series of red dots in the middle line
this means that the market is finally
ready to move
and it will most likely do it in a
somewhat aggressive way
because volatility increases and the
bollinger bands expand
until they are outside of the keltner
channel the author of the indicator
recommends taking a trade on the first
green dot after
one or more red dots but the question
that remains is
in which direction will the market move
now the momentum histogram helps to
determine the direction in which to
trade
if the momentum is above the zero line
and rising
long trades are recommended if the
histogram is below the zero line
and falling lower short trades are
recommended
the histogram bars are color coded bars
above the zero line are green
and below the zero line are red in
addition a bar that is lower than the
previous bar will be a darker color
and a bar that is higher than the
previous bar will be a lighter color
when the histogram changes direction and
starts moving back towards the zero line
that's a signal to sell the momentum
histogram can also be used to determine
specific exit points
like selling when you had two bars in
the new color
for example if the squeeze fires and the
bars are above the zero line and
increasing
you could sell when you see two bars in
a row above the zero line
and decreasing just to be clear
when you analyze a market your focus
should be on the zero line
the red dots by themselves are not a
signal for entering a trade
but should be used in combination with
the vertical momentum bars
as the momentum bars near the zero line
this is the signal or condition that we
should be looking for
which indicates that momentum is
shifting into positive or negative
territory
once these conditions are met an entry
can be considered
there are many options about when to
enter the trade at this point
once a momentum shift has been confirmed
some traders
do so on the first bar others after one
or two bars have been confirmed
this is something that you will have to
determine on your own
in this 15-minute chart we have marked
several squeeze signals
the first squeeze is quite clear it is
marked on the left side of the chart
as you can see the ttm squeeze indicator
is telling us that there is a movement
ready to go in price
and it will most likely be bearish as
the red bars appeared exactly with a
squeeze
however the second squeeze direction is
not so clear
the ttm squeeze histogram tells us that
it will most likely be a bearish one
but the truth is that it ended being a
bully squeeze in any case
this is a perfect example of why we
should be using stop loss orders to
avoid extreme losses
the third squeeze even when it takes
some time to finally move
does it to the upside here's another
example on the one hour time frame
the ttm squeeze gives a perfect long
entry
several red dots appeared indicating the
market has built enough consolidation
energy
and is ready for a squeeze the red dots
have a green histogram
rising upwards indicating that there is
bullish momentum
lurking beneath this energy the previous
trend was also bullish
an important aspect to consider when
analyzing a setup
my preference is to look for squeeze
trades in the direction of the main
trend
in this case as expected the market
responds with an aggressive spike
upwards
don't expect the market to move
immediately after that color change
in some cases the market will take some
time to start a new move
up or down here's an example to
illustrate this 21 hour time frame
we can observe the red dots shift to
green dots
and we know there is bearish momentum
behind the potential squeeze
an ideal entry for a short trade the
setup was obvious for a short rate
but the price didn't move right away in
the expected direction
we had to wait a bit longer before the
move came and of course
in some cases it will move in the
opposite direction so make sure your
risk and money management is on point
here are other examples of valid traits
[Music]
another way dtm squeeze indicator can be
traded is by using divergence
divergence is when instagram momentum
bars begin to slope toward
or away from the zero line and the price
moves in the opposite direction
on the upper part of the chart bearish
divergence
is when price is making higher highs but
the slopes of the histogram on the ttm
are making lower highs on the positive
side of the zero line
voltage divergence is when the price is
making lower lows
but the histogram is sloping toward the
zero line from the negative side of the
line
like any other technical indicator the
ttm is no magic bullet
and it would be best used with other
indicators as a confirmation of price
direction
you could add a moving average or the
ichimoku cloud for example
or even switch to a high kanashi chart
to visualize the main trend better
also the ttm squeeze can be used in many
time frames
my preference is to look at the same
market in multiple time frames for
confirmation
for example if a squeeze is firing on
both a daily and an hourly chart at the
same time
that's a stronger signal than a squeeze
that is only firing in one time frame
[Music]
so
lower time frames are typically used as
entry and exits
to support the higher time frame when
day trading or swing trading
just remember these steps find areas of
consolidation
with the red dots look for momentum to
break out
in the direction of the main trend and
confirm the movement
with a higher time frame if you learned
something new and found value
leave us a like to show support and
don't forget to subscribe and hit that
bell icon to get notified when we
release new videos
until next time