Many traders and investors use indicators
to spot market patterns and trends and most
of these indicators fall into two types: leading
and lagging.
A leading indicator is a tool designed to
anticipate the future direction of a market,
in order to enable traders to predict market
movements ahead of time.
In theory, if a leading indicator gives the
correct signal, a trader can get in before
the market movement and ride the entire trend.
However, leading indicators are by no means
100% accurate, which is why they are often
combined with other forms of technical analysis.
A lagging indicator is a tool that provides
delayed feedback, which means it gives a signal
once the price movement has already passed
or is in progress.
These are used by traders to confirm the price
trend before they enter a trade.
These indicators are commonly used by trend
traders, they don’t show any upcoming price
moves but confirm that a trend is underway.
This tends to give traders more confidence
that they are correct in their assumptions,
rather than providing a specific trigger for
entering the market.
So, what’s the difference between Leading
and lagging technical indicators?
The most obvious difference is that leading
indicators predict market movements, while
lagging indicators confirm trends that are
already taking place.
Both leading and lagging indicators have their
own advantages and drawbacks, so it’s crucial
to analyze yourself with how each works and
decide which fits in with your strategy.
Leading indicators react to prices quickly,
which can be great for short-term traders,
but makes them prone to giving out false signals.
Conversely, lagging indicators are far slower
to react, which means that traders would have
more accuracy but could be late in entering
the market.
Leading indicators react to prices quickly,
which can be great for short-term traders,
but makes them prone to giving out false signals.
Conversely, lagging indicators are far slower
to react, which means that traders would have
more accuracy but could be late in entering
the market.
Lagging indicators are tools used by traders
to analyze the market using an average of
previous price action data.
As the name implies, these indicators lag
the market.
This means that traders can witness a move
before the indicator confirms it – meaning
that the trader could lose out the start of
the move.
Many consider this as a necessary cost in
order to confirm if the move gathers momentum.
Others view this as a lost opportunity as
traders are missing getting into a trade at
the very start of a move.
A lagging indicator often makes use of price
as an input variable and in most cases, requires
a longer look back period in order to ascertain
trends.
Even with the delayed feedback, many traders
prefer to use lagging technical indicators
as it helps them to trade with more confidence
by validating their trade decisions.
Usually traders make use of two or more lagging
indicators to confirm price trends before
entering the trade.
This can be viewed as a conservative way to
trade, but do not let this draw you into a
false sense of security that you can make
the best decisions and make money consistently.
Let’s look at a classic example of a lagging
indicator, namely the moving average.
In this set up we added a 50-period and a
200-period moving average, to trade the golden
and a death crosses, which are bullish and
bearish crossovers of the 50 and 200 SMA’s.
Generally, the asset is said to be bearish
when the 50 SMA crosses below the 200 SMA
and bullish when the 50 SMA crosses above
the 200 SMA.
In this chart notice that the signals generated
by the bullish and the bearish crossovers
of the 200 and 50 period moving averages occur
very late.
In the first signal for example, if you went
short after the bearish signal, it would have
been a losing trade.
This is because by the time price moved lower
and the moving average reacted to this, price
already fell significantly and started to
pull back higher.
I’ve also read a lot of false information
regarding RSI, Stochastic and other Momentum
oscillators, which were associated with the
leading indicators category.
No, they are not leading indicators.
Although those indicators will generate a
lot of good signals if traded correctly, they
will not lead the price.
Just because they tell you how overbought
or oversold a market is, this doesn’t mean
that they are leading the price.
Now, I’m not saying you shouldn’t use
lagging indicators, because they can help
you make informed decisions.
Just remember that lagging indicators can
only provide “today’s “value based on
the historical data.
Since these indicators lag the price of the
asset, a significant move in the market generally
occurs before the indicator can provide a
signal.
The truth is that almost every technical indicator
is a lagging indicator.
Moving averages, MACD, the RSI, Stochastics,
you name it, are lagging.
First there's a move in price, then sometime
later in the game, the indicator signals buy
or sell signal.
They lag behind market action.
They give signals after the fact.
It is really important for you to understand
how the lagging indicators work and how the
data is compiled before incorporating them
into trading strategies and risking capital
on those strategies.
Always remember that the price moves indicators
– not the other way around.
This is why they always look profitable when
you look at them at the left side of the chart
when the price action is already unfolded.
Leading indicators are different.
Leading indicators are indicators able to
precede the price movements of an asset due
to their predictive qualities.
While, lagging indicators follow price movements
and don’t have reliable predictive qualities,
leading indicators are able to anticipate
when major moves in the markets would occur.
A leading technical indicator is designed
to anticipate future price moves in order
to give an edge.
As magical as this sounds, a leading indicator
relies upon the most common variable – price.
A Leading indicator will allow you to anticipate
future price movements and therefore, you
will be able to enter trades potentially at
the start of the move.
The downside is that traders are anticipating
a move before it actually happens and the
market could move in the opposite direction.
As a result, it isn’t uncommon to witness
false breakouts, or, signs of a trend reversal
that just land up being minor retracements.
So which indicators or tools I consider to
be leading indicators.
Well, pivot points are leading indicators.
Pivot Points are levels that were used by
floor traders to determine directional movement
and potential support/resistance levels.
By analyzing today’s high, low, and close,
you are able to calculate the next day’s
pivot point, as well as potential support
and resistance levels.
Part of what makes the Pivots Points so reliable
is the fact that they are based purely on
price.
Plotting these levels allows you to know in
advance some key levels for the next day.
You know that if the price reaches this area,
for example, there will be a reaction: a rejection
or a breakout.
Fibonacci Retracements and extensions are
also leading tools.
This means that you can decide on the likely
direction ahead of it happening as compared
to a lagging indicator which only predicts
movements after it has already started to
occur.
As Fibonacci is a leading indicator you will
see the entry point and place an order in
advance of the market reaching your desired
level.
Other traders also consider volume as a leading
indicator, but only in conjunction with price.
Trend lines, support and resistance levels
can also be considered leading tools, because
you can plot them on your chart and find levels
where the price can react.
Leading indicators tell you ahead of time
where the market is likely to find support
or where the market is likely to find resistance.
Now, SHOULD YOU USE LEADING OR LAGGING INDICATORS?
For traders, it is often the dilemma of finding
a balance between them.
Rely only on leading indicators and chances
are you will see a lot of false signals.
Rely only on lagging indicators and you will
likely enter late and hold on your trades
too long and give back most of the profits.
Traders looking for fast signals will tend
to favor leading indicators.
Traders seeking a greater degree of confidence
will tend to favor lagging indicators.
The trick is to achieve the proper balance
by mixing leading and lagging indicators across
time frames.
If you can accomplish this objective, you
can come up with a trading approach which
is far superior to using either of the two
exclusively.
With these obvious drawbacks, it is best to
develop a trading strategy that combines both
leading and lagging indicators.
For example, you can use a lagging indicator,
like a 200 EMA and a leading one, the pivot
points.
First, determine the context for the trade
using the lagging indicators.
So if the price is below the 200 EMA, we have
a downtrend, and above 200 EMA, an uptrend.
Then establish the entry level using the leading
indicator, namely the pivot point.
You can buy a pullback for example, at the
central pivot point, when the market is above
200 EMA, in the direction of the trend.
You can continue to use the leading indicator
to find a stop placement point, meaning your
stop loss order.
In the case of this uptrend, this would be
below a substantial support level, maybe below
S1 level.
Or you can use a Fibonacci retracement and
an oscillator, like the Stochastic, again
a leading and a lagging tool, side by side.
You can enter after a Stochastic divergence,
or an oversold Stochastic, when the price
rejected an important FIB level.
Again, try find the proper balance by mixing
leading and lagging indicators, with the aim
of stacking the odds in your favor.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support, subscribe
to our channel and click the bell icon to
stay in touch when we upload new videos.
Until next time.