have you ever wondered why 90% of
traders lose money while trading did you
know that almost 80% of traders quit in
the first two years of unsuccessful
trading the harsh reality is that
trading is not easy and you as a trader
must know exactly what you're doing if
you want to stick around in the game for
the long term hay traders this is marios
I traded the forex market for the past
ten years and if you stick with me a
couple of minutes I will share with you
my most important lessons I've learned
so that you don't make the same mistakes
I did
the first lesson I've learned is that
overbought and oversold levels are not
reliable in the long term when I started
trading I took the advice I read on
different books about the overbought and
oversold levels and you know what the
majority of books teach us that if a
market reaches overbought levels meaning
that there are too many buyers on the
market then the prices should go lower
and different market which is oversold
levels meaning that there are too many
sellers on the market the prices should
increase after a lot of money lost I
realized that the trading reality is
that simply because the market which is
overbought or oversold levels does not
mean that the market prices will
immediately reverse in the opposite
direction during periods of strong
upward trends or downward trends the
markets can remain in the overbought or
oversold areas for days weeks or even
months let's look at this chart many
traders believe that when the RSI or the
stochastic indicator hits or exceeds
values of seventy or thirty they should
enter in the opposite direction that's a
wrong approach to what concerns these
indicators sometimes the prices can stay
a long time in the overbought and
oversold areas and during this time they
can continue to go higher or lower for
every valid overbought or oversold
signal offered by these indicators there
are other
ten false signals in the long run
chasing overbought and oversold levels
is not profitable I have stopped
watching these levels a long time ago
and never looked back another lesson is
that the 200 DMA was the only moving
average I needed on my charts let me ask
you if this sounds familiar you plot
five or six indicators on the chart and
after a bad week you remove those
indicators and add others and the next
week you repeat this process once again
this was my style when I started trading
my charts consisted of many indicators
once I removed from my charts all the
other indicators and moving averages and
focused only on the 200 EMA my trading
improved a lot the 200 EMA turned out to
be very effective during training
periods and an important tool for
identifying trends for establishing
potential areas of dynamic support or
resistance and even accurate entry
points on the market why is the 200 EMA
so reliable in the technical analysis
well it is believed that many
institution like banks hedge funds Forex
dealers are following this indicator if
we take a look at this EMA on any
currency pair commodity or even
cryptocurrencies we can immediately see
its value another lesson was that demo
trading won't accurately predict how you
will perform when trading with real
money the reason is simple and obvious
if there is no money on the line you
eliminate one of the most important
variables that affect your trading
decisions the psychological pressure of
risking real money even if you perform
extremely well when trading a demo
account your results when you start to
trade on a live account might differ
considerably so you should demo your
strategy until you feel comfortable
taking your signals what I personally
would not get focused on demo accounts
for too long once you tested your
strategy and managed to have a positive
returns on
demo open a micro account and trade
there for a couple of months start small
with few money and trade with sense
instead of dollars even if you trade
with sense you will feel the market much
better than trading on a demo account
another critical lesson was that losing
money is in fact a good thing as I said
before trading is not easy and you
should treat it as a learning experience
losing money is very important for every
traders development it will teach you
many things that you are not aware of
now don't get me wrong
losing is not fun and you will probably
find it very unpleasant while it's not
enjoyable to lose money while trading in
the end you will learn more from taking
a loss than from a winning trade the
important thing when you lose money is
to learn from this experience and not to
do the same thing again you get an
education for that lost money and come
out a little smarter in the future
believe me once you learn an important
lesson when losing money this prevents a
much larger future loss another lesson
was that you should trade a strategy
that matches your personality when I
started trading I found an online course
that was teaching sculpting they claimed
a high success rate and I tried their
approach for a couple of weeks after
that I was down 20% in my account you
see the key to successful trading is
finding a strategy that works and that
fits your personality the reason I was
struggling with scalping was because I
didn't enjoy that fast paced trading
style I didn't want to monitor the price
section very closely and I didn't want
to sit all day in front of the screen
even if their trading strategy worked it
did not fit my personality so I ended up
losing a lot of money my advice for you
is to find your risk aversion your risk
tolerance you should look for the
timeframe that matches
your training style see if you are
day-trader a swing trader a position
trader or a scalper ask yourself if you
are a technical trader or if you prefer
fundamental setups choose the indicators
or other tools that you feel most
comfortable trading with these simple
elements will help you in establishing a
strategy that will fit your personality
the final lesson was probably the most
important one when I stopped thinking
about the huge profits I could make and
focused on preserving my capital I
noticed a vast improvement in my trading
results successful traders concentrate
their efforts on how much money they
could lose before thinking about how
much money they could win the key to
making money over the long term from
trading is simply staying in the game
you need to preserve your capital so
that you can stay in a game long enough
to see your trading system reward you
when I started trading I had a gamblers
mentality and I suspect a lot of you
have this mentality too I focused almost
entirely on how much money I could win
with almost no regard for losses when
you start trading you should ask ask
yourself when I will become profitable
you should ask yourself how can I trade
while preserving my capital and what
should I do to limit my losses and be in
the game one month one year from now so
in order to be successful you first need
to become a break-even trader the beauty
of being a break-even trader is that you
protect your capital while gaining
market experience you don't lose money
and guess what you will be ahead of 90%
of traders those were the most important
lessons I've learned in the past ten
years during my trading journey I've had
my ups and downs I am still losing
trades and I still have my doubts when
taking a trade but there's the job of a
trader and whoever tells you that
waiting is easy well is lying to you
if you got
any value from this video please
consider subscribing to this channel and
give us a like as it will help us to
grow in the future until next time
[Music]