Support and resistance levels and supply and
demand zones are two trading concepts which
are closely related to one another.
They each define points in the market where
the price is likely to reverse.
The main difference between the two, is that
supply and demand areas have a zone which
you can use to look for entries, and support
and resistance levels are simply lines which
you can monitor for entries.
In today’s video I will share an effective
swing trading strategy and I will show you
how I combine both trading concepts to time
the markets and find high probability signals.
Many traders think there aren’t many differences
between supply and demand zones and support
and resistance levels, but in reality there
are actually quite significant, because having
a zone you can use to watch for entries is
much easier than having a line.
That, coupled with the fact that supply and
demand zones form less frequently than support
and resistance levels, means that it’s easier
to trade reversals from supply and demand
zones than it is from support and resistance
levels.
And this is why the strategy of combining
both concepts work.
The aim here is to combine the preciseness
of support and resistance levels with the
area aspect of supply and demand.
In this way, we will be able to pinpoint entries
into supply and demand zones.
The main problem with trading support and
resistance levels alone is the fact that the
market will often fail to turn exactly on
the level itself.
Tell me if this sound familiar.
A lot of the time, price will either move
slightly beyond the level before reversing,
or will reverse before touching the level.
This can make trading support and resistance
levels quite a frustrating experience.
You almost never have this problem when trading
supply and demand zones.
The reason why is because the zones give you
an area in which you know the market should
reverse in.
You don’t really have to worry about a reversal
signal forming at an exact point, like you
do when trading support and resistance levels,
because you’ve got a whole zone you can
use to watch for entries into trades.
You know that no matter where the reversal
signal ends up forming, as long as it’s
found to be somewhere inside the supply or
demand zone, it’s a sign a reversal could
be taking place.
Determining where support and resistance lines
are located is quite a simple process.
For those of you who don’t know, support
and resistance lines are points where the
market has a high probability of reversing.
The reason they have a high chance of causing
the market to reverse, is because the lines
are derived from the points where the market
has reversed in the past.
The idea is if the market has reversed multiple
times from roughly the same point in the past,
then it has a good chance of doing the same
in the future.
This means all we need to do to identify where
support and resistance lines are located in
the market, is look for the points where multiple
reversals originated from similar prices to
one another.
Here’s an example with multiple reversals
which took place.
You can see that each of the reversals originated
from prices which are quite close to one another.
This tells us that a resistance line must
be found somewhere close to where these reversals
started.
And here are other multiple reversals.
Again, each one of the reversals you see here
started from similar prices, which means there’s
a support line around here.
Now, because this is a swing trading approach,
meaning the lowest time frame I would analyze
the market is the one hour chart, I look for
the big round numbers which are closest to
the lines I marked through the reversals which
took place at similar prices.
The reason why support and resistance lines
are always found to be at big round number
levels is because of a phenomenon called order
clustering.
Order clustering is where orders will accumulate
around round number levels in the market.
So, in the first step of our strategy, you
have to identify the support and resistance
lines by marking the points where multiple
reversals occurred on your chart.
Then you have to mark the round numbers, which
are found closest to these reversals, and
finally, you have to move the lines so they
sit on top of the round number prices.
Here you can see what the chart looks like
once I’ve adjusted the reversals lines to
go through the round numbers.
These lines are now the correct support and
resistance lines you will use to look for
entries into buy trades if the market returns
to the lines in the future.
The second step consists in drawing supply
and demand zones.
Supply zones can be located by looking for
a major drop away from either a single candle
or small consolidation structure.
You mark the supply zone from the open of
last BULLISH candle before the drop and the
most recent high before the drop.
Demand zones are found when the market makes
a large move up from a single candle or a
consolidation structure.
You mark the demand zone from the open of
last BEARISH candle before the drop and the
most recent low before the up move.
If you want more details about supply and
demand zones, make sure you watch this video
first.
Third step is to identify confluence areas.
If you combine support and resistance levels
with supply and demand zones you can get the
best of both worlds.
You can eliminate the issue not knowing if
the market failing to touch the level or just
moving beyond the level is still a reversal
signal, whilst also having a better idea of
where a reversal out of the supply or demand
zone is likely to take place from.
Here’s an example of a demand zone which
caused a reversal to take place.
The lines you see here are all the support
and resistance levels which had formed inside
the demand zone.
The market reversed out of the zone after
hitting the lower support level found at this
round number.
Here’s another demand zone.
This zone also contained three support levels
which had the potential to cause the market
to reverse once it entered the zone.
In real time, you wouldn’t know which of
these levels the market was going to reverse
at before the price dropped into it, you would
just know that it’s almost certain for it
to reverse at one of these levels.
In this instance it ended up turning once
it hit the support level found at this round
number price.
If we go onto the 15 minute chart you can
see that when the market hit the support level
a couple of bullish engulfing candles began
to form.
You could have used these engulfing candles
to get a buy trade placed to take advantage
of the reversal, knowing that any reversal
out of the demand zone is likely to begin
once the market has hit one of the support
levels inside the zone.
How To Trade Support And Resistance Levels
Inside Supply And Demand Zones
Like I said, the reality is that that you
don’t know which support or resistance level
inside the zone is going to cause the market
to reverse, and this means that you can’t
really use a pending order to enter a trade.
The only other option is to watch for a price
action signal to form when the market hits
one of the support or resistance levels.
Now, once you’ve got the support and resistance
levels and supply and demand zones marked
correctly, you need to begin watching the
levels for potential entries.
The best way of doing this is to switch to
a lower time-frame and monitor the price action
that forms when the market starts to encounter
each of the levels inside the zone.
This example shows the price structure which
formed on the 15 minute chart when the market
hit each support level found inside the demand
zone.
You can see that when the market hit the first
support level a bullish engulfing candle formed
and caused a slight move higher to take place.
This move ended up failing and caused the
market to fall down to the other support level
found below.
The second support level caused another engulfing
candle to form and pushed the market above
the high of the upswing created.
There are two ways in which you could have
traded the bullish engulfing candles.
After seeing one of the engulfing candles
form, you could have entered a buy trade with
your stop loss placed below the nearest support
level.
Or you could have entered a trade with a stop
loss placed at the edge of the demand zone
itself.
Usually having the stop placed at the edge
of the zone is the better option, because
it will save you from any spikes which may
occur after getting your trade.
Lets take a look at another example.
Here’s another demand zone.
I’ve marked the support and resistance levels
found in and around this demand zone on the
chart.
Lets now go down to the 15 minute chart to
see if there was a price action signal we
could have used to get a buy trade placed
when the market was inside this demand zone.
On the 15 minute chart we can see that when
the market hit the support level found in
the middle of the demand zone two bullish
engulfing candles formed.
The first caused the market to move out of
the zone, but did not cause it to reverse
completely, while the second did cause the
market to reverse out of the zone.
You can also look for other price action patterns
to get your signal, pin bars representing
other great price action signals.
Your entry into this trade would be on one
of the bullish engulfing candles that formed
after the market hit the support level.
Your stop loss on either trade would be placed
at the support level which makes up the edge
of the demand zone.
When you’ve got yourself into a profitable
trade, and the market has reversed out of
the supply or demand zone, the final step
to do is take some profits off the trade,
to make sure you don’t end up coming out
of the trade with nothing if the price action
changes and causes the market to move against
your position.
The best time to take profits is after you’ve
seen the market makes a new higher high, if
you’ve got a buy trade placed into the market,
or after a new lower low has formed, if you’ve
got a sell trade placed.
You either move you stop loss higher or you
partially close half of your position.
Of course, exiting the trade always comes
down to your personal preference.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.