Have you ever heard of the phrase “the trend
is your friend” when trading or investing”?
Sure you have.
Of course, most profits are generated when
markets are trending, but, I have to disagree
with this quote.
The correct phrase is “the trend is your
friend, if it can be found”.
If you cannot tell if a market is trending
or not, the trend has no use to you, you cannot
profit from it.
There are many ways that can help you to spot
a trend, and one of the best approaches is
with Heikin-Ashi candlesticks.
So, today we’ll talk about Heikin-Ashi charts,
you’ll discover the importance of adding
them into your trading arsenal and you’ll
learn how to use them to stay on the right
side of the market.
Before we continue, if you’re new here,
make sure you subscribe, turn on the notifications
and leave us a like to show your support.
So, Heikin-Ashi is a Japanese technique based
on the candlestick theory but taking it to
a higher level for trend determination.
Heiken means average and ashi means pace,
taken together Heikin-Ashi represents the
average pace of prices.
A Heikin-Ashi chart look like the classic
candlestick chart.
But the method of calculating and plotting
the candlesticks on the Heikin-Ashi chart
is different from the regular candlestick
chart.
On the candlestick charts, each candlestick
is independent and has no relationship with
the previous or next candlesticks.
But Heikin-Ashi candlesticks are different
and each candlestick is calculated and plotted
using some information from the previous candlestick:
1.
Open price:
The open price in a Heikin-Ashi candlestick,
is the average of the open and close price
of the previous candlestick.
2.
Close price:
The close price in a Heikin-Ashi candlestick,
is the average of the open, close, high and
low prices.
3.
High price:
The high price in a Heikin-Ashi candlestick,
is chosen from one of the high, open and close
price of which has the highest value.
4.
Low price:
The low price in a Heikin-Ashi candlestick
is chosen from one of the low, open and close
price of which has the lowest value.
The major difference between Heikin-Ashi and
regular candlestick chart is the way up candles
and down candles are formed.
In order for an up candle to form on a traditional
candlestick chart, the closing price must
be above the opening price; a down candle
forms when the closing price is below the
opening price.
In a Heikin-Ashi chart, an up candle forms
when the price closes above the midpoint of
the prior candle and a down candle forms when
price closes below the midpoint of the prior
candle.
This important difference is why Heikin-Ashi
charts make it easier to spot the current
trend.
So candlesticks in a Heikin-Ashi chart are
related to each other, because the open price
of each candlestick is calculated using the
previous candlestick’s close and open prices.
Also the high and low prices of each candlestick
is determined by the previous candlestick.
So a Heikin-Ashi chart is slower than a candlestick
chart and its signals are delayed.
They work somehow like a moving average.
When reading these candlestick charts, there
are a few important things to pay attention
to.
The size of the candlestick, the relative
direction of the candlestick, and even the
color of the candlestick (red versus green)
can all help traders draw conclusions about
what trends may be occurring.
The charts themselves can be easily adjusted
depending on the desired timeframe used by
each trader.
Five minute, fifteen minute, hourly, and daily
Heikin-Ashi candlesticks are all among the
most commonly used.
When the market is bullish, Heikin-Ashi candlesticks
have big bodies and long upper shadows, but
no lower shadow.
Pay attention at the big uptrend in this chart.
As you see, almost all of the candlesticks
have big bodies, long upper shadows and no
lower shadow.
At first glance, the bullish Heikin-Ashi trend
looks like a normal Japanese candlestick trend.
However, you will notice that the Heikin-Ashi
trend is built primarily by bullish candles
and is absent of lower candlewicks.
When the price is shooting up, the price action
creates very little to no lower shadows.
When the market is bearish, Heikin-Ashi candlesticks
have big bodies and long lower shadows, but
no upper shadow.
So here is a big downtrend and as you see,
almost all of the candlesticks have big bodies,
long lower shadows and no upper shadow.
This indicates that the declining momentum
is very strong.
Reversal candlesticks in the Heikin-Ashi charts
look like regular doji candlesticks.
They have no or very small bodies but long
upper and lower shadows.
The doji, when it appears after a directional
move, has a reversal potential and indicates
that the price action is stalling and might
be poised to start a counter trend move.
So, in short how do you analyze a Heikin-Ashi
chart?
It’s simple.
When prices are trending up, Heikin-Ashi bars
have no lower shadow.
When prices are trending down, Heikin-Ashi
bars have no upper shadow.
Doji bars with both lower and upper shadows
are possible turning points and can also appear
during choppy price action.
Now, Heikin-Ashi chart is much smoother looking
in terms of price action.
Easier to identify trend and profit from it.
But the problem is that Heikin-Ashi candles
do not show true prices.
Yes, we derive these candlesticks from true
prices, but we need to treat it as more of
an indicator than a price chart itself.
So, that’s why it’s very important to
highlight the pros and the cons of using Heikin-Ashi
.
There are a few benefits to the Heikin-Ashi
chart that can be seen immediately.
The first is the smoothness.
The Heikin-Ashi chart creates a much smoother
flow of price movement without the gaps and
choppy movements typical price action can
make.
Heikin-Ashi indicator compared to the regular
price chart slows down the speed of the market,
eliminating unnecessary false signals.
Also, it’s easy to read trends: both the
size, direction, and color of a Heikin-Ashi
candlestick will tell you a lot about the
trend in a short amount of time.
This is extremely valuable for day traders
who need to make quick decisions.
Another advantage of Heikin-Ashi is the fact
that it will allow you to stay in the trade
without being nervous or making any unnecessary
moves.
Also, the adaptability is another benefit.
The “trading period” on Heikin-Ashi charts
can be easily adjusted to reflect different
time periods.
Some traders will look at 15 minute and daily
charts side by side in order to develop a
more comprehensive analysis.
These charts can also be applied in many different
markets including stocks, forex, indexes,
and various others.
However, a Heikin-Ashi chart has some disadvantages:
Every indicator that is based on slowing down
the signals does its best on trends only.
Heikin-Ashi smoothed signals don’t let you
to notice the reversal in time.
Any Heikin-Ashi strategy should take into
consideration that lagging indicators not
only dismiss useless signals to open the trade
but also provide you with a late signal for
closing the trade.
That is why you will often see the market
slowly destroying your profit and later on,
you will understand that the trend has already
changed.
In other words, don’t rely too much on Heikin-Ashi
when you want to take your profits.
Another important drawback is the fact that
this indicator does not fit short-term and
scalping strategies.
I’ve talked with many traders that used
Heikin-Ashi on the 1-min or 5-min chart, trying
to scalp the market, and all of them were
disappointed.
So, short term trading could be inefficient
when using Heikin-Ashi .
Now, developing a Heikin-Ashi trading strategy
is surprisingly easy.
These charts rarely contradict other technical
indicators, rather, they simply amplify the
trend to make it easier to identify.
When used correctly, Heikin-Ashi charts are
incredibly reliable.
If your goal is to catch longer and persistent
trends, then using a Heikin-Ashi chart will
help you toward that end.
A simple way to use Heikin-Ashi is to add
them to a h4 or daily chart and apply price
action rules.
On higher timeframes like the 4 h or d1, the
Heikin-Ashi trading style puts an emphasis
on persistent trends.
Small corrections and consolidations are left
behind and they are barely visible on the
chart.
You will notice that when the direction changes
on a Heikin-Ashi graph, the price most likely
starts a new move.
This helps to distinguish between the potential
beginning and the end of a trend.
Since chart noise is filtered, you basically
see the naked trend.
Heikin-Ashi charting is very powerful when
combined with price action analysis.
Look for the emergence of new trends, or for
the reversal of already existing ones.
Look for support and resistance levels and
important swing points, and keep in mind that
these could act as future turning points on
the chart.
Now, if you found value and learned something
new, make sure you subscribe to our channel,
turn on the notifications so you don’t miss
future uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time