The triple exponential average (TRIX) is a
momentum indicator that shows the percentage
change in a triple exponentially smoothed
moving average.
This indicator it is designed to filter out
price movements that are considered insignificant
or unimportant.
TRIX is also implemented by traders to produce
signals that are similar in nature to the
moving average convergence divergence (MACD).
Although many consider TRIX to be very similar
to MACD, the primary difference between the
two is that TRIX outputs are smoother due
to the triple smoothing of the exponential
moving average (EMA).
The TRIX indicator smooths price data and
then looks at the daily (or whatever time
frame is being used) percentage movement of
that smoothed price data.
This filters out much of the price noise that’s
seen on the price chart.
TRIX will rise on sustained moves higher in
price, and will fall on sustained moves lower
in price.
Since TRIX is smoothed it takes time to react
to changes in price direction.
This can be beneficial, because not every
little pullback means a trade should be exited
or that the trend is going to reverse.
How TRIX is calculated
It is a four step process to calculate TRIX.
The indicator is “triple smoothed,” which
means we are taking a moving average of a
moving average of a moving average.
15-period exponential moving average (EMA)
using closing prices.
15-period EMA of result from step 1.
15-period EMA of result from step 2.
1-period percent change of step 3.
Step 4 is the TRIX, which will fluctuate from
period to period.
A different number of periods could be used
in the calculation.
Increasing the number of periods, for example
to 40, will decrease the sensitivity of the
indicator and may be more useful to long-term
traders.
Decreasing the number periods, for example
to 10, will increase the sensitivity of the
indicator; if you are a short-term trader,
you may prefer this.
Now, how to read the TRIX indicator
0.0 (zero level) on the indicator is used
a baseline.
When the TRIX is below 0.0, and especially
when it’s moving lower, the trend is considered
down.
When the TRIX is above 0.0, and especially
when it’s moving higher, the trend is considered
up.
TRIX helps confirm trends, indicates when
a trend reversal may be underway, and can
also be used to generate trade signals.
Divergences are another useful aspect of the
indicator.
Bullish divergence is when the price makes
a lower low but the TRIX doesn’t.
It indicates selling momentum is not as great
as it was on prior price drop.
Weak selling momentum could lead to an eventual
reversal.
Bearish divergence is when the price makes
a higher high, but the TRIX doesn’t.
It signals weakening buying momentum, which
could result in an eventual reversal.
As an additional step, a moving average (which
is visible) can be applied to the TRIX indicator.
This is useful for providing crossover trade
signals.
The moving average is typically of shorter
length than the number of periods used in
the TRIX calculation.
For example, if using a 20-period TRIX, a
7-period moving average could be applied to
it.
However, if you followed my channel, you already
know that I’m not a fan of moving average
crossovers.
If you want to back test some crossovers between
TRIX and another moving average, make sure
you use it on higher timeframes, with small
positions.
So how to trade using TRIX oscillator.
A popular TRIX strategy is to watch for price
reversal signals, such a trend line or support
or resistance breakout, which is confirmed
by a TRIX zero line crossover.
For long trades, you buy when the TRIX crosses
above 0.0 if there is some evidence that the
price has started to reverse higher (you need
to search for trend line breakout, higher
swing high or higher swing low).
For short trades, you go short when the TRIX
crosses below 0.0 if there is some evidence
that the price has started to reverse lower
(so you need confirmation, namely a trend
line or support or resistance breakout, lower
swing high or lower swing low).
This strategy is simple and is mainly useful
for entries.
Unfortunately, the entry point has little
regard for an appropriate place to put a stop
loss.
To control risk, a stop loss must be implemented,
preferably just above a recent high if taking
a short position, or just below a recent low
if taking a long position.
Waiting for the price to move back across
the zero line to exit the trade can mean giving
back a lot of profit.
For this reason, you shouldn’t rely in TRIX
indicator to offer an exit.
Here are some examples of TRIX 0-crossover
signals, combined with price action breakouts.
Divergence signals are another great way to
use the TRIX indicator.
This is my favorite approach for this indicator.
This occurs when the price action and indicator
are not aligned which is a precursor of a
momentum shift.
If you pay attention at this example, you
can see how the indicator puts in a retest
of its lows, but the indicator on the second
test is above the zero line.
This ultimately leads to a massive run higher,
where the indicator makes fresh new intraday
highs on each push higher.
In this example the second high had a lower
reading on the indicator, which is a precursor
for a likely pullback.
As always, try to incorporate price action
with this approach and don’t rely exclusively
in the indicator.
Price action first, confirmed by the indicator.
Now, bearish divergences do not work well
in strong uptrends.
Even though momentum seems to be weakening
because the indicator is producing lower highs,
momentum still has a bullish bias as long
as the indicator is above its centerline.
Upward momentum may be less positive, but
it is still positive as long as it stays above
0 baseline.
The rise is just not as fast as before.
The opposite is true for bullish divergences.
These do not work well in strong downtrends.
Even though the indicator shows less downside
momentum with higher lows, downward momentum
is still stronger than upward momentum as
long as the indicator remains below its centerline.
So, the trick is separating the bad signals
from the good signals.
Which means you must read price action and
identify the appropriate support and resistance
levels and patterns.
Here are some examples of valid TRIX divergences.
So what are the advantages of TRIX.
Two main advantages of TRIX over other trend-following
indicators are its excellent filtration of
market noise and its tendency to be a leading
than lagging indicator.
It filters out market noise using the triple
exponential average calculation, thus eliminating
minor short-term cycles that indicate a change
in market direction.
It has the ability to lead a market because
it measures the difference between each bar's
"smoothed" version of the price information.
When interpreted as a leading indicator, TRIX
is best used in conjunction with other market-timing
indicator - this minimizes false signals.
Regarding TRIX limitations, the TRIX doesn’t
always reflect what is happening in the price.
The price may be trending higher while TRIX
is trending lower.
We talked before about divergences which signals
a potential end to the trend, but a trend
can persist for a very long time even on weakening
momentum.
Using the TRIX in this situation can be deceiving,
and can result in missing out on some great
upside potential in the price.
That’s why, when used alone, TRIX can offer
false signals.
False crossovers are another common issue.
A false crossover is when the TRIX crosses
above or below the zero line, only to snap
back the other way, resulting in a losing
trade.
False signals can result in many losses within
a short period of time.
That’s why I recommend to use longer-term
trend analysis to help avoid some of these
false signals.
Ideally, only take buy signals when an overall
uptrend is underway, and sell signals when
an overall downtrend is underway.
The indicator also has no regard for setting
a stop loss.
A stop loss must be placed manually above
a recent high (shorts) or below a recent low
(longs).
If there is no respective high or low near
the entry point, maybe you should consider
avoiding the trade.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, don’t forget to subscribe,
click the bell icon to enable notifications
for new uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.