The price rate of change (ROC) represents
a momentum oscillator, measuring the speed
at which the price is changing within a defined
time period.
The rate of change (ROC) calculates the percentage
change between the most recent price and the
price registered a certain number of periods
ago.
The plot forms an oscillator moving above
and below the zero line as the rate of change
moves from positive to negative.
So the ROC indicator is plotted against zero,
with the indicator moving upwards into positive
territory if price changes are to the upside,
and moving into negative territory if price
changes are to the downside.
Like other momentum indicators (Stochastic
oscillator, for example), ROC can be interpreted
in numerous ways, traders using this oscillator
for overbought/oversold signals, divergences
and zero-line crossovers.
A value above zero indicates an increase in
bullish momentum and a negative value suggests
an increase in downward momentum.
A rising ROC typically confirms an uptrend.
But this can be misleading, as the indicator
is only comparing the current price to the
price N periods ago.
A falling ROC indicates the current price
is below the price N periods ago.
This usually helps confirm a downtrend, but
isn't always accurate.
When the price is consolidating, the ROC will
hover near zero.
In this case, it is important traders watch
the overall price trend since the ROC will
provide little insight except for confirming
the sideways movement.
Overbought and oversold levels are not fixed
on the ROC, and each asset will generate its
own extreme levels.
Traders can see what these levels are by looking
to past readings and observing the extreme
levels the ROC reached before the price reversed.
All markets can work well with the ROC indicator.
There are no right or wrong settings to use,
but every trader has to make decisions depending
on the market conditions and the volatility
of the financial markets.
The ROC indicator can be used on various time
frames.
It can be used for short-term trading but
in general, the value of the ROC indicator
is better used for identifying the long-term
trend.
There are various settings that can be used
for the ROC oscillator.
The common settings used for this indicator
is 9-periods.
Other commonly used settings include 14, 21
and even 50.
Remember that there is no absolute number
that can magically give the right settings.
Rather, it is important to analyze the behavior
of the stock or currency you’re trading
in order to use the right or the most appropriate
settings for the price ROC oscillator.
The volatility of the market being analyzed
is of course of utmost importance.
Using too small a number (like 9 for example)
can lead to very choppy readings, while using
a higher configuration setting could potentially
lag the ROC to the point that signals can
be very delayed.
If we take a look at this market, you can
see that when using a 5-period setting for
the oscillator, the ROC can be choppy.
While it might look easy in hindsight, it
is important to note that this oscillator
will have problems to pick up the tops and
bottoms or in other words, rising and falling
momentum in price.
So you need to find the right balance suited
for the market you’re trading and the timeframe
you’re mainly using.
How to trade with the price rate of change
First strategy, using the ROC indicator as
a timing tool within a trend analysis
We already know that price never moves in
a straight line.
The price posts a series of highs and lows
within the trend.
The challenge is of course in buying near
the low point or the dip in the uptrend or
selling near the high point or the rally in
the downtrend.
The ROC indicator can help you to find these
points.
Trends can be analyzed either by looking at
the highs and lows or by looking at the signals
from the technical indicators such as moving
averages.
In this first approach of using the ROC to
analyze a market, let’s look at a simple
set up that involves one moving averages and
the ROC.
Now, maybe the most common way traders use
the ROC oscillator is entering the market
when the plotted line crosses the zero line.
A breakout in either direction indicates increasing
/decreasing momentum.
By itself, this signal is not reliable.
Because sometimes, the ROC can dip below the
zero-line only to reverse back higher.
And this is an important point to note.
The ROC reacts to the price and not the other
way around.
Therefore, you need to focus on the price
and price action as well before trading this
simple method with the ROC indicator.
We can improve the zero line crossover approach
when we combine the price rate of change with
a trend indicator.
As we can observe in this example, when used
in combination with a moving average the ROC
offers several entries in the market, when
the line crosses below the zero-line.
As most of the oscillators, the rate of change
works well in a trending scenario.
The first step is to determine the prevailing
trend on the market.
You can use the classic moving averages (50,
100 or 200).
In this example I opted for a 50-period simple
moving average
When the price trades above the 50-period
simple moving average, consider taking only
long entries.
And when the price trades below the 50-period
SMA search for short entries
Then you monitor the rate of change indicator
and take the zero line crossovers only in
confirmation with the 50-period moving average.
Consider exiting your position when the slope
of the rate of change turns in the opposite
direction.
Here are some examples of zero line crossovers
confirmed by the moving average.
The second strategy involves using the ROC
for divergences
The concept of divergence is the same, whether
you are using the Relative Strength Index
(RSI), the Stochastics or the Price rate of
change.
A divergence is common to all oscillators.
When the oscillator forms a fresh low but
price does not, or when price forms a high
but the oscillator does not, it can indicate
a possible divergence and signals a correction.
Using this knowledge, you can apply the price
rate of change and look for divergences with
price.
So a divergence occurs when the price of a
stock or another asset moves in one direction
while its ROC moves in the opposite direction.
For example, if a stock's price is rising
over a period of time while the ROC is progressively
moving lower, then the ROC is indicating bearish
divergence from price, which signals a possible
trend change to the downside.
The same concept applies if the price is moving
down and ROC is moving higher.
This could signal a price move to the upside.
A divergence is a leading signal but could
prove to be a notoriously poor timing signal
since a divergence can last a long time and
won't always result in a price reversal.
Timing a divergence is maybe even more important
than spotting the pattern.
This example shows the ROC indicator posting
a long term divergence.
There are several peaks for the ROC reading,
and all of them would have given wrong trading
signals.
One method to time the divergence and filter
the bad signals is to wait for a trend line
breakout on the chart.
Also, you could wait for the price rate of
change to cross below zero level.
In this example, we can see an instance of
divergence that is forming.
Here, price posted a lower low, but the ROC
oscillator posted a higher low.
This divergence, known as bullish divergence
can be used in two ways.
You can go long on the market after this trend
line breakout and after the ROC indicator
crosses above 0, indicating a bullish momentum.
The third approach involves Overbought and
Oversold Conditions
These levels are not fixed, but will vary
depending on the market being traded.
Traders look to see what ROC values resulted
in price reversals in the past.
They try to find both positive and negative
values where the price reversed with some
regularity in the past.
When the ROC reaches these extreme readings
again, they will watch for the price to start
reversing to confirm the ROC signal.
Honestly, I don’t like this approach at
all.
This strategy might work in a non-trending
market, but during strong trends traders often
get false signals, as shown in this example.
As I said before, the ROC show readings at
extreme values, but it has no boundaries.
In a very strong uptrend the ROC oscillator
could show readings outside the usual range
within a specific time period.
These overbought or oversold extremes could
be monitored as they could indicate a trend
reversal, but these extreme values are highly
subjective.
So, I wouldn’t concentrate my attention
on overbought or oversold levels.
Another potential problem with using the ROC
indicator is that its calculation gives equal
weight to the most recent price and the price
formed a number of periods ago, despite the
fact that some traders consider more recent
price action to be of more importance in determining
likely future price movements.
This can result in multiple false signals
for trend trades.
That’s why it’s important to keep an eye
on the price action, on recent market swings
and always look at the big picture, on multiple
time frames, to increase you odds of trading
in the right direction.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.