Here is what most of market gurus are teaching
you about moving averages.
You take a short-term moving average and a
long-term moving average and you buy and sell
when you see crossovers.
Nice, so you buy here, the price rallies,
you exit here with 100% profit, you sell here,
another winning trade, one more buy, another
win...this is too easy, like printing money.
What they don’t tell you is that these results
happen maybe 10%-15% of trading days, if you’re
lucky.
Here is how the normal trading day looks like.
Not so profitable anymore, right, with all
the choppiness and false signals?
If you follow a crossover pattern, in 2 weeks
your account is gone, guaranteed.
If i learned something in my over 10 years’
experience of trading is that moving average
crossovers don’t work like advertised.
So in the following minutes, we’ll talk
about moving averages, how you should use
them correctly and I’ll show you how i use
the crossovers in my trading plan.
Before we continue, if you’re new to our
channel, make sure you subscribe, click the
notifications bell and leave a like to show
your support.
Now, why are moving average crossovers so
popular?
Because, a moving average is a trend indicator,
and you were told that the trend is your friend,
so why not using 2 or 3 moving averages, to
increase your chances.
Here is a hard truth and, please keep in mind
that this is simply my discovery after 10
years of trading.
Moving averages crossovers don’t work on
lower time frames.
Period.
I’ve tested hundreds, thousands of combinations.
Some of them were decent, some of them damaged
my account.
You’ll have a hard time trading crossovers
on the 5-minute or 15-minutes charts.
If you found a magic crossover that works
on lower timeframes, go ahead and share it
with me, because i simply wasn’t able to
record consistent profit by trading crossovers
on lower time frames.
On higher time frames, well, we have another
story here, and you might be able to profit
from crossovers.
But first, let me explain why is dangerous
for you to trade crossovers on lower time
frames and why this strategy will most likely
lead to frustrations and bad results.
The biggest drawbacks of moving averages is
the fact they lag price.
Price moves first and the moving average moves
second.
You are always behind the price.
The moving average is a trend following indicator.
It can only tell you when the trend has already
happened.
You can’t forecast a new trend with a moving
average because it’s a lagging indicator.
Pay attention in this chart that the moving
average was still rising whilst price hit
the resistance level and went down by a considerable
amount.
The second problem with moving averages is
the noise.
One of the best things about using moving
averages for trading is that they are designed
to smooth out the erratic price data so that
you can be able to detect and stay with the
trend.
However, even the best moving averages suffer
from noise.
On lower time frames, you will witness many
false signals if the market is consolidating
or the price spikes up and down due to higher
volatility.
Another drawback of a moving average crossover
system is the sideways markets.
Nothing is more frustrating than trying to
use a crossover strategy in a sideways market!
Your stop losses won’t stand a chance!
Regardless of what type of moving average
you use in a sideways market, they will not
work effectively.
So, if you are a day trader, I would say is
better to avoid crossover strategies on lower
time frames.
There are better ways to use a moving average.
Moving averages are great to determine the
trend direction of your instrument.
While price action and structure should be
your main focus, you can get a general idea
of the market direction with a moving average.
So, here is how you could take advantage of
a moving average:
First, to identify and confirm market trend
While keeping in mind that are lagging indicators,
you can use the slope of the moving average:
up sloping is an uptrend and down sloping
is downtrend.
You can also use price location: if price
above moving average, look for long trades.
Below the average you would look for short
opportunities.
A stock is considered to be in an uptrend
when the price is above a moving average and
the ma’s slope is upward
A stock is considered to be in a downtrend
when the price is below a moving average and
the ma’s slope is downward
The second way you could use a moving average
is as support and resistance level.
Moving averages offer traders dynamic areas
of support and resistance because are changing
depending on recent price action.
Being so common and followed by so many traders,
you can often see on charts that the popular
moving averages work excellent as support
and resistance levels.
A simple ma could be considered as a dynamic
area of support or resistance
The area between two moving averages could
also be considered as a dynamic area of support
or resistance.
A longer-term moving average like ma 200 has
a greater relevance to the price, and offers
less false signals, compared to shorter-term
moving averages.
Now, let’s come back to the crossovers.
So a moving average crossover system will
catch good movements when markets are trending.
However, when markets are trading in a range,
this system is subject to many losing trades.
And on lower timeframes, the odds are not
in your favor.
So, are moving average crossovers useless?
Well, not quite.
On higher timeframes, for traders and investors
that hold positions for several months using
higher time frames like daily, weekly, or
even monthly charts, the moving averages have
higher chances of indicating a valid signal.
But there’s another problem here.
A two-moving average crossover system is usually
a “stop and-reverse” strategy, meaning
that you will be in the market at all times
when used as a mechanical strategy.
Once an entry is triggered, you will remain
in the market until the opposite signal is
generated, at which time your current position
will be liquidated and a new one entered in
the direction of the new signal.
But even on higher time frames, this strategy
is risky.
So, i would only take long positions and completely
ignore short signals.
And here’s another important tip which will
cut your losses even more.
When a buy signal is generated, you must wait
for the bar to be completely finished before
entering the trade.
I can’t remember how many times I traded
a crossover signal without waiting for the
candle to be closed.
So, wait for the candle to close and confirm
the crossover, it will save you a lot of bad
entries.
Once you have triggered your entry, there
are several ways to manage this trade.
Traditionally, you would remain in the trade
until an opposite signal appears.
While waiting for an opposite signal to exit
your position may be the “normal” approach,
you may find this method to be inconsistent,
depending on the market’s behavior.
This approach will often lead to extremely
late exits, which can severely cut into your
profits.
Instead, you could try other tactics like
using a traditional trailing stop, using a
single moving average crossover exit, using
a fixed profit target, using Fibonacci extensions
as targets or using visual support and resistance
levels as targets.
I personally use the 200 EMA and the 20 EMA
on the daily chart to search for buy entries
on stocks with good fundamentals, but these
2 moving averages are not set in stone.
Depending on the stock traded, you can have
other values for your crossover signals in
a daily timeframe.
As you may know, the market will change over
time.
At times, a market may be quiet and trending,
while other times it may be erratic and directionless,
so you should adjust the moving averages of
your crossover system to find the best fit.
So, no shortcuts here, there is no universal
moving average crossover that works on any
market.
You must continually back test and adjust
your moving averages by yourself.
With today’s trading platforms, you can
even scan the entire market of stocks with
specific criteria to find those that are behaving
in a similar manner.
You only need a good stock screener, and trade
stocks with good fundamentals.
To increase your chances when trading a crossover
strategy, it’s good to have fundamentals
on your side, this is why i only trade companies
what have good perspectives.
With a stock screener, you still have to do
your homework, but you can set screens to
create your watch list based on your crossover
conditions and it’s going to save you a
lot of time, especially if you’re monitoring
hundreds or thousands of stocks.
So, don’t neglect the power of a stock screener,
it can help you a lot in your trading.
Now, if you found value and learned something
new, make sure you subscribe to our channel,
turn on the notifications so you don’t miss
future uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.