Over the last few years, supply and demand
trading has become one of the most popular
trading strategies.
And for good reason because this trading style
takes the best of support and resistance and
adds the concept of supply and demand.
The result is a strategy that allows you to
pinpoint where the banks are buying and selling,
giving you the chance to get into some of
the biggest reversals BEFORE they begin.
In today’s video, I'm going to give you
a full breakdown of how to correctly find
and draw supply and demand zones and the common
mistakes you should avoid when trading these
areas.
News events, economic announcements, and just
general market action all cause different
groups of traders to buy and sell, resulting
in changes to the supply and demand equation.
These changes manifest visually as the rises,
declines, and consolidations we see on our
charts.
When we see price rising, demand outweighs
supply.
When we see price falling, supply outweighs
demand.
When supply and demand are in relative balance,
a consolidation forms.
Changes in supply and demand will ONLY OCCUR
when the banks and other big traders buy or
sell.
We, retail traders, can't cause price to rise
or fall because we don't have enough money!
Only the banks, with their high buying/selling
power, can make price move.
In Forex for example, the banks can never
place their full position all at once.
Their positions are so large they must break
them into smaller chunks and place each trade
individually, around a similar price, to avoid
pushing price away and potentially forcing
the entry at a bad price.
This way they achieve the same effect of placing
one huge position, by placing a bunch of small
ones instead.
But, here's the banks’ problem:
These positions are often so big that not
enough people exist on the opposite side to
get them placed - buying when the banks want
to sell, or selling when the banks want to
buy, even if they convert their positions
into smaller chunks.
So, they must let price move away and then
make it return later on to get the rest of
their position entered.
Now, supply and demand trading is all about
finding points where the banks have bought
or sold and then jumping into trades when
price returns to pick up the rest of the banks’
position to get into the reversal, right beside
the banks.
Supply and demand trading is a method where
the idea is to find points in the market where
the price has made a strong advance or decline
and mark these areas as supply and demand
zones using rectangles.
The point in which the price has made a strong
advance is marked by the trader as a demand
zone.
Demand Zones represent points where the banks
have placed a significant number of buy positions.
These are the support levels of supply and
demand trading, if you will.
A point where the market has made a sharp
decline is marked as a supply zone.
These are points where the banks place a significant
number of sell positions and these are resistance
points where price could fall.
Now, how to find and draw supply and demand
zones.
If you want to be successful trading supply
and demand, you MUST master the finding of
high probability zones and correctly drawing
them on the chart.
It takes time, practice, and experience to
get this right.
The most important rule is to look for sharp
rises and declines in price.
They reveal the banks are buying or selling,
which means a supply or, a demand, must exist
at the source of the rise or decline.
Supply zones can be located by looking for
a swift drop away from either a single candle
or small consolidation structure (commonly
known as a base).
The base consists of a few candlesticks in
a tight sideways range (consolidation).
This is an example of a supply zone formed
with a base.
And this is an example of a supply zone formed
from a single candle.
Demand zones are found when the market makes
a large move up from a single candle or a
base.
Here is an example of a demand zone created
from a single candle.
And here is an example of a demand zone with
a base.
And here is a first important point.
The strength of the movement away from supply
or demand zone is not a determining factor
in how strong the zone is.
As long as a zone has at least one large bullish
or bearish candle moving away from it’s
considered just as valid for trading as a
zone which has a significant move away from
it.
And here’s another important tip.
Supply or demand zones which are formed from
a base tend to result in more successful trades
than zones which form from a single candle.
This is due to the sensitive nature of the
psychology of the traders who had trading
positions back when the base was created.
A zone which forms with a single candle means
not a lot of traders were caught on the wrong
side of the market before the market moved
up or down creating the supply or demand zone.
A zone with a base contains far more trapped
traders because the market was moving sideways
in a consolidation before it began advancing
higher or falling lower.
And when the market returns to a zone formed
from a base the traders who were trapped either
long or short (depending on the zones) will
begin closing their trades.
And this creates liquidity in the market.
Now we know how to find and locate supply
and demand zones on our charts, we need to
actually draw the zones.
Both single candle supply and demand zones
and zones with a base are drawn in the same
way.
There are many different methods of how to
draw the zones properly, but I will share
the one I found to be the most consistent
to me.
We will begin by drawing a supply zone.
You always draw supply zones from the last
BULLISH candle before the drop, if the candle
immediately before the drop is bearish, then
you need to locate the most recent bullish
candle and draw the zone accordingly.
So the open of the bullish candle is where
you want to begin drawing your supply zone
from.
Once you’ve done this you need to drag the
rectangle up to the most recent high before
the drop.
Here are several examples of supply zones.
For demand zones, we draw the zone from the
most recent BEARISH candle found immediately
before the up move creating the zone.
In this example you can see I’ve drawn the
demand zone from the open of the bearish candle
found just before the market made its move
up.
From here you need to find the most recent
low nearest the zone and drag your rectangle
to the low, now you have the demand zone drawn
on your charts.
Here are several examples of demand zones.
In contrast to when we are drawing supply
zones, the candle you’re drawing the demand
zone off must be bearish.
If it happens to be bullish you need to go
back and locate the nearest bearish candle
before the move up and draw your rectangle
from there.
The reason why this is important is due to
how the banks place trades.
Banks do not place trades onto movements which
are in the direction of the trade they are
placing.
In simple terms, if the current candle is
bullish the banks wont be placing buy trades,
if its bearish, they wont be placing sell
trades.
Before you start trading Supply and Demand,
there are 2 key rules you need to understand
to find the right zones on the chart and trade
them correctly using your entry method.
First rule is that old zones rarely work.
Apparently, the longer the market has been
away from a supply or demand zone the better
chance the market has of turning when it eventually
returns.
This is completely wrong.
Recent zones are far more important.
If we compare the old supply and demand zones
(colored blue), with the more recent zones
colored white, its easy to see how trading
zones which have been created recently are
far more effective than trading zones which
were created a long time ago.
Second rule is to trade only fresh/untouched
zones.
Another big misconception you'll hear in the
supply and demand community is the idea that
supply and demand zones have the power to
cause reversals more than once, like support
and resistance levels do.
Again, this isn't true.
Supply and demand zones are ONE TIME USE.
Not two times or three times, one time ONLY.
When price hits a zone and reverses, that's
it; the zone loses its power.
The probability it'll cause another reversal
in the future is low.
The only exception to this rule is if a zone
forms at the top or bottom of a consolidation.
In this case, price will probably reverse
two or three times from the zone, since the
consolidation shows the banks are buying/selling
from similar points.
However, once the consolidation is over, the
zone loses all its power and probably won't
cause another reversal.
Now, this was an introduction to supply and
demand trading and it was impossible for me
to cover everything about supply and demand
trading in this one video.
In future videos, we’ll go deeper and I
plan to explain several supply and demand
trading strategies involving classic support
and resistance levels, using price action
patterns and even trading indicators.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay notified when we release
new videos.
Until next time.