Guppy multiple moving average (GMMA) indicator
provides an interesting alternative to other
popular indicators.
The GMMA implements 2 different exponential
moving averages (EMAs) in an effort to analyze
market behavior on multiple levels.
The Guppy indicator is composed of 12 EMAs,
so essentially the Guppy and an EMA are the
same thing.
Guppy will help you to isolate trades, spot
opportunities, and warn about price reversals.
The multiple lines of the Guppy will help
you to see the strength or weakness in a trend
better than if only using one or two EMAs.
The Guppy multiple moving average (GMMA) is
an indicator that tracks the activity of the
two major groups in the market.
These are investors and traders.
Traders are always probing for a change in
the trend.
In a downtrend they will take a trade in anticipation
of a new uptrend developing.
If it does not develop, then they get out
of the trade quickly.
If the trend does change, then they stay with
the trade, but continue to use a short term
management approach.
No matter how long the uptrend remains in
place, the trader is always alert for a potential
trend change.
Often they use a volatility based indicator,
or a short term 10 day moving average, to
help identify the exit conditions.
We track their activity by using a group of
short term moving averages.
These are 3, 5, 8, 10, 12 and 15 day exponentially
calculated moving averages.
Strong trends are supported by long term investors.
These are the true gamblers in the market
because they tend to have a great deal of
faith in their analysis.
The investor takes more time to recognize
the change in a trend.
We track the investors’ activity by using
the 30, 35, 40, 45, 50 and 60 day exponentially
calculated moving average.
So the GMMA attempts to identify trends by
combining two groups of moving averages with
different time periods.
The long-term EMAs (exponential moving average)
represent the interests and behaviors of investors
that have taken a long-term approach to a
given market.
The short-term EMAs represent traders, or
speculators, who are attempting to capture
short-term profits.
The relationship within each of these groups
tells us when there is agreement on value
- when they are close together - and when
there is disagreement on value - when they
are well spaced apart.
The relationship between the two groups tells
the trader about the strength of the market
action.
A change in price direction that is well supported
by both short and long term investors signals
a strong trading opportunity.
Guppy is an easy indicator that will allow
anyone to determine the overall trend of the
market quickly and without personal bias.
And of course, once you know the general direction
of a trending market, the odds of a successful
trade increase.
The GMMA also offers insight into potential
reversals or periods of consolidation by signaling
changes in market sentiment.
Although Guppy is a standalone trading strategy,
I have found great results combining Guppy
with price action, but we’ll talk about
this later.
So, how to read the GMMA?
The Guppy multiple moving average can be used
to identify changes in trends or determine
the strength of the current trend.
The degree of separation between the short-
and long-term moving averages can be used
as an indicator of trend strength.
If there's a wide separation, then the prevailing
trend is strong.
Narrow separation, or lines that are crisscrossing,
indicates a weakening trend or a period of
consolidation.
The crossover of the short- and long-term
moving averages represent trend reversals.
If the short-term crosses above the long-term
moving averages, then a bullish reversal has
occurred.
If the short-term mas cross below the longer-term
ones, then a bearish reversal is occurring.
When both groups of mas are moving horizontally,
or mostly moving sideways and heavily intersected,
it means the asset lacks a price trend, and
therefore may not be a good candidate for
trend trades.
These periods may be good for range trading.
The indicator can also be used for trade signals.
When the short-term group passes above the
long-term group of mas, the market is bullish.
When the short-term group passes below the
longer-term group, the market is bearish.
These signals should be avoided when the price
and the mas are moving sideways.
Following a consolidation period, pay attention
at crossovers and separation.
When the lines start to separate this often
means a breakout from the consolidation has
occurred and a new trend could be underway.
During a strong uptrend, when the short-term
mas move back toward the longer-term mas (but
don't cross) and then start to move back the
upside, this is another opportunity to enter
into long trades in the trending direction.
The same concept applies to downtrends for
entering short trades.
The green moving averages represent short-term
traders and red represents long-term traders.
When both the red and green lines are moving
in agreement (both trending up or down), we
are given a confirmation of market sentiment
and trend.
The moving averages may also act as support
and/or resistance.
When price finds support at these levels,
it might be a good time to add positions if
you see further upside potential or you have
spare risk capital available.
When price tests the red moving average zone,
long-term traders will look to buy more given
their outlook is still bullish.
The strength of the trend is determined by
the distance between the red and green moving
average clusters.
The further the distance, the greater the
trend.
Another way to evaluate the strength of a
trend is to evaluate the spread between each
moving average cluster.
If the long-term red averages are spread out
nicely, this indicates that the support/resistance
level is broad and strong.
If the lines within a cluster are narrowing,
this indicates momentum is declining, and
a reversal or consolidation could follow.
Just like simple moving averages, you can
use crossovers as entry and exit signals.
When the short-term moving average cluster
crosses over the long-term, this signals a
change in market sentiment and suggest that
short-term traders are starting a new trend.
For instance, this Guppy crossover indicates
that short-term traders have become optimistic
about this pair and could potentially start
a new bullish trend.
The strength of the trend is determined by
the distance between the red and green moving
average clusters.
Like I said before, the farther the distance,
the greater the trend.
Now, if you followed my previous videos on
moving averages, you probably know that I’m
not the biggest fan of moving average crossovers.
Since the GMMA indicator was designed for
trending assets; these moving averages run
into problems when price consolidates.
The indicator shows consolidation and potential
reversals when the short and long-term moving
averages condense.
The main limitation of the Guppy indicator
is the lagging factor.
Each EMA represents the average price from
the past.
It does not predict the future.
Waiting for the averages to cross can at times
mean an entry or exit that is far too late,
as the price has already moved aggressively.
All moving averages are also prone to whipsaws.
This is when there is a crossover, potentially
resulting in a trade, but the price doesn't
move as expected and then the averages cross
again resulting in a loss.
So, in times of consolidation, with multiple
crossovers, i find it useful to combine price
action with GMMA.
You could also use the Guppy multiple moving
average in conjunction with other technical
indicators to maximize your trading odds.
For example, you might look at the relative
strength index (RSI) to confirm a trend, or
look at various chart patterns to determine
other entry or exit points after a GMMA crossover.
From my experience, the GMMA is also useful
from breakout trading, when the price is moving
outside a defined support or resistance level
with increased volume.
A breakout trader enters a long position after
the price breaks above resistance or enters
a short position after the price breaks below
support.
The reason breakouts are such an important
trading strategy is because these setups are
the starting point for future volatility increases,
large price swings and, in many circumstances,
major price trends.
Breakouts occur in all types of market environments.
Typically, the most explosive price movements
are a result of channel breakouts and price
pattern breakout.
So when there is lots of separation between
the GMMAs, this helps confirm the price trend
in the current direction.
Look for agreement between the short term
and long term moving averages and pay attention
to chart formations such as channels, triangles,
and flags.
Whether you use intraday, daily or weekly
charts, the concepts are universal.
You can apply this strategy to day trading,
swing trading or any style of trading.
Once you spot a clear trade setup in your
desired time frame, remember to set the stop
loss just above or below short term moving
averages.
Or, if you want more room, decrease your lot
sizes and place it below or above the longer
term moving averages.
Although a simple indicator, the GMMA can
offer valuable insight to any momentum or
swing trader.
Guppy is a standalone trading strategy; however,
i have found the greatest returns when combining
Guppy with price action, because price action
addresses periods of consolidation, where
Guppy tends to underperform.
So always try to maximize your chances of
a great trade by confirming your bias with
other tools.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support and don’t
forget to subscribe and hit the bell icon
to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.