Traders today are bombarded
with "smart money concepts",
claiming to reveal the secrets of big players.
But these ideas aren't as new as you might think!
These concepts are just a modern
remix of the Wyckoff method.
The Wyckoff method, developed nearly a
century ago, is the original blueprint
for understanding smart money trading!
This is the video you need to watch,
if you really want to learn about the
inception of smart money concepts!
Understanding Market Dynamics
Trading isn't a fair game. It's
not you against other small traders. It's
you against big players with deep pockets.
These big traders have more money, better
tools, and access to info you don't have.
They know how retail traders think. And they
use this to trick small traders like you and me.
Here’s the reality: the
odds aren't in your favor!
Wyckoff teaches you to use
logic to figure out the market.
The big idea is this: when smart money buy
or sell, they leave marks on charts. These
marks show up in price and volume data.
If you know how to read these signs,
you can trade along with the pros. You're
not their prey anymore. You're on their side.
And you're not just guessing
anymore. You have a map.
The Three Fundamental Laws
The Wyckoff method is built
on three key laws that explain how markets
work. These laws help you see what's really
moving prices, not just what's on the surface.
Let's start with the Law of Supply and Demand.
This law is the engine that drives the market.
It's pretty simple: when more people
want to buy than sell, prices go up.
When more want to sell than buy, prices go down.
But it's not just about
numbers of buyers and sellers.
It's about how much money
they're willing to spend.
It's about the intensity of their actions.
One big buyer can have more
impact than many small sellers.
The Law of Supply and Demand says that price,
volume, and trend, all work together.
Price shows which way the market is
going. Volume shows how strong that move is.
When price and volume agree, it confirms the
market direction. We’ll talk about this later.
The Law of Cause and Effect tells us that big
moves in the market don't just happen out
of nowhere. They need preparation. It's
like a rocket launch. Before a rocket
can take off, it needs a lot of fuel.
In the market, that fuel is buying or
selling pressure building up over time.
The size of the cause determines
the size of the effect.
A small cause leads to a small move.
A big cause can lead to a big move.
This is why Wyckoff traders look for
signs of accumulation (which is buying)
or distribution (meaning, selling). These are
the "causes" that can lead to big price moves.
This law helps explain why markets
sometimes seem to move for no reason.
There's always a reason, but it might have been
building up for a while, before you noticed it.
The Law of Cause and Effect also says that if
there's no preparation, there will be no move.
This helps you avoid false signals.
If you don't see a cause building up,
you shouldn't expect a big effect.
It’s all about preparation. In the market,
this often shows up as trading ranges. These
are periods where price moves sideways,
bouncing between support and resistance levels.
To the untrained eye, these might look boring.
But to a Wyckoff trader, they're
exciting. They're where the cause
is building up for the next big move.
Lastly, we have the Law of Effort versus Result.
This law helps us spot when
something's off in the market.
It's about comparing the effort (usually measured
by volume) with the result (the price movement).
Here's how it works. The market is always
trying to move one way or the other.
These attempts can be short or long. Either way,
they represent effort, which we see as volume.
If you see a lot of volume (meaning effort)
but prices barely move (meaning result),
that's a red flag.
It might mean the
current trend is running out of steam.
On the flip side, if prices move a lot on
low volume, that move might not last.
This law helps you spot divergences.
A divergence is when the effort and result
don't match up. It's like a warning sign that
something might be about to change.
The Law of Effort versus Result is
like a lie detector for the market, and is
especially useful for spotting trend changes.
Often, before a trend changes, you'll
see a mismatch between effort and result.
It's like the market is trying hard
to keep going in the same direction,
but it's running out of steam.
Wyckoff Phases
The Wyckoff method breaks down
market action into four main phases:
Accumulation… Mark-up…Distribution…and Mark-down.
Accumulation is the first phase. It happens at
market bottoms. This is when big players
start buying. They do this quietly,
so prices don't go up too fast.
During this phase, prices often
move sideways. It might look boring, but
a lot is happening under the surface.
In accumulation, most people are scared to
buy. They think prices might keep falling.
But smart money sees value.
They buy when others are afraid.
This phase can last a while. It takes
time for big players to buy all they want,
without pushing prices up too much.
Look for these signs:
• Prices stop falling and move sideways
• Volume is low, but picks up on price dips
• Price drops don't last long
• Strong buying when prices fall a bit
The uptrend or mark-up phase comes next.
This is when prices start to climb.
The big players who bought during
accumulation are now letting prices rise.
They might even buy more, pushing prices higher.
In the uptrend,
more people start to notice the market.
They see prices going up and want to join in.
This extra buying helps push prices even higher.
Look for these signs in an uptrend:
• Prices make higher highs and higher lows
• Volume often increases as prices rise
• Pullbacks are short and shallow
• Each new high is met with strong buying
The third phase is distribution.
This happens at market tops.
Big players who bought low are now selling.
They sell slowly, just like they bought slowly.
They don't want to crash the
market by selling too fast.
In distribution, most people are excited.
They think prices will keep going up forever.
But smart money knows better. They're
quietly selling to these eager buyers.
Like accumulation, distribution
can take some time.
Look for these signs in distribution:
• Prices stop rising and move sideways
• Volume might increase,
but price rises don't last
• More volatility, with sharp ups and downs
• Each new high is quickly sold into
The last phase is the downtrend or
mark-down. This is when prices start to fall.
The big players have finished selling. Now
there aren't enough buyers to keep prices up.
In the downtrend, fear takes over. People
who bought high start to panic and sell.
This pushes prices down even faster. Like the
uptrend, the downtrend often moves in waves.
Look for these signs in a downtrend:
• Prices make lower lows and lower highs
• Volume often increases as prices fall
• Bounces are short and weak
• Each new low is met with more selling
These phases don't always happen in a perfect
cycle. Markets are messy. Sometimes a phase
might be skipped, or cut short. Other times,
a phase might last longer than expected.
The key is to be flexible, and watch
for the signs of each phase.
In accumulation, you start to
get ready to buy. You look for signs
that big players are accumulating.
These signs might include failed attempts to push
prices lower, or strong buying when prices dip.
During the uptrend, the goal is to buy pullbacks.
These are temporary dips in an overall rising
market. You wait for the uptrend to be confirmed
before buying. You don't try to guess the bottom.
In distribution, you start to get cautious. You
might take profits on long positions. You watch
for signs that the uptrend is weakening. These
signs could include failed attempts to make
new highs, or increased selling at high prices.
During the downtrend, the goal is to sell short.
Most of the money in a trend is made in phase
2 (the uptrend) and phase 4 (the downtrend).
The transition phases (accumulation and
distribution) are often trickier to trade.
They're more about preparing for the next trend.
One key skill in using the Wyckoff method
is identifying changes in market
character. This is when the
market shifts from one phase to another.
For example, the shift from accumulation to
uptrend, or from distribution to downtrend.
These changes often happen gradually. The
market doesn't suddenly switch from one phase
to another. Instead, it transitions slowly.
Another important aspect of the Wyckoff method, is
understanding the concept of supply and demand. In
accumulation, demand is slowly overcoming supply.
In distribution, supply is slowly overcoming
demand. The uptrend and downtrend
are when these forces play out.
Volume plays a crucial role in identifying
these phases. In accumulation, volume often
increases on price dips.
In distribution,
volume often increases on price rises.
Another key point: in both accumulation
and distribution, big players are
trying to hide what they're doing.
They don't want everyone to know they're
buying or selling big amounts. That’s because
they would move prices before they're ready.
This is where the idea of "smart money" comes
in. These are the big, well-informed players.
And they're always trying to stay ahead
of the "uninformed" traders.
Remember this: accumulation and
distribution are about more than just buying and
selling. They're about the transfer of risk.
In accumulation, smart money is taking on
risk, betting that prices will go up. In
distribution, they're passing that risk
to others, to less informed traders.
And one more thing to remember: emotions play
a big role in these cycles. In accumulation,
fear is the main emotion. People are scared
to buy because prices have been falling.
In distribution, it's often
greed and fear of missing out.
People buy because they're afraid
of missing the next big move up.
Now, before we continue, let us know in the
comments what topics you’d like us to cover!
Tell us what you want to watch next!
Wyckoff Events
Now let's break down Wyckoff events.
They're like clues that help us figure
out what's really going on in the market.
First, we have the Preliminary Support.
This is when big players start to buy,
trying to stop prices from falling more.
It's like putting a floor under the market.
You might see prices stop dropping as fast,
or even bounce a little.
Next comes the Selling
Climax. This is a big moment. It's when
scared sellers dump their positions.
Prices often fall hard and fast. But the
big players are buying during this panic.
They're getting ready for prices to go up later.
After the Selling Climax, we see an Automatic
Rally. Prices bounce up a bit.
This happens because the selling
pressure eases off.
It's like the market
taking a breath after all that selling.
Then we have the Secondary Test. Prices
fall again, but not as low as before.
This is important. It shows that
the big drop might be over.
Big players are still buying,
keeping prices from falling too far.
Now we come to the Spring. This is a
tricky move. Prices dip below the low point of
the Secondary Test. It looks like the market
might fall more. But it's often a fake-out.
Prices quickly jump back up. This is a key
sign that big players are done buying
and are ready for prices to go up.
After the Spring, we see a Sign of Strength. This
is a strong move up, often with lots of trading.
It's like the market saying,
"We're ready to go up now."
And then we have the Last Point of Support. This
is one more dip before the real uptrend starts.
It's like the market taking one
last breath before climbing.
These events don't always happen in
this exact order. Markets are tricky
and always changing. But knowing these
events helps you see the big picture.
If you see signs of accumulation (like
the Preliminary Support or Spring),
it might be a good time to think about buying.
If you see signs of distribution (like a Buying
Climax or Sign of Weakness), it might be time
to be careful or even think about selling.
The end of an accumulation phase, like after a
successful Spring, can be a great time to buy.
The end of a distribution phase
can be a good time to sell.
But remember, you don't need to
catch the exact bottom or top.
What matters is catching the main move.
And don't get too hung up on naming each
event. What's more important is understanding
what these events mean. They're showing you
the transfer of risk in the market.
Like I said before, in accumulation,
smart money is taking on risk, betting
prices will go up. In distribution,
they're passing that risk to others.
Volume Analysis in Wyckoff Method
Volume is a key part of the Wyckoff method.
It helps confirm what price is telling us.
The main idea is simple: volume
should match price moves.
If prices go up, volume should too.
If prices fall, volume should rise.
When volume and price don't
match, it can mean trouble .
Wyckoff saw the market as a
fight between buyers and sellers.
Volume shows who's winning. High volume
on up moves means buyers are strong.
High volume on down moves
means sellers are in control.
We talked before about Wyckoff's
law of effort versus result.
This law says the effect of a price move should
match the effort behind it. The effort is shown
by volume. The result is the price change.
Here's how it works:
• Big volume (the effort) should
lead to big price moves (the result)
• Small volume should lead to small price moves.
• If there's a mismatch,
it can signal a change coming
• High volume with little price change
often means accumulation or distribution
• Low volume with big price moves
usually isn't sustainable
• Rising prices with falling
volume can mean the uptrend is weakening
Volume helps confirm price action. It's
like a lie detector for price moves. Yes,
price alone can sometimes lie, but price
and volume together usually tell the truth.
In accumulation, watch for high volume on down
days, that don't push prices much lower.
This can mean big players are buying,
soaking up the supply. It's a sign
the downtrend might be ending.
In distribution, look for high volume on
up days that don't push prices much higher.
This often means big players are selling into
strength. It's a sign the uptrend might be ending.
During trends, volume should generally
increase in the direction of the trend.
In an uptrend, volume should be
higher on up days. In a downtrend,
volume should be higher on down days.
But it's not just about
whether volume is high or low.
The spread, the body of the price bar matters
too. Wyckoff and later traders like Tom Williams
saw the relationship between volume and spread.
Here's what to look for:
Wide spread, high volume:
this means usually bullish
this means usually bearish
Narrow spread, low volume:
often means consolidation
One common pattern is a climax.
This is a day with very high volume and a wide
price range. It often marks the end of a move.
In a downtrend, it might be a selling climax,
marking the end of the drop. In an uptrend,
it could be a buying climax,
signaling the end of the rise.
After a climax, watch for a test. This is
when prices return to near the climax level,
but on lower volume. If the test
holds, it can confirm the end of
the old trend and the start of a new one.
Volume can also help spot manipulation.
If you see a big price move on low volume, be
suspicious. It might be a false move designed
to trick traders. Real, sustainable
moves usually come with solid volume.
In the Wyckoff method, volume isn't just
about quantity. It's about quality too.
A day with steady buying is different from a
day where all the volume comes in one big spike.
Learn to read the quality of
volume, not just the quantity.
One key skill is spotting
divergences between price and volume.
If prices are making new highs but volume is
dropping, it can mean the uptrend is weakening.
If prices are making new lows but volume is drying
up, the downtrend might be running out of steam.
Volume patterns can also hint at what's
coming. For example, expanding volume as
prices move sideways often precedes a breakout.
The direction of the breakout isn't certain,
but the increase in volume suggests
something big is cooking.
In accumulation, you might see a series
of high-volume down days that fail to
push prices lower. This is often followed
by an upward surge on even higher volume.
This pattern can signal the end of
accumulation and the start of markup.
In distribution, you might
see a series of high-volume
up days that fail to push prices higher.
This is often followed by a downward plunge on
even higher volume. This pattern can signal the
end of distribution and the start of markdown.
Volume can also help with timing. In
a strong trend, wait for a pullback
on lower volume before entering. This often
provides a good entry point with lower risk.
And one final point about this: volume often
leads price. You might see volume patterns
change before price patterns do. This can give
you an early warning of potential trend changes.
Composite Man Concept
Wyckoff talked about the
"Composite Operator" in his books. This isn't
one person. It's a way to think about all the
big players as if they were one.
These big players include banks,
hedge funds, and other pros.
And they often act in similar
ways. They're all trying to make money. And they
have more info and power than regular traders.
The Composite Man isn't real. It's a tool
to help us understand the market. It's like
pretending the market has a mind of its own.
And this mind is smart and sometimes tricky.
Here's what the Composite Man does:
• He buys when prices are low.
• He sells when prices are high.
• He acts in its own interest.
• And he knows how to move prices.
The Composite Man doesn't control the
whole market. But it has a big impact. It
can push prices up or down for a while.
The Composite Man concept helps explain why
markets often move in ways that seem odd.
Why does price drop right before a
good news release? The Composite Man
might be selling into the excitement.
Why does a market sometimes go up on
bad news? The Composite Man might have
already sold. The bad news was expected.
Now it's buying again at lower prices.
Trading with the trend is key. If the
Composite Man is pushing price up, don't try to
short. You'll probably lose. Go with the flow.
Again, always check volume. It's the
footprint of the Composite Man. Big
volume moves are often important.
The Composite Man links to other
Wyckoff ideas. Springs and upthrusts, for
example, are often the work of the Composite
Man. We’ll talk about these in a minute.
This concept also explains why stop hunting
happens. The Composite Man knows where stops
are likely to be. It can push price to hit those
stops. Then it trades against the stop orders.
You'll soon realize that see that many price moves
aren't random. They're often planned.
Spring and Upthrust (Price Manipulation)
The Spring and the Upthrust are
key patterns in the Wyckoff method.
A Spring is a quick drop below
support that bounces back fast.
An Upthrust is a quick push
above resistance that fails fast.
Both are fake-outs that run stops outside
support and resistance. Smart money concepts
named them liquidity sweeps or liquidity runs.
Why do they happen? Because big players often push
price past key levels to trigger stop losses.
This lets them buy or sell at better prices.
It's like shaking a tree to make the fruit fall.
Let's look at Springs first. In a trading range,
price might dip below support. If it jumps back
up fast, that's a Spring. It means there's strong
buying down there. It often leads to a move up.
Here's how to spot a Spring:
• Price is in a range
• It breaks below support
• It doesn't stay there long
• Then it jumps back above support fast
Upthrusts are the opposite.
Price pops above resistance,
but falls back quickly. It shows there's strong
selling up there. It often leads to a move down.
Here's how to spot an Upthrust:
• Price is in a range
• It breaks above resistance
• It doesn't stay there long
• Then it drops back below resistance fast
Both patterns show a fight between buyers
and sellers. In a Spring, sellers try
to push price down, but buyers win.
In an Upthrust, buyers try to
push price up, but sellers win.
For a Spring, the plan is to buy
when price jumps back above support
For an Upthrust, you sell when
price drops back below resistance
But it's not always that easy. You
need to look at the bigger picture too.
For Springs, check if the overall trend is
up. A Spring in an uptrend is stronger than
one in a downtrend. Look for signs
of accumulation before the Spring.
This makes the pattern more likely to work .
For Upthrusts, check if the overall trend
is down. An Upthrust in a downtrend
is stronger than one in an uptrend.
Look for signs of distribution
before the Upthrust.
This makes the pattern more likely to work .
Volume is key in these patterns. In a Spring,
you want to see high volume on the drop
and even higher volume on the bounce.
This shows strong buying.
In an Upthrust, you want high
volume on the push up and even
higher on the drop. This shows strong selling .
Some traders do well without focusing on volume.
The price action itself can be enough.
The context matters a lot. A Spring or
Upthrust at the end of a long trend is
more powerful than one in the middle
of a range. It might signal a big trend change.
One trick is to look for smaller ranges near the
edge of bigger ranges. These often lead to good
breakouts. You might see Springs or Upthrusts
in these smaller ranges before a big move.
Sometimes, you won't see a Spring or Upthrust
at all. This is called a structural failure.
It happens when price fails to reach one side
of a range and then breaks out the other
way. This can be a strong signal too.
One way to practice is to look for these
patterns after the fact. Go through old
charts. Mark the Springs and Upthrusts.
See what happened after. This trains your
eye to spot them in real-time.
Advanced Wyckoff Concepts
Now let's dive into some
advanced Wyckoff concepts.
One advanced concept is the "creek".
This is a small, tight trading range
that forms after a big move.
It's like a pause in the
action. But it's not random.
It often shows up at key points in trends.
Creeks can be hard to spot if
you're not looking for them.
They might look like normal price action.
But they can signal big moves ahead.
Here's how to use creeks:
• Look for them after strong trends
• Check if volume dries up in the creek
• Watch for a strong move out of the creek
If you see these things, it might be
a good trade setup. The move out of
the creek often starts a new trend.
Another advanced concept is the idea
of "tests". These are like mini-versions of
springs and upthrusts. They happen all the time,
not just at major turning points.
A test is when price moves back to
a previous support or resistance level. It's
checking if that level still holds. If it does,
it can be a good entry point for a trade.
Tests are powerful because they show
real supply and demand in action.
They're not just lines on a chart. They
show where real buying and selling is happening.
Here's a pro tip: look for tests that fail. If
price tests a level and breaks through, that
can signal a big move. It means the previous
support or resistance isn't working anymore.
Another advanced idea is "absorption". This
is when big players buy or sell without
moving price much. It's hard to spot,
but it's a powerful signal.
Absorption often shows up as
high volume but little price movement.
It might look boring on a chart. But
it can signal that a big move is coming.
Wyckoff traders always think about context.
They don't just look at patterns. They think about
where those patterns fit in the bigger picture.
For example, a spring in an uptrend is
different from a spring in a downtrend.
A test of support after a long uptrend is
different from a test early in a trend.
Another advanced idea is "swing analysis".
This is about measuring the strength of
moves up and down. It can show you if
a trend is gaining or losing strength.
In an uptrend, you want to see higher
highs and higher lows. But how much higher?
Swing analysis helps you measure this.
If the swings are getting weaker,
it might signal a trend change coming.
Another advanced idea is "the fractal
analysis". This is about understanding that
Wyckoff patterns show up on all timeframes.
A spring on a 5-minute chart works the
same way as one on a monthly chart.
Understanding fractals can help
you trade multiple timeframes.
You might use a bigger timeframe for
direction, and a smaller one for entries.
Now, if you liked what you saw, we have plenty
more interesting trading guides for you!