In today’s video I’ll show you my secret
process to find the BEST stocks to day trade,
and the system I have in place to filter out
the bad stocks and focus on the ones with
the highest profit potential.
First, you want to look for stocks that are
liquid.
This means that there are a lot of buyers
and sellers in the market, which makes it
easier to enter and exit trades without affecting
the price too much.
Also, you want to focus on stocks that are
volatile.
A stock that moves a lot in price throughout
the day gives you more chances to buy low
and sell high.
Another important factor to consider is the
overall market trend.
You want to trade stocks that are moving in
the same direction as the overall market.
So when the market is bullish, you want to
trade stocks that are showing strength.
Now let’s get specific.
Here are the exact filters that I always use
in Finviz screener.
1.
Average Volume
Average Volume is perhaps the most important
filter for finding liquid stocks.
Average volume refers to the number of shares
traded on average each day.
The higher the volume, the more liquid the
stock is likely to be.
I usually set this filter to "Over 1 million
shares" to ensure that there are enough buyers
and sellers in the market.
The more shares that are being traded each
day, the easier it is to enter and exit positions
without causing a major impact on the price.
2.
Price
While not directly related to liquidity, the
price of a stock can also impact how easily
you can trade it.
I generally recommend setting the price filter
to "Over $30 dollars", to avoid stocks that
are too cheap and may not have enough volume.
Setting the price filter to "Over 30 dollars"
can be a good way to ensure that you're trading
stocks with adequate liquidity.
These stocks tend to attract more institutional
investors and large traders.
I try to avoid lower-priced stocks because
they often have smaller market capitalizations
and fewer shares outstanding, which can make
them more susceptible to big price swings
and manipulation.
3.
Relative volume
Another important filter you must use is the
relative volume.
Relative Volume compares the current trading
volume of a stock to its average volume over
a specific period, typically the past 30 trading
days.
When a stock is trading at a higher volume
than usual, it tells us that there's increased
interest and activity around that stock.
And when there's increased interest in a stock,
there's often a greater potential for significant
price action.
I recommend setting the Relative Volume filter
to Over 1, when looking for stocks to day
trade or scalp.
A Relative Volume of 1 means that the stock
is trading at its average volume.
Also, if you want to be more aggressive, you
could set the Relative Volume filter to Over
2.
A Relative Volume above 2 indicates that the
stock is trading at more than twice its normal
volume, which is a strong signal of increased
market interest and potential for significant
price action.
4.
Beta
As short-term traders, we're looking for stocks
that can make big moves in a short period
of time.
We want to get in, ride the momentum, and
get out with a quick profit.
And stocks with a high beta are more likely
to give us those opportunities.
Beta is a measure of a stock's volatility
in relation to the overall market, as represented
by the S&P 500 index.
Essentially, it quantifies how sensitive a
stock is to broad market swings.
Now, the market beta baseline is 1.
So stocks with a beta above 1 tend to be more
volatile than the general market, while stocks
with a beta below 1 tend to be less volatile.
By screening specifically for stocks with
a beta higher than 1, we focus on names that
historically demonstrate above average volatility
compared to the market.
A beta of 1.5, for example, means that the
stock is 50% more volatile than the market.
So, if the market moves up 1%, the stock should
theoretically move up 1.5%.
By setting the beta filter to Over 1, you
can quickly narrow down your list of potential
trades to only the most volatile names.
Depending on market conditions and your strategy,
you might set the filter to Over 1.5 or even
Over 2.
5.
Market cap
I also set the market cap filter to Over 1
billion dollars.
This way, we can quickly narrow down our list
of potential trades to only the most established
and actively traded names.
When we're talking about stocks with a market
cap over 1 billion dollars, we're talking
about the big leagues.
These are the companies that have the attention
of the major players on Wall Street.
Stocks with a market cap over 1 billion dollars
also tend to be more stable and less prone
to manipulation.
These are established companies with solid
fundamentals and a track record of success.
6.
Average True Range
The Average True Range is one of my favorite
indicators for measuring volatility and potential
profit opportunities.
In simple terms, ATR measures the average
range of a stock's price movement over a given
period of time, typically 14 days.
When a stock has a high ATR, it means that
it's experiencing significant price swings
on a regular basis.
The price is moving up and down more dramatically
than a stock with a lower ATR.
I like to set the w filter on Finviz to "Over
1".
This helps me quickly identify stocks that
are experiencing a high level of volatility,
and potential for significant price movement.
And that's exactly what we want to see as
day traders - stocks that are making big moves
and creating opportunities.
7.
Float
The size of a stock's float can also have
a big impact on its volatility and liquidity.
When we talk about a stock's float, we're
talking about the number of shares that are
actually available for trading on the open
market.
That's why I usually recommend setting the
float filter to Over 10 million when scanning
for potential trades.
This helps to ensure that there are enough
shares available for trading, and that the
stock is less likely to experience sudden,
erratic price swings.
8.
50 SMA
The 50-Day Simple moving average is my go-to
indicator to get a more complete picture of
a stock's trend.
You can also use the 20-Day moving average,
as an additional filter.
The 20-Day SMA is a shorter-term indicator
that's more sensitive to recent price action.
It's great for identifying potential trend
changes in the near term.
The 50-Day SMA is a longer-term indicator
that's less sensitive to short-term price
fluctuations.
It takes more time to change course, but when
it does, it can be a powerful signal of a
more significant trend change.
If a stock is trading above both the 20-Day
and 50-Day SMA, that's a strong sign that
it's in a well-established uptrend.
The shorter-term and longer-term trends are
aligned, and the stock has a lot of bullish
momentum behind it.
9.
Gap up
An up gap occurs when a stock opens significantly
higher than its previous day's close.
Gaps are often a sign of strong momentum and
sentiment in a particular direction.
When a stock gaps up, it means that there
was a lot of buying pressure and demand for
that stock in the pre-market or after-hours
trading sessions.
This is why I love to use the Gap Up Over
1% filter, when I'm scanning for potential
momentum trades.
By looking for stocks that have gapped up
by more than 1%, I can quickly identify names
that are experiencing significant overnight
moves and that may be poised for continued
momentum in the same direction.
For example, if a stock gaps up on high volume
and with a wide range, that's often a sign
of strong bullish momentum that could continue
throughout the trading day.
Combined with the previous filter, the 50-day
moving average, if the broader market is in
an uptrend and experiencing positive sentiment,
that may provide a tailwind for stocks that
gap up, and increase the likelihood of continued
momentum.
10.
52-Week High/Low
The 52-Week High-Low filter is a powerful
tool for identifying stocks that are trading
near their highest levels in the past year,
and that may be poised for a breakout or continuation
move.
These are the highest and lowest prices that
a stock has traded at over the past year,
or 52 weeks.
They represent the extremes of a stock's price
range during that time period, and can provide
important context for its current price action.
I like to use the “0% - 10% below high”
filter, and we're looking for stocks that
are trading within 10% of their 52-week high
price.
In other words, we want to find stocks that
are close to breaking out to new highs, but
haven't quite gotten there yet.
When a stock is trading near its 52-week high,
it means that there is a lot of bullish sentiment
and momentum behind it.
And by focusing on stocks that are very close
to making new highs, you will easily identify
names that may be on the verge of a big move
higher.
By combining these 10 filters, you're essentially
creating a powerful system that identifies
the most promising stocks for day trading.
Remember - the market is always changing,
and you’ll need to be flexible in your approach.
There may be times when applying all these
filters will result in a very small list of
stocks, or even no stocks at all.
In these situations, it's okay to adjust slightly
the strategy and loosen some of the filters,
to widen your pool of potential trades.
For example, if you're left with only several
stocks to choose from, skip the “gap up”
filter or adjust the “52-Week High Low”
one.
This will expand your list to include more
potential stocks to day trade.
By using this comprehensive set of filters,
you're putting the odds in your favor and
giving yourself the best possible chance to
find the stocks with the highest profit potential.
And now it’s time to trade them.
These videos will show you my favorite day-trading
strategies.