Many traders ignore volume.
And although volume is a simple concept, it
is difficult to analyze it correctly due to
inherent challenges in the markets.
These challenges make it impossible to read
true volume with the standard volume indicators.
And although most traders are familiar with
price and time oscillators, very few use volume
oscillators.
Volume oscillators are uniquely different
than price oscillators.
Instead of signaling overbought or oversold
price action, the volume oscillator provides
far more valuable information about what is
going on with the stock price before price
actually moves.
This gives traders a leading indicator that
shows the direction of price, breakout moves,
momentum runs, and bottoms or tops ahead of
price action.
But there’s a small problem.
Most volume oscillators you probably use,
like OBV, Money Flow, don’t always have
leading qualities.
If I have to guess, you probably use average
volume indicators where the average of volume
is calculated over a given number of past
bars to see if volume is increasing or decreasing
over that time period.
And it is okay to look at volume this way,
but you will be missing the most vital volume
information.
This isn’t the best approach to analyze
volume.
And let me show you WHY is that.
Volume has inherent distortions which will
lead to a faulty analysis by many traders.
For example in the stock market (and other
markets to a lesser degree), the opening of
the day has a multitude of orders that had
built up overnight and all get processed at
once.
This large influx of trade volume creates
a major distortion to what is actually happening
in the market.
Another distortion is created in the middle
of the day when the majority of market makers
go to lunch and market activity slows down.
A third distortion happens at the end of the
day, when traders try to adjust their orders
before the market closes.
They may want to be flat overnight or they
might want to get into a trade, but this influx
of orders at the end of the day is another
distortion to volume.
Another challenge to using a volume average
indicator is that every instrument has considerably
different levels of volume.
For example compare a stock with 40 million
shares per day vs. a stock with 10,000 shares
per day.
This vast difference makes it difficult to
read volume from one symbol to another symbol.
Additionally, if you change from one time
frame to another there will be huge volume
differences.
The volume on a 1 minute time frame is much
different than the volume on a 60 minute time
frame or a daily chart.
The key to getting past these challenges is
to use the time segmented volume.
Time segmented volume is the way to get consistent
volume data and eliminate all the volume distortions
that we discussed before.
So, Time Segmented Volume (TSV) is a volume
oscillator, and is considered one the best
volume oscillators ever written.
Its main advantage is the fact it reveals
large-lot vs. small-lot activity on the market.
This indicator is similar to on-balance volume
(OBV) because it measures the amount of money
flowing in or out of a particular stock.
But with a big advantage.
Time Segmented Volume is an oscillator that
compares various time segments of both price
and volume.
TSV indicator measures the amount of money
flowing in or out of a particular stock.
The baseline represents the zero line.
It segments a stock's price and volume according
to specific time intervals.
The price and volume data is then compared
to uncover periods of accumulation (buying)
and distribution (selling).
Time Segmented Volume is a leading indicator
because its movement is based on both the
stock's price and volume.
Here’s the key to why time segmented volume
works: Let’s start with volume on a 15 minute
chart and for this example, look at the 10:15
bar.
Now take the average of only the 10:15 bars
over the prior month and compare that average
to the current 10:15 bar.
The difference will give a true reading on
whether today’s 10:15 bar volume is higher
or lower in comparison to the exact same time
bars over the past month.
Now when you read the 10:15 bar you read the
price bar against the volume bar.
For example, let’s say the price action
shows a larger than normal bar, maybe 2 times
normal.
Let’s say price started out close to the
bottom of the bar with no wick, and it runs
up and closes close to the top of the bar.
This means a strong bullish bar, but if you
look down and you see less than average volume,
then you should be cautious about the price
movement.
In contrast, if you see 200% percent volume
you’ll know that increased volume was the
reason for the extra large price bar.
The key to understanding volume is reading
price action and volume action on the same
exact bars, using time segmented volume to
give you the true volume information you need,
and reading the chart to see if price and
volume are in harmony or if they are divergent.
Time segmented volume can confirm the move,
make you suspect of the move, or can tell
you if it is the end of the move and if a
likely change in direction is coming.
In any case, using time segmented volume will
eliminate volume distortions and increase
your trading edge.
Now let’s discuss how to read the Time Segmented
Volume oscillator.
When TSV crosses up through the zero line,
it signals positive accumulation or buying
pressure.
This action is considered bullish.
Conversely, when TSV crosses below the zero
line, it indicates distribution or selling
pressure, which typically precedes a move
down in price.
An important aspect to look for when reading
TSV is a contradiction of trends between price
and TSV.
Look for positive or negative divergences
between price and TSV in order to determine
potential tops and bottoms.
Several consecutive divergences increase the
reliability factor in trying to pinpoint price
reversals.
For instance, if a price is making successively
higher highs while TSV is making successively
lower highs, this would constitute a series
of negative divergences.
This would be a leading indication of a possible
top.
In this case, the TSV indicator exposes the
distribution pattern of the big market players
quietly selling the stock even while smaller
lot buyers push price up to the final high
before the correction.
If the price is making successively lower
lows while TSV is making successively higher
lows, this would constitute a series of positive
divergences.
This would be a leading indication of a possible
bottom.
In this case, the TSV indicator reveals the
accumulation pattern of the big market players
quietly buying the stock even while smaller
lot sellers push price down to the final low
before the rally up.
This is what I call volume divergence trading,
which is more powerful than regular divergence
trading.
You see, the big problem with most technical
traders is that they rely too heavily on price
and time indicators and don’t evaluate volume
indicators sufficiently.
In the current market place however, using
only price and time based indicators isn’t
enough for gaining consistency in the long
run.
Nowadays with the institutions using many
variables of specialized orders that control
price, volume is even more critical to use.
Price no longer is the most important indicator.
A combination of Price, Volume, and Time indicators
offer the most reliable, consistent, and leading
indication of how price is likely to behave
in the near term for short term trades.
So here are other examples of positive and
negative divergence trades, using the Time
Segmented Volume oscillator.
Using an exponential moving average (EMA)
with TSV provides an easy-to-read crossover
signal prior to a breakout move.
This is a huge advantage for technical traders,
especially during choppy sideways markets.
Being able to see the breakout crossover signal
on TSV will allow you to get in ahead of the
breakout.
When the moving average is above the centerline
this is a sign of accumulation and below the
centerline, a sign of distribution.
So, for an upside breakout for example, pay
extra attention to the TSV oscillator.
If you see a period of accumulation, meaning
the moving average above centerline, and you
see a new high in the time segmented volume,
at an important area of resistance, that’s
a high probability signal that the breakout
could be valid and a future upside move could
follow, like in this example.
Keep in mind that as you increase the value
of the moving average, the result is a smoothing
effect.
However, there is a trade-off.
As you increase the length of the moving average,
the indicator becomes less sensitive to daily
fluctuations.
And as a result, the indicator will have a
greater tendency to lag price.
So if you've tried some of the conventional
ways of day trading breakouts and they aren't
working for you, the Time Segmented Volume
will serve you better.
Here are other example of breakout trades,
using
the TSV oscillator.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support and don’t
forget to subscribe and hit the bell icon
to get notified when we release new videos.
Until next time.