If you stay, I'll show you the easiest way
to kick start your day trading journey,
even if you're a total beginner!
So what is day trading. Well,
it’s when you buy and sell different
instruments, such as stocks, currencies,
or crypto, within the same trading day.
When you’re day trading, you closely monitor
market movements, you analyze charts, and use
price action or technical indicators to find
potential trading opportunities.
Market structure
Day trading starts with the market
structure. You open a candlestick
chart, you zoom out, and start reading.
A successful day trader must learn to ride
market trends and figuring out who's running
the show in the market, buyers or sellers.
This is the first big secret to
successful day trading: finding
trades in the direction of the dominant trend.
An uptrend is like a staircase, with each new
high stepping above the previous one.
As long as the lows keep respecting
the previous lows, the buyers remain in control.
When the price takes a dive below a previous low,
that's a shift in market structure – a sign
that the sellers might be taking over.
On the flip side, a downtrend is like a slide,
with each new low slipping below the last.
The sellers keep the pressure on, as long
as the highs can't reach the previous high.
But when the price finally breaks above a previous
high, it's a sign that the buyers might take
control. Again, it’s shift in market structure.
Sometimes, the market takes a break from trending.
This is when the price gets stuck in a sideways
range, bouncing between supply and demand. We call
this a consolidation.
Trend trading
Now, trend trading is the
perfect strategy for beginners.
The simplicity of following the dominant
trend is precisely what makes it so powerful,
especially for newbies.
If your market is trending,
day trading pullbacks is your best choice.
If it’s a trading range day, you’ll enter at
the extremes of the range, and stay out of
the middle because it can be very choppy.
Even safer is to trade ranges that
align with the previous trend.
So if you spot a consolidation after a previous
uptrend, it’s better to trade only the lower side
of the range, looking for “buy” signals only.
You’re still trend trading…but
during range bound conditions.
Price action and candlesticks analysis
In order to correctly read the market, you must
rely on price action and candlesticks analysis.
Learn to read market momentum
using candlesticks…and you’ll
be one step ahead of most traders.
It’s simple. The body of the candlestick
shows the opening and closing prices.
The wicks show the highest and lowest
prices reached during that period.
Bullish candlestick are those where the
closing price is higher than the opening price.
Bearish ones are those with the closing price
lower than the opening price.
During trending days, it's all
about price momentum and follow-ups.
When the market is in a strong uptrend,
you'll see a series of bullish trend candles,
with decent-sized bodies and high closing prices.
The bars slowly ascend, creating a parabolic curve
that makes you wish you had entered earlier.
Any pullback attempts are short-lived, with
narrow bearish bars having wicks at the bottom.
The key is to look for more bullish bars than
bearish ones, both in quality and quantity.
If you witness these conditions, and
market structure confirms the trend,
look for “buy” opportunities.
In a strong downtrend,
you'll see consecutive bearish bars with
average-sized bodies and wicks on top.
Bullish pullback bars are small and short-lived.
The close of each candle is
lower than the previous one.
Again, you look to “sell” pullbacks
if the market structure confirms the trend.
Another way to identify trends is by monitoring
highs and lows of the individual candlesticks.
In an uptrend, each follow-up bullish bar should
have a higher high, a higher low, and
higher close than the previous one.
For downtrends, bearish bars should make
lower lows, lower highs, and lower closes.
Again, when the market is trending, pullbacks
are your best choice. You want to align your
trades with the prevailing market sentiment.
Range days are harder to day trade. Ranges are
essentially consolidation phases.
To read a price action range,
you first you analyze wicks.
Ranges are filled with wicks,
especially at the top and bottom of the range.
These wicks represent failed attempts by
buyers and sellers to push the
price beyond the boundaries.
You’ll also notice an alternation
between bullish and bearish strength.
In a range, both sides are active, but
there is no consistency or continuation.
Bullish and bearish bars are roughly equal in
quantity, and any strength is short-lived.
You’ll also see many Doji candles
and overlapping price action.
Doji candles indicate indecisiveness.
Overlapping bars, where the size of
the bars are similar or inside each
other, also suggest sideways movement.
When you day trade ranges, you always enter at
the extremes of the range. Not in the middle.
Look to “buy” the lower channel of the range
during uptrends, and “sell” the upper channel
of the range during downtrends.
Supply and demand
Market structure and candlestick analysis
go hand in hand with supply and demand.
You see, when you day trade, you don’t
have the ability to influence the market.
It's the big players that really move the market.
They're the ones with the buying and selling power
to create imbalances in supply and demand.
Know this: the smart money never places their
full position at once. They break it into
smaller pieces, to avoid pushing the price
away from their desired entry point.
And that's where supply and
demand zones come into play.
These are the areas where the
banks have initiated positions, causing
sharp advances or declines in price.
Demand zones are like magnets, attracting
buyers and causing the price to bounce back up.
They form when banks place a
large number of “buy” positions,
creating an imbalance that sends the price higher.
Supply zones are pushing the price back down,
when banks unload a significant
number of “sell” positions.
So, how do you spot these zones. You
look for clues in the price action.
You want to find sharp rises and declines
– the footprints of the smart money.
Look for big, bold candles
with little to no wicks.
These are the signs that the big
players are making their move.
To find demand zones, look for a fast upward move.
Place a line at the high of the most recent
red candle before the price increase,
and another at the most recent swing low.
For supply zones, look for a sharp decline and
place your lines at the low of the most recent
green candle and the most recent swing high.
In theory, when price revisits these
areas, it has the potential to reverse.
Now here's the catch – not
all zones are created equal.
There are two golden rules you need to remember.
Recent zones are far more powerful than old ones.
The market is more likely to respond to
zones that have been created recently.
Second, supply and demand zones are one-time use
only. Once the price hits a zone and reverses,
it loses its power. The probability of another
reversal at the same spot is much lower.
There are four main types of price
structures that create supply/demand zones.
The "Rally-base-Rally" is a demand
zone that forms during an uptrend.
It's like a pit stop for the price to catch its
breath before continuing its upward momentum.
First, you'll see a rally, then a
little consolidation (also known
as the base), and finally another rally.
On the flip side, we have the "Drop-base-Drop",
which is a supply zone that
forms during a downtrend.
You'll see a drop, then a little
consolidation, and finally another
drop. This is also a continuation pattern.
The "Drop-base-Rally" forms a demand zone when
the market decides to switch from falling, to
rising. You'll see a drop, a base, and then a
rally. This creates your demand zone.
We also have the "Rally-base-Drop",
which forms a supply zone when the
market decides to switch from rising,
to falling. You'll see a rally, a base, and then
a drop. And this creates your supply zone.
All these zones are like magnets for future price
action. When the price revisits a demand zone,
it's likely to bounce back up
and continue its upward trend.
When the price revisits a supply zone, it's likely
to get rejected and continue its downward trend.
So when the price approaches these
zones, look for opportunities!
VSA
Volume Spread Analysis is the ultimate weapon in
day trading, the secret sauce that will help you
understand imbalances between supply and demand.
V S A has 2 main components: spread and volume.
Spread is the difference between the
opening and closing price of a candlestick.
It's like the market's way of showing us how much
ground it covered during a specific time period.
A wide spread means there was a lot of
price movement, while a narrow
spread indicates less activity.
Volume shows the number of transactions
that occurred during that same time period.
It's like the market's way of showing us how
much effort was put into that price movement.
High volume means there
was a lot of participation,
while low volume suggests a lack of interest.
There are 2 main V S A concepts:
Sign of Strength and Sign of Weakness.
Sign of Strength is when the market is
showing you that the buyers are in control
and demand is overpowering supply. This
imbalance causes the market to rise.
Sign of Weakness is when the market
is telling you that the sellers are in
control and supply is overwhelming demand.
This imbalance leads to a market decline.
V S A goes hand in hand with the WYckoff method.
According to this theory, changes
in market price are the result of
effort versus result, volume versus price.
If price action and volume are in sync,
the trend is likely to continue.
But if there's a significant
difference between volume and price, the
trend may be about to change direction.
These are the top five Sign of Strength patterns.
First up, we have the "Down Thrust." This appears
as a bullish pin bar or a Doji candle
with ultra-high or above-average volume.
The spread is super low,
but the volume is very high.
V S A tells you that low spread should mean
low volume, but when there's a mismatch,
it's a sign that demand is overpowering supply,
potentially causing price to rise in near future.
Next, we have the "Selling Climax." This one
shows up as a high-spread bearish candle with
a big downward rejection wick, accompanied
by ultra-high or above-average volume.
This signals that the market could rise
because there is more demand than supply.
We also have "Bearish Effort lower than the
Bearish Result." This pattern appears as a
high-spread bearish candle with a larger spread
than the previous candle, but the volume is lower.
It's like the sellers are trying to
push prices down, but they just can't
gain strength. This disagreement between price
and volume could lead to a bullish breakout.
On the flip side, we have "Bearish Effort
higher than the Bearish Result." This one
shows up as a low-spread bearish candle
with a smaller spread than the previous
candle, but the volume is higher.
It's like the sellers are pushing hard,
but the price don’t move much. This clash
between volume and price could be a sign
that the buyers are about to take over.
We can also have the "No Supply Bar." This
pattern appears as a low-spread bearish candle
with a downward wick and lower volume than the
previous two candles. It's like the sellers have
just disappeared, leaving the buyers to run the
show. When supply dries up, prices tend to rise.
Sign of Weakness patterns are the market's way of
waving a red flag, warning you that the
sellers might be ready to take control.
First, we have the "Up Thrust." This pattern
appears as a bearish pin bar or doji candle with
ultra-high or above-average volume. The spread
is super low, but the volume is going crazy. When
there's a mismatch between spread and volume,
price has potential to fall in near future.
Next, we have the "Buying Climax." This one
shows up as a high-spread bullish candle with
a big upward rejection wick, paired with
ultra-high or above-average volume. When
supply overpowers demand, it's time
to watch out for a potential drop.
Next we have "Bullish Effort lower than
the Bullish Result." This pattern appears
as a high-spread bullish candle with a
larger spread than the previous candle,
but here's the catch: the volume is lower.
If there's no effort, there shouldn't be
a result. This disagreement between
price and volume could be a sign that
the market might decrease in the future.
On the other hand, we have "Bullish Effort
higher than the Bullish Result." This one
shows up as a low-spread bullish candle with
a smaller spread than the previous
candle, but the volume is higher.
When volume and price don't see eye to
eye, price could fall in near future.
We also have the "No Demand Bar." This
pattern appears as a low-spread bullish
candle with an upward wick and lower
volume than the previous two candles.
It's like the buyers have left the building,
leaving the sellers to run the show. When
demand dries up, prices tend to fall.
Learn all these patterns because Volume
Spread Analysis is one of the most
powerful day trading strategies.
VWAP
VWAP is one of the best day trading indicators.
VWAP is a dynamic indicator that
updates throughout the trading day,
giving you a real-time view of where the price
is trading in relation to its "fair value."
VWAP is like a magnet for price action. It
acts as a dynamic support or resistance level,
and price tends to gravitate towards it.
When a market is trading above VWAP,
buyers are in control, and when it's trading
below it, the sellers running the show.
VWAP can also help you find potential entry and
exit points. When the price is trading above
VWAP and suddenly dips below it, it could
be a sign that the buyers are losing steam
and it's time to consider selling.
Or when the price is trading below VWAP
and suddenly pops above it, it could be a
signal that the buyers are ready to take
charge and it might be the time to “buy”.
VWAP can also help you with the strength of
a trend. If price is consistently trading
above VWAP and making higher highs,
it's a sign of a healthy uptrend.
Another strategy is to use VWAP in
combination with candlestick patterns. If price
is trading above the main line and you see a
bullish candlestick pattern, like a candle with a
long lower wick, it could be a sign to go long.
Pivot points
must be always present on your charts.
These levels are like a cheat sheet for
the market, telling you where the price is
likely to find buying or selling pressure.
Pivot points can act as a magnet
for price action, just like VWAP.
When a market is trading above the main pivot
point, it's like the buyers are in control,
and when it's trading below the main pivot
point, the sellers are running the show.
But pivot points aren't just about the
main level. The other pivot levels can
also provide potential entry and exit points.
When price is trading near S1 or S2 level and
suddenly bounces higher, it could be a sign
that the buyers are ready to take charge.
When price is trading near R1 or
R2 level and suddenly drops lower,
it could be a signal that the sellers
are taking over and it's time to “sell”.
A popular day trading strategy is to use these
pivots as a guide for your entries and exits.
If you see price trading near a pivot and you spot
a bullish candlestick pattern, or a VSA pattern,
it could be a sign to go long.
Confluence of signals
Never enter into a day trading position
without seeing confluence. This is
when multiple factors and signals come
together at the same point in the market.
You want to find setups that have the same
price signal from multiple methodologies.
Supply and demand zones, volume, pivots,
all these factors will offer you signals.
When some of these tools start lining
up at the same location on your chart,
you found a confluence area.
Let's say you spot a bullish V S
A pattern right near a daily pivot point. If
the VWAP is also close, that’s a confluence.
A time to consider a buying position.
Or you find a supply zone that aligns
with a pivot point. If price momentum confirm
that zone, you now have a “sell” opportunity.
Day trading tips for beginners
After over 15 years of experience,
these are my best day trading tips for beginners.
First, use a small account or even a demo
account in your first 6 months, to
practice and build your skills.
Second, manage your risk like your life
depends on it. Always use stop losses to
protect your downside, and don't
let a single trade wipe you out.
Also, losses are inevitable in day trading –
you accept them and move on. And you don’t try
to get back your money after a losing trade.
Also, keep your charts clean and simple. Less
is often more when it comes to day trading.
And accept the fact you won’t become an expert
day trader overnight. You need lots
of market exposure. The more exposure
you have to different markets and setups, the
better you'll become at pattern recognition.
If this day trading guide helped you, make
sure you don't miss out on our next video.