Whether you’re day trading or making long-term
investment decisions, it’s important to
know what the markets are doing.
Often this is done with market indexes, but
these values don’t always give you the whole
picture, and oftentimes they don’t.
That’s why smart traders use market breadth
indicators.
In today’s video, I will share the best
market internal indicators that will reveal
to you the overall market movements.
It may sound complicated at first if you’re
not familiar with these indicators, but trust
me, they are real game-changers and will help
you to make better decisions.
Technical analysis has one major fault.
Almost all indicators and patterns are based
on what happened in the past, not what is
forecasted to happen in the future.
And as being a technical trader myself, I
have to always remember this when placing
my trades.
But there are some indicators that actually
are forward looking and these forward-looking
indicators are known as Market Internals.
If they are used correctly, they might be
one of the best tools you can use to time
the markets!
Market Internals are mathematical formulas
that measure the number of advancing and declining
stocks, and their volume, to calculate the
participation in a stock index's price movements.
By evaluating how many stocks are increasing
or decreasing in price, and how much volume
these stocks are trading, Market Internals
help in confirming stock index price trends,
or can warn of future price reversals.
Breadth indicators are primarily used for
two reasons:
Market Sentiment: because such indicators
can help determine if a market is more likely
to rise or fall.
Trend Strength: because the indicators can
help determine the strength of a bullish or
bearish trend.
There are many different indicators that traders
and investors can use in their analysis.
Here are the most important ones that can
help you break down the market and what move
it’s about to make.
First is the Advance/Decline (A/D) Line
This indicator, mostly used in the U.S. stock
market, can be calculated on both a daily
and weekly basis and is the most basic and
widely used indication of breadth in the major
U.S. stock exchanges.
The construction of the advance/decline line
is calculated by subtracting the number of
stocks declining on any given day, from the
number advancing relative to the prior close.
When more stocks are moving up than are moving
down, this line is advancing (it has a positive
slope and its direction is higher) and vice
versa in a declining trend.
These figures do not take into account stocks
that were unchanged on the day or week, but
only those up or down from the prior close.
The value of the A/D line always begins from
some fixed starting point, and this means
that the initial value begins at 0.
What is most relevant in the advance/decline
figure is the slope of the line, not the absolute
cumulative value.
How to Read the Advance-Decline Line
The advance-decline line is seldom used by
itself.
Instead, the ADL is plotted against its relevant
index.
to confirm trends or for the likelihood of
reversals.
There are four interpretations of the concept:
1.
Advance-Decline Line and Index Trending Upwards
A situation where the advance-decline line
and index are both trending upwards is said
to be bullish.
The rise in the index is driven by the rise
in the majority of stocks in the index.
As such, investors tend to believe that the
market will continue its uptrend in the near
future.
2.
Advance-Decline Line Trending Downwards and
Index Trending Downwards
A situation where the advance-decline line
and index are both trending downwards is said
to be bearish.
The decline in the index is driven by the
decline in a majority of stocks in the index.
As such, investors tend to believe that the
market will continue its downtrend in the
near future.
3.
Advance-Decline Line Trending Upwards and
Index Trending Downwards
A situation where the advance-decline line
is trending upwards, but the index is trending
downwards is said to be a bullish divergence.
The decline in the index is driven by the
decline in a minority of stocks in the index.
Therefore, it indicates that sellers are losing
their conviction.
As such, investors tend to believe that the
market will show a reversal and trend upwards
in the near future.
4.
Advance-Decline Line Trending Downwards and
Index Trending Upwards
A situation where the advance-decline line
is trending downwards, but the index is trending
upwards is said to be a bearish divergence.
The increase in the index is driven by the
increase in a minority of stocks in the index.
Therefore, it indicates that buyers are losing
their conviction.
As such, investors tend to believe that the
market will show a reversal and trend downwards
in the near future.
Second, we have the McClellan Oscillator
This oscillator will be applicable to equities
markets that have a substantial number of
individual stocks that trade actively.
The McClellan oscillator also provides an
indication of the trend in market breadth
and is presented in a familiar way, as a (smoothed)
difference between the number of advancing
and declining stocks on the NYSE.
Because of the nature of momentum, a strong
bullish trend is followed by a large number
of stocks going up.
A weakening bull market is signaled by a smaller
number of stocks making large advances in
price, as discussed already with the A/D line.
Buy indications are given when the McClellan
oscillator falls into an oversold area, which
is defined as –70 to –100, and then turns
up.
Sell signals are generated when the McClellan
oscillator rises into the overbought zone
of +70 and +100, and then turns down.
When the oscillator is above +100 or falls
below –100, it is a sign of an extremely
overbought/oversold market—such readings
can be associated with powerful bull or bear
market trends.
The rule of thumb with such extreme readings
is to assume that the existing trend has staying
power for only another couple of weeks or
somewhat longer.
Like the MACD and Stochastics models, the
McClellan oscillator is best employed looking
for upside and downside crossovers, from within
an overbought/oversold area.
There are often crossovers, for example, in
the slow stochastic that does not occur in
either its oversold or overbought zones.
In a similar fashion, the signals that occur
in the middle ranges of the McClellan oscillator
are best ignored without compelling other
evidence of a technical nature.
Third indicator is the Arms Index (TRIN)
The Arms Index brings in volume to its formula
so is a hybrid indicator, with price and volume.
The Arms Index indicates whether volume is
flowing into advancing or declining stocks.
The index shows whether more of the total
volume is advancing volume or whether more
of the total volume is declining volume, for
all stocks on that exchange.
If more volume is associated with declining
stocks on any given day, that day’s Arms
Index will wind up being above 1.
If more volume is associated with advancing
stocks than declining stocks, the Arms Index
will register under 1, at the close.
The Arms Index is calculated over the course
of the trading day, but the close is primarily
what is of interest.
Extremes in the Arms Index have an inverse
relationship to the market.
High Arms Index readings, well above 1, indicate
heavy selling pressure.
If Arms Index closes above 1 persist over
a few or more days, this is associated with
a likelihood that the market is oversold,
perhaps near a bottom, and might soon turn
up—in this sense the Arms Index functions
as a contrary indicator.
The idea is if everyone is selling, it might
be the time to buy.
It depends of course on the circumstances,
but when either buying or selling activity
predominates, it gets over done, hence the
terms overbought or oversold.
Traders generally take anything under 1.0
to be a buy signal.
Conversely, a number above 1.0 is a sell signal.
The further away you get from neutrality,
the stronger the bulls or bears are on that
day.
However, if TRIN gets too far away from 1.0,
it’s a sign that the market may soon reverse.
A number above 3.0 or below 0.5 could be a
sign of an imminent reversal.
Traders use market breadth indicators in conjunction
with other forms of technical analysis, such
as chart patterns and technical indicators,
to maximize the odds of success.
For example, if the Advance/Decline Line starts
to drop while the S&P 500 is still rising,
traders will watch closely for the S&P 500
to break below a rising trend line, break
below support, or for technical indicators
to turn bearish.
This will help confirm that the price may
be starting to decline, and therefore the
trader can exit longs or initiate short positions.
If the majority of the securities tracked
by the indicator are “advancers”, then
investors expect a rosier market going forward,
while a majority of “decliners” would
give investors pause, indicating weakening
demand for the stocks.
Essentially, market internals point to a convergence
or a divergence in securities markets.
If the data reveals a confirmation then the
market index being tracked will continue its
direction.
If there’s a divergence, then the market
might steer into a different direction.
Market internals can provide a much-needed
clarity for investors, and lead to more stable
and savvy investment outcomes.
So, by determining whether more cash is flowing
in or out of the market, breadth indicators
can be a reliable powerful predictive tool
on market movement and momentum—one that
can give investors a big edge over the competition
on a regular basis.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.