As a trader, you are probably familiar with
several theories concerning market structure
and cycles.
Some of the more popular ones include the
Elliott Wave Principle and the Dow Theory.
In today’s video, I plan to add one more
important type of market analysis to your
trading arsenal, namely a price action based
approach known as the Wyckoff trading method.
The Wyckoff Method consists of a series of
principles and strategies which can be applied
to all sorts of financial markets.
I will break Wyckoff’s method into 4 parts:
• The three laws of Wyckoff
• The Composite Man
• Wyckoff Price Cycle
• Wyckoff Volume Spread Analysis
The three laws of Wyckoff
Wyckoff's method rests on three fundamental
“laws”.
1.
The law of supply and demand
When demand is greater than supply, prices
rise, and when supply is greater than demand,
prices fall.
The trader can study the balance between supply
and demand by comparing price and volume bars
over time, as a way to better visualize the
relation between supply and demand.
This often provides insights into the next
market movements.
2.
The Law of Cause and Effect
The second law states that the differences
between supply and demand are not random.
Instead, they come after periods of preparation,
as a result of specific events.
In Wyckoff's terms, a period of accumulation
(cause) eventually leads to an uptrend (effect).
In contrast, a period of distribution (cause)
eventually results in a downtrend (effect).
3.
The Law of Effort vs. Result
The third Wyckoff law states that the changes
in an asset’s price are a result of an effort,
which is represented by the trading volume.
If the price action is in harmony with the
volume, there is a good chance the trend will
continue.
But, if the volume and price diverge, the
market trend is likely to stop or change direction.
For instance, imagine that a market starts
to consolidate with a very high volume after
a long bearish trend.
The high volume indicates a big effort, but
the sideways movement suggests a small result.
So, there is a lot of activity, but no more
significant price drops.
Such a situation could indicate that the downtrend
may be over, and a reversal is near.
The Composite Man
Wyckoff created the idea of the Composite
Man as an imaginary identity of the market.
He proposed that investors and traders should
study the stock market as if a single entity
was controlling it.
It always acts in his own best interest to
ensure he can buy low and sell high.
Think of composite man as an evil entity,
like the bad guy in a movie, sitting behind
the scenes controlling markets by pushing
buttons.
His goal is to move the markets to your disadvantage.
The composite man is continually seeking to
maximize his profit at “your” expense.
The Composite Man’s behavior is the opposite
of retail traders, but according to Wyckoff,
the Composite Man uses a somewhat predictable
strategy, from which traders can learn from.
Here are some main ideas of composite man:
• Composite man plans and executes his deception
well in advance
• Composite man is there to fool you to
buying positions that he has already accumulated
• Composite man will tempt you to sell at
the worst possible time
• Composite man leaves subtle evidence of
his strategy for those who understand him
Now, let’s use the Composite Man concept
to illustrate a market cycle.
1.
Accumulation
The process of accumulation is the first stage
of the Wyckoff price cycle.
The Composite Man accumulates assets before
most investors.
The accumulation is done gradually to avoid
the price from changing significantly.
Bulls are gaining power slowly and as a result,
they are poised to push prices higher.
Although the Accumulation stage is related
with the bulls gaining authority, the price
action on the chart is flat.
In other words, the process of accumulation
is illustrated by a ranging price structure
on the chart.
Higher lows within the range is usually considered
a signal that the price action is currently
in an Accumulation phase.
2.
Markup Phase (Uptrend)
The Markup is the second stage of the Wyckoff
trading cycle.
When the Composite Man is holding enough power,
and the selling force is depleted, he starts
pushing the market up.
The emerging trend attracts more investors,
causing demand to increase.
There may be multiple phases of accumulation
during an uptrend.
We may call them re-accumulation phases, where
the bigger trend stops and consolidates for
a while, before continuing its upward movement.
As the market moves up, other traders are
encouraged to buy.
At this point, demand is higher than supply.
3.
Distribution
The Distribution process is the third stage
of the Wyckoff price cycle.
Here, the Composite Man starts distributing
his holdings.
He sells his profitable positions to those
entering the market at a late stage.
The distribution phase is marked by a sideways
movement that absorbs demand until it gets
exhausted.
The price action on the chart at this stage
is flat.
One indication that the market is in a Distribution
stage will be the sustained failure of price
to create higher lows on the chart.
The price action creates lower highs which
is an indication that the market is currently
experiencing a selloff.
4.
Markdown Phase (Downtrend)
The Markdown is the last stage of the Wyckoff
price cycle.
Soon after the distribution phase, the market
starts reverting to the downside.
After the Composite Man is done selling a
good amount of his shares, he starts pushing
the market down.
The supply becomes much greater than demand,
and the downtrend is established.
When the bearish trend is finally over, a
new accumulation phase begins.
Wyckoff Volume Spread Analysis
Volume is of a great importance for the Wyckoff
trader, because it can provide valuable information
into what is really going on “behind the
scenes”.
Wyckoff Volume Analysis provides confirmation
of progressing events during the Wyckoff Price
Cycle.
As I said earlier, high volumes can lead to
sustained price moves on the chart.
Wyckoff Volume Spread Analysis also helps
you identify periods when the price is transitioning
between the different stages of the Wyckoff
Price Cycle.
When the price moves through a key level during
the Wyckoff Price Cycle, you should consider
the move valid if the trading volumes are
relatively high during the breakout.
If the volumes are decreasing, then you are
probably looking at a spring (which is a false
breakout) rather than a real breakout.
This is an example of an Accumulation stage.
Notice on the chart that the first two bottoms
are slightly increasing.
This hints that the market is likely in an
accumulating stage.
Suddenly, we see a bearish breakdown through
the lower level of the range.
However, the volume is decreasing during the
breakdown through the level, which suggests
that this could be a false breakout (Spring)
before the real breakout actually takes place.
The price reverses after the breakdown and
at the same time, the trading volume is increasing.
This is a strong indication that the Price
Cycle is likely entering the second stage
– the Markup.
How to apply Wyckoff method in your trading
Traders can use the Wyckoff Price Cycle to
recognize upcoming price moves.
For example, the end of an Accumulation stage
is the beginning of a Markup, which could
be traded to the long side.
At the same time, the end of a Distribution
stage is the beginning of a Markdown, which
could be traded to the short side.
Understanding the different stages within
the price cycle will allow you to position
for the next most likely price tendency.
Ideally, you should enter a trade when the
price action is transiting from Accumulation
to Markup and from Distribution to Markdown.
First, you would need to confirm the current
stage when the price is ranging.
It would help to identify increasing bottoms
for an Accumulation and decreasing tops for
Distribution.
In addition, it would be useful to analyze
the previous price moves for additional clues.
Another way you can attempt to confirm an
Accumulation or Distribution stage is by identifying
a Spring, which is the transitional price
action behavior that often occurs between
the cycle stages.
Chart patterns can also be helpful in identifying
Accumulation and Distribution processes on
the chart.
The potential price move out of a pattern
could help you identify the transition to
a Markup or a Markdown.
The actual trade comes when the price action
breaks the range in the direction of the expected
move.
For example, you could buy when the price
breaks the flat range through the upper level.
Contrary, you could sell when the price action
breaks the lower support level of the Distribution
area.
And, you must keep an eye on volume to confirm
that your decision is correct.
If you are trading a Markup, your stop loss
should be located below the lowest point of
the Accumulation stage.
If you are trading a Markdown, then your stop
loss order should be positioned above the
highest point during the Distribution stage.
Here, the cycle begins with the Distribution
phase.
At this point, the price action breaks the
upper level of the range.
However, the trading volumes at that time
are decreasing, Therefore, we can reason that
a Spring pattern on the chart may be forming.
The price action reverses afterwards and breaks
the lower level of the Distribution channel
on increasing volume.
This was the ideal moment to enter a short
position, placing a stop loss above the highest
point of the Distribution range.
See that the Markdown begins right after the
selloff and the price of decreased aggressively.
Then we see a sideways movement, which hints
that the Markdown phase is probably completed.
If you haven’t reached your profit target,
you would close your trade when the price
action begins to create increasing tops on
the chart.
When price finishes a Markdown stage, it starts
an Accumulation.
During the Accumulation, we see that the price
drops on decreasing volumes and breaks the
channel downwards
Here, we see a breakout through the upper
level of the Accumulation channel.
This is a strong buy signal, which you could
use to go long.
The stop loss order goes below the lowest
point of the Accumulation phase.
The price action enters a Markup stage afterwards,
as the price rises creating higher highs.
After a strong increase the price action starts
to range, suggesting the Markup stage is probably
completed and the new Distribution stage is
on its way.
This video was basically an introduction to
Wyckoff trading and I tried to keep things
as simple as possible.
If you enjoyed this type of content and want
more Wyckoff strategies, leave us a like to
show your support and in future videos we’ll
go deeper with some advanced Wyckoff concepts
that can be applied to day trading and swing
trading.
Until next time.