Tell me if this sounds familiar: you have
a signal to trade, you enter, you place your
stop loss and take profit and then price goes
in the opposite direction.
And then you pray for the chance to close
your trade at breakeven.
You hope that price will return to your entry
point, just to close that bad trade.
This is you, trapped in a losing position.
And your entry point, is your salvation.
That’s the psychology of a trapped trader.
In today’s video, I’ll show how to take
advantage of trapped traders and how to identify
key areas on a chart where traders are anxious
and eager to exit their losing trades.
It’s gonna be interesting, so, like, subscribe,
and stick around for the full video.
The psychology of a trapped trader
When you place a trade, you expect the market
to move in the direction you anticipate.
If the market begins moving in the opposite
direction, your fear takes over.
You will continue to hold the losing trade,
but hoping the market could still come back
to your entry point.
On some occasions the market will end up coming
back to where you entered.
And you will be able to close your trade at
a small loss or even better, at break-even.
Unfortunately the vast majority of the time,
the market doesn’t come back and instead
continues to move further and further away
from the entry point.
True story: that’s exactly how I blew my
first account.
I waited and waited for the market to return
to my entry level.
And at some point, the loss became so large
and I received a margin call.
A trader trapped in a losing position is forced
to take an emotional trading decision.
Your goal is to identify and trade against
the positions of such traders.
You capitalize on the vulnerable traders who
are caught on the wrong side of the market.
So let’s see where you can find traders
holding losing positions in the market.
LONG CANDLES
There is one event in which you can be sure
retail traders will place trades.
This event is when the market makes a large
move in one direction, a large range candle.
These candles always make traders place trades.
When you see a large range candle form in
the market, a big number of traders will place
trades in the direction of the candle.
If the market begins to move in the opposite
direction to which the large range candle
has formed, then all of the traders who have
placed trades will become trapped in losing
trades.
How do you take advantage of this situation?
We’ll you know that their biggest desire
is for price to return to their entry level.
In this example, after this big green candle,
lots if traders were trapped around this area.
If the market continues to move against these
traders, at some point.
some of them will close their positions.
But a lot of them will wait for a breakeven
chance.
And look what happened when price returned
to the previous level.
You see the immediate reaction?
Price rejected the level aggressively.
That’s because the losing traders finally
had their chance to exit their trades.
You want to find those areas on the chart,
and open position when losing traders close
their trades.
LARGE WICKS
In many cases, large range candles often turn
into a different type of candle before they
close.
The candle they turn into is a pin bar.
When pin bars are forming, they will look
heavily bullish or bearish, depending on the
type of pin.
But when big players come in, the candle which
initially looked really bullish or really
bearish, now has a large wick on it.
The wick contains the traders who are now
trapped in losing trades.
The longer the wick (or shadow) of the bar,
the better because it indicates the wrong
movement which has prevailed in the market.
Look at this example, there are many wick,
but this one stands out the most.
This would be the main wick I would try to
trade.
This would be the “point of pain”, the
point where losing traders would happily exit
their trades.
Notice how price challenged the area of the
pin bar, and look what happened.
We have a first, small, rejection, and another
one, this time much bigger.
A long trade here would have been a decent
trade.
You enter a buy position, where other traders
close their previous sell positions.
This adds momentum, to your trade.
FALSE BREAKOUTS
A false breakout is when price moves beyond
the previously established level and then
retreats back below it.
And of course, after a false breakout, many
traders will be trapped on the wrong side
of the market.
If we look at this example, from a typical
retail traders’ perspective, you can understand
why such a large amount of traders became
trapped in losing trades.
To begin with, the market was advancing higher
which made many traders believe the market
was in a strong up-trend.
As the price climbed higher, a bullish large
range candle started to form, which made the
retail traders think they were seeing a significant
up-move taking place.
As a huge mass of retail traders started to
buy, smart money saw an opportunity to take
profits of their own buy trades using the
buy orders from the retail traders.
That resulted into a false breakout and the
retail traders are now stuck in losing long
positions.
And, look what happened the next time price
reached the previous level.
An immediate reaction.
Losing traders had their chance of exiting
their trades, which drove the market down.
Again, you want to target this area, for a
short entry.
BREAKOUTS WITHOUT RE-TEST
A breakout of an important level, with a large
body candle, without a retest, is another
situation, during which a lot of traders are
trapped.
Let’s analyze this chart.
Price fell aggressively right through the
support level.
The breakout candle was a big red candlestick.
No chance of retest whatsoever.
As price continues to drop, buyers are trapped.
They wait for the price to climb back up,
to exit their trades in the hopes of limiting
their losses.
The short traders are now happy and may consider
adding to their positions if the price revisits
the price level.
Lastly, the traders who did not enter the
market yet may go short if the price comes
back to the previous support level, in anticipation
of prices dropping further.
And of course, look at the reaction at the
level.
Human emotions play a big part in the price
action observed in markets.
A price chart can be seen of as a timeline
of optimism and pessimism.
It illustrates how market participants react
to changing future expectations.
ACCUMULATION/DISTRIBUTION ZONES
When you see a range or consolidation in a
chart while there is average to high volume,
the market is in the process of accumulating
enough trapped traders, before it can shake
out of that area and make another move.
In this example, we see an accumulation zone.
We see price breaking below support, before
moving in the opposite direction.
This is called a spring, in Wyckoff’s terms,
a pattern which traps any bearish breakout
traders in a losing trade.
It also traps the bulls out of their long
trades, if they have their stop loss below
the consolidation.
Often you’ll see patterns of an up thrust.
Which is a breakout of the distribution pattern
at the top of an uptrend, which then reverses
and heads down.
In this example, here’s the distribution
zone.
An up thrust is simply a false breakout of
the consolidation area, this green candle,
where weaker hands expect a breakout.
The market breaks out of the consolidation
only to return within the range.
The following candles trap long traders in
a losing position.
Now, during accumulation and distribution
phases, we can’t use the same strategy as
before to take advantage of trapped traders.
We can’t wait for price to return at the
previous spring level to enter, it would be
too late.
Generally speaking, the accumulation phase
forms as institutional traders increase their
buying and drive demand.
After the spring, as more interest develops,
the trading range displays higher lows as
prices position themselves to move higher.
You want to be in the market at the beginning
of a markup phase.
With buyers gaining power, prices push through
the upper level of the trading range.
At this Markup phase, the market will show
a consistent upward trend.
MARKET GAPS
When a gap occurs, usually on stock market,
you can bet a lot of traders remained trapped
in their positions.
You could say that the price “jumped”
a certain distance, meaning that it closed
at one price, and then opened higher or lower,
without touching the intervening levels.
There’s a saying among market participants
that “all gaps need to be filled”.
A gap “getting filled” is when price action
at a later time retraces to the last closing
price preceding the gap.
Once it’s retraced fully, then the gap is
considered filled.
Gaps usually form as a result of low liquidity,
as the market closes and then reopens the
next day.
When gaps form overnight, it’s a sign that
the market sentiment has shifted.
Market participants are no longer willing
to pay the same price on the open of the next
day, as they were on the previous close.
Many times, at least when it comes to the
bigger gaps, it’s a sign that new information
has been released and taken into account by
market participants.
When we have a gap, lots of traders are trapped
in losing positions.
And when the gap is filled, and price reaches
the “point of pain” of many losing trades,
you will often see an immediate reaction.
That’s one of my favorite setups.
A gap which is filled, combined maybe with
another level of confluence, makes for a decent
trade to take advantage of losing traders.
Pullback trap
Markets move in waves with impulsive and corrective
moves.
A very popular trading method is trading the
corrective move and entering a trade in the
direction of the trend, once the corrective
move signals completion.
The issue is that many traders are impatient
and don't want to risk not being in the move.
So they enter trades too early at the first
sign of completion.
But what may appear to be a simple pullback
will actually be a complex pullback on a lower
time frame.
The first wave indicates the first leg of
this pullback and the pin bar looks like it
could indicate a resumption of the up trend.
Traders enter and place their stop below the
candle.
Price then turns around and makes a second
wave, and traps long traders.
Being on the right side of those moves can
move your positions into profit very quickly.
Again, the key is to see where traders may
be on the wrong side of the market and get
yourself positioned, to take advantage of
them when they have to exit their losing trades.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.