This is the video you've been waiting for, in
which I’ll expose the most common traps used by
the big players to manipulate the market, and
exploit unsuspecting retail traders like you.
Let’s start with break of structure trap.
This is a devious ploy used by the smart
money to lure unsuspecting retail traders into
the market at precisely the wrong time.
It's a trap that preys on the inexperience
and emotional impulses of the average
trader, leaving them trapped and helpless
as the market turns against them.
Picture this: the market has been in a
steady uptrend. The buyers are in control,
and the overall sentiment is positive.
Retail traders, seeing this consistent rise,
start to feel confident and begin looking
for opportunities to enter long positions.
When the market breaks above a previous swing
high, it's often seen as a bullish signal,
indicating that the uptrend is likely to continue.
And this is where the break of
structure trap comes into play.
The smart money know that many retail traders
will view this breakout as a buying opportunity.
They understand that the average trader is
trained to look for these bullish signals
and to enter the market when they occur.
So, they engineer a false breakout.
And once they lured in enough retail
buyers, they abruptly reverse course.
They start selling aggressively, driving the
price back down below the broken swing high.
The retail traders, who bought into
the false breakout, are now trapped.
They're left holding long positions, in a
market that's suddenly turned against them.
As the price continues to fall, many of
these trapped traders will start to panic.
They'll sell out of their positions, often
at a loss, just to escape the pain.
And guess who's there to buy up
these positions at a discount?
That's right, the smart money.
They've made their profit,
and they're ready to repeat the process again.
I’m sure you’ve lost dozens of trades this way.
So how can you avoid falling victim
to the break of structure trap.
When you see the market break above a swing
high, don't just blindly rush in to buy.
Instead, wait for confirmation.
See if the price can sustain its
move above the breakout level.
First, look for increased
volume and momentum to validate the move.
If the candles above the previous swing
high aren’t backed by volume, be
patient and wait for a pullback.
Don't just follow the herd and assume that
a breakout is always a buying opportunity.
The smart money is counting
on you to make this mistake.
Try to think like a professional
trader, always looking for bargains.
Change of Character Trap
The "Change of Character
Trap" is another cunning strategy employed by
the smart money to deceive retail traders.
It's a trap that takes advantage of the naive
belief that a broken swing like this one,
signals a reversal of the previous trend.
This assumption can lead to disastrous
consequences for those who fail to
recognize the true nature of the market.
Let's break down this trap, step by step.
First, let’s consider this market in a
clear downtrend. It’s obvious that
sellers are in control and that
the path of least resistance is downwards.
Despite the prevailing downtrend, the smart
money may decide to manipulate the market.
That’s because they always want to sell at a
premium, and want to find new buyers.
With the obvious downtrend, not many
traders are willing to buy, so smart
money must do something about that.
So they start buying, creating a
period of consolidation or a range.
This range gives the impression that
the downtrend may be losing steam.
The smart money will then suddenly push
the price above the upper boundary of
the range, breaking a previous swing high.
You probably know this as a change of character.
Retail traders, conditioned to believe
that a broken swing high in a downtrend
represents a bullish signal, start buying.
They think the character of the market has
changed from bearish to bullish, and they don't
want to miss out on the anticipated rally.
And this is exactly what the
smart money was waiting for.
As the retail traders buy into the false breakout,
the smart money starts selling heavily, dumping
their positions onto the unsuspecting latecomers.
The price, unable to sustain itself above the
broken swing high, starts to fall rapidly.
The retail traders, now trapped in losing
long positions, start to panic as
the market resumes its downtrend.
Many will sell out at a loss, while
others will hold on, hoping for a
recovery that may never come. Meanwhile,
the smart money, having sold at the top,
can now buy back at lower prices, profiting
from the misfortune of the trapped traders.
The key lesson here is to never assume
that a broken swing high automatically
means a change in market character.
Always consider the larger context. If the
overall trend is down, a sudden breakout above
a swing high should be treated with caution.
To avoid falling victim to the "change of
character trap," be skeptical of breakouts
that go against the prevailing trend.
Wait for a confirmation, such as
sustained buying pressure and increased
volume, before committing to a trade.
Remember that markets rarely reverse from
a bearish to a bullish trend so smoothly.
If the breakout is indeed real, you’ll have
your chance to enter your long position after
the price retraces.
Pattern Failure Trap
The "Pattern Failure Trap" is probably the
most common strategy used by the smart money,
to exploit the predictable reactions of
retail traders to common chart patterns.
It's a trap that capitalizes on the belief
that certain patterns, when broken, will lead
to substantial moves in the expected direction.
But as we'll see, this belief can lead to painful
losses for those who fail to recognize the
manipulative tactics of the market makers.
It goes like this: let’s say the market has
been forming a triangle pattern, with the price
bouncing between converging trend lines.
Retail traders, recognizing this pattern,
anticipate a significant move once the
price breaks out of the triangle.
As the price eventually breaks
below the triangle's support level,
retail traders, expecting a continuation of
the downtrend, start selling aggressively.
They believe the pattern has confirmed
a bearish outcome, and they don't want
to miss out on the anticipated decline.
However, this is exactly what the smart money was
waiting for. As the retail traders sell into the
break of support, the smart money starts buying
heavily, absorbing all the selling pressure.
They recognize that the break of support has
likely triggered new sell orders placed
by retail traders, and they are happy to
take the other side of these trades.
And after briefly dipping below the
broken support level, the price suddenly
reverses and starts climbing higher.
The retail traders, now trapped in short
positions, start to panic as their expected
downtrend fails to materialize.
As the price continues to rise,
many of these trapped traders will be forced
to buy back their short positions at a loss,
further fueling the upward momentum.
Meanwhile, the smart money,
having bought at the bottom, can now sell
back at higher prices, profiting from the
failed expectations of the retail crowd.
The key lesson here is to never assume that a
broken pattern will always lead to the expected
outcome. The smart money is well aware of the
common patterns that retail traders watch, and
they will often use these patterns against them.
To avoid falling victim to the "pattern
failure trap," you must learn to think
beyond the obvious. Don't just blindly sell on a
break of support or buy on a break of resistance.
Consider the larger context.
Is the overall trend still
intact? Is the volume supporting the breakout?
By asking these questions you can avoid being
caught on the wrong side of a failed pattern.
Remember, the market is not
always logical or predictable.
The smart money will often try to exploit the
assumptions of retail traders, and they have the
resources to make the market move in their favor.
Patterns can and do fail, and those
failures can be costly for the unprepared.
Weak Rejection Trap
The "Weak Rejection Trap," is another
cunning ploy designed to exploit the inexperience
and emotional vulnerabilities of retail traders.
It's a trap that preys on the common belief that
a rejection candle, especially one with a large
upper wick, signals a reversal in the trend.
Let’s consider this market in a clear uptrend.
At this point, a bearish rejection candle forms.
This candle is characterized by a small body and
a large upper wick, indicating that the price
rallied during the period but was then strongly
rejected, closing near its opening price.
Retail traders, seeing this bearish rejection
candle, interpret it as a sign that the uptrend
is exhausted and that a reversal is on the cards.
They believe that the large upper wick
indicates strong selling pressure and
that the market is about to turn down.
Acting on this belief, they start selling,
expecting to profit from
the anticipated decline.
However, contrary to the expectations of the
retail traders, the price doesn’t reverse.
Instead, it continues in the
direction of the initial uptrend.
The bearish rejection candle, despite
its ominous appearance, proves to be
a mere blip in the ongoing upward movement.
The retail traders who sold on the appearance
of the rejection candle are now trapped in short
positions, as the market moves against them.
As the price continues to climb, they face
increasing losses, and many will be forced
to buy back their positions at a higher
price, further fueling the uptrend.
The key takeaway here is to avoid trading against
the main trend based on a single candle formation.
A rejection candle, no matter how
impressive it may seem, is not a
reliable signal for a trend reversal on its own.
The smart money understand this, and they will
often use these candles to their advantage.
After the rejection candle forms,
the smart money will start buying, absorbing
the selling pressure from the retail traders.
They recognize that many traders will
interpret the candle as a reversal signal,
and they are happy to take the
other side of those trades.
To avoid falling victim to this trap, you must
learn to think beyond single candle formations.
Look for other signs of strength or weakness.
Again, check the volume. There are specific VSA
patterns that may confirm or reject your bias.
Always remember that a candle that seems to
signal a reversal may, in fact, be a
mere distraction in the larger trend.