so you see a trading opportunity looks
like a decent setup you have the
confirmation to enter but you hesitate
you are afraid to lose money or you have
some sort of anxiety that stops you to
pull the trigger it's a problem almost
every Trader will face at some point in
their trading career I also suffered
from the fear of losing money and this
issue led to other mistakes that stopped
me to have the best trading execution
today I'm sharing my process what I've
done to reduce anxiety when trading in
the actual steps I took to improve
trading execution so if you could like
subscribe to the channel and stick
around for the full video
[Music]
do you think the color of a candle
affects you when trading of course it
does tell me if this is familiar you
enter a long trade expecting the market
to go up you gain a few points and then
price goes against you forming a red
candle and you start watching the ticks
every downtick in particular any focus
on the red color of the candle you get
more and more anxious when another red
candle forms this was a big issue for me
in my first years I used to close my
trades after a few minutes when I saw
several red candles below my entry point
the solution to overcome this is simple
change the color of your candles to one
color this way you'll follow price in
its range only
let me ask you which one of the texts on
the screen is easier for you to read
the one with the same color what do you
want with multiple colors
there's a phenomenon in Psychology
called visual perception your brain is
always looking for patterns in trading
when you are using multi-colored candles
you are decreasing your ability to
detect patterns let me repeat your brain
is looking for patterns in one of the
qualities of a pattern is similar colors
color affects your brain your emotions
your psychology potentially your ability
to trade to trade best it requires you
trade in a neutral unbiased State of
Mind
fast-moving red or green candles have
made me take bad trades in the past both
on entry and exit if you are anxious
during an open trade use candles with
the same color
so try this simple tip for decreasing
your reactivity to price moves change
the color to anything but red blue or
green yellow or white candles just stay
away from Red then get back to me in a
week I find myself more calm when using
a single color for Up and Down Candles
maybe this little brain hack will help
you get rid of some anxiety
foreign
[Music]
you see a long opportunity prices around
the key level and you decide to pull the
trigger at let's say 50 dollars
prices at fifty dollars and 10 cents and
you say to yourself I'll wait until the
market goes down a few cents
the market goes down to fifty dollars
and two cents and you still wait then
the market goes up to fifty dollars and
ten cents again and you say to yourself
I'm not entering now it's a worse price
than five minutes ago I'll wait until it
goes down again and of course price
never comes back it goes up without you
and now you're frustrated because you
anticipated a move but your
perfectionism stopped you to pull the
trigger the fear of losing money and
perfectionism can lead to irrational
Behavior over analyzing overthinking and
it slowly drains your mental energy
one issue that I've battled with
personally was wanting to be perfect in
my interest I was looking for the
perfect entry you know it one when you
enter and price never goes against you
not even one point being a perfectionist
and trading is stressful and always
being on the edge will not help you to
make good trading decisions in most
cases when you wait for the perfect
entry you will realize that you just
missed a big move
trying to accurately time the entry
point is a foolish Endeavor Perfection
can be your worst enemy in trading and
can bring in a lot of stress
here's the solution to reduce this
anxiety use ranges instead of exact
prices
as a day trader you won't be able to
monitor price movements every minute of
the day this is why you should use price
ranges rather than exact prices
this will give you some flexibility and
of course you still need to be strict
with yourself when executing your plan
[Music]
good Traders are alert yet patient when
I set up they've been waiting for shows
up they take it without hesitation
but until that time comes they are not
moved by the price fluctuations that
tempt other Traders they choose to
conserve their energy for the setups
they've prepared for and ignore
everything else
they don't chase the market they let the
market come to them the opposite of this
is to force trades you know the feeling
when you wait for a trade you see some
activity and you pull the trigger early
forcing a trade I was doing this almost
every day here's the solution don't use
Market orders and use limit orders
instead basically let the market come to
you
once you selected the instruments you
want to trade and made your analysis you
must identify the prices where you will
buy and sell your goal is simply to buy
and sell at the best prices and you use
your research to identify the acceptable
prices beforehand not only this will
translate into a better execution but it
will also help you avoid making trades
based on emotions
to reduce stress and anxiety The Simple
Solution is to only take action when
conditions are as you expect along the
market come to you is a difficult but
valuable skill to learn so forget about
Market orders and use limit orders this
will reduce emotional involvement and
will stop you to make poor decisions
if you want to reduce stress and anxiety
while trading you might want to move to
higher time frames this will allow you
to have the time required to make
informed decisions I know you will find
it hard at first but you will also
continue to struggle with nerves and
stress until you make the change if you
feel nervous and afraid of losing money
I highly suggest giving the higher time
frames a go again the transition to
higher time frames is hard and most
Traders are reluctant to make the switch
but you must change your environment if
you want a better trading execution
when you're trading in an environment
like the one minute or the five minute
charts you're risking of trading Market
noise granted the higher time frames
won't offer trade setups at such a high
Pace but the signals that are generated
are more reliable and have a much better
chance of working out
it's better to trade a handful of high
quality trades rather than trying to
trade lots of poor quality ones
day trading is exciting but it also
requires to monitor price movements for
many hours most day Traders initially
love the thrill and the action on the
lower time frames but it's only a matter
of time before you experience mental
burnout and once your mental discipline
runs out great frustration anger and
impatience will bring bad traits sending
you into a dangerous state of mind that
is hard to bounce back from
so move to higher time frames you'll
only spend a fraction of the time in
front of the charts and you'll be at the
less risk of experiencing burnout after
a while you'll realize it's much more
easier to keep a cool head while
maintaining your mental and emotional
discipline
there are trait the setup looked great
and then price went straight to your
stop loss before going to your take
profit without you this is probably the
most frustrating scenario many Traders
deal with on a daily basis
because your fear of losing money you
have the tendency to use small stop
losses you don't want to be wrong and
you try to keep your losses small but
putting your stop too close to the entry
candle is a recipe for getting your
account chopped to pieces a narrow stop
relies on you to have very accurate
almost perfect entries and we already
talked about perfectionism in trading if
you repeatedly see that your stops get
hit before price reverses into your
original Direction it's very likely that
you place your stops at levels that
other Traders also use especially if you
trade the obvious price action patterns
my advice start trading with a wider
stop loss and a lower position size away
from your entry your position size
you're using should be so small that
neither a loss nor a winner will affect
your mindset and your ability to keep
Trading
only then you'll truly focus on the
proper execution
[Music]
if you are trading your hard-earned
money in the markets but you don't know
what your trading strategy is and you
don't have confidence in your ability to
analyze the markets you probably
shouldn't trade with a live account
one of the biggest reasons you are
nervous when trading and afraid to lose
your money is because you aren't
confident in your own ability to trade
maybe you don't have a trading strategy
mastered you don't have a trading plan
you don't keep a trading journal you
simply aren't prepared to risk real
money in the markets yet that's why you
feel fear when you trade
basically trading anxiety comes from not
knowing what you are doing
I've talked many times about the value
of a trading journal the key is to use
your trading journal to track when you
are at your best and when you are at
your worst when it comes to your trading
and emotions
in my trading journal I pay close
attention to times when I make mental
mistakes such as not taking a good trade
when I know I should be taking it when
I'm scared of losing money or avoiding a
good trade I look for triggers and
patterns was I distracted am I making
this mistake in a specific Market
condition do I have specific emotions
and feelings from previous traits these
are the tangibles that you should be
tracking in your trading journal
foreign
ERS are fixated on the short-term result
making money by clicking a few buttons
and they pay no attention to the process
that enables that to happen making
mistakes learning from them and
correcting them over and over again
everyone thinks about winning but few
consider the benefits of losing in my
experience most of my wins can be
directly attributed to a big losing
trade in the best that I learned from
making money as a Trader is pointless if
you don't understand why you're winning
because you can't repeat it likewise
losing money is a valuable experience if
you understand why you lost
paradoxically you can't understand why
you're winning without first
understanding how you could have lost in
the same situation
so change the way you think about losses
because they will point you in the
direction of repeatable wins in the
future
if you found value and learn something
new leave us a like this way we'll know
if you'd like to see more videos like
this one and check out our Academy
program if you want to further level up
your Trading
until next time