Here’s the most common scenario.
You see a trade setup, you decide it’s a
good one and you pull the trigger.
Then you place the stop loss, set the take
profit, and that’s it.
Sometimes it hits your stop, sometimes prices
goes right to your target.
But what about those times when price almost
hits your level?
Do you know how to protect your trade?
What if it returns to your entry?
Do you know what to do?
What if it hits your stop loss in the first
place, and then starts to go in your initial
direction?
And what if your take profit is too low and
you’re settling with a small gain?
Taking profit is one of the most critical
aspects of a successful trading strategy.
You want to minimize your risk and maximize
your profits.
Today we’ll talk about this.
So like, subscribe and stick around for the
full video.
Setting single profit targets
Setting single profit targets can seem like
a simple and straightforward strategy, but
it comes with several disadvantages that you
should be aware of.
First, consider the missed opportunities:
By setting a single profit target, you may
miss out on potential profits as the market
moves in your favor.
For example, if you set a profit target at
the price of $100 and it continues to rise
after hitting that target, you would miss
out on the additional gains.
Rigidity and lack of flexibility is another
disadvantage.
Single profit targets can limit your ability
to adapt to market changes.
If the market almost hits your target, then
moves in the other direction, you may be unable
to take advantage of new opportunities or
adjust your strategy accordingly.
Not to mention the psychological burden: You
may feel the pressure to reach that target
and may be more likely to make impulsive decisions.
It’s important to be aware of the disadvantages
of setting single profit targets and consider
alternative approaches.
The benefits of scaling out of positions (multiple
targets)
A better strategy is to scale out of positions
and have multiple profit targets.
Scaling out of positions refers to closing
partial positions at different levels of profit,
rather than holding on to the entire position
until the target is hit.
Let's say you buy a stock at $20 and set a
target profit of $30.
Instead of holding on to the stock until it
reaches this price, you may choose to sell
half of the position at $25 and the remaining
half at $30.
This strategy has several benefits.
First, it reduces the risk of giving back
all of the profits if the market suddenly
moves against you.
By selling partial positions at different
levels of profit, you lock in profits and
reduce your exposure to the market.
Second, scaling out of positions allows you
to manage your emotions and avoid becoming
too attached to a trade.
Holding on to a position for too long can
create anxiety and fear, especially if the
market moves against you, when you’ve already
been in profit.
By selling partial positions, you can reduce
the emotional impact of a trade and make more
rational decisions.
You can also leave a portion of your trade
open even after you final target is reached.
You bought at $50 and sets 2 profit targets:
$55 and $60.
You can sell 25% of your trade at the first
target, 50% at the second and final target,
locking in profits and reducing your exposure.
And you let the remaining size opened.
Who know, maybe the market will move to $70,
$80.
This way, you have a chance to capture a much
bigger move.
The benefits of trailing stop-loss orders
A trailing stop can be a powerful tool to
ensure that you maximize your profits while
minimizing your risks.
Suppose you bought a stock at $100 and set
a trailing stop at $10.
If the stock price rises to $110, your stop
loss will adjust to breakeven, at $100.
If the price continues to rise to $120, your
stop loss will continue to move up, always
remaining $10 below the current price.
The most obvious benefit of using a trailing
stop is that it allows you to maximize your
profits.
By continuously adjusting your stop loss as
the price moves in your favor, you can lock
in profits while avoiding premature exits.
This can be especially useful when the market
is trending in your direction.
Another benefit of using a trailing stop is
that it helps you minimize your risk.
As the price moves in your favor, your stop
loss moves with it, ensuring that you are
protected in case the market turns against
you.
This way, you can avoid losing money on a
trade that was in profit.
A trailing stop is a dynamic exit point that
changes as the price changes.
This allows you to stay in a trade for as
long as possible while still protecting your
profits.
You can choose a trailing stop based on a
percentage of the price or a set number of
pips, depending on your personal preferences.
Never use a dollar target as take profit
Here’s a common mistake.
You see a trade opportunity, you enter, and
you set a money target of $100.
When you see that you are 100$ in profit,
you exit, even though the price may have further
room to develop.
While the idea of having a specific amount
of profit in mind can be motivating, it can
also be an obstacle to your trading account
growth.
There are several disadvantages when you set
money targets.
First, a money target can cause you to make
irrational decisions.
When you are so focused on reaching a specific
monetary goal, you will make impulsive trades
or hold losing positions longer than they
should, which can lead to bigger losses.
Second, money targets are not always realistic.
You may set an overly optimistic target, which
can lead to disappointment and frustration
when the target is not met.
And on the other hand, setting a target that
is too conservative can result in missed opportunities
for profits.
So, instead, you should focus on developing
a comprehensive trading strategy that takes
into account market conditions, volatility,
and other price action factors.
Previous swing highs/lows
Scaling out of positions at previous swing
highs or lows is probably the simplest strategy
if you are looking to manage risk and maximize
profits.
Basically, you take partial profits and minimize
the impact of potential market reversals.
Let’s say you have a short position in a
downtrend.
If the price reaches a new swing low, you
take some profits off the table and reduce
your exposure.
At the same time you can move your stop to
breakeven.
This can provide a safety cushion in the event
of a market downturn.
You can use the swing high or low points to
re-evaluate your trading plan and make any
necessary adjustments.
For example, if price reaches a swing low
but then fails to break out to new lows, this
may indicate a change in market sentiment
and you may want to consider exiting your
position altogether or adjust your stop loss
levels even closer to the current price.
Supply/demand
Taking profits at supply and demand areas
is another strategy.
The main idea behind this approach is to take
advantage of the natural forces of supply
and demand that drive the price movement of
a market.
For example, you bought at this demand level
and price has risen to a significant level
of supply.
Here you may choose to sell a part of your
position.
This way, even if the price does eventually
fall, you will have already captured some
gains and protected your capital.
Another benefit of scaling out of positions
at supply and demand areas is that it can
increase the efficiency of your account balance.
By closing partial positions at key levels,
you can free up capital that can then be used
to enter new positions.
ATR/ADR
Taking profits using average true range or
average daily range (ATR) is another strategy.
This technique involves monitoring the market’s
volatility, as measured by the average true
range, and using it to determine the best
time to take profits.
Knowing the average daily range is extremely
useful since it allows you to estimate how
much profit potential there is in the market.
For example, if you are a Forex day trader,
there is no point looking for 100 pips of
profit from a trade, if the average daily
range for that currency pair is only 60 pips.
The ATR can be used in combination with other
take profit strategies to improve the accuracy
of trade timing.
For example, you may choose to take partial
profits when the ATR crosses above a certain
level, and price reaches a major support or
resistance level, or an area of supply and
demand.
Fibonacci extensions
Taking profits using Fibonacci extensions
is my favorite take profit method.
Fibonacci extensions can be used to project
potential levels of price action beyond a
retracement.
In short, you get clear and objective exit
points.
For example, if you buy a market in an uptrend,
you can use Fibonacci extensions to find potential
levels of resistance where you can scale out
of your position.
If the price reaches the 100% extension level,
you may choose to sell a part of your position,
locking in profits while reducing your risk
exposure.
If price continues to move higher, you may
choose to sell more of your position at the
161% extension level, and maybe move your
stop higher.
By using these clear and objective exit points,
you avoid overstaying in a trade.
VWAP or Bollinger Bands
Using VWAP bands or Bollinger Bands is another
alternative to scale out your positions.
The idea is simple: you will use these bands
to identify dynamic support and resistance
levels.
If price is approaching the upper VWAP band,
it may be a good time to scale out of a long
position and take profits.
This is because the price is likely to experience
some resistance at the upper band, which may
cause it to retrace.
Similarly, if price is approaching a lower
Bollinger band, it may be a good time to take
profits on a short position.
This is because the price is likely to experience
some support at the lower band, which may
cause it to bounce back up.
Pivot Points
Taking profits using pivot points is another
reliable method.
Rather than relying on subjective interpretations
of price action, pivot points offer a systematic
approach you can use to make decisions.
This can help you avoid the biases and emotions
that can often lead to poor decision-making.
For example, if price reaches a resistance
level marked by a pivot point, you may choose
to take some profits at that level in anticipation
of a potential price decline.
End of the day/week
The end of the day or the week can be an ideal
time to scale out of positions because it
allows you to take a step back and evaluate
your positions in the context of wider market
conditions.
If you are a day trader, and your trade is
in profit at the end of the session, you might
want to limit your risk.
You don’t know how the market will react
at the open of the next session.
The same if you are a swing trader, and you
have a decent profit on your trade.
Before Friday’s end of the session, you
may want to reduce your overall risk.
You’ve seen those big weekend gaps.
So, take some profits off the table and move
our stop to breakeven.
Taking profits in a trending market versus
a ranging market
a ranging market requires different approaches
as the market dynamics and price movements
can be vastly different.
In a trending market, prices move in a sustained
direction, whereas in a ranging market, prices
oscillate within a certain range.
In a strong trending market, you can look
to take profits at key levels of resistance,
or at Fibonacci extension levels, where the
trend strength appears to decrease.
On the other hand, taking profits in a ranging
market can be more challenging, making it
difficult to determine when to take profits.
Pivots are good targets when market is stuck
in a range.
VWAP bands or Bollinger Bands are also very
useful during these conditions.
You need to understand the market conditions
and use the appropriate tools and techniques
to determine when to take profits.
Now, your take profit will never be hit if
your stop loss is constantly being hunted
by market makers and smart money.
If you want to learn how to avoid stop loss
hunting and avoid market manipulation, you
must watch this video.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!