Price tends to move from structure to structure,
squeezing one side of the market participants
most of the time.
It rewards one side of the market, while punishing
the opposite side of participants.
And liquidity clear outs are constant processes
observed on the markets every day.
Today we’ll talk about liquidity extraction
and you’ll finally understand why the market
moves against you the moment you enter the
market.
So, if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
Do you know the depth of the market you are
trading?
Regardless of how long you’ve been trading,
at some point you should have questioned the
depth of the market you are trading.
In other words, its liquidity.
Make no mistake, trading the EUR/USD for example
offers different conditions than trading an
instrument like CAD/NZD (Canadian Dollar versus
the New Zeeland Dollar).
Or Bitcoin versus Shiba Ina Coin.
Or Tesla versus some random penny stock.
Liquidity is the #1 element to make a market
functionable and competitive.
For a market to be rich in liquidity, there
must be an ample participation of both buyers
and sellers.
This is why it makes sense for smart money
or market makers to extract the liquidity
from the market.
Liquidity hunting is a very common practice.
It is nothing more than the art of flushing
the losing players out of the market, which
are known as weak longs or weak shorts.
Liquidity clear-outs will often form against
the main trend
The larger the liquidity zone buildup, the
more likely it is for that zone to be targeted
by the smart money, especially if it is a
counter trend setup.
Often, liquidity clear-outs will form against
the main trend.
For example, in an extended bullish trend
structure, in a consolidation, you will often
see a clear out of highs and a price reversal
downwards.
This is more common in very liquid markets
such as Forex or stocks that trade on strong
volume.
And why is that?
Because smart money knows how retail traders
think.
Smart money knows how retail traders use different
indicators, moving averages, candlesticks,
and chart patterns in their attempt to day
trade or scalp the markets.
Smart Money can easily trap retail traders
into the market at poor trade locations and
then move against their positions, stopping
them out.
They know that retail traders are programmed
with the phrase “trend is your friend”.
That’s why many clear-outs will be formed
against the overall trend direction or against
overall retail trader participation.
Here’s how liquidity is often positioned
around structures in the market.
Many traders will use these price levels to
place their entries or exits at, but more
frequently, their exits or stop losses.
And these are exactly the zones used by smart
money to trigger a liquidity clear out.
Institutional players cannot trade the same
as the retail trader, because in low liquidity
price areas, they might push price too much
with large orders.
So they use high liquidity zones to put their
own large orders in the market without having
too much impact on the price.
Clearouts of liquidity are frequent in crypto
and Forex markets because a strong trending
market attracts many un-experienced traders
who step into margin trading, usually buying
around the lows and highs.
Since they are unaware of the trap, it is
relatively easy for the market maker to replay
the pattern repeatedly, stopping the traders
with liquidity clear-outs.
Structural symmetry is most important concept
when it comes to liquidity clear out
One critical concept for a liquidity clear
out is the consistency of structural symmetry.
Most targeted clear outs will happen around
structures where the price is consistently
bouncing from a demand/support level or resistance/supply
level for multiple times before it actually
breaks it.
So very important, you should only focus on
such structures to identify and trade liquidity
clear-outs.
The more bounces in structure, the better.
The more time it passes, the more the liquidity
will increase
As time passes and if price cannot break areas
with multiple highs or lows, chances are the
liquidity around those price levels will increase
with time.
The more time it passes, the more the liquidity
will increase (if major highs/lows don’t
break).
Because of this factor, if you want to trade
a liquidity hunt pattern, you should be aware
of how time plays a role in consolidating
the orders above/under key liquidity zones.
Liquidity clear-out and stop loss hunting
Now, a clear out is a liquidation event where
the stop losses of buyers or sellers are taken
out, and the breakout traders are trapped
in.
Liquidity clear-out and stop loss hunting
are similar concepts.
Stop loss hunting can happen around any price
or no structure at all, while a liquidity
clear-out will most of the time happen around
dense price structures with multiple bounces.
So remember: liquidity clear-outs are most
common around symmetrical structures where
many traders will watch the same price level
or place stop losses around the same price
level.
Therefore market makers would want to see
that level broken and enter their positions
while liquidation is taking place and absorb
opposite orders.
Look for a rapid reversal of price back into
the structural support or resistance
For retail traders like you and me, the aim
should be to spot such potential liquidity
zones and join the game of market maker and
to avoid being a liquidity target.
A liquidity clear out should always present
itself with a rapid, strong reversal move
after a critical low/high is taken out—basically
a rapid rotation of price back into the structural
support or resistance.
The speed of rotation back will usually depend
on the market or the liquidity of the market.
In some markets, the reversal back might take
15 or 30 minutes as the smart money needs
to collect as many orders as possible over
time, while in FX or crypto, the reversal
will be much quicker on average (between 1-15
min) since those markets are much more liquid.
Monitor the lowest low or highest high of
a structure
If the structure is not even on highs or lows
positioning (for example, when highs or lows
are connected through a trendline instead
of flat line), then the main area to watch
is the lowest low or highest high of structure,
that is where the majority of condensed stop
losses will sit and where breakout traders
might initiate other positions.
This is the difference between a flat vs.
a trend line positioning of lows and the importance
of deepest low.
No matter how the structure is positioned,
the low of the structure will be the key level
that the market maker will want to clear out
and where the majority of stops will likely
sit.
There’s a difference between a targeted
and a non-targeted liquidity clearout, meaning
triggered by the market maker or triggered
by overall market action.
On the left side we have a targeted attempt
and on the right a non-targeted one.
The difference between strong quick moves
initiated by the smart money and the move
triggered by overall market action is usually
spotted depending on where price starts the
actual move and if that move is consistent.
In the case of a targeted attempt, most of
these moves will be initiated in the middle
of the structure where not much liquidity
sits.
Meanwhile, strong moves triggered by overall
market action are usually going to be on very
symmetrical and obvious price extremes.
The 10 candles rule
After the liquidity clear out under the lows
or above highs, the price should start reversing
back inside the structure relatively quickly.
Timing is the key.
Let’s say you’re a scalper and you’re
using 1 minute chart.
My own rule is that it should not take more
than 10 1-minute candles for the price to
rotate back above support.
This depends a lot on how big the structure
is, how many candles are in each leg of the
structure.
The more candles per leg, the longer it might
take for the liquidity clear out move to happen,
but it should not be more than 10 candles.
In the best scenario, it happens within the
first 3 to 5 candles.
Again it’s a relative concept as it scales
with the time frame chosen.
Use price alerts below the structural lows
or above highs
To trade a liquidity clear-out, you need a
clear plan to find the pattern.
Using price alerts is a useful way to support
the searching process.
The plan is quite simple.
Once the potential symmetrical structure is
spotted (with variables that fit a potential
liquidity clearout), you place an alert below
the structural lows or above highs, depending
if it's a bull or bear pattern.
This is important because once an alert is
placed, you can relax and do other stuff and
only come back once the alert rings and the
price clears the required liquidity area.
It’s an important tip that helped me a lot.
Using price alerts is critical to minimize
the screen time and to be more patient and
"fresh" as a trader.
At the liquidity clearout area, there should
be significant volume traded
The key when trading a liquidity hunt is to
focus on volume.
At the clearout price area, there should be
significant volume traded.
Let’s analyze this liquidity clearout pattern.
We have a clear downtrend, with lower lows
and lower highs in the structure.
This is our main focus point, the lowest low
in the structure.
This is where our price alert should be.
A drop into the lows will usually be initiated
by the market maker with a heavy market order
that will remove liquidity and swipe price
under lows.
Look at the volume traded at the liquidity
hunt.
It increased considerably once the lowest
low in the structure was taken out.
For an entry, you should wait for the liquidity
clear-out and then for the price to start
moving back above support for a long entry.
Your risk should be the lowest low of the
clear-out.
This is where your stop loss should be.
Here’s another liquidity hunt.
-we first observe a heavy selloff ahead of
structure
-we then find a symmetrical structure with
approximately even lows (ensuring even stop
loss placement under them)
- high volume on the clearout, with the highest
volume candle in the whole structure
- volatility on the market is high (meaning
we have a wide range)
- and we have a sharp and quick reversal after
clearout and a reclaim of the previous support
So after the liquidity clearout, an important
sign should be the volume.
The volume traded was the highest 1-minute
volume candle inside the whole price structure.
As price quickly reclaimed support and then
pushed higher, this was a good moment to open
a buy position, with a stop loss below the
most recent low.
A key component for trading the clearout is
that it has to reclaim the support for a long
trade (or resistance for short trade).
If it does not reclaim, there is no trade
in the first place, it’s a breakout.
Here’s an example with high volume clearout
under lows as the long traders are stopped
out, but the price did not reclaim the support
level, thus this is not a long trade.
Remember this important point: the faster
the price reclaims support and pushes above
after the clearout, the better the trade.
On the best trades, price should reclaim support
within the first 5 candles after the clearout.
If the structure is not symmetric (with evenly
positioned lows), it is hard to base the entry,
that is why I prefer to trade structures that
are clean and symmetric.
This allows precise entry conditions across
all trades.
Let’s look at this asymmetric structure
and clearout.
You can observe that lows are not evenly positioned.
We even have some higher lows.
This is the deepest lower low, the main area
that you should wait for.
We have the liquidity clearout and the quick
reversal after clearout.
But now the question is, where’s our entry?
This isn’t so clear like in a symmetrical
structure.
That’s why I prefer the symmetrical ones.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.