Take a look at this chart.
This is one of the most common traps used
by smart money to fool both buyers, and sellers,
at the same time.
You probably faced this yourself.
Market breaks a swing high, you think is a
breakout, but instead of continuing higher,
it aggressively moves lower, also breaking
a recent swing low.
Basically, a double liquidity clear-out.
It happens every day, on all time frames.
And if you identify it correctly, it might
be one of the best smart money setups to trade.
Let’s talk about this.
You know the drill, like, subscribe, and stick
around for the full video.
The Double Liquidity Clear-out TRAP
It all starts with a breakout that fails to
continue beyond a level, resulting in a ‘false’
breakout.
False breakout patterns are one of the most
important price action patterns to learn,
because a false-break is often a very strong
indication that a momentum move might start
soon.
Trading is a game of deceptions and traps,
and you must learn to play accordingly.
So, firstly, price will break a swing high,
but then it quickly reverses, deceiving all
buyers who took the ‘bait’ of the breakout.
It’s often the case that amateurs will enter
what looks like an ‘obvious’ breakout.
Then the professionals will push the market
back the other way.
This is the first liquidity clear-out.
The second part of the pattern consists in
another trap.
Price will fall and will break a swing low,
this time trapping traders on the short side.
This is the second liquidity clear-out, designed
to trap the ‘weak hands’ in the market.
This include traders that take positions when
a market is already quite extended or they
try to ‘predict’ a breakout from a key
support level too early.
Smart money of course watch for these missteps
by the amateurs.
As a price action trader, you want to learn
how to use this double liquidity clear-out
to your advantage, rather than falling victim
to it.
From my backtests, after I spot this double
liquidity clear-out setup, I try to find a
trade in the direction of the initial false
breakout.
It’s basically a trend continuation setup.
Don’t get me wrong, it takes discipline
and a bit of ‘gut feel’ to know when this
pattern is likely to occur, and you can never
really know ‘for sure’ until after the
second liquidity clear-out has formed.
But when you find it, the high probability
trade is in the direction of the initial breakout.
Both buyers and sellers are trapped in losing
positions
The double fake out pattern occurs in all
market conditions; trending, consolidating,
counter-trend, but, from my experience, the
best way to trade it is in-line with a dominant
trend.
Have you ever been stopped out, only to see
price reverse from that very same level?
I’m sure you have and you’re not alone.
Many traders tend to place their stops in
the same types of places, without sufficiently
weighing the fact that they are incredibly
easy to hit.
In this chart, we have a clear downtrend in
place and a double liquidity clear-out, first
to the downside, then, to the upside, within
a larger downtrend trend.
When you have the second trap, baiting buyers
in the market, where movement is against a
dominant trend like this, it’s usually a
very good signal that the trend may be ready
to resume to the downside.
Amateur traders love to try to pick the bottom
in a downtrend or the top in an uptrend, and
most of them are happy to trade a reversal,
instead of a continuation.
On each of these false-breakouts in this example,
2 different types of traders were trapped.
First, traders that entered short when the
market was making a new low and the second
batch of traders that thought the downtrend
was over and so they started buying.
So initial sellers were removed from the market,
as their stops were probably around the area
where buyers anticipated a breakout.
Buyers were also trapped after the second
liquidity clear-out.
And then professionals took advantage of the
temporary strength within the down-trending
market and entered short from value, and then
the downtrend resumed, flushing out all those
amateur traders with weak positions.
Enter after the second liquidity clear-out
You want to position yourself after the second
liquidity clear-out, in line with the smart
money and with the dominant trend.
I can’t give you an exact entry, but price
action is again your best friend.
When price returns inside the previous range,
after the second liquidity clear-out, and
there’s no momentum to the upside, you have
to find some sort of signal to enter.
In this case I see a double top and a bearish
engulfing candle, offering several clues that
the downtrend might resume.
You could also add a 20 moving average, and
trade when price moves below it.
There are many methods to enter, you just
have to choose the one you feel most comfortable
with.
Expect liquidity clear-outs when a market
is stuck in a range
The double liquidity clear-out pattern is
very common in trading ranges because inexperienced
traders often try to pick the breakout of
the range.
However, price may stay range-bound for longer
than most assume.
Knowing that liquidity clear-outs are somewhat
common when a market is stuck in a trading
range is a very valuable piece of information.
Trading this setup in a range-bound market
can be very lucrative as you can wait for
liquidity clear-outs at both the support or
resistance boundary of the range, and then
trade back in the direction of the first false
breakout.
It sounds easy in theory, I know.
The best way to be sure you don’t get caught
in the second false-breakout, when you plan
to enter, is to simply wait for price to close
inside of the range.
If this happens, there’s a good chance the
pattern is completed and price is then going
to start trending again.
Pin bars and candles with large wicks
With this setup, pin bars and candles with
large wicks will help you to identify the
liquidity clear-outs and will also help you
to time your entry.
Let’s look at his EUR/USD chart, on the
hourly time frames.
At a quick glance I see not 1, but 2 obvious
setups.
The first one is here.
Liquidity clear-out, reversal, buyers are
trapped, liquidity clear-out, sellers are
trapped and price continues in the initial
direction.
And the second one here.
Liquidity clear-out, sellers are trapped,
reversal, second liquidity clear-out, this
time, buyers are trapped and price continues
its recent downtrend.
Both setups have one thing in common.
Can you identify it?
We have candles with large wicks during the
second liquidity clear-out, on both occasions.
A price action trader can use this false breakout
pin bar signal to trade the setup.
First we get the bullish pin bar at the bottom
of this liquidity clear-out.
This pin would have looked like the big bearish
candle, baiting sellers to enter the market.
A lot of traders shorted the market when the
candle was forming.
And I know that if the market was to move
higher from here, at some point the traders
who have sold during this pin are likely to
close their trade.
The same here.
Before this pin bar became a pin bar it was
actually a large range candle.
And if you watched my previous video about
common market traps, you know that large range
candles are the types of candle which traders
will use to jump into trading positions.
The price made a large up move which seduce
lots of traders into placing trades in the
direction of the candle, the sudden increase
in buy orders means smart money are now able
to complete a trading action such as taking
profits or placing more trades.
When smart money make their decision, all
of the orders which were coming into the market
from the traders placing trades in the direction
of the candle are consumed and the price moves
in the opposite direction.
And because these actions pushed the price
in the opposite direction to which buyers
had placed their trades, it means their positions
are currently at a loss.
In both cases, if you want to profit from
these trapped traders, a pin bar will make
it easier to place your trade.
You set the stop loss, below the bullish pin
bar here, and above the bearish pin bar, here.
The psychology behind the double liquidity
pattern
It is important to understand the psychology
behind this double liquidity pattern and why
it often reveals that smart money might be
behind buying and not retail "weak hands".
After the first aggressive liquidity clear-out,
many retail traders don’t think of buying,
if anything the opposite.
The magnitude of fresh selling could discourage
buying and trigger selling instead (many traders
start thinking about abandoning their prior
long positions).
If someone is actually strongly buying after
the second liquidity clear-out, it is more
likely than it isn’t a retail participant.
This gives you insight that someone bigger
is willing to defend this area.
After you have been on the wrong side of a
market a few times, you will begin to realize
that this double fakeout can actually provide
high quality tradable opportunities.
The reality is that classic technical analysis,
teached in most trading books, is kinda outdated.
And you should design your trading strategy
around these types of scenarios.
Some of the best trades occur when market
players become trapped and begin to cover
their losing trades.
Accumulation, manipulation and trend phase.
If you have trouble finding this pattern,
try to break it into 3 stages: accumulation,
manipulation, and the trend phase.
Accumulation is the stage where smart money
enter their positions, manipulation is the
stage where the first and the second liquidity
clear out appear, and after the traders are
trapped, the trend phase begins.
The first thing you need to identify is the
accumulation.
Sometimes is obvious, sometimes in not.
Banks either enter the market by accumulating
a long position which they will later sell
at a higher price, or a short position which
they will later buy back at a lower price.
If you can identify the price levels where
banks are accumulating, you will also be able
to identify the direction of future price
movements.
Accumulation is often characterized by a ranging-type
market where the price moves sideways.
It is in this zone that banks regularly enter
the market to accumulate their desired position.
Manipulation is the next step after accumulation.
This stage is characterized by false movements.
And as we already discussed, retail traders
are the victims of such market manipulation.
They take positions when they see that there
is a potential breakout.
But it turns out to be just a fake push and
the price then moves in the opposite direction.
If you ever find yourself in this situation,
it's not bad luck.
In this example the banks are trying to enter
or build up a long position.
At the same time, they're also creating selling
pressure.
They will try to "manipulate" retail traders
into first going long, then short.
To follow the banks, you need to identify
the second and hopefully, the final liquidity
clear-out that marks the end of an accumulation
phase
The third stage, is the trend phase, the continuation
in the direction of the initial fake out.
At this point, the banks have accumulated
their position and created the market manipulation.
They no longer try to conceal their presence.
Now, the banks will try to push the price
in a specific direction, which means this
is where a market trend will begin.
And yes, trying to avoid the traps and recognizing
the pattern is difficult.
It takes a lot of research time, and plenty
of live trading and market observing experience,
to notice these stages in real time.
But if you understand how the banks are manipulating
the market, you'll be able to identify the
direction of the market trend that the banks
are trying to push.
Your next task will then be to just follow
the trend, after the second liquidity clear-out.
This doesn't mean you'll never lose when using
this strategy, but it will keep you focused
and ready to win more consistently.
Once you adopt trading strategies that are
in line with those of the big players, your
chances of making profits will go up.
Now, this strategy is designed to take advantage
of market traps.
If you want to easily spot areas on your chart
that are likely to be targeted by Smart Money,
you should definitely watch this video, because
it will show you how to adapt to the different
challenges that the market will throw at you.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!