[Music]
hello and welcome today we'll look at
several day trading strategies for
beginners we'll cover the main rules
and we'll also see how to find high
probability signals using the open price
of the day
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
the basis of every successful day
trading strategy is good knowledge of
daily price action
the basic info on daily price action is
the daily open high and low the daily
open is the price at which market opened
the high is the highest point that price
reached during the day and the low is
the lowest point that price reached
during the day
although all three levels are important
for the current day i'm mainly
interested in the daily open price
according to the daily open price you
can forecast the trend direction for the
rest of the day the downtrend the
uptrend or the sideways price
action in order to make it as easy as
possible i found this daily open
indicator to have you easily read and
analyze the price you can find this
daily open price on trading view
now you have a visual representation of
the open price if you look at the chart
you will notice how price never remains
still around a daily open level unless
it's a sideways trend
that's because the opening price is one
of the most important price levels for
the day
essentially it represents the balance
between bullish and bearish forces
that's why when prices are above the
opening price the market is considered
bullish
if prices fall below the opening price
the market is considered bearish
the opening price provides a standard
support and resistance function on the
price chart when price action reaches
the opening price it could act as a
support or resistance
or it could break the level and continue
on intraday trend
notice how price reacts at the daily
open price
when market is active price simply
doesn't stay around the level of the
daily open price
but forms down or uptrend above or under
the line instead
so this is the first thing you need to
remember the daily open line will become
strong support or resistance during the
trading day this is very important and
you should always check the level
regardless of which strategy you use
support and resistance levels based on
the daily open price level can be used
just like traditional support and
resistance levels
the key is to watch price action closely
when these levels come into play
should prices decline to support and
then hold you can look for a successful
test and bounce of support
it often helps to look for a bullish
chart pattern or a candlestick formation
or an indicator signal to confirm an
upturn from the support
similarly should prices advance to
resistance and stall you can look for a
failure at the resistance and a decline
again you should look for a bearish
confirmation or an indicator signal to
confirm a downturn from resistance
all things considered if you see price
action approaching the opening price
level on the chart
you should treat the situation as a
normal trading level
nonetheless if the price starts
hesitating when reaching this level and
suddenly bounces in the opposite
direction you might then trade in the
direction of the bounce
but if the price action breaks through
the opening price level then you could
expect the action to continue in the
direction of the breakout
what you need to know is that the open
price sets the general tone for the
price action
a move above the line is positive and
shows strength
while a move below the line shows
weakness
so how to trade using the open price
the location of the open price line on
the chart represents an important
information to be aware of because
there's a high probability that will be
reached
at the beginning of the day i like to
compare the value of the open price with
the value of the previous day
if the current open price line is higher
than the previous one i only consider
taking long entries during the day
if the current open price line is lower
than the previous one i consider taking
only short entries
basically i want to find trends and to
date rate the continuation in the
direction of the short-term trend
i will sometimes miss huge moves in the
opposite direction but this filter will
also save you many losing trades
i will also take into account the
distance between the open price line
meaning the range
open price lines located at a short
distance one from another indicate a
possible range i avoid trading on
markets where the most recent open lines
are close as price will most likely stay
flat and offer low probability entries
just look at this example the opening
price is almost the same
yes we have some bounces but we also
have many false signals if you trade
when the distance between lines is
narrow change from a day trading
perspective to a scoping one and try to
get in take some points and get out
quickly
opening price lines drawn at the larger
distance between them indicate a
trending market
this is what i like to see a separation
between lines which means we have a
short-term trend at least
and i don't like the line to be touched
often i don't want to see price moving
above and below the line crossing the
line often
i want the opening line to be an obvious
zone of support or resistance when price
reaches the area i like to see a
rejection or a momentum breakout also
when the distance between the opening
price lines is too wide you could also
have a consolidation day
this means that we had an aggressive
move the day before a high average true
range so the market may pause the next
day
while you can perfectly trade with this
setup alone if you are good at reading
price action it's better to combine it
with other trading tools
so let me show you several strategies
involving the opening price line first
one is the pin bar rejection strategy
trading with a trend is the best way to
trade any market and a pin bar entry
signal rejecting the opening price line
in a trending market can offer a high
probability entry and a good risk to
reward scenario
in this example we can see a bullish
beam bar that formed in the context of
an uptrending market
right at the opening price line
this type of bim bar shows rejection of
lower prices with a long lower tail
so it's called the bullish pin bar since
the implication of the rejection
reflected in the pin bar is that the
bulls will resume pushing the price
higher
when trading a pin bar counter to or
against the dominant trend you should do
so from a key chart level of support or
resistance and again this is where the
opening price is important
this key level the opening price adds
extra weight to the pin bar formation
have a look at this chart we have a
double pin bar setup against the trend
right at the opening price line
it's not uncommon to see back to back or
double pin bar patterns to form at key
levels in the market
these patterns are traded just like a
normal pin bar except they provide a
little more confirmation since they
reflect not one but two consecutive
rejections of the level
[Music]
the second system is the exponential
moving average high low channel strategy
price action naturally swings up and
down over the course of a day but these
swings tend to stay within a certain
range and thus create a general upward
or downward trend
a moving average channel allows you to
observe where the price is moving
and time trades around the opening price
line as they find additional supporter
resistance against the channel
i've talked about the moving average
high low channel in this video so make
sure you watch it after this one
basically instead of plotting one moving
average based on the closing price i
started using a moving average channel
you will have two moving averages
forming a channel which are applied to
the bar's high and low prices instead of
the bar's close price
this moving average channel will filter
a lot of all signals you know them well
when price closes above or below the
moving average you initiate a position
and then immediately the price closes on
the opposite side of the
average with a channel you'll have an
area a safety net and you reduce some
market noise
using a moving average channel you
remove the short-term fluctuations
around the line and at the same time
knowing the overall direction and the
trend of the market
when a price experiences a strong move
the price will have a tendency to track
back to the moving average channel but
then continue the original direction it
was moving
when the channel and the opening price
line come together around the same price
level you get an area of value from
which you can take your trades
a trading signal can be triggered when
the price retreats to the moving average
channel in this case the 200 exponential
moving average high low area around the
opening price line and reacts with a
bounce
if you watch price action in real time
you will often see how the price
slightly touches the moving average
channel and in some cases the touch will
also include the opening price line only
to get forcefully rejected back in the
opposite direction
when the moving average channel is
trending upwards you should consider
buying when the price bounces off the
channel and the opening price
the reverse supplies when the channel is
trending downwards in which case you
should be selling when the price rallies
toward the channel and gets rejected
there
if you find a pin bar that's even a
better signal remember the previous
strategy
if you have a previous market swing
around the area offering another layer
of confluence
again even better
[Music]
the third setup is the hackanashi
strategy
when you are day trading or scoping
candlestick charts may flip-flop
constantly from a green bar to a red bar
but ikanashi charts tend to have longer
stretches of bars
this provides clear highlighting and
confirmation of current trends
while hacking as you won't show the
exact price all the time there are some
benefits to using these charts the main
advantage is that they look much
smoother which helps to identify the
trending direction more easily
hacking issue charts are also color
coded as long as the price is rising
then the bars will show up as green
as long as the price is falling then the
bars will show up as red
the price is above the opening price
line with the heckiness candle turning
green from red it indicates that the
price is about to turn higher so you
want to trade green high kanashi bars
above the opening price line
if the price is below the line and high
canadian candle turns red it indicates
that the price is about to go down
again trade red bars below the line
remember that green candle sticks with
no lower shadow or weak indicate a
strong uptrend
so if you enter the long trade for
example you can remain in the trade
until the color of the hakanashi
candlestick changes from green to red
this allows your profits to run while
riding the short term uptrend
by the way this strategy also works as a
scoping setup
[Music]
if you learn something new please hit
the like button since it really helps us
out and subscribe to stay up to date
with our latest releases
and check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time