Market manipulation occurs on a daily basis,
right under the noses of retail traders.
You witness this yourself, every day.
And you’re wondering why the theory of support
and resistance you read in almost every trading
book, doesn’t seem to work in real markets.
Today I’m sharing my experience with support
and resistance trading, but in the context
of smart money, and you’ll learn the best
practices to trade, and avoid being manipulated
by big market players.
You know the drill, like, subscribe, and stick
around for the full video.
The biggest lie in trading
True or false?
The more times a level is tested, the more
“valid” it is.
If you said true, you are wrong!
This statement is one of the biggest lies
in trading.
In my experience, really strong support/resistance
levels immediately push price away from them.
There is enough buying pressure at support
(enough buyers waiting to buy at the level),
that the market is immediately moved up and
away from the level.
If price can hang around the level or quickly
comes back to the level, it suggests a certain
lack of conviction on the part of the bulls.
If the market is able to retest the level
many times, then you have a potential setup
for a breakout through the level.
In this example, the orders at the support
level are absorbed each time price revisits
the area, until buyers lose their power.
Price then plunges through the zone with little
difficulty.
And also look at this resistance level.
The upper zone was tested several times and
sellers came in pushing the price down.
This resistance level was gradually eroded
as more and more sellers had their order filled.
Eventually there were less sellers and price
broke through.
Personally, I avoid buying a support which
has been tested multiple times in the past.
The greater the number of times a zone is
tested, the more likely it is to break.
When a support area is tested multiple times,
some or all of the waiting buy orders are
executed, leaving less willing buyers at that
level.
Once all the buyers have gone, price can move
through that level to the next area.
From my experience, the best entry is the
one where price drops to support and quickly
moves up, leaving a long shadow on the candle
that dropped through support.
A liquidity clear-out.
I would much rather buy a broken support,
after a liquidity clear-out, than clean support…
that trade is 10 times better (to me) than
buying a clean, exact support level.
Strong imbalance between buyers and sellers
At one point, price leaves a support or resistance
level and starts trending.
A strong imbalance between buyers and sellers
leads to strong and explosive price movements.
As a rule of thumb, remember that the stronger
the movement away from a level, the more interest
will usually still exist – especially when
the time spent at the level was relatively
short.
So when price goes from selling off to a strong
bullish trend, there had to be a significant
amount of buy interest entering the market,
absorbing all sell orders AND then driving
price higher.
So the next time price revisits the area,
I would be very interested to buy that support.
Always look for extremely strong turning points;
these are often high probability price levels.
Price manipulation around support and resistance
Price manipulation is a series of actions
carried out by smart money to induce either
buying or selling activity from other traders.
Why would they do that?
Smart money uses position sizes that stop
them from simply hitting buy or sell as you
and I would do.
Because their position sizes are so massive
they must enter over a period of time so as
to not spike the price and reveal the position
they’re entering.
Because of this they have to seek out areas
in the market where there is enough liquidity.
A great deal of orders reside around support
and resistance zones.
Stop Entering When the Pro's are Taking Profit
Take a look at this example.
This shows a very common pattern in the market:
the key differences of where the professional
money enters and where the retail trader enters.
The retail trader buys and takes a long trade
when price breaks a previous resistance level
and price is at a new high.
Admit it, it’s a strategy you use often.
But soon after the entry, price moves lower
from the previous high.
And you often times get stopped out.
At the same time you are stopped out, the
professional traders are entering the market.
That’s the difference between retail and
smart money.
Retail traders buy at support.
Smart money buy below support.
And when price moves higher the professional
traders will cover their long trades and start
taking their profit.
At that time, the retail traders are just
starting to enter long.
When you enter from these areas that are at
extreme highs or lows, the big guys are taking
profit.
And obviously entering the market when the
smart money are getting out is not a smart
plan.
A common saying in trading is: buy any weakness
and sell any strength.
So if price moves lower from an extreme high
then you can look to buy from a value area,
and if price moves higher from an extreme
low, price can be sold from a value area.
Here’s price moving from an extreme high
back lower.
This is price showing weakness and moving
to a value area for a possible buy entry.
If you have entered a long trade from the
high, you would have been stopped out.
But if you have instead entered a long trade
when price showed weakness and moved back
lower, you would have entered at a much better
area.
The consolidation trap
Price spends most of its time in consolidation.
This is the market showing you a balance in
price.
There are several reasons for the price to
consolidate.
One of them is liquidity generation.
When price consolidates for an extended period
of time, the masses start to place support
and resistance levels at the extremes of the
consolidation zone.
Any sudden break out of this consolidation
range will tempt traders to enter.
These entry opportunities are traps set by
the market makers using this consolidation
technique.
If you’re using certain indicators, things
are even worse.
When the market is in consolidation, moving
averages, probably the most common indicator,
will get very close together.
The most common entry signal is given to retail
traders when these 2 moving averages cross.
A breakout outside the consolidation, plus
the crossover, indicate to retail traders
that the trend has now changed.
This is “a false” signal that the price
will increase.
All of these confirmations are seducing the
average retail trader to take a buy position,
in order for the smart money to fill their
massive sell positions.
And by the time the indicators signal the
change to a downtrend the market has already
made most of its move.
The point is: smart money knows that even
the smallest break outside of a consolidation
area will set off the signal to the masses.
This is well known tactic used by market makers
to trick retail traders into buying or selling
certain levels.
Liquidity clear-outs
Liquidity is just a fancy word for you taking
a position.
The more people taking positions, the more
liquidity you have.
The big players need LOTS of liquidity in
order to fill their massive orders.
How do you think they get this liquidity?
By creating well known retail chart patterns,
in order to involve the retail traders into
the market.
These patterns are used by smart money to
induce you take a position.
You might have a small account, and trade
with mini lots, but remember, millions of
beginner traders are in your shoes, and use
the same information to trade.
Smart money vs dumb money
Trading will always be a game against the
smart money and the dumb money.
How many times have you traded a triangle
pattern, for example, just for the price to
do the exact opposite as soon as you jump
into your position?
Retail traders might see these patterns as
continuation patterns, but the smart money
are seeing them as reversal patterns.
You have to start putting yourself in the
shoes of the large institutions and big-money
players.
Think like the hunter, not the prey.
Always remember that smart money are always
searching for pockets of liquidity in order
to fill their desired positions in the market.
They are always looking to shake out weak
hands, particularly around support and resistance
levels that are being widely watched.
It’s time to reconsider how you see support
and resistance levels and to start building
a strategy that allows you to join the smart
money, after a liquidity clear-out.
Trade In The Direction Of The Most Recent
valid High/Low
Most of the traders who trade support and
resistance try to predict where a movement
will end instead of trading in the direction
of the movement itself.
What these traders typically tend to do is
mark all the levels which the market hasn’t
encountered yet and wait for the price to
enter these zones before going either long
or short.
But there are lots of levels forming in the
direction of the current movement which the
trader is neglecting to trade because he is
so focused on predicting where the price will
reverse.
My advice is to start taking trades at levels
which formed in the direction of the most
recent high or low.
A new high or low is a signal that the current
momentum is to the upside or downside, by
trading against this momentum you are unnecessarily
putting yourself at risk of losing money because
you’re trying to trade against the trend.
Big Round Number Prices
I said it quite a few times before, one of
the best places you can find high probability
support and resistance levels, is around the
big round number levels.
The support and resistance levels you can
find situated around these prices have a high
probability of causing a large reversal to
occur.
Just open any chart and you’ll see that
many big reversals will begin once the price
has either almost hit a big round number,
or has just moved beyond it.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.