In any market, price moves from supply zones
to demand zones and back: over and over again.
If you learn to find these zones, you can
get into decent trades, precisely at the
point when banks start to place their trades.
That’s why today I’m sharing one of my favorite
smart money strategies, using supply and demand
areas, in combination with psychological levels.
You know the drill, like, subscribe
and stick around for the full video.
Supply and Demand
Demand Zones form when banks place
a large number of buy positions.
This creates an imbalance, and results
in the price aggressively moving higher.
These are the support levels
of supply and demand trading.
Supply zones are points where the banks place a
significant number of sell positions, resulting
in price aggressively moving lower.
These are the resistance points
where price could fall.
So if price returns to
certain supply and demand zones, it has a
high probability of rejecting these areas.
Let’s be clear, it takes time, practice, and
experience to identify the best supply and
demand areas to trade.
Here’s MY process.
You already know that supply
and demand zones are formed
when banks are placing large quantities of orders.
Well, on a price chart, a sharp rise,
or a sharp decline, appears in price.
These are the first signs
that smart money are active.
Market imbalances
Identifying market imbalances is the first step to
finding supply and demand zones. Market imbalances
refer to big price shifts in one direction.
To locate demand zones, you
look for fast impulse move.
The key point to remember while finding the market
imbalances is to keep an eye on big green candles.
You can identify these candles by their
long bodies with little to no wicks.
Once you have identified a fast impulse move, it
becomes a lot easier to find the base of the zone.
You find the most recent down candle before the
impulse move and place a line at its high price,
and a line at the most recent swing low,
that formed at the source of the move.
It’s a slightly different method to draw
the area, compared to my previous videos,
but I’ll explain later why I
choose to use this method instead.
To find supply zones, first,
you’re looking for fast declines.
Sharp declines occur when supply comes into
the market, which happens when the banks sell.
Again, you look for big red candles,
with long bodies and little or no wicks.
In theory, price has a high probability
of reversing once it returns
to the source of the decline.
You then find the most recent up candle before the
sharp down move and place a line at its low price,
and another line at the most recent swing
high, that formed at the source of the move.
psychological levels
Human emotions play a part in the
price action observed in markets.
Many traders prefer to set their “buy”
and “sell” orders around round numbers.
It’s not that common to have
an order placed at $60.12.
No, instead we like to work with round
numbers, and that’s why these numbers
are psychological levels that have breakouts
and big amounts of activity attached to them.
To plot these round numbers, I first add
on Tradingview the horizontal grid lines.
Then I simply adjust the right
margin, and play with the scale,
depending on the market I’m trading.
These psychological levels are perfect
for identifying high probability
supply and demand areas.
A supply zone, in combination with
a psychological level, is a high
probability area to initiate a buy position.
A demand zone, which includes psychological
level, again, offers a low risk -
high reward sell situation.
We are looking at Crude Oil.
I prefer to analyze higher time
frames, and pinpoint the entry on lower ones.
On the daily time frame, I see a demand area.
I see this big strong lineup of candles moving
up. Candles with long bodies and small wicks.
We then identify the origin of the price movement,
the last bearish candle before the rally.
We also adjust the scale on the right, to
have a $1 grid, to find the round numbers.
Our demand zone includes 3 psychological
levels at 64, 63 and 62 dollars.
We don’t know which one will hold. You can set
a limit order at one level inside the zone,
the aggressive entry, or you could wait for a
price action signal to confirm the rejection,
the conservative method.
I prefer the second approach.
I look for pin bars or engulfing candles
to form inside a zone, rejecting a
psychological number and then I enter.
Now, we determined our value area,
let’s see if price returns to it.
We move the M15 time frame, to pinpoint the entry.
This is the signal. A pin bar candlestick forms
right after price enters the zone and rejected the
$63 round number. This is our signal to buy.
Stop loss below the demand zone.
Take profit, as usual, depending
on recent market structure. I’ll
set my first target here, at $72,
at this potential supply zone.
And the second target around $78 level,
again, below this other supply zone.
We move to Bitcoin, on the H4 time
frame. I see this potential supply zone,
after this aggressive down move.
The STRENGTH OF THE MOVE is very
important. The stronger the price moves away
from a zone, the more out-of-balance supply
and demand are at that zone. It means
a heavy order is placed by smart money.
You also must analyze how far the
price moved away from the supply zone.
The longer the distance the price moves away from
a zone before returning to that zone, the better.
First-time retrace to the supply
zone is the strongest to enter.
Always make sure the zone is still “fresh” which
means that after the initial creation of the zone,
price has not come back to it yet.
Each time price revisits a supply zone,
more and more previously unfilled orders
are filled and the level is weakened.
Ok, now let’s wait for a retrace back to our
zone. Observe we have 3 psychological levels
inside the area. So, again, we’ll
wait for price action confirmation.
Here’s the rejection, an evening
star candlestick formation.
Stop loss is placed above the supply zone.
And we’ll target this demand zone.
Let’s move to stock market. Tesla.
On hourly time frame we find the
potential demand zone. We draw the zone based
on last bearish candle before the sharp rally.
Now we’ll keep an eye on the future price
movements to see if it retraces back to this
demand level, because in theory there should be
more buy orders waiting to get executed here.
I set a $10 grid on this market, and observe
that our demand zone includes 2 round numbers.
Now we’ll wait for a confirmation, because
we don’t know which level will hold.
A good idea for confirmation is to wait for the
first reaction on the round number, to see if the
price is strongly pushed away off that level.
I also want to see signs
of weakness in price action:
• Momentum loss (decreasing candle range and body)
• And lower wicks on the candles
when price is inside the demand zone
Ok, price found support at this
psychological level, inside the zone.
The stop loss is placed just
beyond the extreme of the zone.
The take-profit is the next major supply level,
which would be right here. So I’ll set my target
a few cents below this area. The risk to reward
ratio on this trade is quite good, around 6.
Like I said before, you can be
aggressive and use limit orders.
It’s a decent way of trading supply and demand,
and you can be quite successful with it.
The problem is that a limit order entry provides
NO confirmation that price will reverse from a
zone. You will blindly place the order at the edge
or inside the zone and hope that price reverses.
This would not be a problem if all supply and
demand zones worked all the time. But, they don’t!
Price blasts through zones
frequently, usually without stopping.
With the limit order entry, you cannot avoid this.
So, you’ll end up with many losing trades.
With the price action entry,
however, things are different.
It’s better to find the supply or
demand zone on the HIGHER TIME FRAME,
wait for the price to come to this
level, and see any acceptance or
rejection from this zone on a lower time frame.
You look for any reversal price action signal
on the lower time frame, rejecting the
psychological number, inside the zone.
And yes, you’ll have a delayed entry,
sometimes not even inside the zone.
But, in the long run, price action confirmation
will save you from many losing trades.
We trade EUR/USD, on the hourly chart.
This would be my minimum time frame
to find supply and demand area.
I see this supply zone right here,
which had a huge drop consisting
of multiple bearish large candles.
This supply zone also aligns with the current
trend, which is down. So another tip would be
to trade zones in the direction of the main trend:
• If the trend is down, you look for supply areas
• If you have an uptrend,
you search for demand zones
We have 2 round numbers inside the
zone. So, as usual, we’ll wait for
a clear rejection, inside the supply zone.
Let’s pinpoint the entry on the M15 time frame.
Just as expected, price found resistance
at the first round number inside the zone,
forming a pin bar candlestick.
This is the confirmation I needed. Stop
loss on the other side of the supply zone.
Take profit, a few points below
the next major demand zone,
which would be here.
A risk to reward ratio of over 4.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like. This way we’ll know if
you'd like to see more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want to
further level up your trading. Until next time.