if you want to increase your chances to
succeed at scalping you must find
confluence
confluence is when several trading tools
give the same signal you combine more
than one technique to increase your odds
of a winning trade
today i'm sharing a sculpting strategy
which i'm currently back testing on the
five minute time frame the strategy
relies on trend and momentum breakouts
confirmed by trading volume
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
the strategy requires to analyze the
main trend the prevailing momentum and
the volume to find low risk high reward
trade opportunities
as i said before we look for confluence
between these three forces
trend momentum and volume
we'll use multiple trading tools that
give the same reading as a way to
confirm the validity of a potential buy
or sell signal
for determining the trend we'll use hike
and ashy candles for analyzing the price
momentum we'll use the rsi bars
indicator and for confirming our entry
we'll use a volume spread analysis
indicator
[Music]
a high kennedy chart offers an unique
perspective on price action its
essential contribution in our strategy
is that it eliminates small price
fluctuations to highlight price trends
a moving average smooths a price chart
as well so what is the difference
between a moving average and a heckiness
chart
while the smoothing effect of a moving
average depends on its look back period
the high can actually chart doesn't
require a look back period and with such
smooth and wavy price action a part of
market noise is eliminated
now despite being plotted as
candlesticks hacking ashy charts don't
directly represent the real prices
they overlap with the actual traded
prices but they are not the same just be
aware of this when you backtest
hakanashi make sure you have these tabs
checked in trading view
the last price line and the real prices
on price scale
hackiness candles are a great tool to
detect trends in an easier way a very
common heck and ashy behavior is for
candles to stay green during uptrends
and for candles to stay red during
downtrends
green candlesticks without lower shadows
are indicating a strongly bullish
movement
red candlesticks without upper shadows
are strongly bearish
also the size of each candle tends to be
associated with the strength of the
movement just like in regular
candlesticks
a long green candle is an indicator of
strong bullish forces
a long red candle is an indicator of
strong bearish forces
always remember the best way to analyze
a chart is by thinking and trying to
make sense of price action through logic
candles are a visual representation of
the actions of buyers and sellers
so what we are really care about is how
buyers and sellers are behaving
i found this indicator on trading view
rsi candles
this indicator changes the color of the
price bars if the relative strength
index the rsi is above or below a
certain value
we'll use the rsi as a momentum
oscillator because it measures the
velocity and the magnitude of price by
comparing upward and downward movements
the indicator was originally designed to
find over bath and oversold levels at
the 30 and 70 level
while many traders use the rsi mostly to
reveal overbought and oversold
conditions we'll use a different
approach
our target in the scoping strategy is to
identify the energy behind the move
we'll change both inputs to 50 and we'll
focus on the middle line of the
indicator
we'll also change the length of the
indicator to 50.
because this is a sculpting strategy i
want to eliminate the noise as much as
possible so higher period on the rsi
will help us in this way
the color of price bars change every
time the rsi crosses above or below 50.
when the rsi is above the 50 line the
price has upwards momentum
and the high kanashi candles are green
when the rsi is below the 50 line the
price has downwards momentum and the
high canadian candles are red
when the rsi is crossing the center line
the momentum is switching from one
direction to the other and the candles
are changing color
[Music]
for volume confirmation i use this
indicator called volume spread for vsa
it shows you how the relative change in
volume between bars is happening
it's very easy to read volume using this
indicator
red means ultra high volume
yellow is high volume
green is average volume and blue is low
volume
this is probably the best vsa indicator
on trading view if you want a separate
video about this indicator let me know
in the comments
now volume is the ultimate leading
indicator when there is unusually high
volume in any given time period then the
price tends to continue in the same
direction in the future
in the sculpting strategy volume will
confirm the strength of the move or will
show its weakness
if the price is rising for instance and
the volume is increasing
then this suggests that we have a strong
price move supported by an increasing
number of buyers
when you are sculpting and day trading
the process is much harder because
numerous opportunities come up every day
and it gets challenging if you don't
know what to look for meaning what is a
good trade setup and when is a good time
to enter the trade
even though the trend is up momentum is
bullish and volume is increasing because
of the nature of scoping you will still
witness a lot of false signals that's
why when i'm scoping i'm focusing on the
short-term breakouts
this breakout filter aims to enter a
trade as soon as the price manages to
break out of a previous support or
resistance level
we are looking for strong short-term
momentum and the actual breakout is the
signal to enter the position
volume will help to validate the
breakout
when the market is consolidating on low
volume a pickup in volume can signify
that a breakout is due
a breakout happening on rising volume is
a valid breakout
while a breakout that attracted no
interest from traders occurring on low
volume is likely to be false
for a long entry trend is up meaning
hekenashi candles are green
momentum is up rsi candles are green
price is moving above a resistance level
volume confirms the breakouts meaning we
must have high or ultra high volume
a confluence of factors all indicating a
continuation of the price move
for a short entry trend is down meaning
heck and ashy candles are red
momentum is down rsi candles are red
price is moving below a support level
and volume confirms the breakout
meaning we must have high or ultra high
volume
this is the 5 minute chart of apple
after an uptrend the price switches
directions and starts moving sideways
creating a consolidation area
meanwhile there are a couple of swing
lows created observe the area around the
lower weeks of the candles which creates
our support area
when trading breakouts it's best wait
for a candle close beyond the support
area to confirm the breakout with this
break of structure we have a potential
down move in place
the trend condition is confirmed by the
red hakanesh candles
momentum is also down with the rsi
candles being read
at the moment of the breakout we see an
obvious increase in volume which is our
third condition
so trend momentum and volume are
indicating the same thing
this is the power of confluence you
don't guess the market direction or
randomly enter when you see some
activity you time the market when
multiple energies are indicating
strength or weakness in the market
this is how i personally place my stops
i look for the breakout candle the one
which really confirms the level is
broken
if the volume is high or ultra high i
set my stop loss above that particular
candle and i aim to win double the
amount i've risked i look for a positive
reward to risk ratio such as two to one
which would dictate that my potential
profit is larger than any potential loss
this is the five minute chart of tesla
notice that we have an obvious uptrend
with price making higher highs and
higher lows
momentum is clearly up with many
consecutive green candles
observe this price contraction after the
up move
like other contracting patterns this
will eventually lead to a breakout and
create a new price movement
the direction of the breakout is
typically unknown this means that the
breakout from the pattern could send the
price in either direction for this
reason even though you expect an upward
breakout you will continue carefully to
watch both the support and resistance
levels for potential signs
this is the candle which moves above the
upward level the resistance
after the price breaks through the upper
level you have to confirm if the
breakout is valid using the volume
you see increasing volume and more
importantly above average volume which
indeed confirms that there is strength
in the market from the buyer's side
again trend momentum and volume are in
harmony
long trade here
stop loss below the breakout
and we target double the amount we
risked
here is euro usd on the 5 minute time
frame
after this period of consolidation we
have our breakouts followed by a big
bold candle
the candle closes well below the support
level
we have a little break of structure
which could prepare the market for a
shift in the short-term trend
this is highlighted by the shift in the
color of the hakanashi bar momentum also
shifted to the downside with the red
candle appearing right at the moment of
the breakout
the volume is increasing and is yellow
which means we have consecutive bars of
high volume
breakouts that occur on high volume show
greater conviction which means the price
is more likely to trend in that
direction
and this combination of multiple
energies trend momentum and volume all
agreeing on the same basis is very
important to filter the market noise and
bad signals
short position after the scandal
with a stop loss above it
and a two to one reward to risk ratio
[Music]
being a scoping and day trading strategy
you obviously want to catch minor trends
or shifts in the market which means you
need to make quick decisions given the
number of trades you will make in a
single day it's important to lower the
amount of margin dedicated to any single
trade and minimize risk
my advice is to never risk more than one
or two percent of your initial deposit
this will allow you to have two or three
positions at a time without having a big
exposure
you can improve the strategy as you wish
if you don't like using hackanashi
candles you can use regular candlestick
charts and add the moving average or
view up to determine the short-term
trend
if you don't want to use the rsi bars
you can remove them because high kanashi
candles can also show price momentum if
you are analyzing the wicks
rising momentum can be illustrated by
green high kanashii candles with no
lower wicks
decreasing momentum is shown by red
hakanashi candles with no upper wicks i
like to add the rsi candles because it
hides some unimportant red candles in an
uptrend and some green candles in a
downtrend it's visually more appealing
for me but if you feel you can take
signals without it you can remove it
you can also remove the volume
confirmation
sometimes you can sculpt a few points
even without having high or ultra high
volume
there are many breakouts that occur on
average volume
the point is you can customize the
strategy and add your own filters to
improve it and make it even better
if you found value and learned something
new leave us a like this way we'll know
if you'd like to see more videos like
this one
and check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time