If you clicked this video… you've probably tried
scalping, day trading, or even swinging gold!
And nothing worked consistently… until now!
This strategy is different - and I'll prove it!
So gold prices fool traders every day! This
particular market requires perfect timing!
Most traders always seem to
be too early or too late!
Well, this guide combines multiple
technical factors - trendline breaks,
resistance-support flips, and retests -
into high-probability trade opportunities.
So let's break down the key components and
explore why this approach can be effective,
from a supply and demand perspective.
This chart shows an upward trendline
that's been in place for some time.
This trendline represents a series of higher lows,
indicating consistent buying pressure.
However, the strategy focuses on the moment
when this trendline is broken to the downside.
A trendline break is significant.
It suggests that buyers are no longer able to
maintain the previous rate of price increase.
When price breaks below the trendline,
it often indicates that selling pressure
is starting to overcome buying pressure.
After the initial break, price often returns
to the underside of the trendline. This retest
serves several purposes.
It confirms the validity
of the break. If the trendline now acts as
resistance, it strengthens the bearish case.
Also, it provides a more favorable entry point
for short trades, with a tighter stop loss.
And it often traps late buyers who see
the pullback as a buying opportunity,
not realizing the trend has changed.
From a supply and demand perspective,
the area just above the broken
trendline becomes a zone of supply.
Sellers who missed the initial move down are often
eager to enter short positions at this level,
creating additional selling pressure.
The strategy also incorporates a key
support level that has now flipped to resistance.
This concept is powerful because it demonstrates
a clear shift in market psychology.
Previously, this level acted as support,
meaning buyers were consistently willing
to step in and purchase at this price.
This area now acts as resistance. And
this indicates that previous buyers at
this level are now looking to exit their
positions, creating selling pressure.
New sellers view this level as an
opportunity to enter short positions.
And the overall market sentiment has
shifted from bullish to bearish.
The power of this strategy lies in the
confluence of multiple bearish signals:
• the broken upward trendline
• the successful retest of the broken trendline
• and the previous support
now acting as resistance
When these factors align, it creates a
high-probability setup for a short trade.
The confluence of signals increases the
likelihood that the bearish move will continue,
because it represents a significant shift
in market dynamics and psychology.
The retest trade is effective for several reasons:
Markets often have a "memory" of significant price
levels. When price returns to a previously
important level (like a broken trendline or
a broken support), it often reacts strongly.
Also, many traders who missed the initial
uptrend see the pullback to the trendline as
a "second chance" to enter long positions.
When price fails to move higher, these traders are
forced to exit, adding to the selling pressure.
At the same time, traders looking for
short entries often wait for a retest
of a broken level. This allows them
to enter with a tighter stop loss.
And the retest confirms that the broken
level is now acting as resistance.
Understanding why buyers become
trapped above this level is key.
As I said, some buyers enter long positions
when price briefly moves above the previous
support (now resistance) level,
thinking the uptrend is resuming.
Other traders see the pullback to the
trendline as a buying opportunity,
not realizing the trend has changed.
As price fails to move higher and
instead drops below the entry points of these
trapped buyers, their stop losses are triggered,
adding to the selling pressure.
And the realization that the
trend has changed can cause panic selling
among those who were previously bullish.
From a supply and demand
viewpoint, this setup represents
a significant shift in the balance of power:
We clearly have an Exhaustion of Demand. The
break of the upward trendline implies that buying
pressure (the demand) is no longer strong enough
to maintain the previous rate of price increase.
We also have an increase in Supply: The area above
the broken trendline and the flipped support
level becomes a zone of increased supply.
Sellers are more willing to enter or
add to short positions at these levels.
And this creates an Imbalance: the
confluence of signals creates a
situation where supply significantly outweighs
demand, leading to downward price movement.
So this trading strategy combines
multiple technical analysis concepts.
It relies on a shift in market dynamics
and psychology, as represented by the
broken trendline and flipped support level.
And the power of this method lies in its
ability to identify situations where
supply is likely to overwhelm demand,
leading to downward price movement.
Now let’s look at a buy signal.
This combines two key breakouts - a diagonal
trendline break and a horizontal resistance break.
This dual breakout setup can signal a strong
shift in market dynamics, often leading to
significant upward price movement.
Let's start with the trendline break.
In a downtrend, price makes lower
highs and lower lows. And we draw
a trendline connecting these lower highs.
When price finally breaks above this trendline,
it's a sign that selling
pressure may be weakening.
This break is step one of our “buy” signal.
But a break alone isn't enough.
After the initial break, price
often pulls back to the trendline.
This retest is crucial. If the
old resistance (the trendline)
now acts as support, it confirms the breakout.
It shows that market psychology has shifted.
Then, there’s the horizontal breakout. During a
downtrend, certain price levels act as resistance.
When price not only breaks the downward trendline,
but also pushes above one of these horizontal
resistance levels, it's a strong signal.
The power of this breakout
comes from its dual nature.
You're not just seeing one type
of breakout, but two. The diagonal breakout (the
trendline) shows a change in the overall trend.
The horizontal breakout shows that
a specific price level, which had
been holding price down, has now been overcome.
From a supply and demand perspective, this setup
is fascinating. The downtrend represents
a period where supply outweighs demand.
Sellers are in control, pushing price lower.
The trendline break suggests that this balance
is shifting. So demand is
starting to overcome supply.
The retest of the trendline and the
previous resistance is a key moment.
It's where old sellers (the supply)
may try to reassert control.
If they fail – so if price bounces off the
old trendline - it shows that new buyers
(the demand) are now strong enough
to absorb this selling pressure.
The break of horizontal
resistance adds another layer.
These resistance levels are prices where
supply previously overwhelmed demand.
Breaking through shows that
demand has not just increased,
but increased enough to absorb all the supply
at that price level, and push even higher .
It's all about market psychology. During the
downtrend, traders get used to selling at
certain levels. When price breaks higher,
many don't believe the move at first.
They see the pullback to the
trendline as a chance to short again.
But if price bounces off the trendline,
these shorts are now trapped. Their
stop-losses become fuel for the next move up.
The same happens with the horizontal breakout.
Traders who've seen price turn down from this
level before may try to short there again.
If price pushes through, their
stops add buying pressure.
This brings us to trapped sellers.
In the original downtrend, selling at the
trendline or at resistance levels was profitable.
As price breaks higher, these sellers
start to doubt their positions.
Each push higher puts more pressure
on them. Eventually, they have to buy, to cover
their shorts, adding even more upward pressure.
The confluence of these signals - trendline break,
successful retest, and resistance-to-support flip,
creates a powerful buy setup.
Volume often plays a key role here too.
Look for higher than average
volume on the initial breaks.
This shows strong buying pressure.
Then, look for lower volume on the retest.
This suggests that sellers aren't
putting up much of a fight anymore .
Candlestick patterns can add extra confirmation.
A strong bullish candle on the breakout,
followed by small, indecisive candles
on the retest, can be a good sign.
It shows strong buying on the break and a
lack of selling pressure on the pullback.
This strategy works well because it
aligns with how markets often move.
Trends don't reverse in an instant.
There's usually a period of struggle as
buyers and sellers battle for control.
This setup captures that battle and
signals when buyers are winning.
It's also a versatile strategy.
You can use it on any timeframe,
from intraday to daily charts.
The longer the timeframe, often
the more significant the signal.
One strength of this strategy is that it
gives clear entry and stop loss levels.
You can enter on at the confluence zone,
after the retest, with a stop loss below it.
Another chart! First, you identify a
clear downtrend and draw your trendline.
You then mark the key
horizontal resistance levels.
Then wait for a break of both the trendline
and a significant resistance level.
After that, you look for a pullback to
retest the broken trendline and the previous
resistance. This is the confluence zone.
If price bounces off this retest level,
consider entering a long position.
You place your stop loss just
below the retest low.
And you may taking partial
profits at the next major resistance level,
while also moving your stop to breakeven.
This strategy is about catching
a potential momentum change.
And the real profit potential comes if you've
truly caught the start of a new uptrend.
In that case, after your entry, you might see
price making a series of higher highs and higher
lows, the opposite of the previous downtrend.
In essence, this method is about spotting
the shift from a seller-dominated
market, to a buyer-dominated one.
The trendline break shows the first
crack in the sellers' control.
The break of horizontal resistance
shows that buyers are strong enough
to push into new territory.
And the retest of the confluence
zone shows that buyers are stepping
in to support price at higher levels.
When all these factors align, they provide a
strong signal that market dynamics are changing.
Another trade. This chart shows an upward sloping
trendline connecting the lower lows of price
action. This trendline represents the overall
bullish sentiment in the market, where buyers have
been in control, pushing prices higher over time.
The first key event is when price
breaks below this upward trendline.
This is a significant moment, because
it signals that the buying pressure that has
been supporting the uptrend, may be weakening.
The break of the trendline is the
market's first hint that the balance
between buyers and sellers might be shifting.
Simultaneously with the trendline break,
we're watching a horizontal level that used to act
as support now potentially flipping to resistance.
This is a key psychological level for traders.
In an uptrend, this level might have been a
place where buyers consistently stepped in.
Now, if price can't push back above it,
it shows that these buyers are
no longer defending this level.
The support flipped into resistance.
And after the initial break, price often
returns to "retest" the broken trendline.
It's a moment where the market is deciding
if the break was genuine or just a temporary dip.
During this retest, the old zones (the trendline
and the support level) are
now acting as resistance.
If price fails to push back above this confluence
area, it confirms that the previous buyers are no
longer strong enough to maintain the uptrend.
The power of this sell signal comes from
the confluence of both a diagonal and
horizontal resistance, now working together.
When price fails to break back above both of these
levels, it's a strong indication that selling
pressure is overcoming buying pressure .
From a supply and demand viewpoint,
this setup makes a lot of sense.
During the uptrend, demand
consistently outweighed supply at each higher low.
The trendline break suggests that this balance is
shifting – supply is starting to overcome demand .
The retest of the trendline and the old support
level is a critical juncture.
It's where the remaining
demand try to reassert control.
If it fails – if price bounces
off these levels – it shows that new sellers are
now strong enough to absorb this buying pressure,
and push prices lower.
This retest trade is all
you need to trade succesfuly.
It’s all about market psychology.
During the uptrend, traders got
used to buying at certain levels.
When price breaks lower, many don't believe
the move at first. They see the retrace to
our confluence area as a chance to buy
again, expecting the uptrend to continue.
But if price fails to push higher from
these levels, these buyers are now trapped.
Their stop-losses, typically placed
just below their entry points,
become fuel for the next move down.
As price drops, these stops are hit,
creating additional selling pressure.
So these trapped Buyers are practically
forced to sell, to cut their losses, adding
even more downward pressure to the market.
As I said before, you can
confirm your trade using volume.
Look for higher than average volume
on the initial break of the trendline.
This shows strong selling pressure.
Then, ideally, you'd see lower
volume on the retest.
This implies that buyers
aren't putting up much of a fight anymore.
If you see high volume as price approaches
the confluence zone, but fails to break
through, it's an even stronger confirmation.
It shows that despite significant buying effort,
sellers were still able to push price back down.
Specific candlestick patterns can
add extra confirmation to this sell
signal. Look for bearish patterns at the
retest point, such as engulfing patterns,
or even just long upper wicks on candles.
These patterns show rejection of higher
prices and can be the final piece of the
puzzle in confirming the sell signal.
Again, this strategy can work on multiple
time frames, but the higher the time frame,
generally the more significant the signal.
A 4-hour chart showing this pattern might
indicate a major trend change, while a 5-minute
chart might signal a shorter-term move.
Now, you might think this
setup anticipates reversals.
And it’s true, it can pinpoint
the start of a new trending move.
But you can also trade it as a continuation setup.
So this chart shows a textbook example of a
trend continuation pattern, marking
the end of a complex pullback, and
signaling a resumption of the previous uptrend.
It all starts with a clear uptrend, starting from
the lower left corner. This sets the stage for
our analysis, as we're looking for opportunities
to join this existing trend after a pullback.
After the initial uptrend, we see a pullback.
This isn't a simple, straight-line retracement.
Instead, it's a complex pullback, forming
a series of lower highs and lower lows. This
complexity often shakes out weak hands and can
make traders doubt the original trend.
That’s why you’ll see a trend on one
time frame, and another one on lower ones.
During the pullback, we can draw a descending
trendline connecting the lower highs.
This trendline acts as dynamic
resistance during the pullback phase.
At the bottom of the pullback, we see
price repeatedly touching a horizontal level. This
level, which initially acted as resistance earlier
in the uptrend, now becomes potential support.
The first major signal comes when price breaks
above the descending trendline.
This break suggests that buyers
are starting to overpower sellers .
Simultaneously, we see the horizontal level
that was previously resistance, now potentially
acting as support. This "flip" will be a powerful
indication of a change in market structure.
And after breaking this area, price often
comes back to "retest" it.
This is when we’ll see if
we have our confirmation, if the old
resistance will now act as support.
It's a key psychological moment
where buyers who missed the initial
break get a second chance to enter
The buy signal gains strength from the
confluence of both the trendline break
and retest, and the support-resistance
flip occurring at the same price level.
I always look for a momentum confirmation during
the retest, not just a simple touch of the zone.
Look for a strong bullish candle forming after the
retest. This candle confirms that buyers
are indeed stepping in at this level.
So while this pattern might look
similar to a reversal setup,
it's actually a continuation pattern.
The key difference is the context - we're
looking at a pullback in an existing
uptrend, not a reversal of a downtrend.
This is important because trading with
the larger trend increases your odds.
Complex pullbacks are tricky. They last longer
and have more price swings than simple pullbacks.
This complexity often causes
traders to doubt the original trend.
Some traders who bought the initial uptrend
might exit their positions during this pullback.
Others might even try to short,
thinking a reversal is happening.
But when price breaks the trendline
and flips the resistance to support,
all these traders are caught on the wrong side.
Their scramble to exit losing positions or enter
new long positions adds fuel to the next leg up .
The combination of breaking a diagonal trendline
and a horizontal resistance
level is particularly powerful.
The diagonal break shows that the rate of
price decline is slowing and reversing.
The horizontal break shows
that a significant price level,
where sellers were previously in
control, has now been overcome.
Together, they signal a significant shift
in the balance between buyers and sellers.
If you’re in doubt about
a setup, check the volume!
Look for increased volume on the
trendline break and during the retest.
High volume on the break
shows strong buying interest.
Lower volume on the retest, followed by higher
volume as price moves up, confirms that sellers
are exhausted and buyers are taking control.
This setup works because it captures a key moment
in market dynamics.
The complex pullback allows the trend
to "digest" its previous gains and transfer
positions from weak hands to strong hands.
The trendline break signals
that buyers are returning.
The retest and support-resistance flip
confirm that the market structure has changed.
Traders who sold during the pullback are now
trapped and need to buy to exit their positions.
New buyers see the resumption of the trend
and enter, adding further buying pressure .
And of course, not every break leads
to a trend resumption. Sometimes,
price will break the confluence zone,
trigger buy orders, and then reverse sharply.
This is why waiting for the retest and
the volume confirmation is important.
It allows the setup to "prove
itself" before you enter.
Another trend continuation setup! Price
keeps making lower highs and lower lows.
This is our starting point for a sell signal.
During this downtrend, price starts to pull back.
But it's not a simple, straight-line move up.
Instead, we see a complex pullback. The price
zigzags, creating a series of higher lows
and higher highs within the larger downtrend.
As this pullback unfolds, we can draw an
ascending trendline connecting the lows.
This line acts as dynamic support
during the pullback phase.
At the same time, we notice a support level where
price has struggled to break through before.
After the price breaks below both levels,
we start to prepare. This is our first
clue that the pullback might be ending.
Our confirmation comes in the form of a
retest. Price often climbs back up to touch
or slightly exceed our confluence zone.
This is a key moment where sellers who missed
the initial break get a second chance to enter.
Again, the sell signal gains strength from
the confluence of both the trendline break,
and the support-resistance flip,
occurring at the same price level.
While this pattern might look
like a reversal at first glance,
it's actually a continuation pattern.
The key is context - we're looking at a
pullback in an existing downtrend,
not a reversal of an uptrend.
The combination of breaking an ascending trendline
and a horizontal level is particularly powerful.
A diagonal break shows that the rate of
price increase is slowing and reversing.
The horizontal break shows that a significant
price level, where buyers were previously in
control, has now been overcome by sellers.
And together, they signal a significant shift
in the balance between buyers and sellers.
If you see increased volume on the break,
even better.
High volume on the
break means strong selling interest.
Lower volume on the retest, maybe
followed by higher volume as price moves
down, confirms that buyers are exhausted
and sellers are taking control .
And from here, it’s simple, you
now have a clear level for stop loss placement.
You can place it just above the confluence zone.
For profit targets, look at
the previous swing lows.
And although I trade this setup on gold market,
it has a decent win rate on other ones, especially
the crude oil market, and most blue-chip stocks.
It works because it captures a key moment in
market dynamics, using basic price action.
The complex pullback allows the downtrend
to "digest" its previous losses and transfer
positions from strong hands to weak hands.
The trendline break signals
that sellers are returning.
The retest and resistance-support flip
confirm that the market structure has changed.
Traders who bought during the pullback are now
trapped and need to sell to exit their positions.
New sellers see the resumption of the downtrend
and enter, adding further selling pressure.
Now, if you’re ready for more interesting trading
methods, go ahead and watch one of these videos!