if you are a day trader or a scalper you
definitely must try out these indicators
first one is the RSI candles this
indicator is a powerful tool that
combines the strength of the relative
strength index with candlestick
visualization first you set the up level
and down level values to 50 this means
that the indicator will use the 50 level
as the critical threshold for
determining bullish or bearish sentiment
by adjusting these levels you can focus
on the middle line of the RSI which is
often considered a significant point of
reference next we'll change the length
of the indicator to 21 by using a longer
period you smooth out the RSI
sensitivity to short-term price
fluctuations and capture a more reliable
picture of the overall
trend when the RSI value moves above 50
the indicator will paint the current
Candlestick a green color signaling a
bullish sentiment in the market this
visual queue immediately draws your
attention to potential buying
opportunities and highlights the
strength of the upward momentum on the
flip side when the RSI value dips below
the 50 level the indicator will
transform the Candlestick to a red Hue
alerting you to a bearish sentiment
taking place this color change acts as a
warning sign prompting you to consider
potential selling opportunities or to be
cautious about entering long positions
the beauty of the RSI candles indicator
lies in its Simplicity and visual appeal
rather than having to constantly monitor
the rsze numerical value you can quickly
assess the Market's Mood by observing
the color of the candlesticks a sea of
green candles suggest a strong bullish
Trend while a series of red candles
indicate a bearish environment this is
one of the best momentum indicators for
day trading and
scalping the unbalance volume is another
useful day trading tool for analyzing
the relationship between volume and
price movements by tracking the
increasing or decreasing volume obv aims
to project future price trends and
anticipate Major Market moves the obv
indicator operates on a simple principle
it increases or decreases based on
whether the closing price is higher or
lower compared to the previous day's
close if the current day's close is
higher the volume for that day is added
to the running total of obv if the
current day's close is lower the volume
is subtracted from the running total the
main assumption behind obv is that
volume movements precede price changes
in other words before a significant
price trend emerges there will often be
a noticeable shift in the volume and by
monitoring these volume changes obv can
provide early signals of potential price
moves Joseph Granville the creator of
obv emphasized the importance of volume
as the driving force behind Market
movements he believed that changes in
volume are often leading indicators of
impending price changes so this is how
you can use it for day trade in if obv
is consistently rising and is above zero
it suggests that there is a strong
accumulation and buying pressure is
building up this increasing volume trend
is often seen as a precursor to an
uptrend in price if obv is steadily
falling below zero it indicates that
there is a distribution phase with
selling pressure mounting this
decreasing volume trend is typically
interpreted as a signal that the price
is likely to enter a corresponding
downtrend Granville also proposed an
interesting concept related to obv and
price movements he theorized that if
volume begins to significantly increase
or decrease while the price remains
relatively stable it could be a sign of
imminent price explosion in other words
if there is a buildup of buying or
selling pressure without a corresponding
price move this pressure is likely to
eventually result in a sharp price move
either to the upside or downside
depending on the direction of the volume
Trend thus you can use obv to confirm
trends when obv is rising and the price
is trending upward it reinforces the
bullish sentiment and suggests that the
uptrend is likely to continue when obv
is falling and the price is trending
downward it confirms the bearish
sentiment and indicates that f price
declines may be expected one of the
strengths of obv is its ability to
identify potential imbalances between
price and volume an imbalance occurs
when the price makes a lower low but obv
makes a higher low suggesting that
despite the declining price there is
underlying buying pressure that could
lead to a price reversal another
imbalance happens when the price makes a
higher high but OB V makes a lower high
indicating that selling pressure is
building up and a price drop may be
imminent by closely monitoring the obv
indicator and its relationship to price
action you will understand market
dynamics much
better the whole moving average is a
highly responsive day trading and
scalping indicator this tool provides
the option to choose between three
different whole variations allowing you
to select the one that best best suits
your trading style and market conditions
you also have the flexibility to choose
between two visualization modes as bands
or as a single line the indicator also
offers the option to paint the
candlesticks according to the current
Trend determined by the hull moving
average I like this feature a lot
because it enhances the visual
representation of the trend making it
easier to identify bullish or bearish
Market market conditions at a glance one
of the powerful features of this
indicator is its ability to incorporate
multiple time frames into the analysis
the indicator allows you to display the
hull moving average from a higher time
frame on the current chart perfect
feature especially for scalping this
higher time frame hole moving average
acts as a reference point indicating the
overall trend Direction and potential
support or resistance levels
the whole moving average is known for
its responsiveness to price changes and
its ability to generate smooth lag-free
signals by reducing the lag typically
associated with traditional moving
averages the whole line can help you
identify Trends and potential entry or
exit points more quickly and accurately
when the price is above the whole line
and the indicator is sloping upward it
suggest a bullish trend you may consider
entering long positions or holding
existing long positions during this
phase when the price is below the whole
line and the indicator is sloping
downward it indicates a bearish trend
you may consider entering short
positions or exiting existing long
positions during this phase crossovers
between the price and the whole moving
average can signal potential Trend
changes when the price crosses above the
hole moving average it may indicate a
shift from a bearish to a bullish Trend
while a cross below it may suggest a
shift from a bullish to a bearish trend
you can use it for finding Dynamic
support and resistance levels prices
touching or bouncing off the line May
indicate potential entry or exit points
by utilizing the whole average from a
higher time frame you can enter based on
the Confluence of Trends across
different time frames and you can filter
out short-term noise and focus on the
more significant longer term Trend I
like it because this can help you avoid
getting caught up in minor price
fluctuations and maintain a clearer
perspective on the overall Market
Direction the day trading booster has
become one of my favorite indicators
this indicator provides key information
to help you navigate the market
effectively you can ad adjust various
settings based on the markets you want
to focus on and the visual
representation of the data the indicator
plots the opening price of the current
trading day or session additionally it
displays the opening range which
represents the price range during the
initial period of the trading day you
can choose to view the opening range
based on different time frames this
information helps you a lot if you like
to trade breakouts the indic Ator also
provides reference levels which are
calculated based on either the average
true range or the previous day range
these reference levels act as potential
support and resistance areas and can
help you identify key price levels to
watch during the trading day in addition
to the Daily open the day trading
booster also displays the opening prices
for the current week and month this
information allows you to assess the
broader Market Market context and
identify potential long-term support and
resistance levels the indicator also
includes the vwap another popular tool
among day Traders if you don't know the
vwap is the average price weighted by
volume helping you to determine the
overall Market sentiment and potential
price levels you even have several
anchoring options for the vop allowing
you to customize its calculation based
on your preferences
the day trading booster also features
swing pivots which are widely used by
day traders to identify potential key
areas the pivot detection will help you
spot key price levels where the market
may experience a change in direction or
a breakout these swing pivots are
subject to repaint during the first 20
candles so please read the explanations
once you apply the
indicator besides these swing pivots the
indicator also displays the price
changes and the traded volume between
two pivots this is actually
game-changing and very important
information to have the day trading
booster also includes a moving average
component allowing you to choose among
various types of moving averages to help
you identify the overall trend Direction
and potential Dynamic support and
resistance levels the indicator presents
a tabular view of the major Forex
markets opening and closing hours this
feature allows you to quickly assess
which sessions are active at any given
time and plan your trading activities
accordingly Additionally the indicator
includes a countdown timer that helps
you keep track of the remaining time
until the next session opens or closes
if you're serious about day trading this
tool is a must have on your charts so go
ahead and adjust its various settings
select and deselect the features you
don't need based on the markets you
trade and if you're still looking for a
new strategy to test go ahead and watch
one of these videos
[Music]