So in today’s video I’m gonna show you
my go-to smart money strategies, setups I
trade every day for the past 2 years.
This day trading system is designed to be
simple yet effective.
It involves using two time frames, the 30-min
chart and the 5-minute.
Location, context and market structure are
key components.
Here are the step-by-step instructions:
1.
You start by analyzing the 30 min chart.
You look for the direction of the "market
structure" which indicates whether the price
is currently bullish or bearish.
You aim to trade in the same direction as
the order flow, as it provides a general market
bias.
Trending markets are simply markets that are
continuing to break in one direction, either
creating bullish or bearish market structure.
These markets are characterized by two important
moves, the impulsive move, and the retracement
move.
It’s a basic step, but you should be able
to identify these moves almost immediately,
otherwise you will not be able to make the
correct decisions.
An impulsive move is one where the market
moves strongly or heavily in one direction,
covering a great distance in a short period
of time.
Bullish market structure is defined by a market
that is trending up and is creating Higher
Lows (HL), and Higher Highs (HH).
It typically has impulsive up moves and corrective
pull backs.
Bearish market structure is defined by a market
that is trending down and is creating Lower
Highs (LH), and Lower Lows (LL).
It typically has impulsive down moves and
corrective pull backs.
These corrections form against the trend and
they shouldn’t be traded.
You need to know when the corrective moves
ends, and when the impulsive move begins.
Your plan is to anticipate the end of the
corrective moves and the beginning of new
impulsive moves.
By using supply and demand areas.
2.
The next step is to find major supply or demand
areas near the most recent price action.
Or if you’re an ICT student, you look for
order blocks.
So a bullish trend is identified by a series
of movements where the high points exceed
previous highs.
Once identified, your goal will be to find
entry points in Demand zones (when market
is underpriced).
In those zones, buyers add to their positions
and create an imbalance moving the price high.
A bearish trend is confirmed when there are
higher lows and lower lows.
And is characterized by a series of movements
where the low points break the previous lows.
Once determined, your goal will be to find
entry points in lower highs to sell in supply
zones (when market is overpriced).
In those zones, sellers add to their positions
and create an imbalance moving the price lower.
So supply zones represent sellers while demand
zones represent buyers.
In an area of demand there is increased buying
pressure, and the price is expected to rise,
and in an area of supply there is increased
selling pressure, and the price is expected
to decrease.
The idea is to find areas on the chart where
demand overcame supply in an uptrend (for
long trades) or where supply overcame demand
in a downtrend (for short trades).
This is how you draw these zones.
For a supply zone, search the last BULLISH
candle before an important price drop.
And mark the extremes of the candle.
For a demand zone, look for the most recent
candle before an important up move.
As supply and demand traders you will be paying
very close attention to the bigger picture
trend and both the strength of the imbalances
and where in the overall trend these new imbalances
are being created.
There are 2 types of supply and demand zones:
trend continuing zones and reversal zones.
You will mainly look for trend continuing
patterns of supply and demand.
These are formed within the trend.
When the market is moving in an uptrend, price
consolidates for a certain period of time,
forms the the base and then starts to rise
upwards again where it creates an area of
demand.
So, an uptrend requires a Rally followed by
a Base followed by another Rally.
A long position should be entered when the
price comes to mitigate or revisit this area.
In a downtrend, you aim to trade when the
price falls and consolidates, creating a base,
and further breaks down and creates a supply
zone.
A short position is targeted when the price
comes to mitigate this area.
In this continuation pattern, the market doesn’t
retrace much, it pauses and enters in a minor
accumulation or distribution phase before
moving strongly in the same direction.
3.
The third step is wait for the price to retrace
and touch one of your supply or demand zones.
Once the price touches the zone, you move
to the 5-minute chart.
Here’s an important point.
The strength of the impulsive move on the
higher time frame is important when you’re
looking at these imbalances.
It's a key characteristic that can give you
useful information.
But, it's not the only thing you need to consider.
Sometimes, even if you see a very strong imbalance,
where one side (buyers or sellers) is dominating
the market, the market doesn't always react
at the supply or demand zone as you would
expect.
It's like the imbalance is completely ignored
and disappears without any significant impact.
That’s why understanding the context of
the market you're trading in can have a big
impact on your results.
Focus on markets where momentum is strong
and significant price movements, the impulses
we’ve talked before, are occurring.
These markets tend to offer better trading
opportunities.
And, the reason we moved on the lower time
frame was to find other factors of confluence.
When there is confluence, it means that multiple
factors are pointing towards the same conclusion,
reinforcing the significance of that particular
area in the market.
The more technical tools or signals that validate
a price move or confirm the importance of
a specific price level, the stronger that
level becomes.
I mainly use 3 factors of confluence:
• Ultra high volume candle
• Daily vwap rejection
• Change of character
These confluence factors adds a layer of confirmation
and increases the confidence in a trade setup.
4.
Trade only during the London or New York sessions
if you’re trading Forex, indices or crypto.
If you’re trading stocks, you trade of course
during NY session.
This is an important filter.
The London and New York sessions are known
for their high trading volume and liquidity.
Higher liquidity means there are more participants
in the market.
These sessions often experience increased
market volatility compared to other sessions.
Volatility refers to the magnitude of price
fluctuations within a period.
And higher volatility can present more trading
opportunities as prices tend to move more
rapidly, providing potential profit opportunities.
Ultra high volume candle
Let’s talk about the first confluence factor,
which is a high volume candle or an ultra
high volume candle.
I look for pin bars and engulfing bars, to
reveal market rejection.
This is the Yen Futures on the M30 time frame.
As you can see the market was trending down,
making lower lows and lower highs.
As the trend is down, we need to find a supply
zone.
I spot this possible drop-base-drop continuation
pattern, right here.
We move on to the M5 minute time frame.
Market returned to test the zone during the
London session, so this checks another condition.
Now we look for high volume candles, to find
a short entry.
I see this candle with a wick on top of it,
almost a pin bar, having high volume.
This is the VSA condition checked, our factor
of confluence indicating the selling pressure.
Our green light to go short.
Stop loss above the supply zone.
And take profit at the next major demand zones
in the market structure.
I like to take partial profits as the market
moves in my direction.
Same market.
Price made higher high and higher lows.
So we must find a demand zone.
I spot this potential Rally-Base-Rally demand
zone, right here.
Let me quickly explain how these zones are
created.
You need to understand the process.
Before the first rally, we had bank traders
placing trades in the consolidation.
They consume all of the buy orders coming
from retail traders.
The consumption of buy orders means the market
makes a small move lower, this creates the
base, which the demand zones eventually forms
off.
The move lower causes a large number of retail
traders who went long on the rally higher
to close their trades at a loss, which puts
a lot of sell orders into the market.
In addition to this, there will be a small
number of retail traders who think the move
down is a trend reversal, meaning they will
place sell trades with the expectation that
the market is going to move lower.
With two sets of retail traders placing sell
orders, the banks begin buying again knowing
they will make the market move higher, and
in the process cause anybody who sold on the
move lower to close their trades at a loss,
which ends up being the bank traders profits.
And during the buying process, the bank may
not find enough sellers and it can’t buy
all the quantities, so it will leave significant
limit orders in the same level, which is a
demand zone, and when the market returns to
test it, prices will be rejected.
Now, let’s go to the M5 time frame, for
the VSA condition.
First, price returned to our zone during the
London session.
I see 2 potential trades.
First one is this pin bar on ultra high volume.
And the second one is this large engulfing
candle on high volume.
Both of these candles were valid buy signals.
With screen time and practice, you will notice
that when the market tests the zone, there
are two possibilities:
Either price goes strongly up, because the
orders left in the zone are enough to push
the market up.
Or the market will still need time to accumulate
enough orders, so we can see a few candles
that form an accumulation phase before the
strong up move.
Stop loss below the demand zone.
And take profit at the next major supply zones
in the market structure.
One more example.
British Pound Futures, M30 time frames.
The price is making lower lows and lower highs.
So we must find a supply zone.
We are in a corrective phase.
The market was trending up, forming a small
rally.
It was followed by a very small consolidation
or a base, and then a very strong move down.
This Rally-Base-Drop supply zone represents
a footprint of financial institutions that
sold the price from that level.
So you follow the footprint and do what the
big boys are doing.
Let’s find the VSA condition on the M5 time
frame.
As you can see the market returned to test
the supply zone, but during the Tokio session.
When you encounter situations like this, it’s
better to wait for the London open, and then
find your entry.
This is important, don’t take trades outside
main market hours.
Prices were initially rejected, but the market
didn’t go down strongly.
Here’s the entry trigger.
Right at the London open.
An engulfing candle with an ultra high volume.
Stop goes above this area, or, if you want
to be conservative, above the supply zone.
Take profit at the next major demand zone,
somewhere around here.
Daily Vwap rejection is another confluence
factor you could look for.
VWAP represents an important price level,
especially in day trading, because it serves
as a reference point or benchmark.
I said it before, when banks execute large
orders, they aim to minimize the impact on
the market by executing the orders gradually
over a period of time.
The VWAP is used as the benchmark price for
this execution period.
To achieve an average price that is equal
to or better than the VWAP, banks place buy
or sell orders based on the price relative
to the VWAP.
On a day when the market is trending upward,
these algorithms will issue buy orders when
the price drops below the VWAP.
This allows them to take advantage of prices
that are below the average, potentially getting
a better deal.
On a day when the market is trending downward,
the same algorithms will issue sell orders
when the price breaks above the VWAP.
This enables them to capitalize on prices
that are above the average, potentially maximizing
their profits.
So how can we, as retail traders, take advantage
of this?
Most retail traders wait for price to cross
the main VWAP line before entering a position.
And that’s a valid strategy, I’ve used
it a lot in my trading.
But the problem is that you are entering very
late.
Often, a big part of the move already took
place and you’re joining the party too late.
That’s why lately, I’ve started taking
trades at the VWAP bands.
VWAP bands are lines above and below the VWAP
projected with multiples of the standard deviation.
I now plot the first and second set of bands,
and I try to take my trades in the area between
them.
Just look at the difference between these
2 potential buy positions.
One at the first VWAP band, and the other
one when price crossed the main VWAP line.
This entry distance is significant.
This can and will make the difference between
a good trade with a proper risk to reward
ratio and one delayed entry, with a poor trade
management.
We are trading EUR Futures.
Price is making lower lows and lower highs.
We are in a downtrend, so we must find supply
areas.
And here is Rally-Base-Drop Supply zone.
Sometimes the base or the consolidation is
not necessarily formed by multiple candles,
as you can see in this example, the market
moved up, formed a pin bar, and then moved
down strongly.
So the base was formed only by one candle,
and this happens frequently in the market.
If you find patterns like these where the
market rallies and drops surprisingly, these
setups are still considered a rally-base-drop
zones.
We move to the lower time frame, to find the
VWAP confluence.
I’ve removed the main VWAP line, and I kept
only the bands.
Look at what happened when the market returned
to test the zone, as you can see, the market
stopped moving up, but before the London session.
We even had a VSA confirmation, with this
engulfing candle on high volume.
Observe how the VWAP bands are offering dynamic
resistance, right at the supply zone.
When this happens, I wait for a pin bar or
an engulfing bar to form in this area.
Stop loss above the supply zone.
And take profit at the next demand zones in
the price structure.
Another trade.
I see an upward trend.
Higher highs and higher lows.
In a strong trending market like this one,
look for a continuation pattern that is composed
of a rally-Base-Rally: a move up followed
by a pause and then another move up.
And here it is: the Demand zone we’ve been
searching for.
The base was not quite a retracement, there
was only a small pause before another move
up.
Now it’s time to find the actual entry point
on the M5 time frame.
First, the retracement happened during the
London session, so we’re good to go if we
find a trigger.
When price retraces to test this zone, we
hope for a rejection, expecting more buy orders
from the banks in this zone.
And look at the power of the VWAP bands.
Price stopped right in the area between the
first and the second VWAP band.
Which also aligns with the demand zone.
The conservative entry is after you find a
pin bar, or an engulfing candle.
But it’s not wrong if you pull the trigger
inside this area.
I’m extra conservative, and I like a candle
confirmation, as an extra confluence.
Stop loss goes below the demand zone, and
take profit and the next supply zones.
Another entry, and maybe the most conservative
and the most delayed one is after a break
of market structure on lower time frames.
A change of character if you are an ICT student.
In simple terms, the first time a lower high
or a higher low is removed from a chart is
known as a CHoCH.
A ChoCh marks an initial shift in order flow
that can sometimes signal a short or even
long-term price reversal.
So this pattern is generally considered a
reversal one, as we’re seeing prices break
internal structure (where a minor level or
supply or demand zone fails).
A change of character should really only be
used as a confluence factor and shouldn’t
be something you rely on solely for getting
market direction.
Use it as a confirmation on the lower time
frames.
We are analyzing EURO Futures.
M30 time frame.
So price is making higher swing highs and
higher swing lows.
The plan is to find a demand zone, and trade
a CHOCH on a lower time frame.
Here’s a bonus tip to find the best demand
zones:
It’s a good sign if you see successive large
bullish candles at the beginning of the supply
zone.
Sometimes the bullish move can come from just
one single large candle.
Other times, there are a few candles appearing
one after another.
But when you see this on your charts, it’s
a clear sign of bullish pressure.
We moved to the lower time frame to find the
change of character.
In this case, we can observe a shift in market
behavior from bearish to bullish on the 5-minute
time frame.
Initially, there was a bearish structure,
but this changed when the last point of supply
failed.
Of course, this CHOCH came as a reaction from
our higher time frame demand zone.
Look at what happened when the market retraced
back to test the demand zone.
A clear rejection.
The concept here is that if price was truly
going to continue in a bearish direction,
it would have respected the last zone of supply
and continued to break through any demand
levels created during the pullback.
However, in this case, the price failed to
do so, indicating a potential shift in momentum.
Another point to consider, the CHOCH happened
outside our trading hours, but very close
to London session.
Again, please don’t rush and try to be patient,
and wait to take your trade during the active
market hours.
You can proceed with your entry in 2 ways.
You can enter right after the CHOCH appears
on the lower time frame.
And this is the risky approach.
There is a risk that price may just be sweeping
the zone before continuing in the same direction
as the previous established trend.
And this presents a danger for those who solely
rely on ChoChs, as they can produce quite
a few false signals.
To increase the accuracy of identifying high-probability
CHOCHs, you might want to use additional confluences.
And this is the second entry method.
You find another lower time frame demand zone,
because you want to buy, and take your trade
from that area if the price returns to it.
This is the conservative entry.
In our case, price indeed retraced to this
5-min demand zone, at the beginning of the
London session.
Keep in mind that if the market has momentum,
you may not get the chance for an entry after
the CHOCH.
Once you’ve identified a good quality supply
or demand zone to trade and in which you’re
expecting a reaction from, you can step down
to the 5-minute timeframe and search for entries
by looking for a change of character.
Keep in mind that sometimes looking for a
ChoCh on the 5-minute may not be enough to
justify placing an entry.
So leave volume indicator on your charts,
or the VWAP, and when things are unclear,
you can consult those tools to make a decision.
We are looking at the futures market of Aussie
dollar.
Obvious uptrend.
A bullish market characterized by rising prices
with many impulsive up moves and smaller corrective
pull backs.
I spot a continuation pattern that forms in
this uptrend, a Rally-Base-Rally demand zone.
This means a move up followed by a short accumulation
phase followed by a move up.
As usual, the plan is to go on the lower time
frame.
When price retraces to test this zone, we
expect to see a rejection, hoping for more
buy orders of other banks in this zone.
In this time frame, we can observe a shift
in price action from bearish to bullish.
Initially, there was a break of structure,
but it turned out to be nothing more than
a liquidity run, taking stops below this zone.
Price broke above the last swing high and
confirmed the change in character.
This is the textbook shift in order flow to
the upside.
One that previously had a liquidity run.
The demand rejection happened during Tokio
session, and the CHOCH happened right at the
beginning of the London session.
This is another sign than you are trading
on the correct side of the market.
It’s always nice to see immediate volatility
and market reaction when you’re entering.
Again, you can proceed with your entry in
2 ways.
The risky approach: right after the CHOCH
appears on the lower time frame.
With the risk that price may just be sweeping
the zone before continuing in the downward
direction.
Or you wait for price to retrace to a recent
demand zone, formed prior to the change of
character.
The conservative entry.
In this particular example, the retracement
never came.
Market had momentum at the beginning of the
session, and of you didn’t enter after the
CHOCH, you didn’t get the second chance
for an entry.