If I had to guess one of your biggest struggles
in trading, it would be not knowing when to
take your profit, or let the trade run to
its full potential.
You often exit a profitable trade with a small
amount, missing a huge opportunity.
And other times you leave the trade open,
just to see the price come back to your entry
level.
What if I told you I have a solution for this?
It involves using Bollinger Bands indicator,
and it will help you finding the trend in
a second and you’ll know exactly where to
set your targets and stop orders.
You know the drill, like, subscribe and stick
around for the full video.
Let’s start with the setup of your chart.
This may look weird at first.
We’ll use not one, not 2, but 3 Bollinger
Bands.
First Bollinger Band indicator will have a
period of 200 and a standard deviation of
1.
Second one will have a period of 200 and a
standard deviation of 2.
And the third one, the same 200 period and
a standard deviation of 3.
And make the middle Bollinger Band more obvious,
increase its thickness and also change its
color.
Now, the main advantage of this system is
the fact that Bollinger Bands which use standard
deviation to establish where hidden support
and resistance levels might be found.
These are also known as volatility channels.
A volatility channel plots lines above and
below a central measure of price.
These lines widen or contract depending on
how volatile or non-volatile a market is.
With this setup you’ll read the trend strength,
you’ll time your entries during trends and
during range markets and you’ll also finding
potential reversal points in a dynamic, adaptive
manner.
Determining the trend
I don’t know about you, but for me, with
this setup, the trend is pretty obvious.
In this example, I see an uptrend, but with
different phases.
When price is located between the middle line,
and the first band, we have a weak uptrend.
When the price gets within this area, there
is no strong momentum, and the price is likely
to fluctuate within a range, and may even
go below the middle line.
You can enter a buy trade in this area, but
only if you have confluence with other factors.
We’ll talk about this later.
When price is located between the first band
and the second Bollinger band, we have a strong
uptrend.
There is a higher chance that the price will
continue upward.
As long as the candles continue to close in
this buy zone, the odds favour maintaining
current long positions or even opening new
ones.
When price is located between the second band
and the third Bollinger band above the middle
line, we have a very strong uptrend.
Price is overextended and I would avoid buying
if price goes outside the bands.
In this area, if you are experienced, you
could look for divergences, to find reversals
signals.
Again, we’ll talk about this later.
And here’s a downtrend.
Price is below the middle line, between the
200 EMA, and the first band.
This is a weak downtrend.
There is no strong momentum, yet, and the
price is likely to fluctuate within a range.
When price is located between the first band
and the second Bollinger band, below the 200
EMA, we have a strong downtrend.
There is a higher chance that the price will
continue downward.
When price is located between the second band
and the third Bollinger band, we have a very
strong downtrend.
You see how this set of 3 bands will give
a better insight into a trend.
You don’t just say, it’s a downtrend.
You evaluate the volatility and the price
location and you know the strength of the
trend, which is more powerful.
Confluence entries
Now you know the strength of a trend.
How and when do you enter?
As always, I rely on confluence.
The term confluence refers to the overlap
of two or more key levels or areas of value.
These can be trend lines, horizontal levels,
and even other channels.
Let’s use simple support and resistance
levels.
Looking for overlaps of key levels with Bollinger
Band is an excellent way to find high probability
setups.
These areas of confluence tend to attract
more buyers or sellers, resulting in a reversal
or a continuation of the current trend.
With this confluence you are basically finding
pullbacks in a strong trend.
When a market is in an uptrend, meaning price
is above the middle Bollinger band, and you
find a confluence between a recent support
or resistance level and one of the standard
deviation bands, you can trade a bounce of
that area.
On the other hand, when price is in a downtrend,
below the middle band, and a recent support
or resistance aligns with one of the lower
volatility bands, a decent pullback trade
may be on the cards.
Here’s EURJPY.
Before finding the confluence trade, just
look how price was respecting the bands, almost
religiously.
Even when price was below the middle band,
it found support at the lower bands.
This alone makes this system a very powerful
one.
Now look here.
Price broke above the middle band and also
broke this resistance level.
Which now will potentially act as a support.
Here’s our value area.
The first band above the middle line and this
level are aligning on the same point.
So a buy trade, in the strong trend area,
is a decent trend continuation opportunity.
And look how easy is to find profit targets.
You just aim for the next bands.
The first take profit is at the second band.
And the next target is the last band.
Always expect a momentum loss when price reaches
the next set of bands.
Always take a part of your profit at these
levels, so you don’t give it back to the
market if price finds resistance and reverses.
In this chart, price broke below the middle
band, enter a weak trend phase, and then also
broke this support level.
Then it targeted the second band, retraced,
found resistance once again at the first band,
and then went for the third band.
Look how powerful this setup is.
Price stopped right at the third band.
Then it retraced back up.
Here’s our value area.
The first band below the middle line and this
previous breakout level are aligning on the
same area.
So there’s a potential sell trade, in the
strong trend area.
You can enter right after the price touches
the band, or you can wait for a rejection
signal, maybe an engulfing candle or a pin
bar.
It’s up to you.
And you just aim for the next bands.
The first take profit is at the second band
below the middle line.
And the next target is the last band.
So I said previously that you can also take
a trade in the weak buy or sell area.
You can do this, if you can find a confluence.
And this may even offer you a higher risk
to reward ratio.
Look right here.
We had a transition for a strong uptrend to
a downtrend.
Price patiently found support at each of the
previous band, and now is returning to the
middle line.
But this area is an important one.
I see a supply zone right here, which aligns
with the middle line.
Yes, you can incorporate this setup into supply
and demand trading.
Let me know if you want a future video about
this.
If you are a classic support and resistance
trader, you have this breakout zone here,
a former support, know potentially acting
as resistance.
So, a sell trade in this area is worth risking.
First band below the middle line is the first
take profit area.
The second band is next area.
And finally the third band.
And please, don’t wait until the third band
is reached to exit.
Take partial profits at each band, and be
conservative.
Heikin ashi
Heikin ashi candles work very well in combination
with this setup and will make your trading
a lot easier.
Heikin Ashi shows the average price movements,
creating a smoother appearance, which helps
to identify market momentum more easily.
You have the trend with the help of Bollinger
Bands, and know you add the momentum aspect,
using Heikin Ashi candles.
If you don’t like candlesticks that may
flip-flop constantly from a green bar to a
red bar to a green bar, maybe you should try
Heikin Ashi charts, because they tend to have
longer stretches of green and red bars.
When the market is above the middle Bollinger
line, look for Heikin-Ashi candlesticks that
have big bodies and long upper shadows, but
no lower shadow.
When the market is below the middle Bollinger
line, look for Heikin-Ashi candlesticks that
have big bodies and long lower shadows, but
no upper shadow.
What I like about them is the fact that small
corrections and consolidations are somewhat
left behind and they are barely visible on
the chart.
You will also notice that when the direction
changes on a Heikin-Ashi, the price will most
likely go to the next set of bands.
Also, the market noise is filtered, so maybe
there’s a less chance you’ll be distracted
from choppy price action.
And again, you look for support and resistance
levels and important swing points, to find
confluence levels.
Divergence trading
If you want to catch reversals, you could
trade divergences, after price spends a lot
of time in the very strong trend territory,
between the second and the third band of the
setup.
A divergence is an event that is associated
with increased levels of volatility.
I’ve added the MACD histogram, to easily
spot points of inconsistency between price
and indicator.
A bearish divergence is when the market makes
a higher high, but the MACD shows a lower
high (which is a sign of weakness).
A bullish divergence is when the market makes
a lower low, but the oscillator shows a higher
low (and this is a sign of strength).
You want the signal to appear when price is
near the outer limits of the bands.
And here’s the trick.
When you find a divergence, you don’t enter
at the third band.
You enter at the second one.
This is a riskier trade, against the trend,
and you know that price likes to rest at the
Bollinger bands, before continuing its move.
So you wait for a movement at the second band,
then you target the first band, and the middle
band as the final target.
But most of the times, you’ll have a decent
win rate if you just target the second band.
Here’s Bitcoin.
We see a price move outside the bands, while
the MACD indicated a bearish divergence.
This suggests weakness and a potential reversal
to at least the first band, and maybe even
the middle Bollinger Band.
Very important: always wait for a trendline
breakout before entering into a divergence
trade.
This will filter a lot of fake divergences.
You want to enter after a trendline breakout,
somewhere around the second Bollinger band,
with a stop loss above the third band.
Again: this is a riskier trade, so if it’s
not your style, stick to trend continuation
setups.
Now, if you want to learn more about finding
the best confluence signals, make sure you
watch this video here.
It contains many tips and tricks, you could
add to your arsenal.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!