Have a look at this Heikin ashi chart.
We have an aggressive down move, then a quick
reversal to the upside.
But, there’s a specific price action signal,
during this period, which revealed sellers
were no longer in control.
Can you spot it?
It’s right in the middle.
3 consecutive lower wicks which revealed bullish
pressure, around this price level.
This is one of the best ways to anticipate
a change in momentum, with a low risk, a potential
high reward.
Let’s talk about it.
You know the drill, like, subscribe, and stick
around for the full video.
Buying/selling pressure zones
Candlesticks wicks can tell you a lot about
the psychology of market participants and
it definitely must play an important role
in your price action analysis.
In a Heikin-Ashi chart, large wicks can indicate
a high level of volatility or uncertainty
in the market.
For example, if the high and low prices for
a particular time frame are significantly
different from the open and close prices,
it may indicate that there was a lot of buying
and selling activity during that period.
This could be a sign that the market is indecisive
or that there is a lack of clear direction.
On the other hand, if the wicks are small
or absent, it may indicate that the market
is more stable.
A series of candlesticks with long wicks on
a Heikin Ashi chart is something you should
paying attention to, because this can potentially
indicate a change in trend.
So the plan is to look for periods when momentum
is fading away, and a potential trend change
is on the way.
In a Heikin-Ashi chart, trend changes can
be identified by looking at the shape, size
and direction of the candlesticks.
For example, in this chart we are in in an
uptrend, but the candlesticks start to become
smaller and more evenly sized.
This may indicate that the uptrend is losing
momentum and a trend change is imminent.
The same here, the market was in a downtrend
and the candlesticks started to become smaller
and more uneven, and this is the first sign
that the downtrend is losing strength and
a trend change is coming.
Consecutive candle wicks during this period
reveals bullish or bearish pressure.
Now, a strong Heikin Ashi pressure zone is
not defined just by one candle with a big
wick.
A single price bar might not be sufficiently
reliable for a trading setup.
To filter false signals, you must identify
a group of candlesticks.
Therefore, instead of a single Heikin Ashi
candle, look for at least 2 consecutive bars
with overlapping upper or lower shadows, more
even better.
Remember, wicks indicate potential buying
or selling pressure.
When these shadows overlap, they create a
price zone that is more likely to exhibit
the buying or selling pressure you anticipate.
Here’s a bullish pressure zone.
1.
We have 3 consecutive Heikin ashi bars with
overlapping lower shadows.
2.
We mark the zone, by outlining the lowest
low and the highest closing price
3.
This area is the bullish Pressure Zone
Now, very important.
Small shadows can create unreliable pressure
zones.
The wicks of these candles must be somewhat
larger in size.
I mean I wouldn’t say this is a strong buying
zone, the wicks are too small.
This one is more significant.
And here’s a bearish pressure zone.
1.
We have minimum 3 consecutive Heikin ashi
bars with overlapping upper shadows.
2.
We outline the highest high and the lowest
closing price within this sequence
3.
This area is the bearish Pressure Zone
It is also important to note that these consecutive
wicks in Heikin Ashi charts should not be
used in isolation.
It is always a good idea to use multiple tools
and indicators, and to carefully consider
the overall market context, when trying to
identify the potential trend reversals or
changes in market sentiment.
Support/resistance confluence
So instead of taking signals and trades all
over the place, the better trades usually
happen at key price levels, and are followed
by an opposite color candle.
Here’s the bullish Pressure Zone.
These consecutive Heikin Ashi wicks, indicate
sellers are losing their strength.
On its own, this zone is not relevant.
But it appeared at an area of previous resistance,
which turned into support.
And this is important.
These candles where followed by a green Heikin
ashi one, which also has a lower wick.
This is a weak buy signal.
The strongest signals appear when a green
candle with no lower wick appears.
A good entry area is after you have the first
green Heikin ashi candle, rejecting the bullish
pressure zone.
Stop loss placement is obvious, below the
zone and you target double the amount you’ve
risked.
Here’s Pound dollar, on the hourly time
frame, with several bullish and bearish pressure
zones.
First one is bullish zone, right here.
3 consecutive candles with lower wicks, followed
by a green candle.
This is a weak signal, because the signal
didn’t appear at a clear support level.
The second signal was here.
A bearish pressure zone, which was located
around the same area.
A previous support turned into resistance,
and multiple Heikin ashi wicks.
We have a short trade signal when a red HA
candle forms.
Stop goes above the pressure zone and as usual,
you go for a risk to reward ratio of 2.
And I see another bullish zone, again, around
the same area.
Previous resistance turned once again in support,
consecutive long wicks, so this was a good
opportunity to buy when a green Heikin ashi
formed.
We even had a green candle with no lower wick,
which is the strongest signal.
Again, stop loss below the zone, and you go
for a risk to reward ratio of 2.
Now, as a side note, you decide how you want
to manage your trade.
I recommend to wait for the trade to unfold.
But, if you want to minimize risk, when the
Heiken ashi candles change color, you may
also decide to move your stop to breakeven,
or you may even decide to close 50% of your
the trade manually if a red candle with no
upper wick appears.
There is no best way to manage your trade.
In some cases, it’s better not to close
the trade when an opposite candle appear.
In other cases, this action will preserve
your profit.
VWAP confluence
One of my favorite ways to trade bullish and
bearish Heikin ashi zones is with weekly VWAP.
Not many traders are using the weekly VWAP.
They don’t even know it’s possible to
add it on their charts.
But this is one of the most reliable tools,
offering dynamic support and resistance.
VWAP line that acts as a support if the price
is trading above it and as a resistance if
the price is trading below.
The advantage of this strategy is that it
places less emphasis on the length of a single
shadow and instead focuses on multiple shadows.
You want to find bullish pressure zones, above
the weekly VWAP and bearish pressure zones
below it.
In this example, I see a very good signal.
First, as price is trading above the weekly
VWAP, you need to find a buy zone.
Which is right here.
Multiple red Heikin ashi candles with lower
wicks, right at the VWAP line.
And as another layer of confluence, I also
see this support or demand zone, right here.
Stop below the VWAP and below the multiple
wicks.
And you take the profit at the next major
resistance level.
We trade GBP/JPY, on the M15 time frame.
Price is below the weekly VWAP, so the plan
is short the currency pair at a bearish pressure
zone.
Which is here, a tripe wick zone, right below
the VWAP line.
This area is an important one because I also
see a support zone, turning into resistance.
Multiple layers of confluence around the same
area.
So, we found our value zone.
The next red candle after the pressure zone
is our trigger to place a short position.
Stop loss above the wicks and take profit
at next swing low in the price structure.
Now, I suspect our entry level also aligns
with a Fibonacci level.
Just as I thought!
It was the 50% Fib retracement.
Another layer of confluence.
Psychological numbers
Heikin Ashi pressure zones work extremely
well in combination with psychological numbers.
Have you ever wondered why prices tend to
stall at certain levels in the market?
Is this just a coincidence or is there a valid
reason behind this happening?
Well, this phenomenon may actually be explained
based on the psychology of traders.
As humans, we tend to think in terms of whole,
round numbers rather than in terms of uneven
random numbers.
Psychological numbers, also known as "round
numbers," are numbers that end in zero, such
as 50 or 100.
These levels go under the radar of many traders,
but these are very important in trading because
they are often used as reference points.
Traders are more likely to take action when
prices reach these levels.
They are more likely to place orders or set
limits at round numbers, which can create
additional demand or supply at these levels.
In this chart, I see a bullish pressure zone.
3 red Heikin ashi candles, with lower wicks,
forming at a round number.
We even have a support level in this area.
This is a good opportunity to place a buy
trade.
This strategy is quite versatile and you can
trade on any time frame.
I must say, I prefer it on higher time frames.
By looking at higher time frames, you can
get a sense of the overall direction of the
market with the help of Heikin Ashi and at
the same time, you identify pressure zones
that may not be visible on shorter time frames.
One of the main benefits of using higher time
frames for finding pressure zones is that
they can help you filter out the short-term
noise.
For example, here we are looking at the H4
time frame, First, we see fewer price fluctuations
compared to someone looking at a 5-minute
chart, and is easier to identify major support
and resistance levels.
Consecutive wicks on lower time frames are
quite common, it happens all the time.
But on higher time frames, it has more relevance.
And on higher time frames, psychological numbers
are more obvious.
Usually the more zeroes at the end of the
price, the stronger the psychological level.
In this chart, we have a perfect, text book
example.
3 consecutive wicks forming our bullish pressure
zone, appearing at a major round number, 200.
I will take this buy trade every time I’ll
see it.
As you can see, the location of the pressure
zones in the market is probably the most important
factor to consider when trading, as it can
provide context and will help you determine
the likelihood of the signal being accurate.
For example, a bullish pressure zone that
occurs at a key support level is more reliable
than a zone that forms at a resistance level,
because the support level suggests that there
may be greater demand at that price.
The location of the pressure zone can also
be important in the context of trend analysis.
A buy zone that occurs during an uptrend is
more reliable than one that occurs during
a downtrend, as it is in line with the overall
direction of the market.
Follow these rules, find the zones on a higher
time frame, and you’ll see you’ll have
stronger and more reliable signals.
Now, this strategy works perfect in combination
with supply and demand levels.
If you want to learn to trade them on Heikin
Ashi charts, and not on classic candlestick
charts, you definitely must watch this video.
And also check out our academy program, if
you want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!