There is no feeling more depressing than getting
stopped out of a trade, only to see the market
taking off in your direction immediately after
your stop gets triggered.
And it makes you wonder whether you are simply
a victim of bad luck, or whether something
else is happening within the markets you trade.
Today it’s all about smart money manipulation,
and I’ll reveal how big players are seducing
you to press the buy or sell button, to their
advantage.
So, if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
Smart Money can see the balance of supply
and demand far better than anyone else can
Many new traders are surprised to learn that
the markets can be manipulated in many ways.
There are all sorts of professional interests
in financial markets: brokers, dealers, banks,
trading syndicates.
But the main price movements are funneled
down to a limited number of major players
known as market-makers, or the ‘smart money’
or ‘professional money’.
These traders are the one that create a market.
They are able to see all the buy and sell
orders as they arrive.
They may also be filling large blocks of buy
or sell orders (with special trading techniques
to prevent putting the price up against themselves
or their clients).
These traders have the significant advantage
of being able to see all the stop-loss orders
on their screens.
They are also aware of ‘inside information’.
Despite ‘insider dealing’ being illegal,
let’s face it, privileged information is
used all the time in different ways to make
huge sums of money.
So to say it simply, smart money can see the
balance of supply and demand far better than
anyone else can.
Smart Money trading activity is shown in the
volume and the price spread
Professionals trade in many different ways,
ranging from scalping to the long-term accumulation
and distribution of prices.
The result of smart money trading activity
is shown in the volume and the price spread.
The volume is telling you how much trading
activity there has been.
The spread or price action is telling you
the position the professional money are happy
with on this activity (which is why the price
spread is so important).
However, you do need to recognize that smart
money can do a number of things to enhance
their trading positions, like gapping up or
gapping down stocks for example, shake-outs,
testing and up-thrusts.
These are moneymaking strategies helping the
smart money to trade successfully, at your
expense.
Smart Money have to keep their activities
as secret as possible
Market-makers can see windows of opportunity
better than most other traders.
Good or bad news is an opportunity.
You, as retail trader, hear little of these
activities.
The last thing smart money want is for you
or anybody else to know that a stock is under
accumulation or distribution, for example.
They have to keep their activities as secret
as possible.
Smart money have been known to go to the extremes,
producing false rumors (which is far more
common than you would perhaps believe), as
well as actively selling a stock in the open,
but secretly buying it all back, and more,
through other ways.
For example, when the Smart Money are expecting
higher prices, they want to catch all the
stops before moving the price up.
If they expect the price to go up, of course,
they want to buy at the best possible price.
Or when you’re looking at great earnings
reports and fundamentals for a stock, which
would create public expectation of higher
prices, and then you witness a drop in the
stock’s price, again, this is a common smart
money practice.
Top professional traders understand how to
read the interrelationship between volume
and price action.
From a practical point of view, professional
money consists of a mass of trades, which
if large enough, will change the trend of
the market.
However, this takes time.
Their lack of participation is always as important
as their active participation.
When these traders are not interested in any
up-move, you will see low volume, which is
known as ‘no demand‘.
This is a sure sign that the rally will not
last long.
Remember, it is the activity of the professional
traders that causes noticeable changes in
volume – not the activity of retail traders,
such as you or me.
Smart Money will use good or bad news to enhance
their trading position and to capitalize on
known human weaknesses
Smart Money understands human psychology.
They know that most traders are controlled
in varying degrees by 2 main FEARS: the fear
of missing out and the fear of losses.
Frequently, they will use good or bad news
to enhance their trading position and to capitalize
on known human weaknesses.
If the news is bad and if, at that moment,
it is to their advantage, the market can be
marked down rapidly by the market-makers.
The result?
Weak buyers are liable to be shaken out at
lower prices (this is very effective if the
news appears to be really bad).
Stop-loss orders can be triggered, allowing
the stock to be bought at lower prices.
At the same time, many traders who shorted
the market on the bad news, can be locked-in
by a rapid recovery.
Then those traders have to cover their position,
they are practically forced to buy, helping
the professional money, which has been long
all the time.
The main thing smart money want to hide from
you is not the price, but the VOLUME
you is not the price, but the VOLUME.
Seeing the price will give you either fear
or hope, but knowing the volume will give
you the facts.
Markets may differ in some details but all
free markets around the world work the same
way.
The more liquid or heavily traded a market
is, the more difficult it will be to manipulate.
Market-makers cannot just mark the price up
or down at will, as this is only possible
in a thinly traded market.
You will frequently see market manipulation
and you must expect it.
But, smart money need some windows of opportunity;
like a temporary thinning out of trading orders
on their books, or taking full advantage of
news items (good or bad).
'Smart Money' knows how you will act as an
investor or trader
Whether we admit it or not, human beings are
conditioned to act as a herd and the media
play a key role in helping investors and traders
form an opinion about traded instruments such
as stocks, futures, Forex or crypto.
When media-induced opinions about traded instruments
are wrong, and the “uninformed Herd” believe
them, it will cost them dearly.
Because 'Smart Money' know how you will act
as an investor or trader.
They know how to steer you.
They know that the two most powerful human
emotions are greed and fear, and those emotions
are our worst enemies when it comes to making
investment or trading decisions.
You may also wonder, are the smart money evil
beings intent on stealing your money?
Of course not.
These are clever institutions who understand
human nature and market structure.
They view their activity as a game, and have
acquired the knowledge and the skills required
to win.
They simply take advantage of opportunities
that arise in certain situations.
They have the financial supremacy and understanding
of the financial markets.
They have an edge over the retail investor
or trader, and they use this to their advantage
to make profits.
Volume Spread Analysis is the retail trader’s
weapon against Smart Money
At this point you may be thinking, "Why is
this relevant to making money trading?
Why can't you just show a strategy"?
The answer is volume spread analysis.
But before you learn VSA, it's vital and important
to know this information, because in order
to win the game, you must first accept it
exists and understand it.
I did not initially accept this as reality
when I first started trading, but as I began
to examine the markets closely, I noticed
consistent patterns.
And you know the patterns.
You see a strong support level, maybe even
a confluence area with a moving average or
a round number, you buy expecting the price
to go up, then the market drops below support,
takes your stop loss, and then it shoots back
up, maybe hitting your initial target.
It happens all the time.
And you blame your broker.
Yes, if you are using a broker from a dubious
country and you experience abnormal price
movements or strange spread increase, then
yes, that broker has some shady practices.
But it is NOT your broker that is hunting
your stop.
Smart money are involved because they need
your stop to make money.
Stop loss orders represent liquidity in the
markets.
And the big players need liquidity.
Those big players cannot just enter a trade
at once, but they slowly have to build a position
by “hunting for liquidity”.
And stop loss orders in the markets are the
best way to get liquidity.
Smart Money seduce retail traders to take
trades in the wrong direction
Here are 2 common trading myths:
The more obvious a support or level is, the
stronger and more reliable the signals around
it.
Or, put your buy order right at the support
level and your stop right below it.
Those are just a few examples of things that
you read in most trading books.
And I probably said that in the past in my
older videos.
However, think about this for a moment…If
everyone wants to buy at a certain price,
who are they going to buy it from?
You need a seller for every buyer.
If the smart want to buy a certain support
level but expect the mass of other traders
wanting to do the same, they’ll have to
find ways to get traders on the other sides
of their trades.
What smart money wants to do is to seduce
traders to take trades in the wrong direction.
It’s a very simple thing to do and you have
noticed it before as well, probably without
being aware of it.
Again, let’s say you want to buy a support
level after a price drop.
The price rarely stops right at that level.
Only in trading books.
In reality, you’ll see the price going through
the level.
It looks like the level isn’t holding and
the price is breaking out.
This scenario is ideal for smart money.
First, those traders who have impatiently
bought a potential bounce off support see
the price heading for their stops (which are
essentially sell orders).
And second, other traders are now looking
to sell the breakout.
Those retail traders are now selling to the
smart money who are happily buying at a very
good price, below support.
And now prices will rise and will take out
the stops from the traders who sold the fake
breakout – which is accelerating the bullish
move even more.
The traders who are left with profits are
smart money.
The frustrating part for us, retail traders,
is that our initial idea of buying support
was correct.
But at the end of the day, we lost money.
Smart Money Are Triggering Your Greed and
Fear
Let’s say the price is currently at 58 dollars
and keeps falling towards the very important
support level at 50 where you, and probably
90% of all other traders, want to buy.
Very often you’ll then see a reaction ahead
of the level.
When price starts consolidating at 52 dollars
and starts moving up a few pips, the impatient
retail traders will get very nervous and fear
that price has already found support and will
take off without them.
We, retail traders, are a very greedy bunch
of individuals and we hate it when price misses
our orders.
Smart Money of course knows this and will
use it to their advantage.
They once again seduce the amateur traders
to pull the trigger early and take a long
trade even if the price hasn’t come to the
actual support level yet.
And you know what happens next, the smart
money can now drive price further down, generating
panic among the long positioned traders and
then buy back from them when they exit their
trades because they think the price is breaking
down.
Is Market Manipulation a good thing or a bad
thing?
So you may be asking, “Is Market Manipulation
a good thing or a bad thing?”
I feel that if you can learn to read a chart
correctly using Volume Spread Analysis, you’ll
discover some of the intentions of the smart
money, thus trading in harmony with what’s
happening.
I mean, wouldn't you do the same - buy at
the lowest price knowing you could sell it
later for much more than what you bought it
for?
That's the trading game: buy low, sell high.
But first, you must learn how to avoid becoming
the victim of market manipulation.
You need to know how the big players think
and trade.
You must align yourself with the big players
and join them.
If this make sense, make sure you watch our
smart money playlist.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.