Building trading bots and indicators used
to be for tech geniuses. Well, not anymore!
I have zero coding experience
and I’m creating my OWN trading
bots in TradingView… in just a few minutes!
So today I want to help you create and optimize
your own indicators and strategies in Tradingview,
using AI, without any experience in programming!
THIS is the ultimate shortcut to smarter trading!
So let me walk you through the
entire process step by step.
I’m using Claude AI on Poe app,
but you can use any AI model you like.
I sometimes switch to Deepseek or O1
models when I get several errors in a
row, but the process remains the same.
Let’s start with the most critical
part: crafting the starting prompt.
Your trading bot's capabilities depend entirely
on how well you structure these instructions!
So first let's create a prompt that
turns your AI into a trading agent.
Use this prompt: “I want you to be my trading
assistant. You're an expert in trading and coding,
especially Pine Script 6 for TradingView. You
can create any indicator or strategy I need,
with clean code and few errors.”
Ok, now let's make your assistant
even smarter by feeding it more information
about your specific trading preferences. This
step is crucial for making the AI truly yours.
Tell your bot about your preferred markets:
do you prefer trading stocks, forex, crypto?
Tell your bot about your typical timeframes: do
you enjoy scalping, day trading or swing trading?
You’ll also mention your risk tolerance, your
trading style, like trend following or breakouts.
For instance, you might say: "I primarily swing
trade stocks using price action methods
on 4 hour charts. I prefer to use minimal
indicators and focus on market structure."
The more context you provide, the more
tailored the advice becomes.
After creating your assistant,
it's time to see if it works as expected.
Let’s start with something easy. I use exponential
moving averages a lot in my trading, and I want to
ask my AI assistant to help me color-code an EMA.
I want it green when price is above
it, and red when price is below it.
We'll ask it to modify the basic EMA code
to change colors based on price position.
Now we'll copy the standard EMA code from
TradingView and paste it into our chat.
Then we’ll wait for the assistant to do its magic.
Nothing groundbreaking yet, we're just making that
information more visible.
Okey, we’ve got our code.
Now let’s implement it in TradingView.
You open your TradingView chart and look for the
Pine Editor button at the bottom of your screen.
Click it to open the coding interface. When the
editor opens, you'll see a blank
canvas or some template code.
You just click on "New" and select
"Indicator" from the dropdown menu.
This creates a fresh Pine Script file.
Don’t forget to delete any template code,
then paste the code your AI assistant provided.
Then give your script a name and save it.
Next, you press "Add to Chart"
to see your creation in action.
If there are no errors, your
indicator will appear on your chart.
If there are errors, and you will encounter
them, just copy them or make a print screen,
and ask the assistant to fix the errors
and rewrite the entire code again.
So this indicator seems to work as
intended. The visual feedback is instant.
When candles close above the EMA,
the line turns green. When price
dips below, it immediately switches to red.
Let’s check if this works on any timeframe.
It does, so this works as expected.
Now let's continue with something
practical involving pivot points.
Pivot points are powerful tools, but sometimes
I want them to be calculated on lower timeframes.
So I want to ask my AI assistant to modify the
pivot point indicator, to show
hourly pivot levels, since daily
is the lowest timeframe available by default.
Fun fact, ten years ago, I paid a programmer
$200 to code this exact indicator for me.
So, we'll ask our AI assistant to modify
the standard pivot point indicator code,
to calculate pivots on an hourly timeframe.
This should be a simple change
in the timeframe reference.
So we'll copy the pivot point code from
TradingView and paste it into our chat.
The classic pivot point calculation shows
daily support and resistance levels, that help
identify price combinations quickly and easily.
But I want them displayed on an hourly basis.
I want pivot points to confirm
intraday bias in the markets.
I like to compare the current trading
day's central pivot with the previous
day's to establish bias, and then confirm
that bias based on where price opens.
Having this on an hourly timeframe will
give me more granular entry opportunities.
Ok, the modified code came back quickly.
Now let's head over to TradingView,
and open the Pine Editor.
Again, we'll clear out the
default code and paste in the modified
pivot point script from my assistant.
We can immediately see the
hourly pivot points appear.
Each horizontal line represents a key
support or resistance level, calculated
from the previous hour's levels.
The indicator works beautifully,
showing clear pivot points that
align perfectly with price reactions.
I can use these pivot levels alongside
other tools for confirmation.
Also, when you make your own tools,
don’t forget to check if they work
on different symbols and timeframes.
Testing it on various charts confirms
it's working perfectly across the board.
Honestly, I'm amazed at how much things
have changed. In the past, getting this kind
of custom indicator made would have cost me
$200, required many back-and-forth emails
and taken a full two weeks to complete.
But today? The entire process took less
than 3 minutes from start to finish!
Now, let's create a more complex indicator. I
want a tool that highlights engulfing candles,
with their volume higher
than the previous 5 candles.
Engulfing candlestick patterns are powerful
signals, especially when confirmed by volume.
They occur when a larger candle
completely engulfs the previous candle.
When combined with volume analysis, these
patterns become even more significant.
I'll ask my AI assistant to
create a custom indicator
for these high-volume engulfing patterns.
This should be straightforward since we just
need to check two main conditions: the engulfing
pattern formation and the volume comparison.
First, let's define what
makes an engulfing pattern.
For a bullish engulfing, the current candle
must be green and its body must completely
engulf the previous red candle's body.
For a bearish engulfing, the current candle
must be red and its body must completely
engulf the previous green candle's body.
The wide spread of these engulfing candles
sends a clear signal with one message: sentiment
is STRONG, either bullishly or bearishly.
So we'll ask our assistant to write code that
identifies these patterns and checks if the
volume is higher than the previous 5 candles.
This is a key condition. Volume is crucial
because it validates the price action. If we
see a large engulfing candle but the volume
is below average, it's a warning signal.
Only when volume rises with the price pattern,
it shows real market strength or weakness.
Ok, the assistant has finished the
code so let's head over to TradingView.
We'll clear out any default code
and paste in our new indicator.
Now let’s see the indicator in action.
Ok, so the indicator works by placing colored
markers on candles that meet our criteria.
Looking at some examples on the chart,
we can see how these high-volume patterns
often mark significant turning points,
or continuation signals.
Testing on different
timeframes shows the indicator works
well across various chart settings.
One interesting pattern I'm noticing is that
many of the bearish engulfing candles with high
volume appear at resistance levels, while bullish
engulfing candles with high volume often appear
at support. This aligns with what we know about
volume profile analysis – it takes effort for the
market to move away from established levels,
and this effort shows up as increased volume.
I could also look for additional confirmation,
like adding a moving average or another
indicator. But the main condition,
price action and volume, is in place.
So I will save this indicator because
will be particularly useful for spotting potential
continuation and reversals after a strong move.
When combined with support/resistance
levels and other volume profile analysis,
it becomes a powerful edge for
entering trades with conviction.
Now let’s increase the difficulty notch!
Let's create a momentum indicator that
measures the strength of price
action over the last X candles.
This indicator will count recent bars
and measure the body of bullish candles,
versus bearish candles, giving us a clear
picture of which side is winning the battle.
The body of a candle tells us about
strength - a long body shows strong
commitment from either buyers or sellers.
When consecutive bodies become larger,
it shows increasing momentum, while
smaller bodies indicate slowing momentum.
That's exactly what our indicator will track.
I'll ask the assistant to write a custom indicator
that adds up the body sizes of bullish and
bearish candles over a look back period.
This will give us a momentum
score for each side of the market.
The size of these bodies matters greatly.
Remember that in every bar, the same
number of contracts or shares are traded.
The only reason a bar ends with a higher
price is that buyers were more committed
and aggressive than sellers. The reverse
is true for bearish candles.
So the body size directly
reflects the strength behind the move.
That’s why I want the indicator to loop through
the last X candles, to measure each body size, and
to add them to either a bullish or bearish total.
We have the code, now let's head to
TradingView and paste our new indicator.
No errors when we add it to chart!
We can see three lines appear - one
for bullish momentum, one for bearish
momentum, and one showing the ratio.
Let’s hide the ratio for now, and
let’s focus on the main lines.
Looking at the chart with our new indicator,
we can spot some interesting patterns.
When the bullish line rises sharply while
the bearish line remains flat, we see price
making strong upward moves. This aligns with
a well know candlestick analysis principle:
a wide body represents strong market sentiment.
This tool works well with the concept of
consecutive candles increasing
or decreasing in size.
When we see the momentum lines diverging, meaning
bullish line rising while bearish line falling,
it often corresponds to consecutive candles
getting larger in the direction of the trend.
This pattern frequently appears
at the start of strong moves.
If the bullish line starts to
flatten after a strong rise,
it suggests buyers are losing control -
an early warning of a potential reversal.
When the bearish line flattens after a decline,
it signals sellers may be losing control.
Volume validates price action, so as a next step
we might enhance this indicator by factoring
in volume. But even in its current form, it
provides valuable insight into market momentum.
I like using it on the 4-hour time frame
and I must say, this is pretty accurate.
Perfect to identify when momentum is slowing or
rising. I can predict the next 4-hour candle with
a pretty high accuracy using it.
You may find this useless,
but for me, this indicator is amazing.
By measuring the relative strength of buyers
versus sellers over the last several candles,
this little tool helps me "read the momentum",
based on actual price action.
Now let’s create a trading strategy
using the indicator we just built.
The rules are simple: enter long
when bullish strength crosses above bearish
strength, and price is above the 100 SMA.
Enter short when bearish strength crosses above
bullish strength and price is below the 100 SMA.
The strategy logic is to check for
crossovers between the bullish and
bearish strength lines, while confirming
the price position relative to the 100 SMA.
When all conditions align, the
strategy enters a position.
When I first ran the code, I got an error.
This happens often when building strategies,
so I just copied the error message
and asked the assistant to fix it.
We went back and forth a few times,
fixing bugs and refining the logic.
One issue was with the crossover detection -
we needed to make sure we were only entering
on the bar where the crossover happened, at
the candle close, not in the middle of it.
After a few iterations, we had working code. I
pasted it into TradingView's and ran a backtest.
I checked if the strategy was taking
trades at exactly the right moments,
as intended - entering longs when bullish
candles started overpowering bearish
ones, above the 100 SMA, and shorts when
bearish candles dominated below the 100 SMA.
The backtest results were promising. The strategy
showed positive returns and a decent win rate.
The best results were on the 30 minutes
time frame, with the 200 SMA as a filter,
and the indicator measuring the
strength of the last 10 candles.
This makes sense because we're essentially
trading with the more dominant market force,
while also respecting the overall
trend direction with the SMA filter.
Then I asked the assistant to assess the backtest
results. And it noted that the strategy was
profitable but had a relatively low Sharpe ratio.
The Sharpe ratio measures return relative to risk,
so this suggested our returns
weren't quite high enough,
compared to the volatility we were experiencing.
The Sortino ratio, however, was relatively high.
This is important because the Sortino
ratio focuses specifically on downside
risk - the bad volatility that hurts
us - rather than all volatility.
A high Sortino ratio means our strategy is making
money, while controlling drawdowns effectively.
Of course, I can go deeper with the
adjustments, but you get the point!
The assistant suggested we might
improve performance by refining entry
and exit conditions or adjusting position sizing.
One specific recommendation was to test increasing
position size, since the strategy appeared
reliable enough to potentially handle larger
positions, without significantly increasing risk.
What makes this strategy smart is the fact it
doesn't try to predict the future. It just
measures what's happening right now - which side
is showing more strength - and trades accordingly.
We're not trying to guess; we're responding to
actual market behavior.
What I like about this
trading bot is that it doesn't rely on complex
indicators. It simply measures what's happening
with price action - the size of bullish
versus bearish candles - and trades when
a clear advantage appears for one side.
The SMA filter adds another dimension by
keeping us on the right side of the larger trend.
Overall, the assistant concluded this was a decent
combination of high returns, high win rate,
and controlled risk. So I’ll keep adjusting
and back testing it in the future!
Here’s another tool I’ve created. I
wanted an indicator to highlight
the trading range for each day.
This Daily Boxes indicator tracks each
trading day with colored boxes. It want
to see daily highs and lows at a glance, which
is critical for understanding market structure.
This tool provides a broader
perspective of price movements,
and helps me identify key levels and trends.
Green boxes show bullish days, where price
closed higher than it opened.
Red boxes show bearish days,
where price closed lower than it opened.
What makes this indicator powerful is how
it lets me quickly see the sequence of daily highs
and lows. When analyzing charts, I pay attention
to the number of up boxes or red boxes.
This helps determine the strength of
buy or sell scenarios. The boxes make
this pattern recognition much easier.
I’ve asked the assistant to let me choose how many
days I want to display, and what colors to use.
Then I wanted a clear function to detect when
a new trading day begins. This is important
because we need to know when to start a new box.
I had a few problems here as I got many errors,
but in the end, the indicator worked as I wanted.
Each time a new day starts, the indicator creates
a fresh box starting at the current bar.
The box extends to the right and gets
updated throughout the day as price makes new
highs or lows. The box color changes based
on whether price is currently above
or below the day's opening price.
From a price action perspective, these boxes
help me identify the premium and discount zones
that are so important in trading.
The daily highs and lows marked
by these boxes become significant levels.
Previous daily highs offer short-term resistance
levels, if price reaches those levels again.
Similarly, the lowest low traded in the
previous day can offer significant support.
These levels are precisely what banks and
institutions often monitor for
buying and selling interest.
By having them clearly boxed on your chart,
I can position myself strategically for
these potential moves.
The indicator also helps
identify order flow patterns.
In a bullish order flow,
buyers dominate the market, driving prices higher,
and the market tends to seek buyside liquidity,
above the previous day's highs.
You'll see this as a series of
green boxes with higher highs.
Conversely, in bearish order flow,
sellers dominate, and the market seeks sellside
liquidity, below the previous day's lows, visible
as a sequence of red boxes with lower lows.
With these boxes, you can spot when a day's range
is much smaller or larger than previous days,
indicating potential changes in market sentiment.
Another tool I’ve created is an Average Daily
Range indicator. This helps me understand market
volatility and how much a market has moved
today, compared to its typical daily movement.
This tool answers key questions: Is today more
or less volatile than normal? Has the market
already reached its typical daily range?
Is there still room for price to move?
The ADR concept is rooted in market volatility
analysis. Markets trade with an average daily
range that varies by instrument.
And this variation is critical for
setting realistic profit targets and stops.
The code creates a simple yet powerful
indicator that calculates the average
range over a set number of days,
then compares today's range to that average.
I wanted the indicator to have a user input
for how many days to include in
the calculation, usually 20 days.
It also asks for a pips multiplier, which helps
adjust the decimal places for different markets.
It also calculates what percentage of the
average range today's move represents.
This information is crucial for my trading
decisions, especially with my profit targets.
For instance if today's range is already at
95% of the average, I might expect limited
further movement and consider taking profits.
But if the ADR is only at 30%, there might
still be substantial movement ahead.
I can also use the ADR to set targets
based on the previous day's high and
low, using the daily boxes indicator.
For example, if today's range is
small compared to the average,
the previous day's high or low might be realistic
targets, depending on the trend direction.
I wanted this tool because instead of using
arbitrary numbers, I want to use the market's
own volatility signature to guide my decisions.
Your AI assistant can build almost any trading
tool. You just need to know how to ask.
Tools that once took months to perfect, now take
minutes. And you don't need coding skills anymore.
Now, it won’t be perfect from the first prompt,
you will get errors or different bugs.
When the code had bugs, I simply copied the
error messages and asked the AI to fix them.
And this takes minutes,
not days or weeks of debugging.
With AI, you can now create custom tools
that match your specific trading approach, instead
of using generic indicators everyone else uses.
And the process becomes educational
too. As you describe what you want
and review the requirements, you
learn how these tools actually work.
What's truly revolutionary is that the
AI can turn any Tradingview indicator
into a complete trading strategy.
Once you have an indicator you like,
simply specify the entry and exit rules.
The AI transforms this into strategy code
that you can backtest immediately.
This lets you validate trading ideas
much faster than traditional methods.
If the strategy produces bad results or
is completely unprofitable, simply ask for
improvements from the AI. Make a screenshot
with the results and ask for other adjustments.
If you’re like me and you prefer trading based on
price movement, AI can help you make simple tools.
These tools can show you when the market is
leaning in a certain direction. Or thy can
highlight the specific situations you've found
useful in your own trading.
Again, the key is being
specific with your requests.
Tell the AI exactly what your indicator
should measure, how calculations should work,
what the visual display should look like, and for
strategies, the exact entry and exit conditions.
The more precise your description,
the better the result.
If you want a follow up video
about this, let me know in the comments.
And if you're curious about mastering
other trading techniques, go ahead
and watch one of these videos next!