if you are a scalper or a day trader you
definitely must try out these
strategies the failed new high or low of
the day is the first scalping setup that
takes advantage of price action and
Market structure this strategy aims to
catch quick moves when price fails to
sustain a break above the previous day's
high or below the previous day's low so
the core idea is to look for Price
attempts to make new highs or lows
compared to the previous trading day
when these attempts fail it often
signals a potential reversal creating a
scalping opportunity you see previous
day highs and lows are important levels
watched by many big Traders these levels
often act as significant support and
resistance when price approaches these
levels it's testing the balance of
supply and demand when price breaks up
above the previous day's High it implies
demand is overcoming Supply if this
break quickly fails it shows that Supply
is still strong at these levels the
opposite is true for breaks below the
previous day's low this failure often
traps traders who entered on the brake
as these Traders exit their positions it
adds fuel to the reversal move this is
how to trade this setup first identify
the previous previous days high and low
these are your key reference points then
watch price action as it approaches
these levels look for signs of
hesitation or rejection as price nears
the previous day's high or low wait for
the break and failure if price breaks
the level but quickly reverses this is
your potential entry trigger it's best
to look for confirmation this could be
in the form of a reversal Candlestick
pattern turn a shift in momentum or
increased volume on the
reversal once you have confirmation
enter in the direction of the failure
for a failed High you would go short for
a failed low You' go long this scalping
setup works well because it aligns you
with the likely intentions of big
players this key levels are often where
large institutions Place their orders
creating liquidity pools when price
fails to break these levels it often
indicates these big players are
defending their
positions perfect strategy for beginners
as this setup offers a clear mechanical
approach to entering trades in this
example we've marked the previous day
levels as the new trading day begins we
see price trending downwards towards the
previous low as price approaches it you
start paying close attention
there's a quick Spike down breaking
below the previous day's low however the
next candle's immediately reverse
closing back above the previous day low
this is a failed new low we also notice
that the volume on the reversal candles
is higher than the previous candles
implying strong buying interest this is
your confirmation so long trade here
just above the high of the reversal
candle the stop loss goes below the
failed low for your Target you might
look at a previous swing High sometimes
price will even go to test the previous
day's high in this chart we've marked
the previous day's levels as the new day
starts we see price pushing upwards
towards the previous High we see a quick
Spike above it but the next candle
closes back below it this is our failed
new high this this is almost a textbook
setup with a pin bar with a large Wick
above the previous High short trade just
below the low of the pin candle stop
loss goes above the failed High one key
aspect of this scalping method is
understanding the concept of liquidity
previous day highs and lows are often
areas with lots of stop- losses and
limit orders big players in the market
may push price into today's area us to
hunt these orders creating the failed
break we're looking to trade so with
this setup you're essentially trying to
align yourself with the smart money for
more advanced Traders you might consider
incorporating additional factors for
example you could look at the overall
Market structure is the market in a
larger uptrend or downtrend failed
breaks that align with the larger Trend
might have a higher probability of
success
you could also consider the time of day
failed breaks that happen during Major
Market opens like London or New York
might be more significant due to the
increased volume in participation of
institutional Traders at these times
[Music]
in
the first major pullback after a market
structure shift is another great
scalping setup that combines price
action and smart money Concepts this
strategy aims to cat catch quick moves
right after a significant change in
Market structure a market structure
shift refers to a clear change in the
overall trend or direction of the market
this usually happens when price breaks a
key level like a previous high or low
when we see this shift we know big
players are likely changing their stance
on the market and after a shift we often
see a pullback this is when price moves
back towards the level just broke smart
money often uses these pullbacks to add
to their positions before the next big
move when price breaks a key level it
shows that demand for an upward break or
supply for a downward break has overcome
the opposite Force at that level but
markets rarely move in straight lines
after the break some Traders take
profits causing a temporary shift in the
supply demand balance this creates the
pullback however if the structure shift
is real and not a false break the supply
demand imbalance that caused the break
still exists so when price pulls back to
the broken level we often see a reaction
as the dominant Force buyers in an
upward break and sellers in a downward
break step in again so this is how to
trade this setup first look for a clear
break of a previous high or low this is
your first clue that smart money might
be changing direction after the break
don't chase the move instead wait
patiently for price to come back to the
broken level this is where you'll look
to enter as price approaches the broken
level watch for signs that the dominant
force is stepping in again this could be
a strong rejection candle a shift in
momentum or a volume Spike if you see
confirmation enter in the direction of
the break your stop loss should go just
beyond the broken level since this is a
scalping strategy look to take profits
quickly this setup works well because it
aligns you with the intentions of big
players you're not trying to catch the
exact bottom or top but rather jumping
on board after smart money has shown its
hand this strategy offers a clear
mechanical approach to entering trades
you are not trying to predict anything
just reacting to what the market is
showing
you in this chart we notice that price
has been in a downtrend then we see a
strong bullish candle that breaks above
the previous swing high this is our
Market structure shift after this break
price starts to pull back we watch as it
approaches the level of the previous
High which is now likely to act as
support as price gets close to this
level we see a longtailed pin bar form
showing rejection of lower prices this
is our confirmation we enter a long
trade just above the high of the pin
bar here we notice that price has been
in an uptrend but we suddenly see a
strong bearish candle that breaks below
a significant swing low this is our
Market structure shift to the downside
price then starts to Rally back towards
the broken level as price approaches our
value area we notice volume starting to
increase this indicates that sellers
might be stepping in we also see an
inside bar form just below the broken
level this often indicates hesitation in
the market a short trade can be taken
once price breaks below this inside
bar also be aware that false break outs
can happen sometimes price will break a
level pull back but then continue in the
original Direction This Is Why waiting
for confirmation on the pullback is
crucial for advanced Traders this
strategy can be combined with other
techniques like volume analysis or order
flow to increase its effectiveness
he
[Music]
another scalping setup uses the volume
weighted average price as a key
reference point in combination with
engulfing candle basically this strategy
combines price action analysis with the
volume weighted line we'll use this
indicator as a trading Benchmark that
shows the average price a market has
traded at based on both volume and price
the engulfing candle is the second
component a price action pattern where
one candle's body completely engulfes
the body of the previous candle it's
seen as a strong Ral signal especially
when it occurs around the
mainline the perfect signal looks like
this price approaches the volume
weighted line an engulfing candle forms
at or near this area then price bounces
off the main line in the direction
indicated by the engulfing
candle from a supply and demand
perspective here's what's happening the
vwap represents the equilibrium price
for the day when price is above vwap
buyers are in control when price
approaches VW up it's entering a Zone
where supply and demand are roughly
balanced the engulfing candle that forms
here represents a sudden shift in this
balance a bullish engulfing candle shows
demand dominating Supply while a bearish
engulfing candle shows Supply overcoming
demand the bounce of vwap confirms this
shift and implies that a new Supply
demand balance is like likely to persist
at least for a short
while this is how to trade this setup
first monitor the vew up on your chart
as price nears the line start paying
close attention watch for an engulfing
candle to form this is your key signal
after the engulfing candle forms look
for price to move away from vwap in the
direction indicated by the engulfing
candle once you have confir of the
bounce you simply enter in the direction
of the engulfing candle place your stop
just beyond the opposite side of the
engulfing candle you might set your
first Target at the next significant
level this scalping method works well
because it combines multiple high
probability factors vwap is a key level
watched by many Traders especially
institutions engulfing candles are
strong reversal signals the bounce
confirms the reversal and shows that the
new trend has some momentum one key
aspect of this strategy is understanding
the significance of vwap institutional
Traders often use vwap as a benchmark
for their trades if they're buying they
want to buy below the line if they're
selling they want to sell above it this
is why vwap often acts as a dynamic
support and resistance
level in this example example we see
price approach the line from below this
suggests that sellers have been in
control but price is now entering the
equilibrium Zone as price touches the
main line we see a large bearish candle
form this candle completely engulfs the
body of the previous candle this is our
signal the next candle continues to move
downward this confirms the bounce we
enter a short trade at the low of the
signal candle stop loss goes just below
the high of the engulfing candle for the
first Target you might look at the
previous swing
lows another signal again we have our
vwap clearly visible we see price
approach the line from Above This
implies that buyers have been in control
but price is now entering the
equilibrium Zone as price touches the
line with see a large bullish candle
form the candle completely engulfes the
body of the previous one the next candle
continues to move upward this confirms
our bounce we enter a Buy trade as the
high of the engulfing candle is taken
out very important market conditions can
affect the effectiveness of your
scalping results in very choppy markets
price might cross vwap frequently making
making it less reliable as a support or
resistance level you don't want to see
the line being tested in recent
candles for more advanced Traders you
might consider incorporating additional
factors for example volume analysis
engulfing candles that form on higher
volume might be more
significant Market structure also
matters is this vwap bounce happening at
a significant swing high or low also
vwap tends to be more significant during
the middle of the trading session early
in the day it's still establishing
itself and late in the day other factors
might become more
important another factor to consider is
the distance of price from vwap the
further price moves from the line the
more likely it is to eventually return
to it this can help you anticipate
potential setup
also please note that this scalping
setup doesn't always require an exact
bounce of the line sometimes price might
hover around the line and won't touch it
before the engulfing candle forms
[Music]
next scalping setup involves a fair
value Gap fill after a breakout this
strategy takes advantage of markeet
inefficiencies and price action
Dynamics fair value gaps are created
with within a three candle sequence they
are typically seen on charts as a large
candle whose neighboring candles upper
and lower weeks don't fully overlap the
large candle here's how it works price
breaks out of a significant level
support or resistance during this
breakout a fair value Gap forms due to
the rapid price movement after the
breakout price often retraces to fill
the Gap this retracement provides a
potential entry point for a trade in the
direction of the original
breakout from a supply and demand
perspective here's what's happening the
breakout represents a significant shift
in the balance of supply and demand the
fair value Gap forms because the price
movement is so Swift that normal price
Discovery doesn't occur in that area
this creates an inefficiency in the
market that often gets filled later when
price returns to fill Gap it's testing
the new Supply demand Balance
established by the breakout this retest
often provides a high probability entry
in the breakout
Direction This is how to trade this
setup first you identify important
levels on your chart these are potential
breakout points then watch for breakouts
when price breaks a key level with
strong momentum pay attention this is
the first part of our setup
next identify the Gap look for the three
candle pattern during the breakout move
after the breakout and GAP formation
price will often retrace to fill the Gap
as price approaches the fair value Gap
get ready for a potential trade entry
look for signs that price is likely to
continue in the breakout Direction after
filling the Gap this could be a reversal
Candlestick pattern or a bounce off the
broken level once you have confirmation
enter in the direction of the original
breakout this strategy offers a clear
systematic approach breakouts often lead
to strong trending moves gaps tend to
get filled due to the Market's nature to
seek fair value and retests of broken
levels often provide good entry
points in this example we've identified
a key resistance level that price has
been respecting for the past few few
days we see a break above it with a
strong candle this three candle sequence
has created Our Fair Value Gap after
this sequence we see price start to
retrace pulling back towards the Gap
giving us our potential entry
opportunity as price enters the Gap area
we see a bullish pin bar form this is
the confirmation signal a long trade is
the play here just above the pin Bar's
High the stop loss is placed just below
the original breakout
level here's a cell setup we've
identified a key support level that
price has been bouncing off for the past
few hours we see price approach this
level and then break below it with a
strong candle this three candle sequence
has created Our Fair Value Gap as price
retraces to fill the Gap we have our
potential entry opportunity a bearish
engulfing candle this is our
confirmation
signal the key aspect of this scalping
setup is understanding the concept of
Market
inefficiencies Fair Value gaps are areas
where normal price Discovery didn't
occur creating a sort of vacuum in the
market prices often return to these
areas to fill this vacuum which is what
creates our trading
opportunity for more advanced Trad ERS
you might consider adding additional
factors one of them is Market structure
a breakout that changes the market
structure from bearish to bullish or
vice versa might be more significant
time of day also matters gaps that form
during Major Market opens like London or
New York might be more significant due
to the increased volume another factor
to consider the size of the Gap larger
gaps might might be more significant and
have a higher probability of being
filled
[Music]
another powerful method combines Market
structure analysis with Fibonacci
retracements this approach aims to catch
quick moves by entering trades at Key
Fibonacci levels after a significant
break of structure a break of structure
occurs when price breaks above a
previous high in an uptrend or below a
previous low in a downtrend it signals a
shift in market dynamics and often
precedes a strong move in the New
Direction once you found a major break
of structure you add the Fibonacci
retracement on it this tool is used to
identify hidden support and resistance
levels we are interested in the golden
Zone the area between the 61 and 78%
levels when a break of structure occurs
it shows that either Supply in a
downtrend or demand in an uptrend has
been overwhelmed the subsequent pullback
to the Fibonacci golden zone is a period
where the market is Seeking a new
equilibrium you are betting that the
original imbalance will reassert itself
at these key Fibonacci
levels this is how to trade this setup
first you identify the break of
structure watch for price to break above
a significant previous high for an
uptrend or below a significant previous
low for a downtrend once you've
identified the break Mark the swing that
includes the break of structure from the
low to the high in an uptrend or from
the high to the low in a
downtrend then simply draw the Fibonacci
retracement after the break of structure
price will often pull back in the golden
Zone look for signs that price is ready
to resume the trend this could be
Candlestick patterns a volume shift or
simply price action showing rejection
from The
Zone once you have your confirmation
enter the trade in the direction of the
original break place your stop just
beyond the opposite side of the golden
Zone as for take profits you might set
your target at the next key levels in
the market
structure this scalping method works
well because it combines multiple high
probability factors the break of
structure shows a clear shift in market
dynamics Fibonacci levels are widely
watched by Traders and often act as
support and resistance and the golden
zone is considered a high probability
reversal area this strategy offers a
structured approach to entering trades
you are looking for a clear break of
structure then waiting for a pullback to
a specific Zone before
entering in this chart we see price
break above a significant previous High
signaling a break of structure to the
upside we marked the swing from the
recent low to the high of the break of
structure candle we then draw our
Fibonacci retracement on this swing then
price pulls back and we see it enter the
golden zone now we start looking for
entry signals here we see a strong
bullish engulfing candle this is our
entry
signal now we see price braks below a
significant previous low signaling a
break of structure to the downside we
Mark the swing from the recent High to
the low of the breakoff structure candle
we then draw our Fibonacci retracement
on this swing price pulls back and we
see it enter the golden zone so we start
looking for entry signals this time a
candle with a long Wick is rejecting The
Zone the length of the break of
structure can affect the effectiveness
of this strategy you want to see price
breaking a previous swing with
conviction in very choppy markets false
breakouts are more common which can lead
to failed setups so keep in mind this
aspect before taking any
trade for more advanced Traders you
might consider add a momentum indicator
to find divergences at the value area if
the golden Zone aligns with other ke
levels it can also increase the
probability of a reversal
[Music]
now if you want to learn other scalping
and day trading tactics you need to
watch one of these videos next
[Music]