here's the biggest lie in trading you
are told to buy when the market is
oversold and to sell when the market is
overbought
but it doesn't work this way I'm afraid
if you want to slowly lose your money
using this technique go ahead but what
if you did the opposite
sell when prices are oversold and buy
when prices are overbought could this
work
let's find out you know the drill like
subscribe and stick around for the full
video
foreign
[Music]
for this experiment we'll use the RSI
every serious Trader should know about
the RSI or the relative strength index
the problem is that not everyone knows
how to read the RSI and this is
especially true for beginners
RSI basically measures how fast trades
happen and how fast the price moves the
indicator moves on a scale of 0 to 100
if the readings drop below 30 they say
Market is oversold the reading said 70
or higher indicate over both conditions
here's where most Traders are getting it
wrong
these values indicate best price
movements but don't show any future
price Direction
a value above 70 or below 30 isn't
necessarily an invitation to enter a
trade
a market may stay above or below these
levels for an extended period of time if
the trend is strong
many Traders are still using this
strategy because it's promoted in almost
every trading book
so let's do the opposite we'll look to
buy when the RSI goes above 70 and will
sell when the indicator crosses the 30
level
here's the logic behind this strategy
when the RSI reaches the overbath and
oversold area it means the recent price
movement is extremely strong
in case of an uptrend this means that
the price is currently pushing into new
highs
from now on when we see over a buff we
see an extremely strong Trend that is
moving higher with a strong force
and vice versa for oversold levels
we'll try to profit from newbies and
Traders that are entering in the wrong
way of the market
[Music]
I also used to trade these levels when I
first started and as I recall the market
will make a very shallow pullback
baiting traders to enter before
continuing in the initial Direction
so that's the trade plan we won't enter
when the RSI enters the overbought or
oversold area we'll wait for a shallow
pullback to trap dump Traders and will
enter at the first sign of trend
continuation
Williams Fibonacci retracements to
determine our entry area
we'll keep only the 23 the 38 and the 50
levels because like I said we are
interested in shallow pullbacks
and we'll keep the RSI with the default
settings of 14.
so for a Buy trade when we see that the
RSI crosses above 70.
we wait for a pullback
when you have some sort of downward
movement
you apply a FIP retracement from the
most recent swing low
to the highest point of this previous up
move
you enter a Buy trade at the first sign
of rejection at one of the FIB levels
we'll talk about stops and Targets later
for a short trade when you sit at the
RSI crosses below 30. again you wait for
an upward pullback
then you apply a fib retracement from
the most recent swing High
to the lowest point of the previous down
move
you enter a sell trade at the first sign
of rejection at one of the FIB levels
Let's test this theory on Forex Market
Euro USD 15 minute time frame
I see an uptrend with Market making
higher highs and higher lows
they are a side lags behind price and
also moves with a steady upward slope
now we have the overbought signal with
the RSI Crossing above 70.
remember the plan we'll buy after the
market makes a pullback to one of our
FIB levels
so let's apply it this is the most
recent swing low
and this is the highest point of the
current trend
and that's our buy area
okay we have the rejection a massive
engulfing bar rejecting the 38-fib level
stop loss goes below the 50 level
and will aim for a two to one risk
reward ratio
now I see another potential trade
our previous take profit coincided with
another overbought reading on RSI
so let's apply our Fibonacci once again
this is the most recent swing low
and this is the highest high in the
current trend
our buy area is here
we have our first green candle but this
is not a bullish candle I expected let's
wait for further confirmations
price went below our buy area and here's
a bullish engulfing candle
even though price is below our buy area
we are still buying at a discount so
there's no reason not to take this trade
we'll put our stop loss below this low
and will once again Target a risk reward
ratio of 2.
let's move the stock market Apple 15
minute time frame
I see a break of structure here
Market is making lower lows
so this might turn into a downtrend
here's an oversold signal with RSI
Crossing below 30.
So the plan is to sell after the market
returns to one of our FIB levels and we
see some sort of rejection
this is the most recent swing High and
this is the lowest point of the current
trend
and that's our cell area
and here's the rejection an engulfing
bar rejecting the 38-fib level
stop loss is placed above the 50 level
and let's aim for a three to one risk
reward ratio
and here's another potential trade
after hour take profit was hit I see
another oversold rating on RSI
so let's apply our FIB once again
this is the most recent swing High
and this is the lowest low in the
current trend
our cell area is here
we have the first red candle but let's
wait for further confirmations
okay now I see this bearish engulfing
candle which is the ideal entry
will put the stop loss Above This
consolidation
and will Target the risk to reward ratio
of 3.
if you are a beginner and maybe you
don't have the intuition to detect the
main Trend or you want fewer signals you
could add a moving average
so let's apply a 50 period exponential
moving average to determine Trend
Direction
this is done by simply observing the
location of price in relation to the
moving average
and the slope of the line itself
when a market is in an uptrend the
moving average is below the price action
in this case you look for over both RSI
signals and Target Long positions you
want to trade in the direction of the
moving average and try to profit from
Traders shorting over both conditions
when a market is in a downtrend the
moving average is above the price action
in this case you look for oversold
signals and Target short positions
against traders that will buy when the
RSI is below 30.
we trade down Jones on the 15 minute
time frame price is above the 50 EMA
trend is up so we want our site to reach
the 70 level
here it is now we wait for a retracement
to one of our levels
this is a textbook rejection I will take
the signal every time I'll see it
a beam bar rejecting the 38 feet level
and a 50 EMA at the same time
we enter long with a stop below the
pullback and we set a risk reward ratio
of 2.
so the key aspect of the strategy is
that you don't enter immediately after
you spot an overbought RSI
you wait for a small pullback and then
make your move
allow the market to trap Navy's Traders
you'll probably remember what it was
like to be on the wrong side of the
trade you enter and the market actually
gives you the impression you made the
right call and goes in your favor for a
bit
and then it aggressively moves against
you that's why you wait for the
retracement you want many trap traders
to be caught on the wrong side
this is Euro Yen price was trading below
the 50ma
Market is making lower lows lower highs
now let's mark the areas when the price
entered oversold conditions
observe how each time the price kept on
trending downwards that's why fading
these levels is the better trading
approach
most traders who aren't experienced will
buy the market
you need to reprogram your mind if you
are tempted to trade these levels the
classic way a trend can and will keep
going for a very long distance even
though the price is in oversold
territory
so from now on you'll use overbought and
oversold as an additional Trend
continuation signal
here's another important tip the longer
drsi stays in an overbought or oversold
State the less effective the RSI is
let's look at this example RSI was below
the 30 level for over 10 candles
which is significant
lots of Traders enter long during this
period
so when we had this retracement to the
first FIB level
and we saw this bearish engulfing candle
this was a good opportunity to short the
market
in the direction of the main Trend which
was obviously down
with price staying below the 50 moving
average and its slope was pointing
downwards
time can also impact the RSI reading so
don't forget to take it into
consideration as well
this strategy is more suited to day
trading and scalping and not so much to
swing Trading
on Lower time frames Traders are more
impatient and more reactive more
emotional when the market goes against
them
so they have the tendency to close
trades prematurely or they use small
stop losses which will be the main fuel
for our positions
so stay on the 15 minute or the 30
minute time frames
the entry trigger is also important I
prefer engulfing candlesticks rejecting
a fib level but a pin bar also works
well
ideally you should be able to gain at
least double the risk you are taking
but in some volatile markets with many
swings a lower risk reward ratio of 1.5
might be better
and of course instead of RSI you can try
any indicator which allows for
overbought or oversold readings like
stochastic CCI or Williams percent range
you just have to slightly adjust their
settings to suit your markets
and you can also change the length and
the type of the moving average
I use the 50 EMA but you can apply any
moving average you prefer
so adjust this technique to suit your
markets and use over bath and oversold
signals as an additional Trend
continuation pattern
thank you
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
if you want to see more videos like this
one leave us a like And subscribe
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time