90% of traders fail because they can't
read Fibonacci signals correctly.
Today it’s time to finally discover how to use
Fibonacci effectively, in any market condition.
Fibonacci’s effectiveness
depends on how you apply them.
And the key is to use them on
the correct price swings.
When you're looking at a price
chart, you'll see many price swings.
You might connect two points on the
chart that seem significant to you,
but another trader might choose different points.
This doesn't mean one of you is wrong; it just
highlights the subjective nature of this tool.
To apply Fibonacci retracements correctly, you
need to start by determining the dominant trend.
Once you've identified the trend, your
next step is to find the most obvious swing
high and swing low. These are the points
you'll use to draw your Fibonacci lines.
In a bullish trend, you'll draw the Fibonacci
retracement from the swing low to the swing high.
This makes sense because in an uptrend, you're
looking for potential support levels, where the
price might pause or reverse during a pullback.
In a bearish trend, you'll draw from the
swing high to the swing low.
You're looking for potential
resistance levels, where the price
might stall or reverse during a bounce.
When drawing these lines, it's important
to use the wicks of the candlesticks for
your swings, not just the bodies.
The clarity of your chosen swing
points is probably the most important aspect.
The clearer the swing low and high, and the more
defined the trend between these points, the more
reliable your Fibonacci levels are likely to be.
One common mistake is trying to force Fib
levels to fit where they don't naturally apply.
Remember, not every price move will align
perfectly with Fib levels, and that's okay.
The most helpful Fib retracements
are those that are obvious on the
chart without much effort to spot them.
If you find yourself squinting at the chart
or trying to convince yourself that a level fits,
it might be best to look for a clearer setup.
When applying Fibonacci retracements, it's
helpful to think about the market structure.
In an uptrend, for example, you might
look for buying opportunities near
these Fib levels, as the price pulls back.
The idea is that the trend will eventually
continue, and these retracement levels offer
potential entry points, at a better price.
Number one rule is that Fibonacci
levels work best in trending markets.
Without a clear trend, these levels lose their
significance and impact on price movement.
When you spot a trend, look for the logical price
swings to place your Fibonacci retracement tool.
This step is critical and often
where most traders struggle.
The trick is to find the most relevant high
and low points that represent the current
market conditions.
So in this uptrend,
I would draw the Fib retracement from
this swing low, to this swing high.
For this downtrend, I would draw it from
this swing high, to the swing low.
Once you've placed your Fib levels, you'll
notice several key retracement levels.
The most commonly used are
23, 38, 50 and 61% levels.
These lines can act as potential support areas in
an uptrend, or resistance zones in a downtrend.
Many traders focus primarily
on the 61% retracement level,
as it's often considered the "golden ratio."
But I wouldn’t discount the power of
other levels.
In strong trends,
price might only retrace to the 38% level
before continuing in the trend direction.
In weaker trends, price might
extend to the 78% level.
Now, it's worth noting that these Fibonacci levels
don't act as exact support or resistance points.
Instead, they help you find
areas where price might react.
So think of them as zones,
rather than precise lines.
Remember, Fibonacci levels often become
self-fulfilling prophecies in the market.
Many traders watch these same levels
and place their orders around them.
This collective action can create
real support and resistance zones.
And please note that Fibonacci levels struggle
in sideways or ranging conditions. If the
market is consolidating, it's often
better to wait for a clear breakout
before applying a Fibonacci analysis.
Here’s another common mistake. When you apply
Fibonacci retracements to very small price moves
or shorter timeframes, you might run into some
issues that can make your trading less effective.
Think about it this way: on shorter timeframes,
price movements are often more
erratic and less significant.
These small, rapid price changes
don't always reflect the true market
trend or important levels.
When you try to use Fibonacci
retracements on these short-term moves, the
levels you get are often too close together.
This closeness makes it hard to tell which levels
are truly important, and which are just noise.
Another problem with using Fibonacci on
short timeframes is that you're more likely
to see false breakouts and price spikes.
These quick, sharp moves can trick you
into thinking a level has been
broken, when it hasn't really.
This can lead to poor signals, like entering
a trade too early or exiting one too soon.
Think about it: stops and take-profit
points are key for managing your trades.
But when you use Fib retracements
on short timeframes, it becomes
tricky to place these effectively.
The retracement levels are so close
together that they create narrow confluences.
This means there's not much room between levels,
making it hard to set stops that protect
you from normal market noise, while still
giving your trade room to breathe.
So, what's the solution? Focus on
larger timeframes when you apply Fib levels.
You get a clearer view of the long-term trend.
This helps you apply Fibonacci
retracements in the right direction,
aligning with the overall market movement.
When you use Fibonacci retracements on larger
timeframes, you're looking at
more significant price moves.
These bigger swings are more likely
to represent important market levels.
The levels drawn on these larger moves are
spaced further apart, making it easier to
see which levels might be important.
And you don't have to stick to just
one timeframe. You can use a multi-timeframe
approach. You might start with a larger timeframe
to find the overall trend and major Fibonacci
levels, then zoom in to a smaller timeframe.
Another benefit of placing
Fibs on larger timeframes,
is that it can help you avoid overtrading.
When you focus on smaller moves, it's
tempting to take many trades, thinking
each small retracement is significant.
But by zooming out and looking at the bigger
picture, you can be more selective with your
trades, focusing on the moves that
are more likely to be significant.
When we talk about retracements, we're looking at
how much a price pulls back after a strong move.
These pullbacks can be shallow, or deep.
Shallow retracements happen in strong trends. When
a market is moving with conviction, it doesn't
pull back much before continuing its journey.
In these cases, you'll often see the
price only retreat to the 23 or 38% areas.
The trend is so strong that it doesn't need
much time to refuel, before zooming off again.
When you spot these shallow pullbacks
it's a sign that the trend is
healthy and likely to continue.
Deep retracements are more common
when a trend isn't fully established yet.
The price might make several ups and downs,
testing previous highs or
lows without breaking them.
Deep retracements often reach the
61, 78, or even 88 Fib levels.
These deeper pullbacks can be tricky.
They might make you think the trend is
over, but it's not always the case.
It's more like the market is taking
a longer break, perhaps reassessing its
direction before deciding to continue.
The key difference between shallow and deep
retracements, is in what they tell us about
the strength of the trend.
Shallow retracements
signal a strong, confident trend.
The market barely hesitates before pushing on.
Deep retracements suggest more uncertainty.
The trend might still continue,
but it's taking its time to gather strength.
If you see a shallow retracement in a strong
trend, it might be a good opportunity
to join in the direction of that trend.
With deep retracements, you might need to
be more cautious. While they can still lead
to continuation of the trend, there's also a
higher chance the trend might be losing steam.
And if the price retraces 100% of the last move,
it might be a sign that the trend has failed.
Now, when price reaches a Fib level,
look for specific candlestick patterns.
These patterns can confirm if the
level is likely to hold, or break.
It's like getting a second
opinion before making a trade.
There are a lot of candlesticks, but the most
useful patterns at Fib levels are engulfing
patterns, and candles with long wicks.
Candles with a long lower wick
show up at the end of a down move.
This long wick shows that sellers tried to
push price lower, but buyers stepped in and pushed
it back up. When you see it at a Fibonacci support
level, it might mean the down move is over.
If you spot a candle with a long upper wicks at
a Fibonacci resistance level, pay close attention.
They often signal the end of up moves. Buyers
tried to push price higher,
but sellers took control.
Engulfing patterns are also decent signals.
In a bullish engulfing pattern, a large green
candle completely covers the previous red candle.
This shows buyers taking control from sellers.
A bearish engulfing pattern is the opposite,
with a large red candle covering the previous
green one. These patterns at Fibonacci
levels can be strong reversal signals.
From my experience, using candlesticks with
Fibonacci levels works best on longer timeframes.
This is because bigger moves tend to respect
Fibonacci levels more. And candlestick patterns
on longer timeframes often carry more weight.
Let's say price is in an uptrend and pulls
back to the 50% Fib level.
This level acts as a potential
support. If you see a candle with a long
candlestick forming right at this level, it's
a decent sign that the pullback might be over.
The Fib level shows where buyers might step in,
and the candle shows that they actually did.
Here, price is in a downtrend and bounces
up to the 38% Fib level.
This level will act as a
potential resistance in a downtrend.
If an engulfing candle forms here,
it implies the bounce might be over.
So the Fib level shows where sellers
might return, and the engulfing candle
shows they're actually taking control.
These engulfing patterns at
Fib levels show a sudden,
strong shift in who's controlling the market.
And an engulfing pattern that completely
swallows several previous candles at a
key Fibonacci level is hard to ignore.
Volume can add another layer of confirmation
to candlestick patterns at Fibonacci levels.
A reversal candle with high
volume at a Fibonacci support
level is more convincing than one with low volume.
The high volume shows strong buying interest right
where buyers were expected to step in.
Now, one common mistake is to focus
only on exact Fibonacci levels.
As I said, in reality, these levels
are more like zones than exact lines.
A candlestick pattern doesn't have to
form exactly at a Fibonacci level to be valid.
If it's close, it's worth paying attention to.
And another key point is to
look at the bigger picture.
A candlestick pattern at a Fib level is more
meaningful if it aligns with the larger trend.
For example, a bullish pattern, at a Fibonacci
support level, in an overall uptrend, is typically
stronger than one that goes against the trend.
The “Golden zone” method is a smart way to
trade using Fibonacci levels.
This method focuses on the
50% - 61% area, which we call the Golden Ratio.
First, you find a clear trend in the market.
You then apply Fibonacci tools to this trend.
You’ve practically market the key levels where
the price might turn around.
The strategy gets interesting
when the price starts to move against
the trend, when price starts going up.
You watch closely as it
moves past the 50% Fib level.
The key is to see if the price can
break and close above the 61% level.
In the perfect scenario, the
price reaches the 50 – 61 % zone,
but doesn’t close above it. And this could be a
signal that the downtrend is ready to continue.
In real market, the price will
touch and even go a bit above
this area. This doesn’t invalidate the setup.
So, it's okay if the price goes above the 61 line.
Once it returns below the 61.8% line,
that's a good sign for our strategy.
This moment is when we get ready to make
a move. We're looking for signs that the
price is about to turn back down.
Maybe it's a bearish candle forming,
or other factors lining up.
The idea is to catch the market just as
it's deciding to follow the original trend again.
In this chart, once we see the price bounce off
the Golden zone, we start looking
for a move back up. The next target
might be the 38% Fibonacci level.
If the price breaks above the 38%
level, it could mean the previous
uptrend is picking up steam again.
After the 38% level, the next stop might be the
23% level. This is another place where the price
might pause or bounce a little.
But if the uptrend is strong,
even this level might not hold.
In that case, we could see the price go all
the way back to where the downward move started.
We call this a 100% retracement.
So these Fib levels aren't just
targets for where the price might go.
They're also useful for managing your trade.
You can use these levels to decide
when to take some profits.
For instance, you might decide
to sell a part of your position when the price
hits the 38% level, and more at the 23% level.
If the price never got
higher than the Golden zone,
you might put your stop loss just above that line.
This way, if the market suddenly changes direction
after you entered, you're protected.
Combining multiple Fib retracements will
help you find stronger trade setups.
Start by looking at the big picture.
Draw Fibonacci retracements on larger
timeframes, like the daily chart.
This shows you the main
trend and important levels.
Then, zoom in to smaller timeframes, like
1-hour charts, and draw Fibonacci retracements
there too. After that, you might see some
levels from the bigger timeframes matching
up with levels on the smaller timeframes.
These matching levels create confluence.
For example, the 38% Fibonacci level
on the daily chart might line up with
the 50% level on the 1-hour chart.
This overlap becomes a strong area
to watch. It's like two different
paths leading to the same place.
These levels often act like magnets, pulling
the price back, before the main trend continues.
It helps to watch how the price acts
when it hits these Fibonacci levels.
Does it pause? Does it turn around quickly? These
reactions can tell you how strong the level is.
So this technique is all about finding
areas where different Fibonacci levels
from various timeframes overlap, creating
a strong support or resistance level.
In this case, we see a confluence, where the 61%
Fibonacci retracement from the 4-hour timeframe,
meets the 38% retracement
from the daily timeframe.
This overlap creates a buy zone that's much
stronger than a single Fibonacci level alone.
The power of this approach comes from the
fact that traders using different timeframes
will all see this area as significant.
Those looking at the daily chart will
see the 38% level, while those on the
4-hour chart will notice the 61% level.
When both groups see the
price reacting at this zone,
it can create a self-fulfilling prophecy,
increasing the likelihood of a bounce.
Combining Fibonacci retracements
this way helps filter out weaker
setups and focuses your attention on
the most promising trade opportunities.
It's not just about drawing lines on
a chart, but about building a complete
picture of potential market turning points.
In this example, the price pulled back to the
confluence zone and found support there, which
is exactly what we look for in an uptrend.
In this chart, we see another example of
confluence. Two different Fibonacci retracements,
drawn on different timeframes, have
aligned at the same price area.
This creates a strong resistance zone,
setting up a potential selling opportunity.
In this case, we see a confluence between the
4-hour 38% level and the 1-hour 50% Fib level.
This is a key resistance zone where sellers
might enter the market, in a previous downtrend.
And indeed, this zone acted as a ceiling
where price struggled to break through,
then changed direction.
Fibonacci and moving averages
combo is also a viable method.
When used together, they create a
synergy that can confirm your signals.
Fibonacci alone can point to possible
support or resistance levels, but
they lack the weight of confirmation.
This is where moving averages step in, adding
an extra layer of validation to your analysis.
Moving averages serve two key
purposes in this partnership.
First, they help you spot trends. A simple look at
the slope of a moving average can tell you if the
market is trending up, down, or sideways.
And second, moving averages act
as dynamic support and resistance.
As price moves, these averages shift, creating
flexible barriers that price often respects.
And when a Fibonacci level lines up with a moving
average, you've found a spot of confluence.
In this example, price has been climbing
steadily. You draw your Fibonacci
retracement from the recent low to the
high. The 50% retracement level catches your eye.
Now, you notice the 200-period exponential moving
average is sitting right at that same level.
This is confluence in action. The Fibonacci tool
and the moving average are both pointing
to the same price area as significant.
This confluence increases the odds
of price reacting at this level.
You might see price pause, bounce,
or even reverse at this point.
It's not a guarantee, but it's
a strong hint from the market.
This combination is powerful because Fib
retracements can sometimes seem arbitrary.
And moving averages, on their own, can
lag behind price action. But together,
they create a more robust analytical framework.
And is not just about finding potential trade
setups. It's also about understanding structure.
These confluence points often mark key levels
where big players in the market might be active.
It's also worth noting that different traders
might use different Fib levels
or moving average periods.
Some traders swear by the 61% level,
combined with the 200-period moving average.
Others might prefer the 50%
level with the 50-period average.
The key is to find what works best for your
trading style, and the markets you trade.
Now let's talk about how volume
can confirm Fibonacci levels.
When price reaches a Fibonacci support area, I
always look at the volume. Volume is like the
heartbeat of the market.
When price goes up,
you often see big spikes in volume.
It's like a lot of people getting
excited and jumping on board.
But what happens when price pulls
back to a Fibonacci support level?
This is where it gets interesting.
If you see volume getting smaller
as price pulls back, that's a good
sign. It means fewer people are selling.
It shows that most people who wanted to
sell have already done so. There's
not much selling pressure left.
Now, you might think low volume means
people don't care about the market anymore.
But that's not true. It just
means there are fewer sellers.
Smart buyers see this as a chance to get in
at a good price, before everyone else notices.
So watch what happens after price
bounces off the Fibonacci level.
If you see a big jump in volume,
that's a very good sign. It means a lot of
people are suddenly interested in buying.
This high volume after a
bounce is like a green light.
It shows that the Fibonacci level worked as
support, and now more people are jumping in.
It's a sign that the upward move might continue.
Using volume with Fibonacci levels
also helps you spot fake-outs.
Sometimes price might dip below
a Fibonacci level, scaring some traders.
But if volume stays low during this dip,
it might just be a trick. The
real move could still be upwards.
So when you see price approach a Fibonacci
level with declining volume, get ready.
This could be a great entry point. But don't
jump in just yet. Wait for that volume spike
after the bounce. That's your confirmation.
This method works in downtrends too. If price
is falling and then hits a Fibonacci
resistance level, watch the volume.
If it drops off as price goes up to the
level, sellers might be running out of steam.
A big volume spike downwards, after touching
the level, could signal more downside to come.
One of the most underrated ways to trade
Fibonacci levels involves divergences.
A divergence is a leading trading signal, and it
can help confirm if a price reaction is likely.
It’s simple, just choose a momentum indicator. I
prefer to use the MACD. This indicator shows if
a trend is strong or weak. Yes, it lags, but
we don’t need crossovers or other signals.
We simply look at inefficiencies
between the price and the oscillator.
When MACD don't match what price
is doing, it's called divergence.
And as I said, a divergence at a Fibonacci
level is a strong sign of a possible reversal.
Let's talk about how this works in a downtrend.
Imagine price hits the 50% Fib
level and starts to reverse.
Then you look at your oscillator. If
price is making higher highs, but your indicator
is making lower highs, that's a divergence.
It means the upward momentum is slowing,
even though price is still trying to move up.
This implies the bounce might be over,
and the downtrend could resume.
The same idea works in uptrends too.
Let's say price is rising and then
pulls back to the 61% Fibonacci level. If
you see a divergence on your oscillator
right at this level, it's a strong buy signal.
These signals are called leading indicators.
They hint at what might happen before
price actually turns. That's why they're
so valuable. They give you a heads up,
letting you prepare for a potential trade.
Of course, a divergence at Fibonacci
levels doesn't guarantee a reversal.
It just makes one more likely.
You could look for the other signals
we’ve discussed, like candlestick patterns
or volume changes, to confirm the signal.
Probably my favorite strategy is
to look for confluences between
the FIB levels and supply or demand areas.
It doesn't happen often, but when it does,
it can be a sign of something special.
In this example, notice that the price
is approaching a key demand area
that lines up with a FIB level.
That's a confluence perfect for a trade.
If the price bounces off that area,
it could be the start of a beautiful
uptrend that you can ride.
On the flip side, if you see the price
approaching a major supply area, and that
coincides with a Fib level, it could be a sign
that the buyers are about to run out of steam.
If the price gets rejected at that
level, it might be time to start
hunting for short opportunities.
Let's talk about demand areas first.
These are places where lots of people want to buy.
When the price gets near a demand area,
and it's also close to a Fibonacci
level, it's extra special.
This tells us that the price
might start going up soon.
Think about it like this: You're looking at
an uptrend. Then the price is going down.
But then you notice it's
getting close to a demand area.
The price is also near a key Fibonacci level.
You may want to monitor closely this area.
Supply areas are spots where
lots of people want to sell.
When the price climbs up to a supply
area, and it matches a Fibonacci level,
it's another special moment. This might mean the
price is about to turn around and start falling.
Picture this: the market
is in a general downtrend,
then the price has been climbing for a while.
Then you see it's approaching a supply area.
The price is also near an
important Fibonacci level.
This is when you start thinking the
upward move might be running out of steam.
These confluences are like secret messages in
the market. They don't happen all the time,
but when they do, you pay attention.
Again, here price bounce off a demand
area that lines up with a Fibonacci
level. This is a good time to enter a
buy position and ride the price up
as it starts a new upward move.
And here, price hit a supply area
that matches a Fibonacci level,
and then start to fall. This was a good time
to sell, as price started a new downward move.
Now, if you’re ready for more interesting trading
guides, go ahead and watch one of these videos.