Forget everything you’ve heard about moving
averages! 99% of traders use them wrong,
and it’s killing their accounts!
In this video, I'm going to show YOU
exactly how I win consistently, using
a moving-average trading strategy!
Here's the exact path YOU'RE taking today.
We'll start with the most profitable
pullback patterns. Then I'll reveal
why the slope matters more than price.
We’ll talk fake-outs: this one trick
saved me from hundreds of losing trades.
Some of these strategies might surprise YOU,
especially when you see the power of
displaced and adaptive moving averages.
So by the end, you’ll have a complete
moving-average trading strategy
system that actually works.
**CHAPTER 1: 1ST PULLBACK TO
MOVING-AVERAGE AFTER A BREAKOUT**
Here's where traders mess up a
moving-average strategy completely. They chase
breakouts instead of waiting for the pullback.
Most people see price break above the
50-period moving-average for instance
and buy immediately. Bad move. The smart
money waits. I learned this after losing
so much money doing exactly that mistake.
Watch what happens when YOU wait for the
first pullback after a breakout instead. Price
breaks above your moving average. Everyone gets
excited. Price shoots up 10-20 pips. Then it
happens - the pullback. Price comes back down
to kiss that moving average. That's YOUR entry.
Here's how YOU implement this. Set your 50-period
exponential moving-average on your chart.
Wait for a clean break above it with strong
volume. Don't chase. Let price pull back
to the moving average. When it touches and
shows signs of bouncing, that's YOUR signal.
Look at my screen right now. See how price
broke above the moving average. Everyone
bought there. Price went up fast, then
pulled back. That pullback to the moving-average
was my entry. Made easy 30 pips on that trade.
It’s a simple mindset switch. YOU'RE not
chasing breakouts anymore. YOU'RE waiting
for the market to come to YOU.
**CHAPTER 2: MOVING-AVERAGE
SLOPE (ACCELERATION / DECELERATION)**
Now, what I'm about to show YOU about
slope literally changed how I see every chart.
Most traders look at moving averages as static
lines. But they miss the most important
part - the angle. The slope tells YOU
if momentum is building or dying. When the
moving-average points up sharply, momentum is
strong. When it flattens, momentum weakens.
Here's the secret. Steep slope equals strong
trades. Flat slope equals weak trades. I
avoid trades when the moving-average slope
is flat. Because flat slopes mean sideways
markets. And sideways markets chop YOU up.
Look at YOUR chart right now. Draw a line
along your moving average. Is it pointing
up aggressively? That's acceleration. Good
for long trades. Is it starting to flatten?
That's deceleration. Time to be careful.
I use a simple rule. If I can't see a
clear angle on the moving average,
I don't trade. This saved me from
countless losing trades in choppy markets.
Here's how YOU implement this. Before every trade,
check your moving-average slope.
If the steep is up, look for longs.
If the steep is down, look for shorts.
If it’s flat, you stay out. This simple
check improves win rates dramatically.
The slope is telling YOU the story of
momentum before price even moves.
**CHAPTER 3: MOVING-AVERAGE HIGH LOW
CHANNEL (PRICE POSITION RELATIVE TO CHANNEL)**
99% of people use moving averages based on the
close price. I prefer to use a moving-average
channel, based on high and low price.
You see, people get this wrong by treating
the average like a single line in the sand.
But price often moves above or below that
line before reversing. A high-low channel
can give YOU a margin of safety.
Price rarely goes straight up or
down after a breakout. It moves in
waves around the moving average.
Here's the pattern. In an uptrend, price
pushes above the moving-average channel,
pulls back to it, then pushes higher
again. Each high gets a bit higher.
Each low comes back to the moving average.
Watch what happens when YOU start seeing this
channel. Instead of random price movement, YOU
see structure. If price is above the channel
you have a bullish bias, with opportunities
to go long at the top of the channel. Below
the channel means a bearish bias. You look
for shorts at the bottom of the channel.
Take a look at this. The moving-average
channel acts like a magnet, pulling price
back when it gets too far away.
The moving-average channel in
combination with price position makes
the next concept even more powerful.
**CHAPTER 4: FAKE-OUTS AT MOVING AVERAGES**
Now, here's where most traders completely mess
up a moving-average trading strategy.
Many assume that if price touches the
moving-average and bounces once, it will bounce
forever. That’s not always true. Fake-outs happen
when price momentarily breaks below or above the
average, luring YOU in, then flips course again.
The market tricks YOU into thinking the trend
changed. Then it snaps back like a rubber band.
I personally fell for this trap hundreds of
times. Price would break below my moving average,
I'd sell, then it would rocket back up above
the moving average. Frustrating and expensive!
The secret is recognizing fake-out patterns. Real
breaks have volume and momentum behind them. Fake
breaks look weak and hesitant. Real breaks
hold the new level. Fake breaks fail quickly.
Here's my fake-out filter. When
price breaks a moving average,
I wait 15 minutes. If it can't stay on the
new side with volume, it's probably fake.
If it creeps back above the moving-average
within those 15 minutes, I ignore the break.
Watch closely here! See how price dipped
below the moving-average around the market
open. But no volume. Weak momentum. Within 10
minutes, it was back above the moving average.
This is a classic fake-out.
Also check the slope again.
If the slope is still firmly in your
favor, that quick breach might be noise.
Watch what happens when YOU see a big
candle that closes under the average,
but the slope is still pointing up.
Many times, that move reverses swiftly.
Here's how YOU implement this. Never trade
immediately on moving-average breaks. Wait
for confirmation. Watch volume.
Watch momentum. Watch the slope.
Let the market prove the break is real.
And here’s the best part! Failed fake-outs
often create the strongest moves in the
opposite direction. When that fake breakdown
fails, the bounce can be explosive.
**CHAPTER 5: DISPLACED MOVING AVERAGES**
Most people have never heard of this. A
displaced moving-average is the same line,
but shifted to the right on your chart. This
changes how YOU view price relative to that
average. If YOU shift it forward, you might
catch turning points a bit earlier because
the line doesn’t clutter the present bar.
You see, standard moving averages lag behind
price. They tell YOU what happened,
not what's happening now. Displaced
moving averages solve this problem by
shifting the line forward in time.
This creates something magical. The moving-average
appears to predict where price wants to go. It's
not really predicting - it's showing YOU where
price would be if the current trend continues.
Here's where it gets crazy. Price often respects
these displaced moving averages. The market
seems to know where these future levels sit.
In this chart I use a 50-period EMA displaced
forward by 10 periods. This gives me support and
resistance levels that most traders can't see.
Look at that line ahead of current price!
That's my displaced moving average. Most
traders had no idea that level existed.
Here's how YOU implement this. Take your
favorite moving average. Shift it forward by
10 of 20 candles, depending on your time frame.
For example, a 20-period MA gets
shifted forward 10 periods. Now YOU
have future support and resistance levels.
**CHAPTER 6: MOVING-AVERAGE CROSSOVERS **
Okay, here's where it gets controversial.
Moving-average crossovers are probably the worst
moving-average trading strategy ever created.
YOU might be thinking, everyone uses crossovers.
That's exactly the problem. When everyone
uses the same strategy, it stops working.
The classic crossover setup goes like this. A
fast moving-average crosses above a slow one,
so you buy. Sounds simple, and works terribly.
Crossovers fail because they're too late. By
the time the fast line crosses the slow line,
the move is often over. YOU end up
buying tops and selling bottoms.
I tried to make this work, I tested hundreds
of combinations. Win rate was always under
20%. Average losing trade was bigger than
average winning trade. Mathematical disaster.
Here's the brutal truth about crossovers.
They work in trending markets but kill YOU
in choppy markets. And the problem
is, markets chop 70% of the time.
Look at YOUR chart right now. Count the
crossovers from last week. How many actually
led to profitable moves? Probably less than half.
Instead of crossovers, focus on price action
around single moving averages. Much
more reliable. Much better timing.
Here's what YOU should do instead. Use one
moving-average as your trend filter. Trade
pullbacks to it in trending markets.
Ignore crossover signals completely.
The best traders I know stopped
using crossovers years ago.
**CHAPTER 7: MOVING-AVERAGE BOUNCE PATTERNS**
This next part about bounce patterns was a huge
lightbulb for me. If YOU only remember one thing,
let it be this. Price loves to revisit a certain
moving-average and bounce off it in a strong
trend. Maybe it’s the 20MA if the trend is hot,
or the 50MA if it’s slower. Those bounces
can be safer entries than chasing breakouts.
The key is reading the signs
before the bounce happens.
Strong trends create reliable bounces. You
see it all the time: price pulls back to
the moving average, finds support, then
continues the trend. This happens because
the moving-average acts like a magnet for price.
I look for three things in bounce patterns. First,
strong trend before the pullback. Second,
clean approach to the moving average. Third,
signs of buying interest as price
reaches the moving average.
Here's my favorite bounce setup. Price trends
up strongly. Pulls back to the 50-period EMA.
Shows a pin bar or an engulfing candle
at the moving average. Next candle
breaks above it. That's my entry.
Watch what happens when YOU start
seeing these patterns. Instead of random
bounces, YOU see predictable setups.
Look at this market. See how price
bounced perfectly off the EMA three times.
Each bounce led to perfect moves. This
is what consistent profits look like.
Here's how YOU implement this. In uptrends,
watch for pullbacks to your moving average.
Identify if the slope is solid. Look for
reversal candles at the moving average.
Enter on the break of the reversal candle high.
The opposite works for downtrends. Price bounces
down from the moving-average after pullbacks.
You might ask, “How do I pick which average to
watch for the bounce” That depends
on the personality of the market.
Some markets respect shorter lines, like
the 20 EMA. Others might use the 50 EMA.
You need to experiment and back test,
there’s no magical average that will work
on all markets. Once YOU find a line that price
respects, that bounce pattern can be gold.
**CHAPTER 8: MOVING-AVERAGE RIBBONS**
This part can be a game-changer,
if used correctly. You’ll be surprised
how simple a moving-average ribbon can be.
A ribbon is a set of averages for different
periods, spaced out. Picture a colorful band
on your screen. If all lines are stacked
in order, from shortest to longest,
that often signals a strong trend. If they
tangle or flatten, the trend might be weak.
So a ribbon is multiple moving averages plotted
together. Instead of one line, YOU have 8-12
lines of different periods. When they align,
they create powerful trend signals. They help
YOU see the market’s structure at a glance.
Think of it like this. One moving-average
can lie. Two can be coincidence.
But when 8-10 moving averages all
point the same direction, the trend is real.
The ribbon works like a traffic light. Green
when all averages point up and stay separated.
Red when they point down and stay separated.
Here's the secret most traders miss. The space
between the ribbon lines tells YOU trend strength.
Wide spaces mean strong trends. Narrow spaces
mean weak trends. Tangled lines mean no trend.
For starters, you can use a 12-ribbon system.
Periods from 5 to 50. When they fan out nicely,
trade with the trend. When they tangle up, stay
out. The bigger the separation among the lines,
the stronger the momentum. If YOU see them
pinch together, that can mean a slowdown.
I used to ignore these. I thought one average
was enough. But then I realized that a ribbon
can give me early warnings about trend changes.
If the fastest average starts to roll over and
crosses beneath the next line, that’s the
first sign. If the rest follow, that’s even
clearer. And the slope of the entire ribbon can
reveal if the market is accelerating or not.
The ribbon eliminates a lot of bad
trades because it keeps YOU out of
choppy markets. Clean ribbon means clean
trends. Messy ribbon means messy markets.
This filter will improve YOUR
trade selection dramatically.
Speaking of filters, let me show YOU
something that works even better...
**CHAPTER 9: MOVING-AVERAGE ENVELOPES**
99% of traders have never heard of envelopes, but
they're game-changers for moving-average traders.
Envelopes are bands drawn above and below a
moving average. Usually 2-3% above and below. They
create channels that contain most price movement.
When price hits the upper envelope, it often
reverses down. When it hits the lower envelope,
it often reverses up. The moving-average
in the middle acts as the balance point.
So envelopes expand or contract based on a
percentage or volatility measure around a single
moving average. This helps YOU see potential
overbought or oversold conditions in real time.
And this is exactly why envelopes work better than
other indicators. They adapt to market volatility
automatically. In quiet markets, the bands
are tight. In volatile markets, they expand.
Envelopes work most of the time
because they move with the market.
The beauty of envelopes is mean reversion. Price
rarely stays at extreme levels long. It wants to
return to the average. The envelopes
show YOU where extreme levels are.
Take a look at this. See how price bounced
perfectly between the envelope bands. Upper
band rejections led to profitable shorts.
Lower band bounces led to profitable longs.
Now, don’t think envelopes are only for
sideways markets. Actually, a trending
market can also ride the upper envelope band.
If YOU see price clinging to the top band, that
might signal strong momentum. If price wanders
inside the envelope, momentum may be fading.
Here's how YOU implement this. Set a percentage
offset around your 20 or 50 moving average. Maybe
2% or 3%. Watch how price interacts with those
boundaries. When price hits the upper envelope,
look for short setups. When it hits the
lower envelope, look for long setups.
This concept gets even more
powerful when we add volume.
**CHAPTER 10: VOLUME-WEIGHTED MOVING AVERAGE**
If YOU only look at price, YOU might miss a
piece of the puzzle. You see, regular
moving averages treat every price point
equally. A big volume day has the
same weight as low volume day. This
creates problems because volume
shows institutional interest.
Volume-weighted moving averages solve this
by giving more weight to high-volume periods.
When institutions trade heavily, those
prices get more influence on the average.
Think of it like voting. Regular moving averages
give everyone one vote. Volume-weighted averages
give bigger traders more votes. Since bigger
traders move markets, this makes sense.
The volume-weighted average reacts faster
to price changes when volume is high. It
reacts slower when volume is low. This creates
more accurate support and resistance levels.
Here's where it gets interesting. Price often
respects volume-weighted average levels better
than regular moving averages. Because these
are lines where the real money changed hands.
I started using volume-weighted lines
for scalping, after noticing my regular
EMAs were giving too many false signals. The
volume-weighted lines kept me in good trades
longer and got me out of bad trades faster.
Watch closely here. Compare a regular 20-period
average with a 20-period volume-weighted average.
Observe how the volume line hugs
price action better.
The volume-weighted line
works especially well during breakouts. That’s
because breakouts need volume to sustain.
**CHAPTER 11: MULTIPLE TIMEFRAME MOVING AVERAGES**
Now, here's where most traders completely mess
up their moving-average strategies
- they only look at one timeframe.
That’s a missed opportunity. If YOU track a
daily average, and then an intraday average,
YOU can align your trades with the bigger trend.
If the higher timeframe average is bullish,
but your lower timeframe average turns
bearish, maybe YOU only take short-term
quick trades. Or skip the short side entirely.
The daily chart average shows the big picture
trend. The 1-hour chart shows entry timing.
When all timeframes align, trades work better.
When they conflict, you will struggle. This
is why YOU need multiple timeframe analysis.
Here's my timeframe system. Daily chart
for trend direction. 1-hour chart for
entry timing. Both must agree before I risk money.
I use a 10-period simple moving-average on daily
and 20-period on the hourly one.
You might say, “I don’t want to
juggle multiple charts.” But it’s worth it.
Last week I took a long trade on the hourly chart,
not realizing the daily average was sloping
downward. That daily line crushed my trade.
Here’s how YOU do it. Check a lower period
average on a higher time frame. Price
above it? Is it sloping up? That means
the long-term trend might be strong.
Now see a higher period average, on a lower chart.
If that’s also bullish, that’s more confirmation.
And never trade when timeframes disagree.
This filter alone will improve
YOUR win rate by 20-30%.
**CHAPTER 12: MOVING-AVERAGE REVERSION TRADES**
Now, most traders think moving averages
are only for trend following. Not really,
they're equally powerful for mean
reversion in the right conditions.
Mean reversion means price returns to
average after extreme moves. When price
gets too far from a moving average, it
usually snaps back like a rubber band.
You’ll be surprised how simple this reversion
plan can be. It might be dangerous if the
trend is super strong, but in a range or mild
trend, a reversion can bring quick profits.
I used to ignore reversion trades. Then
I realized that markets rarely move in a
straight line. Even in a robust uptrend, price
might get overheated and revert to the line.
If YOU see that price is extremely
distant from the average, that can
be a short-term fade opportunity. Just
watch for slope. If slope is steeply up,
it might be risky to fade. But if slope is
gentle or flat, a reversion trade can work.
The key is identifying when price has moved
too far. I use a simple rule. If price is
more than 3% away from the 200-period EMA, it's
extended. Extended price often reverts quickly.
I enter only if I see a divergence at the top or
bottom of the channel. Or if I see a trendline
breakout. That are my confirmation filters.
Look at this trade. Observe how price gapped
down 4% below the 200 EMA. That long trade was a
good candidate for reversion setup. Price was back
at the EMA by the next day. Easy 100 pip profit.
So here's how YOU implement this. Use envelopes,
or another reversion channel. When price moves
more than 3% away from YOUR moving average,
look for reversion trades back to the
average. Enter on the first sign of reversal,
after a divergence, or a trendline breakout.
And simply target the moving average.
**CHAPTER 13: ADAPTIVE MOVING AVERAGES**
Now very important, most traders pick a
fixed period. For example, they use a 50 period
average no matter the conditions. But an adaptive
moving-average adjusts its calculation
based on market volatility or price
behavior. That helps YOU respond better
if conditions shift from quiet to wild.
You see, regular moving averages never adjust to
market conditions. Adaptive moving averages change
their sensitivity based on market volatility.
When markets are trending strongly,
adaptive moving averages speed up to follow
the trend closely. When markets turn choppy,
they slow down to filter out noise.
Think of it like cruise control that
adjusts to road conditions.
The most popular adaptive
moving-average is the Kaufman one. It uses
an efficiency ratio to determine how much
to adapt. High efficiency means trending
market. Low efficiency means choppy market.
The result is a line that’s dynamic, not
static. It might hug price closer when things
get crazy and drift away when things settle.
Here's why this matters for YOUR moving-average
strategy. Fixed period moving averages give
false signals in changing conditions. But
adaptive moving averages adjust automatically.
I discovered Kaufman adaptive moving-average a
few years ago, after getting whipsawed repeatedly
during market transitions. My regular EMAs kept
giving false signals. The back test showed that
the adaptive average stayed smooth and reliable.
Compare the regular 20 EMA with a 20-period
adaptive average during trends and choppy period.
See how the adaptive average speeds
up to follow the trend closely.
Then it slows down to filter out noise
And a bonus tip: the adaptive average works
especially well during news events and during the
market open, when volatility changes rapidly.
**CHAPTER 14: MOVING-AVERAGE CLUSTERS**
Most people miss this completely,
but moving-average clusters create the strongest
support and resistance levels YOU'll ever see.
A cluster happens when multiple moving
averages converge at the same price
level. Instead of one moving average,
YOU have 2 or lines all sitting together.
If YOU see the 20, 50, and 100
averages all near the same price,
that can be a magnet for the market. Price
might stall there, bounce, or break with force.
Here's why clusters work so well. Each
moving-average represents a different
group of traders. The 20-period
represents short-term traders.
The 50-period represents medium-term traders.
The 200-period represents long-term traders.
When all these groups agree on a
price level, that level becomes
incredibly important. Bounces are sharp.
Breakouts are violent. No middle ground.
I hunt for clusters every morning before
the market opens. They show me exactly
where the big moves will happen that day.
Check this out! Observe how the 20, 50,
and 100-period moving averages all converged
around this area. Well, price bounced over
100 pips off that cluster level.
The plan is simple: if price bounces
off a cluster, trade the bounce direction. If
price breaks through a cluster with volume,
trade the breakout direction.
YOU now have many angles to refine
your own moving-average trading strategy.
Use each chapter’s insights in a way that
fits YOU. If YOU like quick scalping trades,
check slope changes or the bounce pattern.
If YOU prefer a big-picture method,
try multiple timeframes or envelopes.
If YOU love nuance, add
adaptive lines or clusters.
And remember what I showed YOU
about fake-outs and crossovers.
Now, if you're curious about
mastering more techniques, go ahead
and watch one of these videos next!