Big trading educators make fair
value gaps sound mysterious!
Truth is, they're just showing where
buyers and sellers couldn't agree!
They're just fancy words for
supply and demand imbalances!
So today I'll strip away the complexity, and show
you how to spot and trade them, easily!
Chapter 1: Introduction to Fair Value Gaps
Fair value gaps show up when price
moves fast, skipping over some levels.
These gaps happen when buyers
and sellers aren't balanced.
And traders pay attention to these gaps because
they can show where price might
turn around or keep going.
A fair value gap is a place where price
moved so fast, it left a blank space.
On smaller time frames, you can
see no trading happened there.
It's like a vacuum in the market.
But these gaps are important because
they often act like magnets for price.
And the market likes to fill these gaps.
This means price often comes back to these levels.
They are important because fair value gaps can
help you predict where price might go.
And they can also help you find good
places to enter or exit trades.
Chapter 2: The Theory Behind Fair Value Gaps
Markets are always trying to find the right
price for things. This is called price discovery.
It happens when buyers and
sellers agree on a price.
But sometimes, the market moves so fast that it
skips over some prices. This is how gaps form.
Fair value gaps show up when there's
not enough trading at certain prices.
It's like a jump in the market. These gaps
often happen when big players make large orders.
They can take all the available
trades, leaving a gap.
The market wasn't balanced. On one side, there
were more buyers or sellers than on the other.
And this imbalance can give us clues
about where the market might go next.
Fair value gaps often act like magnets.
And the market likes to fill these gaps.
It's like the market wants to go back
and check if the price is right.
Now, there are different types
of gaps. Some happen when the
market opens higher or lower than it closed.
Others, like fair value
gaps, happen during trading.
They all show times when the market moved
fast and left some prices untested.
Fair value gaps will help you
see the market's "memory".
It remembers these gaps and
often comes back to them.
This can help you predict where price might go
or find good places to enter or exit trades.
Now, let’s address the elephant in the room.
There are hundreds of fair value gaps every
day, on all time frame. If you trade every gap
you see, you’ll slowly burn you’re your account.
The reality is that fair value gaps
are just one piece of the puzzle.
On their own, they don’t give reliable signals.
They work with other market signs to give a
full picture. We’ll talk about this later.
Chapter 3: Identifying Fair Value Gaps on Charts
Now let's talk about spotting
fair value gaps on your charts.
We're looking at a specific three-candle pattern.
For a bullish gap, check if the upper shadow of
the first candle doesn't touch the lower shadow
of the third candle in the sequence. The
space between them is your Fair Value Gap.
For a bearish gap, check if the
lower shadow of the first candle
doesn't touch the upper shadow of the third
candle. This area is your Fair Value Gap.
The market makes these gaps when big players
make aggressive moves. This happens because
there's not enough trading activity in that price
zone - creating what we call a liquidity void.
Think of it like this: A Fair Value Gap shows up
during a quick price move where one big player
grabs all the available trades. This creates
a space where almost no trading happened.
The trick is to spot when
these candles don't overlap.
So in a bullish gap, the high of the first
candle shouldn't touch the low of the third.
In a bearish gap, the low of the first
shouldn't touch the high of the third.
When you're looking for these gaps, pay
attention to the market structure too.
Bullish gaps often show up at support.
Bearish gaps tend to form after
a rise to resistance.
Like I said, in theory,
these gaps show up when big players make
moves. They can grab all the trades at once,
marking an imbalance on the chart.
Chapter 4: Fair Value Gaps and Market Structure
So fair value gaps are closely
tied to market structure.
They often form at key points
in the market's movement,
giving us clues about where price might go next.
In a bullish market structure, fair value gaps
typically form during strong upward moves.
The gap shows where buyers were so eager,
that they skipped over some price levels.
This can be a sign that the upward trend is
strong and likely to continue.
In a bearish market structure,
fair value gaps form during sharp downward moves.
Here, sellers are pushing the price down so fast,
that some levels get skipped.
This can indicate that the bearish
trend has strength behind it.
Fair value gaps can also mark
potential turning points in the market structure.
If price returns to fill a gap and then reverses,
it might signal a continuation
in the existing trend.
When looking at market structure,
consider different timeframes.
A fair value gap on a smaller timeframe
might not be visible on a larger one.
But it can still affect how
price moves in the short term.
Remember, structure is all about
support and resistance levels.
Fair value gaps often act as these levels.
Price tends to respect them, either bouncing
off or breaking through them with force.
In ranging markets, fair value gaps
can mark the edges of the range.
Price might bounce between these gaps,
creating a clear structure to work with.
But please understand that these gaps
don't exist in isolation.
They're part of the
bigger picture of market structure.
They work alongside other elements like trends,
support and resistance, and market phases.
If you trade them on their own, you have
small chances to make profits.
So when you're analyzing structure,
look for patterns of higher highs and
higher lows in an uptrend, or lower
highs and lower lows in a downtrend.
Fair value gaps often form during
the strong moves between these swing points.
Chapter 5: Time Frames for Fair Value Gap Trading
A quick word on time frames.
There can be hundreds
of gaps in a single trading day.
And they can appear on various time frames.
On shorter time frames, fair value gaps are
more frequent, but have less significance.
They can be useful for scalping or day trading,
when looking for quick entries and exits.
But these gaps might get filled quickly,
so you need to be fast to act on them.
Longer time frames, like 4
hour or daily, show fewer gaps.
But when they do appear,
they often have more impact.
These gaps can influence price
movements for several days.
I personally like to use a multiple time frame
analysis when working with fair value gaps.
For instance, you might spot a gap on
a higher time frame, mark the zone,
but then zoom in to a lower time frame
to fine-tune their entry or exit points.
Remember, price is fractal. Patterns that appear
on monthly charts can also be seen
on daily or even 5-minute charts.
This principle applies to
fair value gaps as well.
Chapter 6: Entry Strategies
for Fair Value Gap Trades
When trading fair value gaps, timing
your entry is makes the difference.
The plan is wait for price to come back
to the gap before entering your trade.
This strategy works well because
these gaps are pulling price back
to areas where little trading occurred.
Think of this gap as a vacuum in the
market that needs to be filled.
From a supply and demand view,
here's what happens.
First, a big market
player enters with massive orders.
They hit the market so hard and fast
that price jumps, creating that gap.
During this jump, regular traders can't
keep up with the speed, leaving an area
where trading activity is super thin.
When the gap forms, it creates an imbalance.
On one side, you have lots of orders filled,
but on the other side, there's
barely any trading activity.
This imbalance creates a "zone of
interest" that big players watch closely.
So the smart move is waiting
for price to return to this gap.
That’s because market makers must
find fair value for their positions.
They use these gaps as reference points.
And when price returns to fill the gap, it's often
because market makers are balancing their books.
You'll notice something interesting when price
comes back to these gaps - it's trying to
restore balance between buyers and sellers.
This balancing act happens from 3 reasons.
First, market makers need to fill their
unfilled orders from the original move.
Also, other traders spot the imbalance
and try to profit from it.
And finally, the market naturally
seeks equilibrium at these levels.
The key to trading these returns lies
in understanding the original
move that created the gap.
If it was a strong upward move, (a bullish
displacement), the gap below becomes a
potential buy zone when price returns.
The opposite is true for downward moves.
Think about the mechanics: When that initial big
player moved the market so fast, they left behind
other traders who missed their chance to enter.
When price returns to the gap,
these traders often jump in, adding to
the trading activity at these levels.
So from a pure supply and demand perspective, the
fair value gap represents a level where demand
suddenly overwhelmed supply, in an upward gap,
or supply overwhelmed demand, in a downward gap.
The market needs to test these levels
again to confirm if that imbalance was
temporary or part of a larger trend.
The return to this area often shows
clear price action signals.
You might see price slow down
as it approaches the gap, or notice smaller
timeframe consolidation patterns forming.
Watch how price behaves when
it returns to fill the gap.
Clean, swift moves through the gap
might indicate that more movement in
that direction is coming. Choppy, slow price
action might suggest that the level is being
heavily contested between buyers and sellers.
So for a bullish setup, wait for price to return
to the lower edge of the gap. If price
bounces off this level, it could signal
a good entry point for a long trade.
For a bearish setup, watch for price
to come back to the upper edge of the gap.
If it struggles to break above this level,
it might be a good spot to enter a short trade.
While waiting for price to return to the gap,
look for specific candlestick patterns to
fine-tune your entry. These patterns can give
you extra confirmation before you enter a trade.
For instance, if you see a bullish engulfing
pattern form at the lower edge of a fair value
gap, it could signal a strong buying pressure.
This might be a good time to enter a long trade.
A long wick at the upper edge of a bearish gap
could indicate selling pressure,
implying a potential short entry.
FVGs with Break of Structure
Fair value gaps with a Break of Structure
create powerful trade setups, because they combine
two major elements that show us exactly where
big players are active in the market.
A break in market structure happens
when price runs through previous swing
highs or lows with force. But this break
needs an gap inside it to count as valid.
Picture the market moving up in a series of
higher highs and higher lows.
Then suddenly, price drops
hard through a previous swing low.
During this drop, if we see a gap where
the candle wicks don't overlap, that's our gap.
Big players pushed price down with real force.
This area become a magnet
that pull price back later.
Another example.
You see price moving up, making higher highs.
Then a large player hits the market hard,
breaking below a key swing low.
During this break, three candles
form - the middle one creates a gap. This gap
implies the break in structure might be real.
This combination work well
because it shows 2 things.
The market structure break
tells us the trend is changing.
And the gap shows us exactly where
big players left their footprint.
The presence of both signals means
more than just a random price move.
It shows intentional,
institutional trading activity.
When price returns to these levels later, it
often finds strong support or resistance.
What makes this setup special is the
"vacuum effect" created by the gap.
Remember that during the fast move that broke
market structure, some orders didn't get filled.
This creates an area where price
needs to return to find "fair value".
You'll notice these setups work
best when 3 condition are met:
First, when the break in
structure is clean and strong,
The fair value gap forms right at
the point where structure breaks.
And third, price moves away
quickly after creating the gap.
So when market makers move price fast
enough to break structure and leave
a gap, they're showing their hand.
They're telling us they have strong
interest at these levels.
The same for a buy signal.
Look for a clear break of previous swing highs.
Check for a gap forming during this break.
Then wait for price to return
to the fair value gap level.
And watch how price reacts when it hits the zone.
The setup becomes even stronger when the gap
coincides with the actual break point in market
structure. This creates a "double reference" point
that market makers use to balance their books.
The liquidity void that comes with the fair value
gap adds another layer of confirmation.
It shows that one side of the market was
completely overwhelmed during the move.
This imbalance needs to be corrected,
which is why price often returns to these levels.
So after spotting the break in structure and gap,
don't chase the initial move.
The best trades come when price revisits
these levels and shows clear reaction.
This gap becomes a key reference level
for the new trend direction.
FVGs with supply/demand zones
Supply and demand zones mark the spots
where smart money builds positions.
Think of them as launching
pads where big trades start.
When you find a fair value gap near
these zones, you've spotted a place
where institutional traders showed their
hand twice - first building positions,
then moving price fast enough to leave a gap.
The strategy works through a simple market
truth - price wants to trade where it hasn't
traded before. And those gaps represent prices
where little to no trading happened.
Again, markets need to fill these
gaps to find fair value. That's why
price often returns to these levels.
Watch how this plays out on charts.
First, you'll see price moving normally.
Then suddenly, a large candle
appears with no overlap to
nearby candles - that's your gap.
This tells you someone big just
moved with purpose. If this happens near a
supply or demand zone, pay extra attention.
The process follows clear steps. Price
builds up in a supply or demand zone.
Then it moves explosively, creating the gap.
This fast move shows institutional conviction.
Later, price must return to fill this gap.
Another signal. You see here a clean fair
value gap, where candle shadows don't overlap.
The bigger the gap, the stronger the signal.
As this gap form near this demand
zone, you've found a sweet spot.
Then you wait for price to return to the FVG area.
Watch how it reacts. Strong moves often
follow once the gap starts filling.
In combination with a supply or demand
zone, I don’t mind if price completely
fills the gap, and even moves past it.
I always wait for it to return to the
origin point, to the demand zone.
The technical reason this works ties to liquidity.
Gaps mark areas with little trading activity.
When they sit near supply or demand
zones, you get two powerful forces
working together - the need to fill the
gap and the strength of the original zone.
Your edge comes from spotting these
combinations early. Look for clean gaps.
Check if they formed near
strong supply/demand zones.
Also, remember the previous chapter, look if
this move caused a break in market structure.
These setups offer clear entry
points with defined risk.
This is a clear example of
how big players move markets.
They build positions in zones, create gaps with
fast moves, then let price return to fill them.
Each step leaves clues on
charts through price action.
Price moves this way because
markets seek liquidity.
This creates a rhythm you can
trade – accumulation, expansion,
gap creation, then gap filling.
FVGs in Premium/Discount Zones
Fair Value Gaps in premium or discount zones
show where smart money plans their moves.
Market makers work in
specific ways at these spots.
In discount zones, they start buying.
In premium zones, they start selling.
This creates a rhythm in the market - a
back and forth movement you can trade.
The power of this setup comes
from market maker behavior.
They need to do fair valuation for
both their entry and exit positions.
This means they look at premium and discount
zones as places to start big moves.
You need to see the bigger picture first. Look
at the total range of the larger price move.
Find where price sits compared
to recent highs and lows.
Then spot the reference points market makers
watch - the fair value gaps and liquidity voids.
The middle ground, called equilibrium, marks
the 50% point between swing highs and lows.
This helps you know if price
sits in premium or discount.
Market mechanics make this
work. After big market moves,
most traders chase the trend.
Smart money does the opposite.
They expect a pullback before the next move.
These pullbacks often happen right at fair
value gaps in premium or discount areas.
The process shows up clearly on charts.
Sharp price runs leave behind gaps -
areas where little trading happened.
These spots become targets for future trades.
When they sit in premium or discount zones,
they mark prime trading opportunities.
So watch how price behaves in these
zones. In premium areas with a fair
value gap, look for selling pressure.
In discount areas with gaps,
watch for buying pressure.
The mix of zone location and the
gap, creates stronger signals.
Remember what we talked before,
market structure plays a key role too.
True breaks in structure often leave gaps
behind. These gaps confirm the break's strength.
When they form in premium or discount
zones, they show even more power.
Again, the best trades come when multiple
factors line up - zone location, gap presence,
break in structure and clear price action.
Market makers use these areas to build positions.
They accumulate in discount zones
and distribute in premium zones.
And finding gaps at these spots shows
you where they plan to move price next.
The strategy works because it follows market
maker goals. They need to find fair value for
positions. Premium and discount zones
mark places where they take action.
Fair value gaps in these zones show
exactly where they moved with force.
Best trades develop this way. Price
reaches a premium or discount zone.
You find an FVG nearby. Then
price shows reversal signs.
The whole process repeats in cycles. Price
moves between fair value, premium, and discount.
And each cycle leaves gaps behind.
FVGs - Fibonacci confluence
Fibonacci levels match natural market moves,
and when they line up with Fair Value Gaps,
they create strong trade opportunities.
Think of it like using two different
tools that point to the same spot -
it makes that spot much more special.
The magic happens because different
types of traders watch different things.
Some traders only trade fair value
gaps, while others only use Fibonacci.
When these levels match up, both groups
of traders see a good trade opportunity.
This creates more buying or selling
pressure at that exact spot.
The golden zone between the 50% and 61%
Fibonacci levels attracts smart money attention.
When a gap sits in this area, you've found
a place where two powerful forces meet.
This double confirmation
makes your trades stronger.
In an uptrend, look for gaps that line up with
Fibonacci levels for buying opportunities.
In a downtrend, search for gaps matching
Fibonacci levels for selling chances.
Think about how markets move. After a strong
push, price pulls back to test previous levels.
Smart traders use Fibonacci to
find these pullback targets.
When these levels match a fair value gap, they
show where big players plan their next moves.
The process starts with
finding the right swing points.
Draw your Fibonacci from the highest high to
the lowest low in the recent price action.
This gives you the framework for finding the sweet
spots where a fair value gap might matter most.
A lot of big traders watch these same levels.
Some use Fibonacci to plan their trades,
looking for spots where they
can build or exit positions.
And when you see a fair value gap at these
levels, you might want to take action.
The real power comes from understanding
what these confluences mean.
Fibonacci levels themselves don't
act as support or resistance.
Instead, they help you find
liquidity blocks - places
where fair value gaps show market imbalances.
Then watch how price reacts at these spots.
A strong gap needs a big, clean
separation between candle shadows.
When this gap lines up with key Fibonacci
levels, especially the 50 and 61% zone,
you've found a high-probability setup.
The strategy works because it combines
two types of market psychology.
Fibonacci shows natural pullback
points where traders expect reactions.
Fair value gaps show where big money
moved fast enough to leave traces.
And together, they create stronger signals.
Remember that trends make this work better. In a
strong uptrend, gaps that line up with Fibonacci
levels make great buying zones.
The opposite works in downtrends.
The trend gives you another layer of
confluence, making your trades even stronger.
The plan is simple. Wait for price to reach
the Fibonacci level, where your gap sits.
Look for signs that price respects
both the level and the gap.
The best trades come when price pierces
the confluence zone, and rejects it with
a strong candlestick signal. I look mainly for
candles with large wicks, or engulfing patterns.
Time frames matter too. While this
strategy works on any chart, I often
watch the 4-hour and the hourly charts.
These longer views help you spot the
strongest confluences between
Fibonacci and fair value gaps.
Again, the technical reason this works
ties to liquidity. Big players need
certain price levels to build positions.
They use Fibonacci to find these spots.
When they move fast enough to create gaps
at these levels, they show their hand twice.
Trading becomes simpler with this
approach. You don't chase price.
Instead, you wait for it to reach these special
spots where Fibonacci and fair value gaps meet.
This patience puts you in position
for high-probability moves.
The whole process flows naturally. Markets
move up or down with force, creating gaps.
Price pulls back to Fibonacci levels.
When these align, you find spots where
smart money are likely to act.
Think of confluence like different
layers. Each layer, like the gap, Fibonacci,
trend direction, the candlestick confirmation,
makes your trade setup stronger.
The more layers of confluence you have, the
higher the probability of your trade working out.
And use these confluence zones as areas, not exact
prices. Markets rarely turn exactly at a specific
price. Instead, they often react within a zone.
So give your trades room to breathe by
thinking in zones, rather than exact prices!
I prefer this approach because it also
helps you avoid many fake breakouts.
Instead of chasing price, you're waiting for
it to return to these high-probability zones.
This patient approach will keep you out of those
common breakout traps that catch many traders.
Now, if you want to learn
other smart money tactics,
you need to watch one of these videos next.