Most of the information you can find online
is usually about retail trading.
If you look for institutional or smart money
trading, you won’t find much about it.
So today we’ll talk about smart money concepts,
a topic widely discussed among price action
traders, and popularized by ICT (known as
the Inner Circle Trader).
So, smart money trading, what is it?
It’s a style that leverages institutional
trading methods to gain an edge in the market
and avoid getting caught in the banks' liquidity
traps.
Institutions, such as banks and hedge funds,
have significant influence on the market due
to their substantial trading volumes.
And as a retail trader, you should aim to
align yourself with these institutional players.
Think of these institutions as the whales
in the ocean and us as the little fish swimming
alongside them.
You want to understand how they enter the
market and follow their lead to ensure your
safety and protection.
Before we begin, let's first explore some
key terms that will be used throughout this
trading course.
So, smart money refers to the larger players
in the market, such as banks and institutions.
Liquidity represents the pool of stop losses
and pending buy/sell limit orders.
Mitigation refers to the point where smart
money breaks even on a losing position.
Break of structure reveals the strength or
weakness in a trend.
A CHOCH represents a change in character in
the order flow, indicating a possible trend
reversal.
An order block is area where there has been
a large concentration of limit orders waiting
to be executed.
Fair value gap is an imbalance in price created
by a large order.
It may sound complicated at first, but don’t
worry, these smart money concepts are not
something new or invented, but rather revolves
around classic principles of market structure,
supply and demand, accumulation and distribution,
and price returning to previous areas of acceptance.
BOS & CHOCH
Let’s begin with the market structure.
Understanding market structure is crucial
for analyzing and trading the charts effectively.
It provides you vital information about the
current phase of the market.
In an uptrend, prices generally move higher
over time.
This is characterized by the formation of
higher highs (HH) and higher lows (HL).
Each low point is higher than the previous
one, indicating a bullish market sentiment.
In contrast, a downtrend exhibits lower highs
(LH) and lower lows (LL).
Each high point is lower than the preceding
one, reflecting a bearish market sentiment.
Lastly, a sideways trend or a ranging market
is characterized by the absence of clear highs
and lows.
Prices fluctuate within a tight range, indicating
indecisiveness among market participants.
One of the most important aspects in the market
structure, are the shifts above or below previous
swing highs or lows, leading to trend changes
or continuations.
The first concept is the break of structure.
Breaks of structure play a significant role
in determining the strength or weakness of
buyers and sellers.
Break of Structure (BOS) is used to describe
a significant price movement that surpasses
a level of support or resistance on a chart,
in the direction of the previous trend.
This is very important.
A BOS is simply a break above a previous higher
high in an uptrend, or a break below a lower
low in a downtrend.
I must admit that the break of structure terminology
used by ICT confuses me a bit.
This term doesn’t imply a continuation in
a trend.
Maybe I got this wrong.
But, anyway, in an uptrend, when you see a
market making higher highs and higher lows,
you mark the most recent swing high, and if
you have another impulse move closing above
this point, with several candles, then you
found a BOS.
In a downtrend, when you see a market making
lower lows and lower highs, you mark the most
recent swing low, and if you have another
move closing below this low, with several
candles, again, you have found a BOS.
On the other hand, a Change of Character (ChoCh)
represents a trend reversal in the market
after a break of highs or lows.
A change of character describes a sudden and
significant shift in the price action of a
market.
For example, let’s take this market that
has been in a downtrend, making lower highs
and lower lows.
Once the price breaks above this previous
major swing high, this is a change of character
that signals a possible reversal of the downtrend,
as buyers have taken control of the market.
If price continues to make new higher highs
and higher lows, we’ve transitioned into
an uptrend, we you start looking for BOS patterns
once again.
Here, price has been in an uptrend, making
higher highs and higher lows.
Observe the previous breaks of structure,
in the direction of the trend.
Following this break of structure, the price
reverses, forming a new lower low, signaling
a potential trend reversal.
After a minor pullback, the price begins creating
lower lows and lower highs, indicating a new
bearish trend.
So price changed its trend, indicating a change
of character in the market.
The previous bullish trend has now shifted
into a bearish one.
And now you’re looking for new BOS patterns,
in a downtrend.
It’s simple and easy, and you probably knew
these concepts before, with different terms.
So, BOS means continuation in market structure,
CHOCH means reversal.
At least, this is how I see them.
Fair value gaps
Now let’s talk about fair value gaps.
This ICT concept builds upon fundamental market
structure principles, price action, and gap
analysis.
Fair value gaps are used to detect market
inefficiencies or imbalances.
Sometimes you will see them labeled as inefficiencies.
These imbalances arise when buying or selling
pressure is significant, resulting in a large
upward or downward move, leaving behind an
imbalance in the market.
Let's start by examining this chart.
You'll notice that most of the time, when
we have consecutive candlesticks, the price
tends to retrace and leave wicks on both sides
of the candles.
However, in certain instances, we observe
candles with no overlap on either side, like
this candle with one candle to the left and
one to the right.
This phenomenon is what we refer to as a fair
value gap.
The idea behind fair value gaps is that the
market will eventually come back to these
inefficiencies in the market before continuing
in the same direction as the initial impulsive
move.
If you’re familiar with supply and demand
trading, it’s the same principle.
If you are a price action trader, you can
use these imbalances as entry or even exit
points in the market.
For a fair value gap to develop, there must
be a set of three candles characterized by
heavy buying or selling in the same direction.
When there is a large move in either direction,
a gap will be formed between the first candle's
wick and the wick of the last candle, as you
can see here.
In this example, the price movement doesn’t
have a Fair Value Gap, as the previous candle's
high level has counterbalanced the low level
of the third candle.
This price action is considered to be balanced.
The key lies in identifying these fair value
gaps at levels that provide a trading edge
or a strong signal.
Specifically, you want to look for fair value
gaps that coincide with a break in market
structure caused by an impulsive move, or
a change of character.
The area left by this fair value gap becomes
an attractive region to seek entry opportunities
on pullbacks.
For instance, consider a market in an uptrend.
As the price retraces and breaks below a significant
swing low, the market structure shifts lower,
we have a change of character, indicating
potential short opportunities.
Now, we keep an eye out for a retracement,
at a fair value gap, that allows us to enter
short positions based on this shift in market
structure.
In the case of a bullish setup, the fair value
gap operates in reverse.
We witness an upward market movement, followed
by a pullback and another impulsive move that
breaks the previous swing high.
This breakout leaves a fair value gap between
these three candles, with no wick overlap
on either side of the middle candle.
You then scout for pullbacks within this range
to enter long positions.
Identifying Fair Value Gaps (FVGs) in the
markets can be relatively straightforward.
However, if you need extra assistance, there
are numerous free indicators available on
TradingView that can help you in detecting
these imbalances.
I recommend you add this indicator, by Nephew
SAM.
And I advise you to first focus on utilizing
Fair Value Gaps for trend continuation after
a significant impulsive move.
As I previously said, you can anticipate the
price to return to these Fair Value Gaps before
continuing in the same direction as the impulse
move.
You simply wait for the price to reach the
area of interest and then look for a trigger,
targeting a trend continuation.
If the fair value gaps are wider, Fibonacci
retracement levels can be used to refine entry
points.
By drawing a Fibonacci tool from relevant
swing points, such as the high and low of
the fair value gap, the 50% level can serve
as an alternative entry point.
This approach ensures a tighter risk-reward
ratio, although it may result in missing some
initial entries if the price bounces before
reaching the 50% level.
Moving on to another example, let's examine
a resistance level, on a lower timeframe,
such as the five-minute chart.
After breaking this resistance and undergoing
an impulsive upward move, we see a fair value
gap is left behind, providing a potential
trading opportunity on pullbacks.
Once again, it's crucial to identify them
in areas where you expect retracements that
align with the prevailing trend.
Here, we witness a market that breaks below
a swing low, signaling a short entry opportunity.
A fair value gap is present in the area between
this wick low and this wick high.
Order blocks
Now let me address another concept that has
gained popularity, namely the order blocks.
If you followed my channel before, you’ll
realize that this concept is not something
new or invented but rather revolves around
the principles of supply and demand and price
returning to previous areas of acceptance.
Banks use special orders for buying, selling,
taking profit, and closing the orders.
When banks want to open a position with volume,
they do not randomly place a position to upset
the price and trigger their order at a worse
price that may result in lowering their profit.
So, they try to split their positions into
small and manageable blocks.
A Bullish Order Block is the last down candle
or series of down candles before an upward
impulse price move.
A Bullish Order Block will act as a support
for the price to run higher.
A Bearish Order Block is the last up candle
or series of up candles before a downward
impulse price move.
A Bearish Order Block will act as a resistance
for the price to run lower.
Now, it's essential to understand that order
blocks should not be identified everywhere
on the charts, but rather in specific locations.
You want to enter trades in areas where price
retraces back into previous broken swing areas,
providing the best risk-reward scenarios.
In the case of a bullish order block, we observe
a consolidation or candle formation where
buyers take control, absorbing the selling
pressure at the bottom.
This leads to a breakout above a previous
swing high.
We then look for a retracement back into the
area where the price broke out, which serves
as a potential entry point.
Similarly, in a bearish order block, we have
a market trending downward, followed by a
consolidation.
A downward impulsive move breaks the market
structure to the downside.
We then wait for price to retrace back into
the release point or the area just before
the move occurred.
This becomes an opportunity to enter short
trades, placing the stop loss above the swing
high.
These are basically the rally – base – rally
and the drop-base-drop formations in supply
and demand trading.
You target these order blocks for continuation
trades in the direction of the previous trend.
It's worth mentioning that fair value gaps
often align with order blocks.
While these two concepts are closely related,
fair value gaps tend to provide earlier entry
opportunities compared to order blocks.
When an Order Block forms with a Fair Value
Gap to its right, this makes it a high probability
Order Block.
And, when an Order Block does not have a Fair
Value Gap to its right, this makes it a low
probability Order Block, and the price tends
to run the stops below or above the Order
Block.
Order blocks are also formed when the market
transitions from an uptrend to a downtrend,
and vice versa.
A bullish order block, or a drop-base-rally
demand zone, will be found when the market
changes from moving down to moving up.
A bearish order block, or a rally-base-drop
supply zone, forms when the market reverses
from moving higher to moving lower.
Let’s consider a downtrend.
One of the steps mentioned by ICT is the violation
of a previous swing low before the upward
push and the confirmation of the breakout
above the swing high, the change of character.
This price move traps traders who were on
the wrong side, adding fuel to the buying
pressure.
When price returns to the order block area,
sellers who were trapped in their positions
look to close out their trades, further fueling
the buying side.
Additionally, traders who missed the initial
rally are drawn to this area, perceiving it
as an opportunity to enter, resulting in an
upward continuation of the trend.
Here’s another example, involving a bearish
order block.
The recent market structure indicates an uptrend.
Price formed a new swing high, declined, then
formed a swing low.
Prices then rallied again to exceed the previous
high (making a higher high).
This a BOS.
Price then fell to form a new lower low.
A change of character this time.
The previous move trapped buying traders on
the wrong side.
As prices start to rise again, we need to
find an order block.
And when price returns to the order block
area, buyers who were trapped in their positions
look to close out their trades, further fueling
the selling side.
Additionally, traders who missed the initial
down move get their chance to enter, resulting
in a downward continuation of the trend.
For more precise entries, especially on higher
timeframes, if the order block has a wider
range, Fibonacci retracement levels can be
used, particularly between the 50%, 61.8%
and 78.6% levels.
Depending on the context, you may focus on
the candle body or include the wick as well,
when you draw the order block.
Just remember, you need to find the last bullish
candle before a down move, and the last bearish
candle before an up move.
To me personally, order blocks are the same
as supply and demand zones.
They represent areas of high volume accumulation
before a major move occurs.
Whatever you call them, these are high probability
areas to initiate trades from.
Liquidity
Understanding liquidity is a fundamental concept
in smart money trading.
Liquidity acts as a magnet for price, as price
is constantly in search of a place to transact
and either accumulate or distribute positions.
Liquidity primarily refers to the presence
of orders at various price levels.
These orders influence the price movements,
often causing highs and lows in the market
to be breached.
So, where does liquidity form?
We can identify older highs and previous lows
as liquidity points.
Equal highs and equal lows are other liquidity
areas.
Liquidity can be found along trend lines,
within chart patterns, at support and resistance
levels.
Essentially, liquidity refers to pending orders
placed above or below these points.
Your goal is to understand the major areas
where liquidity is concentrated.
First, analyze the trend—where is the price
currently, where has it been, and where it
might be headed next?
When you ask yourself, "Where is the price?"
there should be three possible answers: at
a premium, at a discount, or at the mean.
When you analyze about where the price has
been, you can identify its origin, pinpointing
the major swing point that led to its current
level.
Finally, when considering where the price
is going, you have a few options: it could
head toward a significant liquidity zone or
a supply and demand area, or an order block.
Keep in mind that liquidity is continuously
generated.
When examining liquidity, you can view it
as a reason for markets to move higher or
lower.
For instance, in a downtrend with a clear
trend line, you can interpret it as a potential
reason for prices to head higher in the near
future, despite their current downward trajectory.
Price enjoys creating liquidity, moving through
existing liquidity, and generating more liquidity
along the way.
To simplify this concept, let's consider a
trading range.
Below the support level, we can expect to
find stop-loss orders placed by buyers.
Above the resistance level, there will be
stop losses of sellers.
If the market breaks below the support level,
sell trades will be triggered, while a break
above the resistance level will activate buy
trades.
In this context, liquidity refers to the collection
of orders present on both sides of the market
within the range.
Buy side liquidity represents the presence
of buy stop orders, which are placed above
the resistance level.
These orders are accompanied by stop-loss
orders from sellers who have entered their
positions below the resistance level.
The activation of buy stop orders and the
triggering of stop-loss orders lead to an
influx of buying liquidity.
Institutional participants, who often have
substantial positions to sell, require liquidity
in the form of willing buyers.
By pushing the market above the resistance
level, they can access this liquidity, which
results in their significant selling orders
being executed.
On the other hand, sell side liquidity mirrors
the same principle but in the opposite direction.
In a range where the lows form a support level,
buyers are present at multiple levels with
stop-loss orders below this area.
Below the support level, there are also sell
stop orders, waiting to be triggered if the
market continues to decline.
When the market pushes lower, these sell stops
and stop-loss orders will contribute to selling
liquidity.
The accumulation of these selling orders provides
an opportunity for a participant with significant
buying power to enter the market, potentially
causing a reversal and an upward rally.
Remember this: for big institutions, opening
large orders in the market requires reaching
these liquidity points.
And, understanding buy and sell side liquidity
can provide insights into the intentions and
actions of institutional participants.
As a retail trader, if you frequently experience
stop-outs due to small price movements, it
is likely because you are providing liquidity
to larger market players.
In this example, you can clearly observe the
formation of buy and sell side liquidity.
The market often breaches both sides of the
range, triggering buy or sell orders and stop
losses, which leads to substantial price movements.
By understanding these dynamics, you can incorporate
this knowledge into your trading strategy
or gain a better comprehension of market movements.
So start studying historical market data and
conduct your backtest, so you can witness
yourself the significance of this concept,
whether you develop a trading system centered
on liquidity or use it to avoid entering trades
at major support or resistance levels that
are likely to be breached.
Premium/Discount
Now let’s talk about the concepts of discount
and premium.
It's a simple concept where we mark out a
range, or a swing, using a Fibonacci retracement
with only the 50% level marked.
When marking premium and discount areas, you
have the choice of selecting any major leg
of price action or range on the chart in front
of you.
The line in the middle, the 50% level, represents
the fair value.
The premium and discount concept is straightforward.
You aim to sell when prices are in the premium
range, meaning you sell at higher prices.
And you buy when prices are in the discount
range, which corresponds to the lower 50%
of the range.
First, let’s explore the discount and premium
during a break of structure or change of character.
To place the Fibs, you need to locate where
the market experiences a break in market structure.
Once you identify that point, it becomes your
reference for applying the tool.
And you mark it from the low to the high of
that range.
Now, if you’re looking for a long entry,
you should focus on areas that are not in
a premium or above the 50% Fibonacci level.
For instance, if you have a fair value gap
or an order block right here, above the fair
value line, you wouldn't consider it for a
long entry.
Instead, you would concentrate on this area
for potential long positions.
Similarly, if we observe a shift in market
structure, a change of character, followed
by a retracement, you would be interested
in shorting above the middle line.
You draw your Fibonacci retracement from the
high to the low, and the shorting zone would
be in the premium area.
To be honest, nothing new here, if you’re
familiar with Fibonacci retracements, you
already know this concept.
I consider the premium and discount concept
a great tool to use as a confluence, but being
overly reliant on it can cause you to miss
good quality trade setups just because they
aren’t in premium or discount.
As a tip, price tends to trend and respect
premium and discount in the longer term rather
than in the short to medium term.
Mitigation
Another ICT concept is mitigation.
This is how I define it.
Mitigation is the process of reducing losses
or offsetting unfavorable positions in the
market.
The concept of mitigation can be visualized
by combining it with market structure analysis.
So let’s consider this upward trend, it
means there are buy orders pushing the price
higher.
When we see a break in market structure or
a change of character, such as breaking the
previous higher low, it indicates that more
sellers are entering the market.
This doesn't mean that the market will immediately
go down significantly, but it does suggest
a temporary bearish sentiment in the market.
Now, let's consider the role of banks and
institutions.
Due to the size of their orders, they can't
buy or sell randomly at any given level.
They often need more time and multiple revisits
to accumulate or distribute their positions.
And don’t think smart money have perfect
entries or strategies.
They are susceptible to losses, as we are.
They might have buy positions for this price
move, and sell positions in this wave.
To mitigate this loss, the market may return
to the previous level or even slightly higher
before continuing the downward move.
This action allows institutions to mitigate
their buy positions and stack sell positions,
effectively reducing their risk.
They continue to accumulate or distribute
sell positions, pushing the market further
down.
This is how I view mitigation.
It involves mitigating losses from previous
positions, entering new sell positions, and
pushing the market in the desired direction.
The goal is to bring the price back to a fair
value for institutions and continue the downward
movement.
I personally prefer using the 4-hour or H1
time frames, but feel free to use lower or
higher timeframes based on your preference.
To begin, you need to identify recent market
structure.
If we analyze this move, we can observe a
higher high than the previous high, followed
by a pullback and a new higher high.
Now, this higher high was created starting
from this previous higher low, which is located
right here.
If this level gets violated to the downside,
we can expect a potential return to this area,
possibly slightly above it, before the market
continues its downward move.
Once we witness this break, indicated by a
strong candle, we can start looking for potential
selling setups.
Focus on the fact that those who continued
to hold long positions from the previous high
would be in a loss at this point.
They would want to mitigate that risk by initiating
sell positions.
This is the subject for another video, but
you can switch to the one-hour timeframe or
zoom in further on the 15-minute chart, to
closely examine the price action.
After breaking the previous level, you would
anticipate a retracement to the upside.
You’ll often see bullish momentum on lower
timeframes, inducing traders to go long.
However, it's crucial to understand that this
is part of market manipulation.
As price reaches back up, look for short opportunities.
In this case, you are capitalizing on the
market's manipulation and the potential loss-mitigation
efforts of those who held long positions.
Now, all these smart money concepts will help
you to read the market better and make better
decisions.
But, they are missing one important piece
of the puzzle, and that is the volume.
Trading without volume is one it is one of
the biggest mistakes you could make.
I highly encourage you to watch one of these
trading courses next, to learn more about
how to add the volume component into your
strategies.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time.