Look at this breakout. Every textbook on
Earth tells you to buy the retest. Right
here. That's a trap. That's where they
want your stop-loss. Now watch. That
wasn't a retest. That was a stop hunt.
And that's the real entry.
You see, everything you've been taught
about breakout retests is a lie. A lie
designed to do one thing. Make you the
liquidity for the smart money. So, let's
crack the code. To beat their trap, you
only need to know three secret moves.
Here's the first one right now. Let me
show you what's really happening when
the market retests a breakout level.
Most traders think it's random. They
think the market just decides to come
back and test the level for no reason.
But here's what they're missing. When
that breakout happens, there are two
groups of traders in the market. You
have the breakout traders. These are the
small guys who placed their orders right
at the level waiting for the break. And
then you have the smart money, the big
players. Now watch this closely. When
the breakout finally comes, all those
retail orders get filled. The breakout
traders are now in profit. They're
thinking, "Finally, I caught the move."
But the smart money, they didn't enter
at the breakout. They entered way
earlier when nobody was looking. They've
been sitting in profit for a while now.
So what happens next? The smart money
starts taking profits. They're not
greedy. They don't need to ride the
entire move. And that profit taking is
what pushes the market back toward the
breakout level. It's not random. It's
not the market testing anything. It's
smart money cashing out while retail
traders are just getting started. Think
about it from the retail traders
perspective. You entered at the
breakout. You were in profit. Now you're
watching that profit shrink as the
market comes back toward your entry. And
what do you do? You get scared. You
close your trade while you still have
some profit left. Different traders
panic at different times. The closer the
market gets to the breakout level, the
more traders bail out. And when they
close their trades, they're putting
opposite orders into the market. Orders
that the smart money is happy to take.
Let me show you something most traders
never notice. When you see a breakout
happening, you're not seeing the
beginning of the move. You're seeing the
end of Smart Money's accumulation phase.
Before the breakout, smart money has
been quietly building positions while
small traders are waiting for
confirmation. During the breakout,
retail traders flood in with their stops
and targets, providing the liquidity
smart money needs to begin their exit.
During the retest, smart money uses
retail panic to build new positions in
the opposite direction or add to
existing positions at better prices.
This is where most traders get trapped.
They see the market coming back to their
entry and think, "I need to cut my
losses before it gets worse." But this
panic selling is exactly what Smart
Money was waiting for. Watch what
happens when you add this perspective to
your analysis. That failed breakout
suddenly looks like a perfectly executed
liquidity grab. The retest isn't market
indecision. It's institutional
precision.
Let me show you something that will
change how you trade retests forever.
Look at this chart. Most traders would
mark this breakout level with a single
horizontal line. They'd put it right at
the high and call it a day. They see the
breakout and wait for price to come back
and touch their perfect little line. But
watch what happens. Price breaks out,
comes back, but barely misses their line
before taking off. They miss the entire
trade because they were too precise, or
worse, price comes down, wicks right
through their line, stops them out, and
then reverses. Here's the thing. Support
and resistance are not single price
points. They are zones. They are areas
where a significant battle between
buyers and sellers took place. Now watch
what happens when we stop drawing a line
and instead draw a box, a zone that
covers the entire area of congestion
from the candle bodies to the tips of
the wicks. Completely different story.
Now when price retests this zone, we
aren't guessing if it will hit an exact
price. We know that any price action
inside this area is significant.
This simple shift from a line to a zone
does three things for you. First, it
removes the stress of getting the exact
level perfect. Second, it accounts for
the entire area of liquidity, not just
one arbitrary point. And third, it gives
you a clear area to define your risk.
Your stop-loss doesn't go below a line.
it goes below the entire zone. This is
one of the biggest yet simplest changes
you can make to your trading. Just by
making that one shift, you've eliminated
one of the biggest reasons traders miss
or get stopped out of perfect retest
trades. Here's a situation every trader
faces. You see a breakout. You see the
retest. You think it's time to enter,
but you're not sure if it's a real move
or a fake out. The problem is most
traders only look at price action. They
ignore the one thing that tells you if
the breakout is real or fake, volume.
What you really want is to know if the
breakout has real institutional backing.
You want to know if the smart money is
actually involved in this move. The
result is a simple volume filter that
eliminates most fake breakouts. Here's
how it works. On the initial breakout,
you want to see volume that's well above
average. This tells you there's real
effort behind the move. It takes energy
to break through a level, and that
energy shows up in volume. But here's
the key takeaway. On the retest, you
want to see the opposite. You want to
see low volume because now you're
developing a trend. In a bullish trend,
you want to see rising volume on the
moves higher and falling volume on the
pullbacks.
Most traders think all breakouts are the
same. They see the market break a level
and assume it's good to go. But big
money players know that not all
breakouts are created equal. The amateur
approach is to trade every breakout that
comes along. They see the break, they
enter the trade, and they hope for the
best. They don't discriminate between
strong breakouts and weak ones. But
here's how the professionals do it. They
look at the character of the breakout.
They want to see a clean, decisive move
through the level, not a slow grind, not
a hesitant push. The difference is night
and day. A weak breakout will barely
push through the level. It will close
just a few pips beyond the break. But a
strong breakout will gap through the
level. It will close well beyond the
break point. That gap tells you
everything you need to know about the
strength behind the move. The biggest
mistake traders make with retests is
thinking that a simple touch of the
level is enough. They see the market
come back to the breakout area and
immediately enter their trade. This is
amateur hour. What's really happening is
that you are trying to catch a falling
knife. Just because the market touched
the level doesn't mean it's going to
reverse. You need confirmation that the
level is actually holding. The solution
is to wait for price action
confirmation. Don't enter on the touch.
Enter on the rejection. Wait for the
market to show you that the level is
working. The technique I use is simple
but powerful. I wait for one of two
price action patterns. Either an
engulfing candle or a pin bar. These
patterns tell me that the level is
holding and the market is ready to
continue in the direction of the
breakout. Here's how I execute it. When
I see the market approach the retest
zone, I drop down to a lower time frame.
I watch for my price action signal. But
here's the refinement that separates the
pros from the amateurs. I don't put my
stop-loss at the signal candle. I put it
at the edge of the zone. Why? Because if
the market breaks the signal candle but
stays within the zone, I might still be
right. The zone is what matters, not the
individual candle.
Let me show you my favorite retest entry
pattern. It's the engulfing candle
setup. And when it appears at a retest
level, it's like a neon sign that says
enter here. Watch this chart. The market
breaks support. It comes back to retest
the level. And right at the retest area,
we get a beautiful bearish engulfing
candle. The second candle completely
engulfed the first one. It's telling us
that the sellers are in control. But
here's what makes this setup even more
powerful. Look at the volume. High
volume on the breakout, low volume
during the pullback, and then increased
volume on the engulfing candle. This is
textbook institutional behavior.
If the engulfing candle is my favorite
retest pattern, the pin bar is my most
reliable one. When I see a pin bar at
the retest level, I know the odds are
heavily in my favor. The mistake most
traders make is thinking any pin bar
will do. They see a small rejection
candle and think it's a signal, but
they're wrong. You need a pin bar with
real conviction. What I'm looking for is
a pin bar that sticks out. The rejection
should be obvious. The wick should be at
least twice the size of the body and it
should be clearly rejecting from the
retest zone. The solution is to be
picky. Don't trade every pin bar you
see. Wait for the ones that are obvious.
Here's my technique. When I see a pin
bar forming at a retest level, I check
two things. First, does the wick clearly
reject from the zone? Second is the
volume above average. If both conditions
are met, I have my entry signal. The
execution is straightforward. I enter at
the close of the pin bar. My target is
the next major level in the direction of
the breakout. But here's the refinement.
The best pin bars don't just reject from
the level. They reject violently. They
create a wick that's so dramatic it
tells a story. The story is simple.
Smart money tried to push the market
through this level, but it couldn't. Now
they're going the other way. This is a
rule that separates professional traders
from the rest, and it's incredibly
simple. Remember this, the first retest
is the most important retest. This is my
golden rule, and it's based on years of
watching how markets behave. Here's the
logic. When a level gets tested for the
first time after a breakout, it still
has maximum psychological power. All the
breakout traders are still in their
positions. All the stops are still
there. The level still matters. But once
that level gets tested, its power
diminishes. Some of the breakout traders
have already been stopped out. Some of
the orders have been filled. The level
becomes weaker with each touch.
We've all seen a key level on a chart
that gets tested over and over. Price
bounces off it once, twice, three times.
The problem is that most traders think
that each bounce makes the level
stronger. The reality is the exact
opposite. With every touch, the level
gets weaker, and they keep trying to
trade the third or fourth retest and get
run over when the level finally breaks.
A level holds on the first retest and
propels the market in the direction of
the breakout. But when the market comes
back to test it again, it breaks through
like it was never there. So key point,
focus on the first retest. That's where
the real opportunity lies. That's where
the smart money is waiting to bounce.
All the trap trader liquidity and
institutional interest is concentrated
on that first pullback.
Let's lock this in. You now have a
complete system for trading retest that
puts you ahead of 90% of retail traders.
Here is how they work together as a
complete step-by-step system. First, you
identify a clean breakout from a
well-defined consolidation zone. You
must confirm this breakout with a clear
spike in volume. No high volume, no
trade. Second, you mark the breakout
point as a zone, not a line. Capture the
entire area of the prior battle between
buyers and sellers, including the wicks.
Third, you wait patiently for the first
retest of that zone. You must confirm
that the pullback is occurring on low
decreasing volume. This tells you
institutions are not participating in
the pullback. Fourth, you wait for a
clear price action confirmation signal
to form within or at the edge of your
zone. You are looking for a high volume
engulfing candle or a long wicked pin
bar that clearly rejects the level.
Fifth, you enter the trade only after
your confirmation candle closes. You
place your stop loss on the other side
of the zone, not just the candle to give
the trade room to breathe. And your
profit target should be the next clear
area of market structure.
This system works because it's based on
how the market really operates. It's not
based on theory or hope. It's based on
the actual flow of money in the market.
You no longer see a retest and wonder if
you should enter. You now have a
systematic approach that removes the
guesswork. And if you're ready to fit
this into a full a toz trading system,
that's what our academy is for. Link is
in the description.
[Music]