So today I’ll share with you a complete
smart money trading plan to filter and find
the best possible trades, with the highest
probabilities.
The trading plan revolves around supply and
demand areas, or order block, whatever you
want to call them, fair value gaps, liquidity
runs, and one of my most reliable filters,
pivot points.
If you follow this approach you will achieve
remarkably precise entries, with minimal stop
losses while targeting substantial rewards.
So let’s begin by talking about the core
component of our trading plan, namely supply
and demand zones, or order blocks.
So smart money use algorithms to enter the
market strategically at important levels,
which we, retail traders, refer to as supply
and demand.
Instead of placing large amounts of money
all at once, they split their orders into
smaller parts, forming tight consolidations
on the chart.
These consolidations often precede strong
price movements.
This technique leaves a distinct pattern on
the chart, showing where institutional money
has been active.
So I’ve researched a lot about institutional
trading in the past year, and from several
sources I’ve read that smart money trade
with no protective stop loss.
And at first, this seemed quite controversial
to me.
I might be wrong here, but from what I’ve
read, institutions employ a strategy called
hedging, where they simultaneously buy and
sell, to balance their positions.
You might wonder why they do this instead
of using stop losses.
The reason is simple: institutions have the
power to influence the market and minimize
losses.
Imagine they take both a short and a long
position at a key level.
If market momentum favors the long position,
the short position faces a temporary loss.
After the long position reaches its target,
price must then retrace back down to the short
positions point of origin, to mitigate the
unrealized loss.
You often hear the word mitigation in the
smart money communities.
Mitigation is basically the point where smart
money breaks even on a losing position.
Once the loss is mitigated, the price tends
to align with the dominant trend's momentum.
And while smart money undergo their mitigation,
retail traders often get caught in analyzing
double tops, flags, or various indicators
that that have nothing to do with WHY price
does what it does.
This allows institutional money to manipulate
retail traders' positions, by triggering "stop
hunts" or "fake-outs" to liquidate these positions.
In reality, these are actions executed by
institutional algorithms as part of their
predetermined strategies.
Now that you understand how price is moved
by smart money between areas of interest,
let me reveal the main rules of our trading
plan.
1.
The supply/demand zone must cause a break
of structure or a change of character
2.
There must be a FVG right after the supply
or demand area
3.
A pivot point must offer additional confluence
– we’ll talk later about their importance
4.
And, a liquidity run must trap traders on
the opposite side of your trade (this one
is optional, but if you can find it, it increases
the chances in your favor)
So, the first step is to find a high probability
supply or demand area, meaning that area must
cause a break of structure or a change of
character.
You can easily spot these zones because they
appear as compact consolidation areas situated
between strong and sudden price movements.
You can narrow down your zone to the last
candle that moved in the opposite direction
just before the sudden strong movement.
In this case, when there's a bullish trend
and you want to make buy trades, you should
pinpoint the final bearish candle before the
bullish surge.
If the nearby candles and wicks are small,
it's better to incorporate them into the demand
zone as well.
So remember: this is the last area of institutional
activity prior to the impulse.
This is the area where a hedge position may
be mitigated before continuing bullish momentum.
The same for a supply zone, or a bearish order
block.
You mark the final bullish candle before the
bearish down move.
Now very important, this supply or demand
zone must be responsible for a break of structure
(BOS) or a change of character.
These are price shifts above or below previous
swing highs or lows, leading to trend changes
or continuations.
A BOS is simply a break above a previous higher
high in an uptrend, or a break below a lower
low in a downtrend.
The second component is a fair value gap FVG
right after the supply or demand area.
This can greatly enhance the strength of your
trades.
One of the primary factors you must seek when
spotting a supply or demand area is an imbalance.
This occurs when an order block generates
such strong trading volume in the market that
it disrupts the balance between buyers and
sellers, resulting in a gap.
This is called an imbalance or inefficient
price action.
These gaps act like a magnet for the price
to retreat to, aiming to correct the disruption
in market balance.
For a fair value gap to form, there should
be a sequence of three candles showing significant
buying or selling, ideally in the same direction.
When there's a substantial price movement
either up or down, a gap emerges between the
wick of the first candle and the wick of the
last candle.
Now, very important.
We're not directly trading the imbalance zone
itself.
This is one of the most common mistakes.
If you would trade all the fair value gaps
you see on the chart, you’ll end up with
50 trades in a single day.
The key is to use fair value gaps to enhance
your decision-making process, but only when
aiming for a supply or demand entry.
A supply or demand area that triggered such
a significant disruption in price becomes
a more reliable entry point.
cv
Regarding this imbalance or inefficiency zone,
it's uncertain when they will be filled, but
history shows they eventually do get filled
when conditions are favorable.
This is precisely why you don't solely rely
on them for trading.
Instead, you consider them a valuable confluence
tool to have in your toolkit while analyzing
a market.
The third condition is a pivot point confluence.
These are price levels used by institutional
traders as significant levels in the market.
These levels are calculated as an average
of prices from the performance of a market
in the prior trading period.
As price gets into a pivot point area, whether
it’s the pivot or an s1 or r1 level, it
will act as a support/resistance based on
where the price has come from.
Meaning that if the price comes from beneath
one of the levels it will be held as a resistance
point.
Not a guarantee, however.
But, you are expecting to see a stall at that
level.
If the price comes into one of those levels
from above, then you expect to see the pivot
area act as support.
Remember it’s not enough to find a pivot
point, and think “this is support or this
is resistance”, so let me get long or short.
You want to find a key pivot next to a supply
or demand zone, next to a fair value gap.
I know ICT traders don’t use pivots, but
I consider them one of the best confirmation
tools you could have on your charts.
Fourth and final condition: a liquidity run
must trap traders on the opposite side of
your possible trade.
So if you find a demand area, leading to a
break of structure, a fair value gap next
to it, and a pivot point around the same area,
if you find some sort of liquidity run, you’re
in a strong position to open a buy trade.
Market liquidity is an overlooked topic when
it comes to trading.
Every time you open a trade you are adding
liquidity into the market.
And you're probably familiar with the terms
"stop hunts" or "fake-outs."
These terms describe a situation where a trader's
stop loss is triggered.
And shortly after this loss, the price moves
in the direction the trader initially anticipated.
This inexplicable situation arises because
institutional investors need liquidity in
the market to execute their significant trades.
These movements are the primary reason why
traditional retail trading methods, like relying
on trend lines and chart patterns, like flags
and wedges, tend to be less effective.
If a large percentage of retail traders are
using these methods, and place their stops
around the same obvious levels, it's only
logical that institutional algorithms would
be programmed to exploit the stop losses clustered
around these chart patterns.
Many times, you correctly predict the direction
in which the price will move, but just before
the actual movement, the price intentionally
triggers both buy and sell orders to gather
liquidity from the market.
This process aims to clear out these orders
before the real move occurs.
You correctly anticipated the next move, but
you somehow lost money in the process.
So developing the ability to identify areas
where liquidity might be concentrated is crucial.
We are looking at the 5-min time frame of
S&P, chasing a potential buy trade.
First condition is met: a Demand Zone Causes
a Break of Structure or Change of Character
In this example, this demand zone represents
the area where buyers are likely to step in,
causing a potential future reversal or change
in the price's direction.
Condition no 2: Following the demand zone,
you notice that there is a fair value gap
on its right.
This gap indicates a sudden shift in price
from the demand area, suggesting that buyers
have aggressively entered the market.
Condition no 3 is also met: A Pivot Point
Offers Additional Confluence
You can observe that S1 pivot point aligns
with the demand zone, below the fair value
gap.
And this price level can act as future support,
an additional layer of confluence, reinforcing
the potential bullish bias indicated by the
demand zone and fair value gap.
Condition no.
4 is also present: A Liquidity Run Traps Sellers
on the Opposite Side
As the price moves lower towards the demand
zone and pivot point, it triggers a liquidity
run, trapping sellers who had taken short
positions in anticipation of a downward move.
The liquidity run results in a quick upward
spike in price, further validating the bullish
momentum.
As all conditions in our trading plan are
met, you place a limit order or enter directly
at the top of the demand level.
You place a protective stop loss slightly
below the zone and your target profit is at
the next major supply level or at a recent
swing high, or even at a pivot point.
This is the 5-min time frame, so the stop
loss shouldn’t be too wide, and in most
cases, you’ll get a decent risk to reward
ratio on your trades.
We are analyzing the 5-min time frame of USD
CAD, looking for a potential sell trade.
Step 1: We Found A Supply Zone Which Caused
a Break of Structure or Change of Character
This is the zone where sellers are likely
to step in, potentially leading to a reversal
or a change in the market’s direction if
price returns to it.
You mark the last bullish candle before the
drop, or the cluster of candlesticks where
selling pressure has historically emerged.
Step 2: Following the supply zone, you notice
that there is a fair value gap on the chart,
a sudden shift in price, suggesting that sellers
are actively entering the market.
Step 3: A Pivot Point Offers Additional Confluence
In this case, R1 pivot aligns with the supply
zone, another resistance level.
In this scenario, the pivot point adds an
extra layer of confluence, reinforcing the
potential bearish bias indicated by the supply
zone and fair value gap.
Step 4: A Liquidity Run Traps buyers on the
Opposite Side
As the price moves higher towards the supply
zone and pivot point, it triggers a liquidity
run.
Price experiences an upward surge, forms a
double top, and takes the liquidity, temporarily
trapping traders who had taken long positions
in anticipation of an upward move.
Combined with the supply zone rejection, the
liquidity run results in a sudden decline
in price, further validating the bearish momentum.
As I said, you may not see the liquidity run
on every setup, but it’s a valid condition
to have.
You sell at the bottom of the supply level.
You place a protective stop loss slightly
above the zone and your target profit is at
the next major demand level or at a recent
swing low, or at a pivot point.
Here's another short position.
First we pinpoint a supply zone on the NAS100
chart, indicating a trend continuation and
at the same time a break of structure.
Right after the supply zone, you notice a
fair value gap, signaling strong selling interest
and a significant influx of sellers.
S1 pivot point aligns with the supply zone,
above the fair value gap, acting as an additional
resistance level and reinforcing the bearish
bias.
As the price goes up, it even triggers a liquidity
run, taking stops above this level.
The sudden drop in price also trapped buyers
who were positioned for an upward move.
Considering these elements, you can make the
decision to enter a sell trade, anticipating
the continuation of the bearish momentum generated
by the supply zone, fair value gap, pivot
point, and liquidity run.
4 factors indicating the same thing.
So you sell at the bottom of the supply level.
You place the stop loss slightly above the
zone and you take profits as price nears the
next major demand level on its way down, or
at a recent low, or at a pivot point.
Here's how buy trade on Apple would unfold:
First we marked this demand zone, indicating
a potential trend continuation.
If we look at the past price action, we see
the market making higher highs and higher
lows.
We have this minor break of structure here.
Right after the demand zone, notice this fair
value gap, indicating strong buying interest
and an aggressive influx of buyers.
S1 pivot point aligns with the demand zone,
acting as an additional support level and
enhancing the bullish bias.
In this example, we don’t have a liquidity
run, but this doesn’t invalidate the setup.
Considering these factors, you can decide
to enter a buy trade, anticipating a continuation
of the bullish momentum generated by the demand
zone, fair value gap and the S1 pivot point
You buy at the top of the demand level.
A stop loss slightly below the zone and your
target profit is at the next major supply
level or at a recent swing high, or at a pivot
point.
If you prefer swing trading, that’s not
a problem.
This is USDJPY on the H4 time frame.
The only difference is that instead of using
daily pivots, we’ll change it to weekly
pivots.
And you might want to reduce your lot size,
because the stops will be bigger.
Condition no.
1: Demand Zone causes a break in market structure.
This one is obvious.
We mark it, from the last bearish candle before
the up move.
And this becomes a special spot on the chart
where the price might change direction.
A potential "U-turn zone" where buyers might
start to take control, making the price go
up.
Condition no.
2: Do we have a Fair Value Gap after the Demand
Area?
Yes we have, right after this demand zone,
there's a gap in price.
Even multiple fair value gaps.
It's a sign that lots of traders suddenly
wanted to buy, which pushed the price higher.
Condition no.
3: Do we have a weekly Pivot Point that gives
this area an extra power
Yes, notice that S1 pivot point is very close
to this demand zone and the fair value gap.
That’s our extra layer of support.
It helps the price not decrease too much.
Condition no.
4: Do we have trapped traders with a liquidity
run
I believe we have.
At this minor break of structure.
This is a "liquidity run."
It traps sellers who were betting on the market
to go down.
I would take this buy trade every time I’ll
see it.
The entry can also be adjusted.
You can use a limit order at the top of the
demand area.
But you can also refine it even more, by moving
on a lower time frame, and finding some sort
of confirmation.
Now, you will encounter losing trades.
Even when all 4 conditions are met.
The most important part of this trading approach
is finding the right supply or demand or order
blocks to trade.
To efficiently plot supply and demand zones
on your chart you need to carefully considering
a few key variables:
First is the freshness: The strongest entry
points occur when price retracts to a supply
or demand zone for the first time after its
creation.
This indicates a "fresh" zone that hasn't
been revisited yet.
Time Spent at the zone also matters.
Less time spent there suggests a higher degree
of supply and demand imbalance, meaning that
significant market players are actively trading
at that level.
Distance Moved away from the level matters.
We considered that in our analysis, by looking
from break of structure or change of character.
Areas where the price sharply turned around
indicate high-probability levels.
Also, try to focus on the most recent supply
and demand zones.
This is a trade I lost, taking a buy position
on the H4 time frame.
And I’ve lost quite a few trades before,
using the same principle, until I realized
this.
A lot of traders focus too much on older order
blocks, but the real power lies in newest
levels.
I used to believe that old supply and demand
zones are just as likely to cause price reversals
as new ones.
I thought that old zones work just as well
as new ones, without any difference.
When you look at the charts, it might seem
true.
You'll see old zones making prices reverse
quite often.
If you check charts from weeks or months ago,
you'll find old zones that made prices turn
around.
But, let's think about how supply and demand
zones form.
Banks create supply and demand zones by taking
trades or cashing in their profits.
They lead prices back to these zones because
they haven't finished making all their trades
or taking their profits yet.
But here's the thing: why would they wait
for months to do this?
If they've already made a bunch of trades
to push prices up, why not finish the rest
of their orders sooner?
To me, it doesn't make sense that banks would
wait so long for prices to return to a zone
just for a few remaining trades.
If they want to finish their trades or take
their profits, they'd bring prices back to
a zone quickly.
They wouldn't wait around for weeks or months;
they'd do it right away.
So very important: the time factor is going
to have a huge impact.
In this case the zone was created at the end
of May, and I was taking a signal in August.
Banks already moved on, took their profits,
and I was monitoring a useless area.
So remember: the newer a supply or demand
zone is, the higher the chance that the same
kind of trading activity is still happening
or new traders will respond to it more actively.
Now I want to showcase a type of trade you
will encounter quite often.
We’re looking at the H4 time frame of EURJPY.
Step 1: A Supply Zone Leads to Change of character
This becomes our value area where the price
might change its direction, where sellers
took control and made the price go down.
Right after this supply zone, we spot a fair
value gap in the price.
A sign that lots of people suddenly wanted
to sell, pushing the price lower.
We also see that R1 pivot point is located
close to this supply zone, above the fair
value gap.
This is our resistance level that could stop
the price from going up.
I don’t see a liquidity run, trapping buyers,
so this isn’t an A+ setup.
Now here’s the thing.
If you placed the sell order at the bottom
of the supply zone, and the stop loss above
it, you would have probably lost the trade.
This will happen a lot, because we are dealing
with leading signals, we are trying to anticipate
future price movements.
And this comes with such risk.
If you don’t like to set limit orders around
order blocks, being on a higher time frame,
you could move to a lower time frame, maybe
the M15 chart, and wait for a confirmation.
Maybe a change of character to the downside,
maybe you find another fair value gap to initiate
a short position, you wait for a VWAP breakout
to the downside, or even something else.
With this lower time frame confirmation approach,
you would have avoided the loss.
But don’t get too obsessed with eliminating
losses, if you’re risk management is on
point, there’s nothing to worry about in
the long term.