so you have a small trading account and
you don't have much time to trade what's
the solution well scalping based on
price action and smart money Concepts
without using lagging indicators
the first scalping strategy involves
trading supply and demand areas in
combination with the pin bar inside bar
combo
the pin bar inside bar is my go-to entry
trigger a pin bar is a Candlestick that
has a long week and a small body the
longer the weak the more powerful the
rejection the inside bar is a two candle
formation with the second candle's
entire Range located inside the previous
candles range so the high and low of the
second candle must completely fit within
the range of the previous candle the
inside bar is not technically a direct
signal it's what we call a consolidation
phase this is because during the entire
period the candle was open the market
didn't make any real ground in terms of
movement
the pin bar inside bar combo consists of
a pin bar that is immediately followed
by a small inside bar with this price
action sequence you can capture
potential tops and bottoms to price
movements you identify smart money traps
that can lead to powerful price reversal
moves and you position yourself into
trending moves around supply and demand
areas
this combination forms quite often but
that doesn't mean all pin bars followed
by an inside bar are valid trading
signals in scalping candlesticks have
very little value if you don't see them
in the right price action context namely
near a supply or demand Zone so when you
see a beam bar forming at the supply or
demand area followed by an inside bar or
even multiple inside bars it's time to
take notice because you might have a
potential trade entry on your hands you
simply Mark the area containing the pin
bar and the inside bar and you trade the
breakout of that area
if you back test pin bars and inside
bars and you take the trades at an area
of Supply or demand you will notice they
continuously produce consistent
responses from the market the odds are
in your favor simply because you found
the point of Confluence in the market I
prefer Supply demand zones to the
classic support and resistance levels
because these are areas of Market where
there is a lot of liquidity at a
particular price these are basically
accumulation and distribution zones
where there have been huge volumes of
orders
here's a short trade on crude oil on the
5 minute time frame which involved
taking a trade at this drop base drop
Supply area with a trigger being a pin
bar followed by an inside bar
at this Supply area sellers of number
buyers and push the price down when
price returned to it first we had the
pin bar indicating a rejection of that
level then the inside bar completely
within the range of the previous candle
was indicating a consolidation or
indecision confirming that the market
was poised for a breakout you place a
sale stop order below the low of the pin
bar with the stop loss above the high of
the beam bar or above the supply Zone
and even though it's a scalping setup
you target the next major demand level
taking partial profits at the minor ones
here's a Buy trade on Apple on the 5
minute time frame first I identified
this drop base rally the main area on
the chart
which is a Zone where price tends to
bounce up from we Mark The Zone and wait
for price to come back to it then I
looked for the trigger confirming the
direction of the trade in this case we
want a bullish reversal pattern a pin
bar followed by an inside bar the pin
bar showed that price rejected lower
levels and the inside bar showed that
price Consolidated after the pin bar
these two candles together indicate that
buyers may push price higher so a buy
stop order above the high of the pin bar
with a stop loss below the demand Zone
Target is the next Supply area on the
chart or a risk reward ratio of about
two
another powerful scalping setup is a
view up rejection with an engulfing pin
bar formation as the trigger I've talked
about it in a previous video the
engulfing pinboard is a hybrid of two
candlesticks a candle which is an
engulfing candle but with a large wig so
the candle body must completely cover
the previous candle body signaling
buying or selling pressure
and the candle must contain a wick the
wig shows the area of price that was
rejected and the implication is that
price will continue to move in the
opposite direction of the week
the engulfing pin bar is one of the best
triggers to scalp or day trade just as
momentum is picking up these candles
indicate a strong shift in Direction
because they contain not one but two
signals in one candle
this pattern in combination with a v-wop
will offer pretty decent scalping setups
first consider view up as a trend
indicator depending on where the price
is trading above or below the view
upline price trading above the view up
as the line Rises shows that buyers are
in control and trading below the view up
as the line declines shows that sellers
are in control and if you find an
engulfing pin bar forming near the view
of line you have a good chance to
initiate a trade
in this example we added the daily view
up only one minute time frame price is
trading above the view up testing the
area forming a small range and here's
the signal candle first the candle acts
as an engulfing bar signifying that the
strength of balls have overcome the
strength of bears we also have a wake
below the bar rejecting The View outline
you have two entry methods you can enter
right away after the candle was formed
or you can place a buy stop at the high
of the trigger candle
stop loss is placed below the engulfing
pin bar or below the view up and your
target double the amount you risked or
you set the take profit at the previous
Market swing
we are analyzing euron on the five
minute time frame notice that the price
was trading above and below the view of
line which indicated a period of
choppiness not the ideal market
conditions to scalp but look at this
bullish engulfing pin bar formation add
the view upline breaking above the line
this shows that buyers have taken
initiative and are pushing the price up
the very large week is another sign of
strength from buyers we also have a
decent week on top of the candle which
shows increased volatility it's a large
spread candle so the trade management
must be on point being a large candle I
would place the stop loss below the view
up and not below the candle
in this example I noticed that price was
approaching a strong demand area where
buyers had previously stepped in and
pushed the price higher once price
returned to the Zone a Buy Signal came
in the form of a bullish engulfing pin
bar this gamble stick indicates a
possible reversal of the correction and
the continuation of the bullish Trend as
the market is making higher highs and
higher lows
the candle also rejected the view of
line they seted more Confluence to the
trade as it showed that the price was
undervalued and likely to rise not only
we had the engulfing pin bar we also had
the demand Zone and the view applying
rejection this is the strongest type of
signal entry at the close of the trigger
candle with a stop loss below the low of
the Gamble
aim for a risk to reorder ratio of
minimum 2 and try to take partial
profits at the next Supply areas to
minimize your risk
another price action scalping setup
involves the inside bar liquidity clear
route
price initially breaks from an inside
bar or consecutive inside bars but then
snaps back the other direction creating
a false break of the inside bar
structure a liquidity clear out
smart money ran the stop losses of small
retail Traders removing them out of
their positions and creating a vacuum
for price to reverse back in the
opposite direction the inside bar
liquidity clear out is a strong scalping
signal that price may continue to move
in the opposite direction of the false
Breakout
the easiest way to spot this pattern is
to find the pin bar after an inside bar
so if you find this setup you know that
smart money are driving prices to a
certain level where there are stop loss
orders and the goal is to create
liquidity for their future trades once
stop losses are hit the market goes in
their desired Direction when you spot a
large candle and then several inside
bars be ready to witness a false
breakout in most cases banks will try to
trap retail Traders
my advice is to trade the inside bar
liquidity clear out in a trending Market
so we are looking at pound dollar on the
5 minute time frame the market was
trending up higher highs and higher lows
buyers are in control So the plan is to
find the scalping by trade ideally near
a support level
in this case you expect big players to
hunt retail Trader stops before pushing
the market to go up and here's the
signal first an inside bar then a pin
bar taking stops below the small range
in this example we have two inside bars
within the motherboard structure this is
relatively common and sometimes you live
on C3 or 4 inside bars before the false
breakout occurs
you place a buy stop on the other side
of the inside bar with a stop loss below
the liquidity run or below the pin bar
with this setup you take advantage of
this manipulation instead of being
trapped by the market
the key is to trade this setup in the
direction of the most recent trend on
the time frame you are monitoring
in this example there's a small uptrend
and we find the setup right here inside
bar followed by a pin bar taking stops
above the previous range but this signal
isn't something you should trade
if you short the market here you are
trading against the current momentum you
would have lost the trade the point is
trade the setup as a continuation one
and not a reversal one
this chart shows a valid example of the
inside bar liquidity clear out a cell
signal with a pin bar in a downtrending
market price is making lower lows and
lower highs
we are trading right at the previous
support level potentially turning into
resistance another important factor to
consider in the pin bar testing the
level and hunting stops above the small
range
this was a valid short trade cell stop
below the low of the inside bar with a
stop loss above the pin bar
a series of candlesticks with long Wicks
is something you should paying attention
to because this can potentially indicate
a change in Trend this is one of my
favorite setups the plan is to look for
periods when momentum is fading away and
the potential price change may happen
but first you must analyze the shape
size and the direction of the
candlesticks in an uptrend the plan is
to find Corrections pullbacks with
candlesticks starting to become smaller
and more evenly sized this is the first
sign that the uptrend is losing momentum
then you look for consecutive candles
with lower Wicks during this period to
reveal bullish pressure
in a downtrend again you look for
pullbacks weight candlesticks becoming
smaller a downtrend is losing momentum
when you find consecutive candles with
upper Wicks revealing bearish pressure
so you are not looking for a single
price bar with a large Wick if you don't
have a decent location to trade it one
single candle might not be sufficiently
reliable for an entry this is why a
group of candles with Wicks is a much
better way to filter full signals So the
plan is to find two or three consecutive
bars with overlapping upper or lower
Wicks more even better
remember weeks indicate potential buying
or selling pressure when these Shadows
overlap they create a price Zone that is
more likely to display the buying or the
selling pressure you anticipate
as usual instead of scalping all over
the place the better setups usually
happen at Key price levels here's a
bearish pressure Zone observe the
consecutive weeks indicating buyers are
losing their strength on its own this
area is not relevant but it appeared at
the supply Zone where sellers started a
strong downward wave this is a decent
setup stop loss placement is obvious
above the multiple weeks and you target
the next demand zone or double the
amount you've risk either way take
partial profits as the price goes in
your favor
in this example a possible trade on
dollar Yen on the 5 minute time frame
the setup involves entering a long
position at the demand area right here
where the price has previously bounced
up the trigger for entering the trade is
this area with multiple consecutive
candles having lower weeks indicating
that buyers are pushing the price up and
rejecting lower prices
stop loss is placed below the demand
area and the take profit is set at the
next Supply area
and I repeat take partial profits when
price hits a minor Supply area
in our example the final Target isn't
reached but we have the chance to secure
some profits when price hits this area I
can't stress enough the importance to
take partial profits especially when you
are scalping or day trading okay the
price didn't hit the final Target but at
least you took some profits and removed
your risk by moving the stop to break
even
we are looking at the three minute chart
of Tesla first notice that the market
had a gap up at the market open this
means that the opening price was higher
than the previous close a bullish
pressure
I see this resistance here which was
broken to the upside potentially turning
into a support level
as the price is falling look for signs
of reversal notice that the candles
started to have lower weeks which means
that the price was rejected at lower
levels this indicates that there is
bullish pressure and that buyers are
stepping in I've also added the daily
view up as an additional factor of
Confluence a good Buy trade was when
price moved above the view up as these
consecutive candles with lower Wicks
rejected the line with a stop loss below
the lowest point of the weeks
candlesticks with a very large body or
spread or something special I call them
power candles in volume spread analysis
a widespread between the open and the
clothes indicates strong Market
sentiment either bullish or bearish
depending on the color of the candle
there are two main types of large
candles with and without Wicks when
price action displays a solid candle
with little or no Wick at the top or the
bottom is suggesting strong and
continued sentiment in the direction of
the candle so at the closing end of the
candle there shouldn't be any large
Wicks and the closing price must be
located aggressively towards the closing
direction of the candle in the second
case the price action initially creates
a solid candle but then the sentiment
starts to change and the candle finishes
with the wick at the top or at the
bottom the qualify fires a power candle
the spread of the candle must be larger
than the surrounding candles the candle
must have a dominant presence on the
chart that communicates a decisive move
took place the structure of this power
candles is caused by a decisive and
aggressive move in one clear Direction
the price action of the widespread
candle is sending a clear signal with
one message sentiment for the candle is
strong and the associated volume should
therefore reflect the strong sentiment
with strong volume
as we can see here this power candle was
formed with a high volume this is what
you should expect to see volume to
validate price if the volume is below
average or low this is not a valid
candle to trade the price is being
marked higher but with little effort
a very high spread candle confirmed by
the volume that appears during an
uptrend for example and break some
important resistance level might be a
decent indication of the continuation of
the trend the higher the volume when the
power candle is being formed the
stronger the signal is if this candle is
formed at a low trading volume you skip
the trade
here we have a great trade on Tesla on
the three minute time frame we are
looking for a short opportunity in a
minor downtrend I see the support level
that was holding for a while this also
resembles a head and shoulders pattern
with this support being the neckline So
the plan is to wait for a clear breakout
of this level the entry signal was a
very high spread Candlestick with a
large body and high volume observe also
that volume increased during the recent
price action this shows that the sellers
were in control and that momentum was
strong with power candles the trade
management is tricky depending on the
range of the candle you have to be
flexible with the stop loss and the take
profit the entry is simple when the
candle breaks below the support level
because we also have the volume
confirmation the obvious stop location
is above the high of the candle but in
some cases they stop loss will not offer
an appropriate risk to reward ratio
because the take profit would be placed
far away from the entry a solution would
be to wait for a retest of the breakouts
and then place a stop loss above this
area but be warned in some cases you
won't have the chance for a retest the
power candle breaking on important level
will lead price with even more momentum
here's another setup this time of very
high spread candle on high volume
breaking through resistance the breakout
candle was a big green Candlestick and
in this case no retest and that's why I
previously said that if you wait for a
retest you might not get the chance to
enter the retest will come and there's
another opportunity to enter but it
won't come right away and here's why as
price continues to increase sellers who
shorted the market before the breakout
are trapped they wait for price to come
back down to the previous resistance
level which will now act as a support to
exit their trades in the hopes of
limiting their losses
and look at the reaction at that level
when price returned to the breakout area
three days later instant bombs from the
level
this is another scalping opportunity
short Traders were trapped finally
closed their positions meaning more buy
orders are released in the market and
the price spiked up
so look for these retest after a power
candle breakout these are excellent
trade opportunities
the tower top or Tower bottom formation
is probably one of the most underrated
signals in trading but you should try to
incorporate them in your strategies
because they are really effective it's a
reversal pattern after an up move you'll
see one long bullish Candlestick
followed by a few smaller candlesticks
marking a small range a small period
with a lack of momentum one large
bearish Candlestick completes the
pattern indicating a slow change in
momentum from bullish to bearish
its bullish equivalent forms after a
down wave or a downward momentum move
the first Candlestick will be a long
bearish candlestick
several small Body candles will follow
marking a small range you'll often find
small Dodges or spinning bottom candles
and the last Candlestick completing the
pattern will be a big bullish
Candlestick indicating a slow change in
momentum from bearish to bullish
this is AMD on the 5 minute time frame a
large bullish Candlestick makes a new
recent high and is followed by several
relatively small bodied candlesticks
then a large bearish Candlestick forms a
sign that a small range has ended and
the potential down move May begin as
always location will validate or
invalidate the setup
it appeared as an obvious resistance
level we even had the liquidity clear
out trapping Traders on the long side
another reason to take the short trade
and here's the trick the volume of the
bearish candle must be higher than the
previous two candles this is very
important and it tells you that sellers
are gaining strength if you don't have
the volume confirmation you simply skip
the trade the entry is right after the
large bearish Candlestick forms with a
stop above the bearish candle
here's another example here we have a
big red candle followed by another small
one and another low spread candle
forming a pin bar then we have the big
green candle showing the upward momentum
the signal is located at a clear level
of support we even have a liquidity
clear out trapping sellers after the
spin bar was formed
but we don't have the volume
confirmation the volume is lower than
the previous candle I would have skipped
this trade even though in hindsight I
see that it continued to increase it
would have allowed for a quick scalping
trade
if you see the pattern and you also spot
a liquidity Road the setup is even more
powerful as usual first you must
identify the tower top formation which
is right here green candle consolidation
and the aggressive red candle but do you
see anything special
look at the red candle completing the
setup it's an engulfing pin bar the
candle body completely covers the
previous candle's body signaling selling
pressure
the candle contains a wick showing
another sign of selling pressure we also
have the liquidity clear of condition
this pattern takes the stop losses
located above the swing high and at the
same time traps new buyers Above This
level
and let's check the volume spread
analysis condition the volume of the
bearish candle is higher than the
previous two candles in fact it's the
highest volume in the previous 10 or 12
candles this is very important and tells
you that sellers are taking control
stop loss above the high of the candle
and you target the next demand area
now if you want to scalp the market
successfully you must follow some rules
the first rule is that you should
minimize the use of indicators it may be
tempting to start adding a couple of
indicators to confirm a setup but you
should avoid doing this
as a scalpar you want to catch minor
movements in a market which means you
need to make quick decisions I prefer
scalping based on price action and smart
money Concepts without using lagging
indicators but if you find a setup and
you're not sure if it's worth taking or
not add your go-to indicator to see if
it confirms your bias but that's it
don't overdo it
another tip is to avoid marrying a
position this is when you become
emotionally attached to holding a trait
especially in the face of strong
evidence that this is not the right
position to be in this will lead to
excessive losses and wasted margin this
mistake goes hand in hand with another
one not using stop loss orders it goes
without saying always use a stop loss
when you are scalping and always respect
it also try to avoid over trading and
revenge trading this is when after a
series of losing trades you try to
compensate your losses by opening more
and more positions each one bigger in
size than the previous one if you lose
three or four trades in a row just stop
scalping for that day
also given the number of Trades a
scalper makes in a single day please
lower the amount of margin dedicated to
any single trade and always try to
minimize your risk I personally never
risk more than one percent of my Capital
when I'm scalping this will allow you to
place multiple trades at a time without
affecting your margin even if you have a
small trading account
by keeping your position small you keep
your scalping process under control even
if you record a few losses along the way
also scalping is not for everybody you
will need to be at your screen staring
at the lower charts facing Market noise
you need to be completely focused and to
be able to react very quickly when you
find a signal scalping is very fast
paced especially if you are trading the
one minute time frame if it's too quick
for you move to the three minutes or
even better to the 5 minute time frame
if it's still too fast you can always go
on a higher time frame and adapt the
strategies for day trading and even
swing trading the principles remain the
same
if you learn something new please leave
us a like And subscribe and if you
haven't watched our previous day trading
course you definitely must watch it and
check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time