Price action is often overcomplicated,
and even confusing for many traders.
Well, Heiken Ashi candles simplify everything.
Pay attention because THIS will be your ultimate
price action guide, using Heiken Ashi candles!
So Heiken Ashi candles offer a unique way to view
price action, helping you spot trends
and remove a lot of the market noise.
They differ quite a lot from
traditional candlesticks.
Traditional candlesticks show the open, high,
low, and close prices for a given time period.
Heiken Ashi candles, on the other hand,
use a different calculation method.
This method smooths out price
information, making trends easier to spot.
The main difference lies in how
Heiken Ashi candles are calculated.
Heiken Ashi uses averages.
This averaging process creates a smoother
price chart, filtering out some of the noise
that can make traditional charts harder to read.
Heiken Ashi candles have unique colors and
shapes that tell you about market trends.
In an uptrend, Heiken Ashi candles
often appear as a series of green
candles with small or no lower wicks.
In a downtrend, you'll see a series of
red candles with small or no upper wicks.
The color of a Heiken Ashi candle tells you
about the overall direction of price movement.
A green candle implies upward movement, while a
red one indicates downward movement.
The size of the candle body
shows the strength of the move.
A large body means a strong move,
while a small body implies a weaker move.
Heiken Ashi candles also have wicks,
just like traditional candlesticks.
These wicks can give you clues
about potential trend changes.
A long lower wick on a red candle might
suggest that buyers are starting to enter the
market, potentially signaling a trend reversal.
In a strong uptrend, you might see a long series
of green candles with little to no lower wicks.
This pattern is much clearer on a Heiken Ashi
chart than on a traditional candlestick chart.
Heiken Ashi candles can help you stay in
trends longer, because they filter out
some of the minor price fluctuations, that
might shake you out of a trade too early.
When using these candles, you might notice
that trends appear to last longer and
reversals seem less frequent compared
to traditional candlestick charts.
Now, Heiken Ashi candles aren't perfect.
Because they use averaged prices, they can
sometimes lag behind real-time price movements.
This means that while they're great for
finding trends, they might not
be the best tool for pinpointing
exact entry and exit points for trades.
One key difference between Heiken Ashi and
traditional candlesticks is how they handle gaps.
Because Heiken Ashi uses averaged values,
it doesn't show gaps between trading sessions.
This can be both an advantage and a disadvantage,
depending on your trading style.
If you're trading a market where
gaps are important, like stocks or forex, you
might want to use Heiken Ashi in combination
with traditional candlestick charts.
How to analyze price action
When reading Heiken Ashi candles, you need to
pay close attention to several key aspects.
First, you look at the candle color.
In Heiken Ashi charts, green candles
typically represent bullish movement, while
red candles indicate bearish movement.
The color of the candle tells you
about the overall direction of
price movement during that period.
A green candle means the closing
price was higher than the opening
price, so this means buying pressure.
A red candle shows that the closing
price was lower than the opening price,
indicating selling pressure.
Next, you pay attention to the
size of the candle body.
Larger bodies indicate
stronger moves in the market.
A candle with a large body shows that there was
a significant price movement during that period.
In an uptrend, a large green candle implies
strong buying pressure.
In a downtrend, a large red
candle indicates strong selling pressure.
The size of the body compared to previous
candles can also give you clues about
the strength of the current trend.
If you see a series of candles with
progressively larger bodies of the same
color, it often indicates a strengthening
trend. This means increased momentum.
You can also easily find instances of loss
of momentum. Like in this example, where the
market was in a downtrend and the candlesticks
started to become smaller and more uneven.
This is the first sign that the downtrend is
losing strength and a trend change is coming.
The presence or absence of wicks on Heiken
Ashi candles is another factor to consider.
Wicks can tell you a lot about the
price action during that period.
Long wicks, on the other hand, can indicate
potential reversals or indecision in the market.
A long upper wick on a red candle or a
long lower wick on a green candle might
show that the current trend is losing
steam and a reversal could be coming.
Large wicks can indicate a high level of
volatility or uncertainty in the market.
If the high and low prices for a particular
time frame are significantly different from
the open and close prices, it may
indicate that there was a lot of
buying and selling activity during that period.
This could be a sign that the market is indecisive
or that there is a lack of clear direction.
On the other hand, if the wicks are small or
absent, it may indicate that
the market is more stable
Consecutive candlesticks with long wicks on
a Heiken Ashi chart is something you should
paying attention to, because this can
potentially indicate a change in trend.
When these wicks overlap, they create
a price zone that is likely to exhibit
buying or selling pressure.
Changes in the candle color
are also important to watch for.
A shift from a series of one color to another,
might signal a potential trend change.
For example, if you've been seeing a
long series of green candles and suddenly a
big red candle appears, it could be an early
warning sign of a trend reversal.
However, with Heiken Ashi candles,
trend changes often appear more gradually
than with traditional candlesticks.
You might see a few small bodied candles of the
opposite color before a full reversal takes place.
This can actually be an advantage, as it can
help you avoid getting shaken out of trades
by minor price fluctuations.
Heiken Ashi market structure
Heiken Ashi candles make market
structure easier to read.
In an uptrend, these candles have no
lower shadows when the trend is strong.
This means the low of each
candle is the same as its open.
You see a row of green candles
with only upper shadows.
This pattern tells you buyers are in control.
As the uptrend goes on, each green candle's
high is usually higher than the last.
This creates higher highs. At the same time,
each candle opens higher. This forms higher lows.
These higher highs and higher lows
are the building blocks of an uptrend.
When the uptrend starts to weaken, you might
see small lower shadows on the green candles.
This is a hint that sellers
are starting to push back.
It's not time to sell yet, but
it's time to pay attention.
In a downtrend, things flip. You see red candles
with lower shadows, but no upper shadows.
This shows a strong downtrend. Each red candle's
low is lower than the last, making lower lows.
The highs are also dropping, forming lower highs.
Sometimes, the market takes a break from
trending. This is called consolidation.
With Heiken Ashi candles, you'll see a
mix of red and green candles.
Often, these candles have
both upper and lower shadows.
The highs and lows stay about
the same, making a range.
Heiken Ashi candles can help
you spot when a trend might change.
If you've seen lots of green candles
in an uptrend, and suddenly there's
a red candle with no upper shadow,
the trend might be about to reverse.
When looking at market structure with Heiken
Ashi candles, watch the size of the candles too.
In a strong trend, the candles tend to be bigger.
This shows price is moving
more in the trend's direction.
If the candles start getting smaller,
the trend might be losing steam.
Also, look at how many candles of the same
color appear in a row. A long string of green
candles shows a strong uptrend.
A long string of red candles
shows a strong downtrend.
When you start seeing more
switches between red and green, the
trend might be weakening or changing.
Heiken Ashi candles can help you find
support and resistance levels too.
In an uptrend, old broken
highs tend to act as support.
In a downtrend, old broken
lows often act as resistance.
These levels are key parts of market structure.
The sequence of price swings is also important.
A swing high happens when price
reaches a peak and starts to fall.
A swing low is when price hits
a low point and starts to rise.
These swings show where buyers and
sellers are fighting for control.
In an uptrend, you'll see swing lows
getting higher over time. Each new
low is higher than the last.
Buyers are getting stronger.
At the same time, swing highs are also rising.
Each new high is higher than the one before.
In a downtrend, it's the opposite.
Swing highs get lower over time.
Each new high is lower than the
last. Sellers are in control.
Swing lows also keep getting lower.
Sometimes, swing highs or lows
bunch up at the same level. We call
these equal highs or equal lows. They're
important because they show areas where
price had trouble moving past before.
Watching how these swings form and change
can tell you a lot about market strength.
If swings are getting bigger, it
might mean the trend is gaining power.
If they're getting smaller, the
trend might be losing steam.
Speed matters too. Quick, sharp swings
often mean more power behind the move.
Slow, gradual swings might
mean the trend is weaker.
HA Support and resistance
Heiken Ashi candles can help
spot major support and resistance levels
through color changes and wick patterns.
When candles change their color and form wicks,
it often happens at support or resistance.
With Heiken Ashi, you might see
red candles turn green at support.
This shows buyers stepping in.
So, price is falling with red candles. Then,
at a past price level, the candles turn green.
You might also see green candles turn red at
resistance. This shows sellers taking control.
For instance, price is rising with green candles.
Then, at a past resistance,
the candles turn red.
A long lower wick, on a green candle,
at support, shows strong buying.
A long upper wick, on a red candle,
at resistance, shows strong selling.
For example, price approaches this support level.
You see a red Heiken Ashi candle
with a long lower wick.
The next candle is green.
This pattern implies support was held. The
long wick shows buyers stepped in at the low.
At resistance, you might see a green candle with
a long upper wick, followed by a red candle. This
pattern implies resistance held. The long
wick shows sellers came in at the high.
Sometimes, you'll see a "spinning top"
Heiken Ashi candle at a major level.
This is a candle with a small
body and long wicks on both sides.
It shows indecision.
If this appears at a key level,
it could signal a turning point.
The size of candles matters too.
Big candles show strong moves.
If you see big green candles with
small wicks breaking above resistance,
it implies a strong breakout.
The same goes for big red
candles breaking below support.
Heiken Ashi candles can also help you
spot false breakouts. You might see a
candle break past support or resistance, but
with a long wick pointing back into the range.
This could be a fake out. In this case, you
wait for more candles to confirm the break.
Now, support and resistance aren't
exact prices. They're more like zones.
You might see Heiken Ashi candles change
color near a level, not exactly at it.
The wicks might not touch the exact level, while
the bodies stay a bit away. This is normal.
Also, strong support or resistance
often gets tested more than once.
You might see Heiken Ashi candles change
color at the same price several times.
You might also see long wicks
repeatedly touch the same level.
This repeated pattern can make a level
weaker, with each test of the level.
Sometimes, support and resistance switch roles.
Old support can become new resistance,
and vice versa.
Again, watch for Heiken Ashi color changes
and wick patterns at these flipped levels.
They can signal if the level is holding
in its new role.
Time frames matter
when using these candles to spot key levels.
Higher time frames often show more important
levels. A color change with a long wick on
a higher chart might be more significant.
Heiken Ashi supply and demand
Supply and demand trading becomes a
lot easier using Heiken Ashi candles.
These candles will help you spot
key areas where buyers and sellers clash.
The supply and demand zones are like the spots
where one team suddenly gains the upper hand.
For long trades, you're looking for places
where buyers (meaning demand) overpower
sellers, (supply). For short trades,
it's the opposite – you're looking
for areas where sellers take control.
You're searching for big, bold Heiken
Ashi candles, that really stand out.
These big candles are like flashing neon signs,
telling you something important happened there.
But you don't just want
the big candles themselves.
You want to find where they started – their origin
point. This is where the real action begins.
Once you spot this origin,
you'll mark a zone around it.
This is your supply or demand zone, depending
on whether price moved up or down from there.
Now, Heiken Ashi candles are a bit tricky because
they start from the middle of the previous candle.
So, you need a special way to mark these zones.
For a supply zone (where sellers might take
control), look for the last green (bullish)
Heiken Ashi candle, before a big drop in price.
Then, draw a box from there, up to the
highest point just before the drop.
For a demand zone (where buyers might
step in), find the last red (bearish)
candle before a big move up. Draw your
box from there, down to the lowest
point just before the price jumped up.
These zones come in different flavors:
First, we have fresh zones: they haven't been
touched yet. Price hasn't come back to test them.
Then we have non-fresh zones.
Price has visited them once.
And finally, we have used-up zones.
Price has bounced off them several
times. They're not great for big trades,
but might work for quick in-and-out moves.
When you're marking these zones, use
a simple approach. Don't clutter your
chart with too many zones. Keep it clean
and focus on the most important areas.
Try to have no more than 3 to 5
zones on your chart at a time.
Here's what makes a Heiken
Ashi zone worth your attention:
First, the fresher the zone, the better. Traders
are more likely to still have orders waiting
in a zone that hasn't been tested yet.
Also, strength matters. Look for zones
where price left in a hurry. These strong moves
show a big imbalance between buyers and sellers.
Then focus on zones near the
current price. Don't try to
plot every zone since the beginning of time.
And finally, look for dense zones. Zones where
price hung around for a while, before making a
big move, are often powerful. It's like pressure
building up before an explosion.
Now, let's talk about how to spot
the best Heiken ashi supply and demand zones.
First, check out how price left the zone. Did it
shoot out fast, or did it slowly drift away?
The faster and stronger the move,
the more likely it is that some big
players placed heavy orders there.
Next, look at how long price hung around
in the zone. The less time it spent there,
the more explosive the imbalance
between buyers and sellers.
Also, pay attention to how far price traveled
after leaving the zone. The further it went before
coming back, the juicier the potential trade.
And again, don't forget about freshness. The
first time price comes back to a zone
is usually the strongest opportunity.
Each visit after that weakens the zone a bit.
So, how do you actually trade these
zones? It's pretty straightforward:
For buying, wait for price to touch a
demand zone, and bounce up with a green Heiken
Ashi candle. Ideally, this candle won't have
a lower wick, showing strong buying pressure.
For selling, look for price to hit a supply zone,
and bounce down with a red Heiken Ashi candle.
A candle with no upper wick is better,
indicating strong selling pressure.
Place your stop loss just below the
demand zone for buy trades, or just
above the supply zone for sell trades.
As for when to close your trade, hold it
until price reaches the opposite type of zone.
So if you bought at a demand zone, you'd aim to
sell when price hits the next supply zone up.
Another option is to close part of your
trade when you see the candles change color,
signaling a potential shift in momentum.
Heiken Ashi backtest
Many traders ignore Heiken Ashi
charts because they are unable
to backtest these candles in Tradingview.
I have a solution for this. This is how I
backtest price action using Heiken Ashi.
First, open up TradingView and
look for the chart type selector.
It's usually set to candlesticks by default.
Click on it and change it to "Line".
This will turn your chart into a simple line.
Then, you need that line to
blend in with your background.
So you need to set the line color
the same with your background.
Next, you need to add the
Smoothed Heiken Ashi indicator.
You look for the "Indicators"
button, and you add it to your chart.
Once the indicator is on your chart,
you'll need to adjust its settings.
Find the two length parameters
and set both of these to 1.
This will give you the most basic,
unsmoothed version of Heiken Ashi candles.
And there you have it! Now,
you can step back and backtest.
You should see Heiken Ashi candles overlaid
on your nearly invisible price line.
Volume analysis with Heiken Ashi
Volume leads price. Often, you'll see volume
increase before a big price move.
With Heiken Ashi,
these moves are easier to spot and trade.
Think of volume as the fuel that drives price.
More volume means more traders are active.
So this is how to use Heiken Ashi with volume.
First, look for trends. Heiken Ashi
candles of the same color show a trend.
If you see many green candles in
a row, it's likely an uptrend.
Now, check the volume. Is it rising as
the trend continues? That's a good sign.
It means more traders are joining the move.
Then watch for reversals. Heiken Ashi candles
change color at turning points.
If you see a red candle after
many green ones, it might be a reversal.
But don't jump in yet. Check the volume.
A spike in volume on that red candle
adds weight to the reversal signal.
Also, use volume to confirm breakouts. Heiken
Ashi candles might show a price breaking above
resistance or below support.
A surge in volume at the
breakout point makes it more valid.
Look for quiet periods. Sometimes, Heiken Ashi
candles get small. Volume often drops too.
This can mean a big move is coming.
You can also spot accumulation and distribution.
In accumulation, smart money buys quietly. You
might see Heiken Ashi candles staying in a
range. Volume might be low or steady. This
could mean big players are slowly buying.
Distribution is the opposite. Smart money
sells to the crowd. You might see
Heiken Ashi candles making new highs,
but volume isn't growing. This could mean
big players are selling to eager buyers.
Very important: don't just look at one
candle. Watch how they form over time.
A single high-volume candle might not mean
much. But a series of them is more powerful.
Also, pay attention to where volume spikes
happen. Are they at support or resistance levels?
This can be very telling. High volume at
these points often signals important moves.
Here's another way to use this
method: Look for divergences.
That's when price and volume don't match up.
For example, candles might make new highs,
but volume is dropping. This can warn
you that the move might not last.
These candles are great for showing momentum.
When they're all one color, the trend is strong.
But watch out for candles with long
wicks. These can signal a possible
reversal, especially if volume is high.
You can also use moving averages with these
candles. When price crosses a moving average
with high volume, it's often a strong signal.
And don't forget about supply and demand
areas. When price approaches a key area,
watch the volume. A rejection with
high volume is a strong signal.
Moving averages and Heiken Ashi
candles work well together.
First, you see the trend from moving averages.
Then, you evaluate the momentum from Heiken Ashi.
And together, they help you will
help you make better trades.
Here's how it works:
First, let’s talk about Trend Direction.
Moving averages show you if the
market is going up, down, or sideways.
When price stays above a moving
average, it's likely an uptrend.
If it's below, it's probably a downtrend.
Heiken Ashi candles make trends even clearer.
In an uptrend, they'll have
little or no lower shadows.
In a downtrend, they'll have
little or no upper shadows.
Then we have trend strength.
The space between price and the moving
average tells you how strong the trend is.
A big gap means a strong trend. Heiken
Ashi candles help here too.
Long bodies show a strong
trend. Short bodies or dojis, (when open and
close are very close), show a weak trend.
Moving averages can signal when a trend might
be changing. If price crosses a moving average,
it could mean the trend is shifting.
Heiken Ashi candles give extra clues.
If you see a candle with both upper
and lower shadows after a strong trend,
it might mean the trend is weakening.
Moving averages often act as support in
uptrends and resistance in downtrends.
Price might bounce off these levels.
Heiken Ashi candles can show you how price reacts
at these levels. A long-bodied candle bouncing
off a moving average is a strong signal.
When price gets too far from a moving average,
the market might be overbought or oversold.
It could snap back soon.
Heiken Ashi candles can confirm this.
If you see dojis or candles with shadows
on both sides far from the moving
average, a reversal might be coming.
The angle of the moving average tells you how
fast the trend is moving. A steep angle means
a fast trend. A flat angle means a slow trend.
Heiken Ashi candles add to this. Long candles
in the trend direction show a fast trend.
Short candles or dojis show a slow trend.
When price hugs a flat moving average, the market
is probably ranging. It's not trending up or down.
Heiken Ashi candles in a ranging market
will have shadows on both sides. They'll
be smaller than in trending markets.
Sometimes, price might briefly cross a
moving average but not start a new
trend. This is called a whipsaw.
Heiken Ashi candles can help avoid these
false signals. If the candles don't show
a clear trend change, after crossing the
moving average, it might be a false signal.
In strong trends, price often pulls
back to the moving average before
continuing. This can be a good entry point.
Heiken Ashi candles during pullbacks often
have shadows against the main trend.
When they start showing strong trend
candles again, it might be time to enter.
The distance between fast and slow moving
averages can show market volatility.
A big gap means high volatility.
Heiken Ashi candles show volatility too.
Big candles with long shadows mean high
volatility.
Small candles
with short shadows mean low volatility.
When price gets too far from a long-term
moving average, the trend might be
near its end. It's stretched too far.
Heiken Ashi candles can show exhaustion too. If
you see smaller bodies or dojis after a long trend
of big candles, the trend might be tiring.
The strongest signals come when
multiple factors line up.
Maybe price is at a key moving
average, and Heiken Ashi candles are showing a
strong trend resume. That's a stronger signal.
Now, if you’re ready for more interesting trading
guides, go ahead and watch one of these videos.