Here’s the reality: technical analysis
isn't working for most day traders!
That’s because trading has changed a lot
in recent years, and most traders didn’t
upgrade or refined their strategies!
Here's what actually works today!
Supply/Demand Imbalance Mapping
No matter if you use indicators,
or you rely on price action, you need to start
thinking in terms of supply and demand imbalances.
Market movement is a calculated dance of
institutional power and strategic order placement.
When massive players decide to move
markets, they create invisible highways
of potential price transitions.
Well, supply and demand zones are
those battlefield zones where
market psychology transforms.
And professional traders recognize
these zones as critical transition
points, where market sentiment shifts.
Market makers understand something fundamental:
markets seek balance through imbalance.
When overwhelming buy or sell pressure emerges,
markets create channels to redistribute that
energy. These channels aren't accidental - they're
mathematically precise liquidity pathways.
A supply zone represents a concentrated area,
where selling pressure overwhelms buying momentum.
A demand zone represents potential buying
territory, where massive purchase orders cluster.
And market structure follows predictable phases:
accumulation, trend development
and then distribution.
Each phase represents a
different market psychology.
Know this: smart money doesn't
randomly enter markets - they
carefully orchestrate entry and exit points,
where maximum market inefficiency exists.
Price doesn't move because an indicator crossed.
Price moves because an imbalance happened.
Understanding these dynamics requires you
seeing beyond surface-level price action.
Market participants constantly negotiate
value through supply and demand interactions.
When massive imbalances emerge, markets
create channels to redistribute that energy.
Some price zones generate stronger
directional movements than others.
That’s why tracking these
energy flows becomes critical.
An accumulation zone represents
potential future trend development.
Smart money silently buys during quiet periods.
They build positions while average traders sleep.
A distribution zone represents
potential trend reversal.
When momentum builds, smart money sell
to unsuspecting market participants.
The key with technical analysis isn't
predicting exact price movement.
The key is understanding market psychology.
Where might massive orders cluster?
Where might institutional players
create maximum market inefficiency?
This is the secret to a
proper technical analysis.
Volume Profile Signals
Volume profile reveals where markets breathe.
It transforms flat price charts into
living landscapes of trading activity.
In technical analysis, volume isn't
just a number. It's market memory.
Where massive trading volumes cluster,
something significant happened.
And these zones aren't random. They're strategic
battlegrounds where institutional money fights.
Some price levels accumulate massive
trading volumes. These are thick,
dense areas representing intense market interest.
Other zones remain thin, barely touched.
These volume areas tell
stories most traders miss.
The Point of Control becomes your guide.
This represents the price level with
maximum traded volume, a gravitational
center where market energy concentrates.
Smart traders treat the Point of Control like
a magnetic pole attracting price action.
Volume profile transforms technical analysis
from guesswork to strategic mapping.
I said it before: it's not about predicting.
It's about understanding market psychology.
Where did big players concentrate their positions?
What trading zones represent maximum activity?
The reality is that institutional
traders don't chase tons of indicators.
They read market microstructure.
And volume profile reveals their
strategic positioning.
Thick profile sections show
where massive buy or sell orders clustered.
Thin sections is just market indifference.
Now, traders often ask how to
properly use volume profile.
First, look for volume concentration zones.
Watch how price interacts with these areas.
Does it get rejected? Is it accepted?
These interactions reveal market intent.
Strong trends leave volume profile footprints.
A healthy uptrend shows progressively thicker
volume profiles in bullish regions.
Weak trends show thin, scattered
volume distribution.
Markets communicate
through these subtle volume signatures.
Then combine volume profile with other
strategic tools. Fibonacci retracements
create powerful confluence zones.
When volume profile levels align with Fibonacci
zones, you have a trading opportunity.
When price strongly reverses, volume profile
shows where counterparties became most aggressive.
These are not random movements. They're
calculated institutional strategies.
Order Flow Reading
Footprint charts belong to
a broader concept called order flow.
Retail traders see candles.
Professionals see order flow.
When retail traders look at charts,
they see candles moving up and down.
But professionals see something much
deeper. They see the flow of orders,
the push and pull of buying and selling,
that creates those candles on the charts.
While price action alone works well,
it only tells part of the story.
Footprint charts add depth, by
revealing if big market players and institutions
are actually taking action at these spots.
The real magic happens when you mix
price action with order flow analysis.
This combination takes your trading
from basic, to professional level.
The left side shows selling
volume, while the right side
shows buying volume at specific price levels.
Color intensity matters on footprint charts.
On the buy side, on the right, brighter
green means higher buying volume,
while darker green shows lower volume.
On the sell side, on the left, brighter
red indicates higher selling volume,
and darker red shows lower volume.
This area on your chart marks the Point
of Control, the price level with the
highest trading volume.
This shows where buyers
and sellers were most active.
Point of Control often become
an important price level for future trades.
The space between Value Area High and Value Area
Low contains 70% of all trading volume.
These areas help
identify good entry and exit points.
The chart also displays three key volume numbers:
Total buying volume, which is the
sum of all green side activity.
Total selling volume, which is
the sum of all red side activity.
Total overall volume, which
is buying plus selling volume.
Delta shows the difference
between buying and selling volume.
Green Delta means more
buying than selling occurred.
Red Delta indicates more selling than buying.
This helps you spot market pressure
and potential trend changes.
This is really game changer. You see,
most traders make a critical mistake. They trade
blind, hoping price will move in their favor.
Footprint charts remove that
guesswork. They show you exactly
what's happening behind each price movement.
So start using order flow to see where the big
players are placing their bets.
Look at the volume of orders,
the timing of large trades, and the zones
where institutions are likely to jump in.
I hope you see the difference: retail traders
might focus on price patterns and indicators,
but professionals dig deeper, looking
at the flow of money through the market.
The concept of order flow might
sound hard and intimidating.
But it WILL transform your technical
analysis from a guessing game,
into a strategic endeavor.
Contextual Price Movement
When you analyze your chart, you can't
just look at candles in isolation.
It's essential to understand
the context in which they occur.
This context tells you whether the market is
in an impulse phase, or a corrective phase.
Let's start with impulse movements.
These are strong, directional moves
in the market, where prices trend
sharply either upward or downward.
In technical terms, an impulse move is
characterized by a series of candles
that move in the same direction,
often with increasing momentum.
This is usually accompanied by high trading
volume, which signals strong interest
and participation in the market.
Now, look at corrective movements.
These are periods where the market
takes a breather, moving sideways
or slightly against the main trend.
The candles during a correction are
typically smaller, and the volume may
decrease, indicating less participation.
Corrective phases can be seen as
consolidation periods, where the
market digests previous gains or losses,
before potentially resuming its trend.
Understanding whether the market is
in an impulse or corrective phase can
significantly influence your trading strategies.
Let's say you're observing an upward impulse move.
This might be a signal to enter long positions,
aiming to profit from the strong upward trend.
In contrast, during a corrective phase,
you might employ different tactics.
You can also use support and resistance levels, to
determine where these phases might begin or end.
An impulse move may break through a
resistance level, signaling a strong trend.
A correction might occur as the
price approaches a support level,
potentially reversing or pausing the trend.
Combine this with volume profile or footprint
charts. During an impulse phase,
you often see a surge in volume,
confirming the strength of the trend.
In contrast, a decrease in volume during
a corrective phase, implies a lack of conviction
in moving against the main trend, hinting that
the correction may be temporary.
Liquidity Hunting Techniques
Markets often move to areas
with concentrated liquidity.
When we talk about liquidity, we're referring
to areas where concentrated orders exist.
These zones are like magnets
that attract price movement.
And institutional traders
deliberately target these zones,
to trigger significant market movements.
Picture traders placing their stop-loss
orders clustered around similar price levels.
When price reaches these zones, it creates
a cascade of automatic buy or sell orders.
This sudden surge of orders can cause sharp,
dramatic price movements that
catch many traders off guard.
The process works like a strategic trap.
Traders often place stop-loss orders at
predictable levels. Smart money traders
recognize these patterns and deliberately
push price towards these zones.
When triggered, these stop-loss orders
generate what traders call "sell-side
liquidity" or "buy-side liquidity".
For instance, during a bullish market, traders
might place stop-loss orders just below recent
low points. Big players can intentionally
drive price down to trigger these stops,
creating a sudden influx of sell orders.
This allows them to enter buy positions
at more favorable prices.
Liquidity pools are not random.
They're strategic zones where significant
numbers of buy or sell orders get together.
These pools exist across different timeframes.
In your technical analysis, you must find and
analyze these pools, to identify
potential trade opportunities.
Validation of these liquidity zones
happens through specific price movements.
When price violates a recent low,
sell stops become market sell orders.
When price breaks above a recent high, buy
stops transform into market buy orders.
This mechanism injects liquidity and often
accompanies smart money positioning.
Entry techniques for liquidity hunting
require precision. When a market shows
bullish characteristics, you might place
buy limit orders just below recent lows.
This strategy mimics how institutional
traders would enter positions,
essentially "buying the sell stops".
The reverse holds true for bearish markets.
You can place sell limit orders just above
recent highs, selling the accumulated buy stops.
This approach allows you to trade
like institutional players, taking
advantage of predictable market behaviors.
Basically, you plan to enter in areas where
novice traders are placing their stops.
The truth is institutional traders often
create scenarios that manipulate our perceptions.
They might make the market appear bearish, when
they actually want to accumulate buy positions.
Or they might create a bullish appearance,
precisely when they aim to gather sell positions.
The goal is to trade in low-resistance conditions.
This means identifying paths with
minimal obstacles to profitability.
Every time the market establishes a new
range, mark the high and low points.
Mark the internal and external range liquidity.
It's about thinking several steps ahead,
anticipating where institutional traders
might want to generate order flow.
Market Sentiment Volume Divergence
Markets breathe through volume. Every
price movement tells a story, but
volume reveals the true narrative.
When price rises but volume declines,
it's like the market is losing steam.
Professional traders recognize
this as a warning sign.
The market might look strong on the surface,
but the underlying energy is fading.
Volume divergence happens when price
and trading volume don't align.
Picture a stock climbing higher, but the
volume supporting that climb is decreasing.
This mismatch signals potential market weakness.
Traders call this a "volume divergence" - a
critical indicator of market health.
Think of volume as the fuel powering
price movement. A rising market needs
strong volume to sustain its momentum.
When volume drops during an uptrend, it
implies the move might be running out of steam.
Professional traders see this as
traders losing interest or confidence.
A strong uptrend should have increasing volume.
If volume fails to confirm price movement,
it indicates potential trend reversal. So look for
these subtle signals to anticipate market shifts.
Institutional traders pay close
attention to volume patterns.
They understand that volume tells a
story beyond simple price movement.
When volume decreases during a price rise, it
might also mean smart money is preparing to exit
their positions. This is a classic warning sign.
Consider a market climbing steadily. Normally,
you'd expect volume to increase as price
moves higher. But if volume remains flat
or decreases, it suggests lack of conviction.
This is a potential sign of market exhaustion.
I said it before: volume analysis goes
beyond simple up and down movements.
It's about understanding market
sentiment and trader participation.
A rising market with decreasing volume might
indicate that fewer traders believe in the
current price direction. This could
signal an impending trend reversal.
When volume fails to match price
movement, it raises red flags.
So look for these volume nuances.
And understand that volume is more than just
numbers - it's a reflection of market sentiment.
A rising market with weak volume might look
strong on the surface, but it lacks
the underlying support to continue.
And another point: market psychology
becomes visible through volume analysis.
When traders lose confidence, volume
drops. This silent signal often precedes
significant market movements.
Dynamic Support/Resistance Evolution
A good technician understands that
support and resistance are a dynamic
representations of market sentiment, trader
psychology, and historical price behavior.
These zones aren't just static
lines, they're dynamic areas,
constantly reshaping themselves through
trader participation and market psychology.
When price breaks a support zone, it
transforms into potential future resistance.
This reveals the market's internal memory.
Well, professional traders understand markets
have an intrinsic memory.
When price drops below a
support zone, something critical occurs.
Traders who previously bought at that level,
suddenly realize their position is underwater.
Their psychological pain transforms that zone from
a support area, into a resistance barrier.
Support and resistance are not permanent
structures, they are constantly
reshaped by market forces.
A zone where prices previously consolidated,
becomes a critical psychological
battleground for future price action.
Consider how markets create these dynamic zones.
Traders accumulate positions,
create buying and selling pressure,
and generate areas of price congestion.
These zones become critical transition
points, where market sentiment can
potentially reverse or accelerate.
Technical analysts recognize these
zones as more than simple price levels.
They're psychological battlegrounds
where buyer and seller intentions clash.
When price breaks through these zones, the
entire market landscape potentially transforms.
The market's internal logic reveals itself through
these dynamic support and resistance zones.
Again, previous support becomes future
resistance when price breaks lower.
Traders who bought at those levels now
become potential sellers, creating a
natural resistance ceiling.
And another point: zones that
previously contained price can become
launching points for future movement.
Price congestion plays a huge
role in how these zones evolve.
When price moves sideways for a while, it
creates a zone where lots of orders pile up.
These congestion zones can last
for different amounts of time.
Again, instead of drawing multiple thin lines
close together, view these areas as wider zones.
This gives a clearer picture of where
real buying and selling pressure exists.
The strength of these evolving
zones depends on several factors.
First, how long did price spend there? Longer
congestion periods create stronger zones.
Second, how recently was that zone tested?
Fresh tests carry more weight than old ones.
Third, how dramatic was the move away
from the zone? Big, fast moves show
stronger rejection of that level.
Contextual Indicator Filtering
Technical indicators work best as supporting
tools, not as your main decision drivers.
They're like a compass - helpful for direction,
but you still need to watch where you're walking.
Price remains the core truth in trading!
Every technical indicator comes
from price calculations.
Moving averages, for example,
simply average prices over time.
Oscillators measure price momentum.
These tools can point out things you
might miss on the price chart alone,
but they shouldn't override what price tells you.
That’s why setting up indicators needs
careful thought.
Many traders make the
mistake of using random settings, without
understanding why those numbers exist.
Each market has its own personality, what
works for stocks might not work for currencies.
The key is to match your indicator
settings to the market you're trading.
Also, too many indicators on
your chart create confusion.
If you really think you can’t trade without them,
pick a few that complement each other, and
understand exactly what they tell you.
Know this: markets change
their behavior patterns often.
During some periods, they move in clear trends.
Other times, they swing back and forth in ranges.
Your indicator settings need
to adapt to these changes.
A 14-period RSI might work great in a trending
market, but give false signals in a choppy one.
This is probably the biggest problem
in technical analysis: many traders
fall into the trap of indicator overload.
They stack multiple tools on their charts,
thinking more is better.
This usually leads to
confusion and missed trades.
It’s best to keep your setup simple
and focused on price action.
Let indicators confirm what
price already shows you!
Focus on tools that help you
see the bigger picture, rather than those
that give frequent but unreliable signals.
Good indicators help you understand what's
happening with price, not replace price analysis.
Also, switching between different
indicators or constantly changing
settings usually hurts results.
Pick your tools carefully, understand them,
and stick with them long enough to see how
they perform in different market conditions.
The real power of indicators comes from
how you combine them with price action.
For example, if price shows a potential reversal
pattern, you might use an oscillator, to confirm
whether the market is shows a divergence.
The price pattern matters more than the
indicator reading.
Remember this:
indicators can point out potential trades,
but price action must confirm these signals.
If an oscillator shows oversold conditions
but price keeps making lower lows, trust the
price action, not the indicator!
Price Chart Strategic Insights
Alternative chart types like Renko, Range, or
Tick charts, offer more refined perspectives.
These price charts show market data in
different ways than standard time-based charts.
Tick charts create new bars after
a specific number of trades.
They show real trading activity
rather than time periods.
Active trading periods show more bars,
while quiet periods show fewer bars.
This reveals true market activity patterns
that time-based charts might hide.
Renko charts filter out minor price moves. They
draw new boxes only when price moves a set amount.
This removes time from the equation
and focuses on pure price movement.
Renko charts excel at showing strong trends and
make support and resistance levels very clear.
Range bars create new bars based
on price movement, not time.
Each bar covers the same price range.
This helps you see price momentum:
tight clusters of bars suggest consolidation,
while spread-out bars show strong trends.
These price-based charts show true
market activity, unlike time-based
charts which can mask some market moves.
A time chart creates new candles at set
intervals, whether there's trading action
or not, missing key market dynamics.
Think about trading during major
news releases. On a time-based chart,
you see the same one-minute or
five-minute candles forming steadily.
But during high activity, those candles
might contain thousands of trades,
while during quiet periods, they might show just a
few trades. This hides the real market intensity.
Take the New York session opening as an example.
On a tick chart, which creates new candles
after a specific number of trades, you might see
candles forming in seconds during active periods.
The same tick chart, during quiet Asian trading,
might take several minutes to form each candle.
This visual difference shows you exactly
when the market gets busy or quiet.
The reality is that time charts
may give you a fixed view.
Price-based charts, like tick charts, adjust
their speed based on actual trading activity.
This helps you spot market energy and
potential moves before they happen.
Tick charts reveal the true
heartbeat of the market.
They show you 'inside' market
activity that time-based charts miss.
Professional traders often prefer tick charts
because they display real trading flow,
rather than arbitrary time divisions.
That’s the main advantage: price
charts focus on actual market movement.
During slow periods, fewer candles form.
During active times, more candles appear.
This natural rhythm helps you spot
changes in market behavior.
While time charts show what
happened during fixed periods, price charts
show what happened during actual market moves.
This difference matters because markets
don't move in neat time packages - they
move based on trading activity and price action.
Price charts work especially well for day trading.
They help measure the emotional intensity
of market participants - something that
time-based charts often fail to show.
Now, if you want to learn other day
trading secrets, go ahead and
watch one of these videos next.