If your chart looks like a Christmas tree or some
form of abstract art…you might have a problem!
That’s why in this guide, we'll strip
away all the noise, and focus on the
pure essence of trading - Price Action.
The philosophy behind price action analysis
Price action trading is all about simplicity.
The core idea is that price charts already
reflect all the buying and selling decisions
of market participants, so you don't need
fancy indicators cluttering up your charts.
Everything you need to make trading decisions is
right there in the "naked" price action.
As a price action trader,
you will adopt a "less is more" approach.
By stripping your charts down to the core,
you will focus on what matters most - the only
leading indicator there is - price itself.
So what exactly is price action?
In simple terms, it's the movement
of price on your chart over time.
Price action gives clues about what
buyers and sellers are doing. Their behavior is
visible right there on the candlestick charts.
Market structure
Let’s start with the market structure.
Market structure refers to the overall "map"
of the market - the patterns of highs and lows,
and the price swings connecting them over time.
If you look at any price chart, you'll see the
market structure laid out before your eyes, the
static record of how price moved in the past.
When prices keep rising or
falling, that creates a trend.
In an uptrend, each new high is higher than the
last one. We call that a break of structure.
At the same time, each low stays
above the previous low point.
That bullish momentum continues until the
price finally dips below a prior major low,
which is a change of character.
You can tell a trend is losing
steam when the price fails to make
a new high after the latest rise.
That's a sign buyers may be losing their grip.
In a downtrend, you'll see the opposite - lower
lows and highs that can't
quite reach the last high.
This bearish pressure from sellers
keeps pushing the price down.
The trend stays in place as long as
those lower highs and lows keep coming.
But if the price manages to top the last high, the
trend could be reversing to bullish territory.
Sometimes, the market takes a breather
and moves sideways between trends.
This happens when the highs and lows
are roughly equal, creating a tight
range. We call this a consolidation period.
The price stays stuck bouncing between supply
and demand until it finally breaks out above the
usual highs, or below the normal lows of that
channel. That's when a new trend could be born.
For a trend to flex its muscle, it needs to
keep printing those new highs and lows.
But only one candle testing highs doesn't
mean much. If you see several candles
close above past resistance in a row,
that's a stronger case for buyer control.
And the reverse is true for downtrends - a few
candles breaking below support strengthens
the argument for seller dominance.
Another thing to watch is how far each new swing
travels. If every wave is bigger than the last,
this tells you the dominant force are
gaining momentum with every cycle.
The growing imbalance between supply and demand
is fueling increasingly larger price movements.
So even if the market has entered a sideways
phase, seeing progressively larger waves suggests
the current bigger trend may still be healthy.
Speed matters too - a swift move to new highs or
lows over fewer candles is more powerful than
a gradual climb or descent. It's a sign of
intensifying pressure driving the price.
One of my favorite tools is using
trend-based Fibonacci extensions
to project future structure levels.
You draw it from the lowest to highest point of a
cycle, then to the low of the pullback in between.
This gives you clear targets for
where the price might stall out
if the trend continues as expected.
So while the price action might seem
chaotic at times, market structure
can give you a roadmap to follow.
By tracking the progression of higher highs
and lows, measuring the magnitude of each wave,
and noting the speed of the price movement,
you can assess the health of the current trend.
Combine that with trend-based Fibonacci
extensions, and you've got a solid foundation
for reading future price action.
Support and resistance
Support and resistance are the next critical
concepts you must master. Consider them as
price zones where the market tends to pause,
reverse, or break through with conviction.
A support is simply a price level where
demand is strong enough to prevent
the price from declining further.
When price reaches a support level,
buyers become more inclined to buy and sellers
become less inclined to sell. There's a belief
that the price is low and likely to rise.
If lots of traders subscribe to this view and
act on it, it becomes a self-fulfilling
prophecy - their buying pressure causes
the price to bounce off the support level.
The inverse is true for resistance. This is
a price level where supply is strong enough
to prevent the price from rising further.
At resistance, sellers are keen to sell and
buyers become less interested in buying.
The general belief is that price is high and
likely to drop, so if enough traders act on this
premise, their selling pressure will indeed cause
price to fall back from the resistance level.
But here's the thing - these levels are not
set in stone. They are more like zones than
precise prices. Picture them as rubber bands
- they can bend, but if the market pressure
is strong enough, they will eventually snap.
This is where the concept of breakouts comes in.
A breakout is when price bursts through a
support or resistance with strong momentum.
It signals that the balance between buyers
and sellers has shifted significantly.
If price breaks above resistance, it means
buyers have gained the upper hand and are
willing to buy at even higher prices.
If it breaks below support,
sellers have taken control and are
willing to sell at even lower prices.
The psychology around breakouts
is simple. Before the break,
you often see the market testing the level
multiple times, like it's probing for weakness.
Each test causes an increase of activity,
as traders anticipate a potential break.
False breaks are common. This is where price
pierces the level briefly, only to snap
back - these are known as "bull traps" above
resistance and "bear traps" below support.
But when the genuine breakout
happens, it's usually with conviction.
The move can be swift and sizable, as traders
on the wrong side rush to exit their now-losing
positions, while breakout traders jump in
to establish new positions. This burst of
activity adds fuel to the directional move.
Here's a key point though - after a breakout,
the old resistance level can become
the new support, and vice versa.
This is because traders who missed the
initial breakout will often look to enter
on a pullback to the breakout point.
Also, traders who went short on the
break of resistance may look to close to their
losing positions on a dip back to that level.
When it comes to finding the best levels,
there are some key things to look for.
First and foremost, you want to identify the
major swing highs and swing lows on the chart.
These are the extreme turning points where price
reversed after a significant move up or down.
Swing points are natural places to draw
support and resistance lines because
they represent shifts in supply and demand.
Not every swing point is equal. To qualify as
a strong level, you want to see price
respecting that level multiple times.
Ideally, you'd like to see at least two
clear rejections of the level. This could
be two bounces off a support level or
two rejections of a resistance level.
The more times price respects the
level, the more significant it becomes.
Another clue is how obvious the level is on
the chart. If a support or resistance level
is really important, it should jump right
out at you. You shouldn't have to strain
your eyes or use fancy indicators to see it.
The best levels are usually the ones that are so
clear, they almost seem to "glow" on the chart.
The significance of the move away from the level
is also key. If price just barely pokes through
a level and then slightly reverses, that's not as
significant as if it rockets away from the level.
The more decisive and strong the move away from
the area, the more you can trust that level.
Here's another factor to consider - has the level
acted as both support AND resistance? If a level
has been respected from both above and below,
that's a sign of a very significant price area.
For instance, if price bounces off a level,
breaks above it, and then comes back to test
it from above and bounces again, that shows
the level is important to market participants.
Recency is also important. While support and
resistance levels from the past can
still be relevant, the most important
levels are usually the most recent ones.
Levels that price has interacted with in
the last few days or weeks will generally be more
significant than levels from months or years ago.
Candlesticks analysis
When it comes to candlesticks,
most price action books will advise you
to memorize a plethora of candlestick
patterns or spend hours staring at charts.
I’m gonna give you a better method to read them.
First and foremost, when you open up a
chart, take a look at the recent candles
and focus on their spread.
The spread is the difference
between a candle's opening and closing price,
which forms the real body of the candle.
This spread reveals the market sentiment
for that particular time period.
A wide spread indicates strong
market sentiment, while a low
spread indicate less trading activity.
Next, you look at the upper and lower wicks
of candlesticks, also known as shadows.
These wicks reflect the buying and
selling pressure in the market. Consider them as
'rejection' areas, where the market simply didn't
accept the prices represented by the wick.
The length of the wick, whether at the top
or bottom of the candle, should
always be a main point of focus.
It instantly reveals strength, weakness, or
indecision in the market, and most importantly,
it shows you where buyers
or sellers are stepping in.
Now, considering the spread of
the candlesticks and their wicks,
here are the key patterns you should focus on.
When the body of the candle takes up at least
half of the entire bar range,
you're looking at a trend bar.
Trend bars are the heart and
soul of market fluctuations.
They represent strong market sentiment
and suggest a likely continuation in the
direction of the candle.
When you analyze a chart,
pay attention to instances of consecutive
trend bars closing in the same direction.
If you spot several trend bars in a row, all
pointing in the direction of the prevailing trend,
it's a clear sign of strength in that direction.
If you notice an absence of trend bars over
the past ten or so candles, the
market is likely consolidating.
A trend-based long wick candle is characterized
by a candle with a wick sticking out in the
same direction as the moving trend. The
smaller the body and the longer the wick,
the better the quality of the candle.
Large wicks indicate price moved a lot during
the candle but got rejected, signaling supply
or demand. The upper wick acts as resistance,
while the lower wick acts as support.
In an uptrend, if a Long Wick Candle forms at a
key support level, it means sellers tried to push
prices lower but failed to close with momentum,
causing the wick to stick out. This suggests a
potential continuation of the previous trend.
The length of the wick is the first point of
focus because it instantly shows strength,
weakness, and indecision in the market.
The Momentum candle is characterized by a
larger spread compared to the previous candles,
showing a clear directional movement in price.
In an uptrend, you'll notice each
candle getting larger and larger,
moving a greater distance per candle.
This shows a gain in bullish momentum.
Similarly, in a downtrend, each candle gets larger
and larger, moving a greater distance per candle,
indicating a gain in bearish momentum.
When you see consecutive candles increasing
in size, it's a clear signal that the trend
is gaining momentum in that direction.
In an uptrend, it means buyers are in full
control, and there aren't enough sellers to
cause wide swings in the opposite direction.
In a downtrend, growing candles show sellers
are dominating the market, and there aren't
enough buyers to counter their pressure.
An Inside Bar is characterized by a bar
that neither takes out the high nor the
low of its predecessor. An Inside Bar is easily
recognizable, due to its relatively small spread.
The Inside Bar signifies a loss of
momentum and uncertainty in the market.
The smaller candle suggests
consolidation after a larger move,
as neither buyers nor sellers are able to push
the price beyond the previous bar's range.
The Inside Bar is also hinting at a
potential breakout in either direction.
When an Inside Bar forms at a crucial spot,
such as a major support or resistance,
its break can trigger quite a few
traders in and out of position.
When you see several candles in a row failing
to break through a specific price level,
each forming long wicks in the same direction,
you're looking at a multiple candle rejection.
In an uptrend, if multiple candles try to push
above a resistance level but fail each time,
closing with long upper wicks, it's a
clear sign of rejection at that level.
These wicks form a “selling pressure” zone.
Multiple Candle Rejections show the repeated
failure of price to breach a key level, suggesting
a strong buying or selling presence at that point.
When buyers try to push prices higher but fail
multiple times, it indicates that sellers are
stepping in aggressively to defend that
level. The long upper wicks represent the
failed attempts of buyers to gain control.
Similarly, when sellers try to drive prices
lower but encounter repeated rejection,
it suggests strong buying interest at
that level. The long lower wicks signal the
inability of sellers to close below that price.
These wicks form a “buying pressure” zone.
As price approaches a key level,
you'll notice the candles getting smaller in
size. Their spread gets lower and lower. This
pattern of successive candles decreasing in
size is a clear sign of Decreasing Candles.
Decreasing Candles indicate a loss of momentum as
prices approach a critical point in the market.
The smaller candles suggest that the distance
traveled per candle is getting shorter,
which is an early signal that the
current trend is losing steam.
For example, in an uptrend approaching
resistance, Decreasing Candles show that
buyers are losing control and momentum.
In a downtrend nearing support,
Decreasing Candles reveal that sellers
are losing their grip on the market.
To increase the quality of your trade setup,
look for Decreasing Candles that finish with
multiple long wick candles at the key level. This
combination suggests a strong loss of momentum and
increases the likelihood of a successful trade.
With this method, you’ll soon realize that
reading price action isn't about
memorizing dozens of candlesticks.
It's about observing price bars as
they form and understand what the
market has done and is currently doing.
The context of the price move is crucial.
A candle can have a completely different meaning
depending on where it appears in a price trend.
Is it at the beginning, middle, or end of
a trend? Is it at a support or resistance,
or in the middle of a consolidation phase?
Always analyze candlesticks in the context of
the overall price move, never in isolation!
Pullbacks
Now let’s talk a bit about pullbacks.
A pullback is a temporary price
movement that goes against the prevailing trend.
It's a period of price retracement or correction
before the trend resumes its original direction.
Pullbacks occur when price moves in the opposite
direction of the trend for at least one bar.
The psychology behind pullbacks involves a
temporary shift in market sentiment.
During an uptrend, a pullback occurs
when bearish pressure briefly overcomes
bullish pressure, driving prices lower.
However, this doesn't necessarily
indicate a trend reversal.
If the lower prices fail to attract enough
selling pressure to break the previous swing low,
it suggests the pullback is merely a
correction within the larger uptrend.
As sentiment shifts back to bullish, more
buying enters the market, shorts will cover
their positions, and the uptrend will resume.
Not all pullbacks are created equal. We can
classify them into two main types based on their
depth: shallow pullbacks and deep pullbacks.
Shallow pullbacks are corrections
that typically retrace only about
25% to 30% of the current leg of the trend.
They indicate that the trend is still quite
strong, as the countertrend moves are relatively
minor. However, because the pullbacks are so
shallow, it can be tricky to time your entries
and define your risk when trading these.
On the other hand, deep pullbacks
are corrections that retrace roughly
50% or more of the current trend leg.
These are often viewed as more favorable
trading opportunities, as they allow you
to get into the trend at a better price,
with a more attractive risk-to-reward ratio.
One of the main benefits of trading pullbacks
is the potential for higher probability entries.
When a strong price action signal occurs at a
key level following a pullback, it indicates
a high likelihood of the trend continuing.
Confirmation is key when trading pullbacks.
Look for candlestick patterns to confirm the
pullback is ending and the
trend is likely to resume.
In an uptrend, the more subdued the bearish
pressure during the pullback, the higher the
odds of a successful trend continuation.
If done correctly, trading pullbacks will
allow you to buy low in uptrends
and sell high in downtrends!
Breakouts and Fake Breakouts
When it comes to breakouts and
false breakouts, you need to understand
how to distinguish between the two.
A true breakout can lead to a powerful
new trend, while a false breakout can
trap traders on the wrong side of the market.
One key thing to watch for is how price behaves
after breaking out of a trading range.
If it quickly reverses and comes back
into the range, that's a sign
of a potential false breakout.
Often, these false moves are engineered by large
institutional traders to build liquidity, before
driving the market in the opposite direction.
To avoid getting caught in these traps,
it's wise to wait for a retest of the
breakout level before entering a trade.
Look for price to hold outside
the breakout level on the retest,
ideally with strong volume supporting the move.
In a true breakout, price should continue in the
breakout direction, making new highs or lows.
However, if the breakout fails and price remains
stuck in a larger trading range, that's a sign
that the attempted trend change has failed.
Another thing to consider is the overall market
context. In a bull market, upward breakouts tend
to be more reliable and profitable, while
bear markets favor downward breakouts.
Trading with the prevailing trend
will tilt the odds in your favor.
Remember, the market doesn't have to
respect the levels we draw on our charts.
False breakouts will occur with
varying degrees of aggression!
Chart patterns recognition
There are two main types of chart patterns
that every price action trader should know:
reversal patterns and continuation patterns.
Reversal patterns signal that the
current trend may be coming to an
end and the price could change direction.
The Head and Shoulders is the most popular
reversal patern. It often signals that an
uptrend is about to reverse into a downtrend.
The opposite is an Inverted Head and Shoulders
which can form at the bottom of a downtrend,
hinting at a potential bullish reversal.
Double Tops and Bottoms should be your main
focal point. These form when price tests
a level twice, but can't break through,
suggesting the trend is losing momentum.
A Double Top often leads to a bearish
reversal, while a Double Bottom
can result in a bullish reversal.
Triple Tops and Bottoms are similar,
with the price testing a level three
times before reversing.
Continuation patterns suggest
that the current trend is just taking
a breather before likely resuming.
Flags and Pennants form quite. These
appear as brief consolidations or
pullbacks against the prevailing trend.
They usually lead to the trend continuing
once price breaks out of the pattern
in the direction of the prior trend.
Triangles are usually continuation patterns, with
the trend expected to resume in the direction it
was going before the triangle formed.
Rectangles are my favorite continuation
patterns. These are sideways channels where
price bounces between support and resistance.
I like to trade false breakouts that occur
contrary to the prevailing trend. So in an
uptrend, look to trade false breakouts
below support, and in a downtrend,
trade false breakouts above resistance.
While knowing these classic patterns is
important, you need to look at them
through the lens of price action.
Simply memorizing patterns is not
enough - you must understand the
market dynamics and psychology behind them.
This means paying close attention to market
structure and the key levels on the chart.
Look for price zones where the market has changed
direction multiple times before.
If a chart pattern forms near
one of these key levels, it can add
significance to the pattern's signal.
The overall trend is also crucial.
Trend is your friend, as they say.
In an uptrend, bullish continuation patterns are
more likely to succeed. In a downtrend, bearish
continuation patterns have a higher probability.
You always want to trade in the direction
of the path of least resistance.
When a reversal pattern forms, it's signaling
that the trend may be in trouble. But it's not a
guarantee – often times, reversal patterns will
fail, and the prior trend will resume.
Don't jump in on the first sign of a
reversal - wait for price to confirm it.
During pullbacks or retracements against the main
trend, continuation patterns can offer low-risk
entries if you expect the trend to resume.
Again, look for fakeouts, against the current
trend - when a pattern breakout fails and price
quickly reverses. These are good opportunities
to enter, capitalizing on trapped traders,
how thought the trend was about to change.
No two patterns are exactly alike in the real
world. As you analyze more and more charts, you'll
develop a keener eye for the subtleties that
separate successful patterns from failures.
You'll start to recognize how certain
patterns tend to play out in specific
markets, timeframes, or conditions.
Of course, no pattern is guaranteed. Approach
patterns with the combination of respect and
skepticism they deserve!
Volume Price Analysis
Price Action becomes 10 times more
effective with the help of volume.
Volume is the lifeblood of the markets.
It reflects the actual buying and selling
pressure behind every price move.
When you're looking at a chart,
the price bars show you what's happening, but
the volume bars reveal why it's happening.
Volume tells you about the intensity, urgency
and commitment behind the price action.
Here's how you can use volume to confirm or
question what you're seeing in the price:
First, look for convergence
between volume and price.
In an uptrend, rising prices should be accompanied
by rising volume. This shows genuine buying
interest that can sustain the move.
In a downtrend, falling prices with
increasing volume signal strong selling
pressure that could drive prices lower.
Be wary of divergences. If prices
are rising but volume is falling,
it's a warning sign. The uptrend may be
losing steam. Buyers are less committed.
An upside breakout on low volume is suspect.
Likewise, if prices are falling but volume is
drying up, sellers may be losing control.
The downtrend could be nearing exhaustion.
Look for volume spikes near support and
resistance. Major players often show
their hand at key levels. If there's a volume
surge as price tests a support level and holds,
that's often a sign of strong demand absorbing the
selling pressure. The support is likely to hold.
Also, track volume during
breakouts. A valid breakout,
up or down, should occur with an expansion
in volume. This confirms the price action.
But a breakout on low volume is more likely to
fail, trapping traders in the wrong direction.
Also watch for climactic volume. After a strong
run-up, a huge volume spike with a wide-range
price bar can signal buying exhaustion - a
"buying climax." Supply may be taking over.
The uptrend is in jeopardy. The reverse is true
for a selling climax after an extended decline.
Monitor the volume patterns in consolidations.
Is volume contracting as the price range narrows?
This can be a sign of decreasing volatility
and building pressure for the next move.
Look for high-volume reversal bars. A
wide-range bar on massive volume that
reverses an existing trend is a red
flag. For example, a bearish momentum
bar with huge volume after an uptrend is
a sign that sellers have taken control.
Think of volume as the fuel and price as
the vehicle. A rally or decline can only
go as far as the fuel in the tank.
As a price action trader, you always
want to be on the stronger side of the market -
the side with more aggressive volume behind it.
And, if you want to really take
your trading to the next level,
make sure to check out these next videos.