Hello guys, in today’s video we’ll discuss
about the Ichimoku indicator, I’ll show
you how to correctly read and take signals
with this indicator and we’ll also see some
tips on how we can improve our winning ration
by trading the Ichimoku cloud.
An Ichimoku chart is a trend-following system
with an indicator similar to moving averages.
Ichimoku is one of the trading indicators
that predicts price movement and not only
measures it.
The advantage of the indicator is the fact
that offers a unique perspective of support
and resistance.
For most traders, Ichimoku might seem complicated,
but once you get familiar with how to interpret
the charts you’ll spot great trading signals.
I’ll try to keep things short and simple,
so we don’t overcomplicate things.
First, we have the conversion line.
This is a short-term line also known as the
turning line.
This signals an area of minor support or resistance.
So, if you’re all about short term and scalping,
follow the conversion line.
Second, we have the base line.
Is also known as the confirmation line and
serves as a signal for support and resistance
levels on medium term.
Some traders use base line as a trailing stop
level.
Then, we have the lagging span, also known
as the lagging line, used for confirmation
of signals.
Lagging span can also serve as a support and
resistance level.
Then, maybe the most important tool of Ichimoku
indicator, we have the Kumo cloud.
I don’t want to bore you with numbers and
periods based on which the cloud is calculated,
all you need to know that is formed from 2
lines ( span a and span b), which act as major
areas of dynamic support and resistance.
Now that we saw the main components, let’s
see how you should read the Ichimoku indicator:
As i said before, the conversion line measures
short-term price movement
• if the market price is above the conversion
line, this suggests a short-term upward momentum
• if the price is below conversion line,
this suggests a short-term downward momentum
• an increasing conversion line indicates
an upward trend
• a decreasing conversion line indicates
a downward trend
Now, the base line represents medium-term
price movement – also known as the confirmation
line
• if the market price is above the base
line, this suggests a medium-term upward momentum
• if the price is below base line, this
suggests a medium-term downward momentum
• an increasing base line indicates an upward
trend
• a decreasing base line indicates a downward
Next is the lagging span.
This line indicates the big-picture of the
trend (the evolution of the current price
action in relation to previous price action)
• when lagging span is above the current
price, this indicates that current prices
are higher than previously, and suggest a
bullish bias
• when lagging span is below the current
price, this indicates that current prices
are lower than previously, and suggest a bearish
bias
• when lagging span is near the current
price, this indicates a trading range
And finally the Kumo, plotted as a cloud,
indicates dynamic support and resistance,
based upon price action.
• the longer the price stays below/above
the Kumo cloud, the stronger the trend is
• when the cloud is wide, the expected support
or resistance is strong.
• when the cloud is thin, the expected support/resistance
is weak.
• you should never trade inside the Kumo
cloud, very important rule
Now let’s see, how we can trade with Ichimoku
based on what we’ve learned so far:
The first strategy involves base line – conversion
line crossover, with the lagging line as filter
The crossover between base line and conversion
line can offer trading opportunities, in a
similar fashion to a moving average crossover.
• when fast-moving base line crosses above
the slower-moving conversion line, we have
a buy signal
• when fast-moving base line crosses below
the slower-moving conversion line, we have
a sell signal
We could filter the signals received with
the lagging span, for safer entries.
Thus, we could only take positions that are
in line with the overall trend.
• if base line crosses above conversion
line, you would only buy if the lagging span
indicates a bullish bias.
• if base line crosses below conversion
line,, you would only sell if the lagging
span indicates a bearish bias.
Another similar strategy involves the base
line conversion line crossover ( but the filtering
technique takes the Ichimoku Kumo cloud into
consideration)
• when base line crosses above the slower-moving
conversion line, above the Kumo cloud, we
have a strong buy signal
• when base line crosses above the conversion
line, below the Kumo cloud, we have a weak
buy signal
• when base line crosses below the conversion
line, below the Kumo cloud, we have a strong
sell signal
• when base line crosses below the conversion
line, above the Kumo cloud, we have a weak
sell signal
Another trading technique involves the Kumo
cloud breakout
This signal occurs when the price cuts through
the Kumo cloud.
• when the price enters the Kumo cloud and
breaks its upper wall upward, we have a bullish
signal
• when the price enters the Kumo and breaks
its lower wall downward, we have a bearish
signal
The crossover between span lines forming the
cloud is another trading strategy used by
traders, in a similar fashion to a moving
average crossover.
However, we must take into consideration that
the lines of the cloud are projected forward
by 26 periods.
• when span a of the Kumo cloud cuts the
span b from the below to the upside, and prices
are positioned above the Kumo cloud, we have
a strong buy signal
• when span a cuts the span b from the upside
to the bottom, and prices are positioned below
the Kumo cloud, we have a strong sell signal
• when span a cuts the span b from the bottom
to the upside, and prices are positioned below
the Kumo, we have a weak buy signal
• when span a cuts the span b from the upside
to the bottom, and prices are positioned above
the Kumo, we have a weak sell signal
All in all, the Ichimoku is an interesting
indicator, excellent at offering dynamic support
and resistance levels.
Its main advantage is the fact that is good
at measuring the direction and intensity of
the current market trend.
Just be careful and use it in trending conditions,
because during non-trending markets it will
offer a lot of false signals.
If you got any value from this, please consider
subscribing to our channel, share and like
this video, as it would help us a lot in the
future.
Until next time.