ichimoku cloud is mentioned to be the
king of indicators and with good reason
because with ichimoku it's possible to
get the whole picture of the price
including trend direction the main
support and resistance levels and exact
entry and exit points
ichimoku can be used in many ways it can
be used as a standalone system or it can
be used as a trend in price confirmation
and can be combined with any trading
systems or strategies
today i'm showing you how to use it
correctly and how to perform a multiple
time frame analysis using the cloud
and if you want to show your support
please leave a like to help us with
youtube algorithm and turn on the bell
so you don't miss when new videos are
released
ichimoku indicator has five lines
a conversion line with the default
settings of nine periods
the baseline with default settings of 26
periods
the lagging span with default settings
of 26 periods
and the two lines forming the cloud
faster span a and faster span b
when you use the hmo q indicator as a
charting system you don't aim to get
precise entry and exit signals you want
to get important information about the
market for example the trend direction
and the main support and resistance
levels
and while identifying a trend in the
beginning of it is one of the hardest
tasks for a trader this indicator will
help you a lot
this is how you easily find trends with
each mock indicator first by analyzing
the kumo
to identify the trend you first analyze
this component on its own and versus the
other components and the price
so number one the color of the kumo
if spane is above span b the color of
the kumo is green
and it indicates a possible bullish
trend
if span a is below span b the kumo color
is red and the trend is indicated as
bearish when spanish crosses plan b the
color of the kumo changes and it warns
about a possible trend change
number two the thickness of the kumo the
thicker the kumo the stronger the trend
is a significant kumo means a strong
trend and a tiny kumo indicates a weak
trend as it's more easy for the price to
move through a thin cloud than a thick
one
however it's important to keep in mind
that the top and the bottom of the kumo
are support and resistance lines
so even a thin combo can turn the price
back to its previous direction however
the chances are lower
number three the kumo vs price
one of the most basic fundamentals of
ichimoku is if the price is above the
kumo the trend is bullish
and if the price is below the como the
trend is bearish
it's very visible and easy to determine
if the overall trend is bullish or
bearish with this method every trend
begins with a common breakout when price
breaks out from the common cloud on the
upside or on the downside
when price is moving inside the body of
the cloud the trend is not present
number four the kumo versus the lagging
span
lagging span can be above the kumo
indicating a bullish trend
below the como
showing a bearish trend
or inside a kumo representing a neutral
undecided trend
number five the kumo versus the baseline
and conversion line
the positions of baseline and conversion
line are usually compared to the price
but their location versus the kumo can
be the indicator of the strength of the
trend too
if these lines are located on the upside
of the kumo it supports further bullish
trend
the opposite supports the continuation
of a bearish trend
now let's analyze other components first
the lagging span vs price
if the lagging span crosses up the price
it can be counted as a bullish sign and
vice versa for a berry sign
if the price is on the upside of the
kumo and the lagging span crosses up is
a very strong sign of the possibility of
a long-term uptrend while the opposite
indicates a strong downtrend
if lagging span is inside a kumo the
trend is undecided
number two the baseline versus price
the baseline is behaving as a very
strong support or resistance level so
it's a very important tool of
identifying trend changes we'll use it
later in my multiple time frame strategy
if price crosses it up this is a bullish
sign
and if price crosses it down that's a
bearish sign
a bullish cross can happen above the
kumo being a strong sign
inside a como for a neutral sign or
below the como as a weak sign
and vice versa for a very scenario
the distance between the price and the
baseline is also important as if price
leaves behind the baseline far away it
usually turns flat and attracts the
price
this isn't necessarily a sign of the
trend change
number three conversion line versus
price
conversion line is more sensitive to
minor price movements as it represents
the momentum
however it can be used as a trend
confirmation tool too
for example if price is in a trend it
usually creates waves and moves back
through conversion line to the baseline
and then bounces into the direction of
the trend again
number four lagging span versus baseline
lagging span can be above a bully sign
or below the baseline a berry sign
as baseline is a very strong support and
resistance level as long as the lagging
span is above it the bullish movements
are well supported
and if lagging span is staying below the
baseline the down movements are
supported
it's very common to see the lagging span
bouncing on the baseline before a huge
move happens
number five conversion line versus
baseline
a conversion line baseline crossover can
also indicate the change or the
continuation of the trend
an up crossover can happen above the
kumo for a strong signal
in the body of the kumo for a neutral
signal
or below the kumo as a weak signal
and vice versa for a short scenario
now let's face it each mogu is somewhat
complicated and clutters your chart i
personally simplify these rules
the description of an ideal bullish
trend or confirmation would be the price
is above the kumo conversion line and
the baseline
the kumu is thick and green
and the conversion line has crossed up
the baseline above the kumu
the picture of an ideal bearish trend
would be the price is below the kumo the
conversion line and the baseline
the kumo is thick and bearish
and the conversion line has crossed down
the baseline below the kumo
this is a much simpler way to analyze
ichimoku a faster way to spot a trend
all chemical lines are support and
resistance lines however they don't have
the same strength
regarding the ideal bullish trend we've
talked before the strength order of the
support levels would be
the bottom of the kumo cloud has the
strongest line of support
the top of the kumo as the next strong
line
the baseline and then the conversion
line has the weakest line of support
and for the ideal bearish trend the
strength order of the resistance levels
would be
the top of the kumo the bottom of the
kumo the baseline and the conversion
line
champion markets are the worst nightmare
of most traders but with kumo cloud
ranging periods of the market can be
filtered out with more success
if price moves into the body of the kumo
it means the trend is undecided and the
ranging period is probable it's not
recommended to enter into any position
when price is moving inside a como
the same applies to the lagging span it
doesn't matter if the price has already
broken out from the kumu if the lagging
span is still there the ranging
conditions are not gone yet
now let me share how i perform a
multiple time frame analysis using
ichimoku
a trend identified on the higher time
frames can hold more strength than on
the shorter time frames
for example a kumo breakout or a
conversion baseline crossover is more
relevant on higher time frames than on
the shorter ones
the hardest thing for hmoko beginners is
to create a valid basic analysis for
example what if the price is under the
kumo the lagging span is under the kumo
2 and the conversion is above the
baseline on the one hour time frame and
which signals have more relevance also
what if the 4 hour charts are completely
bearish but the five minute charts are
clearly bullish
that's why you need a multiple time
frame analysis with a precise set of
rules to filter noise and big trends
with potential
these are the minimum requirements that
you should always check to be able to
make a trading decision with each mogul
the price versus the kumo price position
versus the baseline and the komo color
always check them in this order if these
parameters are the same on different
time frames then the trend has potential
to continue
if you find that for example the
conversion line and baseline are
breaking out from the kumo 2 it can
count as a bonus confirmation of the
trend
the premise of this strategy is that you
should always trade only in the
direction of the higher time frames
i would advise to check at least to
higher time frames so if for example you
want to enter on the 15 minutes time
frame you check the one hour and the
four hour charts first
if you plan to enter on the one hour
chart then you check the four hour and
the daily charts first
when checking the higher time frames you
check the previous three minimum
requirements
always start from the higher time frames
and proceed to the lower time frames and
never enter against the higher time
frames
use this checklist with your daily
training routine if you have three
conditions pointing into the same
direction you can move to the next lower
time frame
if you have other three conditions
pointing into the same direction again
you can go to your entry time frame
here's my multiple time frame strategy
using gmo communicator
we go on the highest time frame the four
hour and we check the trend conditions
price is above the como cloud
price is above the baseline
and ideally the common cloud is green
but this is not mandatory on the highest
time frame
then we go on the second time frame in
one hour
and we see price above the kumo cloud
price is above the baseline
and the kumo cloud must be green here
then we move to the entry time frame the
15 minute chart
here i remove all each moco components
and leave just a baseline and i add the
200 exponential moving average
if the baseline is above the 200 ema
then i take the trade in the direction
indicated by the higher time frame
keeping in mind other support and
resistance points on the chart
stop loss goes on the other side of the
200 exponential moving average
and as an exit strategy you aim for a
two to one risk reward ratio
and you monitor closely the 200 dma and
the baseline crossover
if the trend is strong you can catch a
giant move and exit on the opposite
crossover
here's another multiple time frame
analysis this time on more day trading
approach
we move on the highest time frame in one
hour
price is below the como cloud
price is below the baseline
and ideally the kumo cloud is red but as
i said before this is not mandatory
then we go on the next time frame the 30
minute time frame and we see that the
price is below the kumo cloud price is
below the baseline
and the kumo is red
the trend is clearly down so we go on
the entry time frame the 5 minute chart
and look for a short signal
we removed the other components to
better visualize the chart we add the
200 ema and we see that we already had a
beverage crossover between the baseline
and the 200 ema
we entered short around this level
with a two to one risk reward ratio
the risk management here is very
important if you are lucky and the trend
is strong you can use a trailing stop
based on the recent swings or the 200
ema and you can get a much higher risk
reward ratio in my back test i've
managed to catch an 8 to 1 rescuer ratio
these are rare but if things go your way
the profit potential is great
[Music]
as always if you got any value from this
and learned something new drop a like to
help us with youtube algorithm and make
sure you click the bell icon to stay in
touch when new videos are released
until next time