this is one of my most successful
scalping strategies it involves
capitalizing on news releases
understanding liquidity Dynamics and the
Art of anticipating stop hunts let me
break it down for you before a major
news release the market is often in a
state of anticipation Traders are
positioning themselves based on their
expectations creating potential
liquidity zones and these Zones Act as
magnets attracting both limit orders and
stop orders your task is simple before a
major news release move to the 5 minute
chart and mark the most obvious
liquidity levels where the market is
likely to react now here's where the
market psychology comes into play when
the news hit the wires there's often a
sudden surge of volatility this initial
move is often deceptive as it's driven
by a flurry of orders triggered by
algorithms and reactive Traders you
probably lost quite a few trades during
these conditions the reality is that
this initial reaction is often
unsustainable this is where the stop
hunt
begins after a news release the market
will often make a sharp move in One
Direction triggering the stop orders
placed by unsuspecting Traders these
stop orders act as fuel propelling the
price further in that direction the big
players who have anticipated this move
will off often take the opposite side of
the trade absorbing the liquidity
provided by the triggered stops and as
the stop hunt unfolds the market reaches
a point of exhaustion this is where the
Trap is set the price reverses sharply
catching the traders who chased the
initial move they now find themselves
trapped in a losing position forced to
exit at unfavorable prices in our
strategy this is your moment to shine by
anticipating the stop hunt and the
subsequent trap you can position
yourself to enter the market in the
opposite direction you're essentially
scalping the wave of liquidity as the
Trap Traders scramble to exit their
positions scalping news releases was
very different 15 years ago and I had a
different strategy 30 seconds before the
event I placed two pending orders one
was 10 Pips above the current price the
other 10 Pips below then I just waited
for one of the orders to trigger there
was a time when this scalping strategy
really worked but these days making
money by scalping news is tough with the
Advent of highfrequency trading
algorithms the reaction to news events
has become more complex and less
predictable nowadays when a major news
event is released there is often a
flurry of activity in the market the
price will spike in One Direction only
to quickly reverse and then spike in the
opposite direction it's no longer a
simple matter of placing pending orders
and waiting for the expected move that's
why it's much better to exploit the
price spikes after the news release as I
said before the first step is to find
most recent liquidity zones before the
news announcement you analyze the lower
charts to find the most obvious and
nearby liquidity zones you want to Mark
those price levels where there is a
significant concentration of pending
orders these zones are often found at
Major Supply or demand areas round
numbers or at previous swing highs and
lows when the news is released you wait
for the sudden surge in volatility as
Market participants react to the
information this volatility will most
likely trigger a stop hunt where the
price rapidly Moves In One Direction
triggering stop-loss orders placed by
other Traders this stop Hunt is designed
to flush out weaker hands and create a
temporary imbalance in the market once
your zone is hit and the stop hunt
occurs and you see signs of rejection on
the one minute chart you aim to enter a
trade in the opposite direction of the
initial price spike the idea is that
after the stop hunt the market absorbs
the news and regains
equilibrium the placement of stop-loss
orders is a critical aspect of this
scalping strategy Traders often Place
their stop-loss orders at obvious zones
anticipating that the price will reverse
before reaching those levels but you
know that market makers and large
institutional Traders have other plans
they are aware of these common stop-loss
levels and will deliberately push the
price to trigger disorders and the
impact of these liquidity runs on the
market depends on various factors such
as the significance of the news the
deviation from Market expectations and
the overall Market
sentiment to make it even easier I
recommend you add the live economic
calendar indicator available on trading
view the indicator integrates realtime
financial news directly onto your charts
and is designed to keep you informed
about upcoming and past news events it
basically displays future news in real
time you don't have to check other
sources because the next major releases
are plotted right on your charts the
live economic calendar covers a wide
range of financial news events each
event is categorized based on its
expected impact on the market that's why
the indicator uses a colorcoded system
to differentiate between low medium and
high impact events news events marked
with a white color indicate a holiday or
a period of low trading activity
news events highlighted in yellow are
considered to have a low impact on the
Forex Market these events while still
noteworthy are not expected to cause
significant price movements or generate
substantial trading opportunities orange
colored news events are classified as
having a medium impact on the market
these events are expected to generate
moderate price movements and trading
activity this can potentially influence
short term price action and provide
trading opportunities news events marked
in red should be your main focus as they
are considered to have a high impact on
the market these are the most
significant and closely watched events
that have the potential to cause
substantial price movements and
increased volatility high impact events
often include major economic releases
like non-farm payroll data GDP figures
and Central Bank interest rates
decisions with this indicator vertical
lines are plotted on the chart to
represent both upcoming and past news
events lines in the future help you
anticipate and prepare for upcoming
events while lines in the past enable
you to analyze and back test the impact
of previous news releases on price
action by integrating news events
directly onto the chart this indicator
saves you lots of time in manually
searching for and tracking economic
news we are monitoring euro dollar pair
waiting the unemployment claims and
advanced GDP numbers before the news
announcement we marked the most obvious
and nearby liquidity zones the areas
where we expect a lot of stop orders to
be placed by other Market participants
when the news was released there was a
sudden surge in volatility to the upside
in this case the price initially spiked
upwards likely triggering a lot of buy
stop orders however the price quickly
reversed and started moving down this is
a classic sign of a stop hunt the big
players pushed the price up to trigger
the buy stops and then quickly sold into
the artificially inflated prices once
our liquidity Zone was hit and we saw
signs of rejection the correct move was
to enter a trade in the opposite
direction ction of the initial price
spike so by entering a short trade after
seeing this rejection you are
essentially positioning yourself with
the big players you are anticipating
that the initial upward move is a trap
and that the true direction of the
market is likely to be
downwards we are now looking at the gold
one minute chart for the Federal Reserve
statement release we see that leading up
to the announcement gold was trading in
a relatively tight range this suggest
that market participants were likely
waiting for the news before committing
to any significant positions we marked
the key liquidity levels on either side
of the current price the areas where we
expect a lot of stop orders to be
clustered as the statement hit the wires
we see a sharp downward move which was
quickly met with significant buying
pressure this suggest that the initial
selloff was indeed a liquid grab and
that the real sentiment is bullish this
is our cue to enter a long position by
going long after the strong rejection of
the downward move we are aligning
ourselves with the underlying bullish
sentiment the fact that prices not only
recovered but also surged past the
pre-announcement levels is a strong
indication that the market interpreted
the statement as gold
positive we are looking at Dow Jones
industry ual average one minute chart
waiting for the release of the core
price index before the news announcement
we identified the most obvious liquidity
levels where Traders were likely to have
pending orders as the core price index
hit the wires there was an initial
upward move at this time we don't know
if the price will continue to go higher
or reverse but our plan includes shorts
only we hope this move is a temporary
illusion of buying pressure once the buy
stops were triggered and the liquidity
was absorbed we saw signs of rejection
this is where we look to enter our short
position this rejection Candle on the
one minute chart is our signal that the
stop hunt might be over and that the
real Market sentiment is likely bearish
as always risk management is crucial a
logical stoploss placement could be just
above the high of the rejection candle
this allows the trade some room to
breathe while protecting us in case the
market suddenly reverses higher of
course scalping the news on a one minute
chart requires practice and adaptability
you should familiarize yourself with the
characteristics of different currency
pairs or indices and how they react to
specific news events it's also essential
to be flexible and adjust the strategy
based on market conditions and the
specific news announcement it's also
important to note that this strategy
requires quick reflexes and decisive
action you need to be ready to pull the
trigger as soon as you see the rejection
at your key level hesitation can be
costly and you will miss your entry if
you're not prepared this scalping method
is truly one of the best ways to
capitalize on the volatile moves that
often follow major announcements but if
you want other scalp techniques to use
in other market conditions go ahead and
watch one of these videos