I want you to look closely at this image.
On the left, there’s a regular candlestick
chart.
You can see it's super noisy, with candles
bouncing all over the place.
It's a total blur and would be very hard to
trade with so many false signals.
On the right, we have a range bar chart, tracking
the exact same price action.
And this one is way cleaner.
All those back-and-forth fake outs and liquidity
runs gets condensed so you can actually see
the meaningful moves.
There's way less noise clogging up the image.
And it’s easier to spot which direction
the price is really going.
On the left, trading this chart would be a
total guessing game if you don’t have exceptional
price action skills.
But now patterns and levels are obvious.
Range bars strip away noise and distractions
so price behavior really stands out.
As a day trader, it's really important that
you're always exploring new strategies and
tweaking your approach to find an edge.
You don't have to be afraid to try things
that aren't the most well-known.
I was having a bad trading period, so I did
what I always do during these bad periods.
Regroup and readjust slightly my strategy.
And I came back to test range bars.
Unlike candlestick or line charts that are
based on time periods, range bars only care
about price movement.
Time isn't a factor at all.
At first it seemed weird not to see each candle
plotted at a certain minute or second.
But the more I looked at it, the more I realized
range bars could be really helpful for day
trading and scalping.
Because day trading can seem so fast, with
a regular chart, price looks sometimes like
a blur of lines on a small time frame.
Range bars make it easier to spot levels where
the market may reverse or momentum could be
building.
It takes some time getting used to reading
them at first.
But you’ll find range bars will help you
find key areas and make entries and exits
more obvious when markets are moving quickly.
So when I was researching range bars, I found
out they were actually created by a Brazilian
trader way back in the 90s.
The markets at the time were super volatile,
so he focused on developing a way to take
advantage of that volatility.
Since price movement mattered most in those
conditions, he wanted a chart type that centered
on price action alone.
That's why he designed range bars - to remove
the time factor completely.
He felt that just looking at price was key
to understanding market volatility and different
phases like ranging or trending.
Normally on a chart, we see bars or candlesticks
placed at specific times, whether it's minutes
or hours.
But if you think about it, this could sometimes
clutter up the picture.
The range bar idea maps out price swings without
time constraints.
It's like a "zoomed out" view that helps identify
important areas or momentum shifts more clearly.
From what I've seen, most trading platforms
don't have range bars available as one of
the default chart types yet.
Luckily for us, TradingView has it for free,
as one of the standard options.
You can find it here.
So how do range bars actually calculate price
movements?
Unlike normal time-based charts, each range
bar just represents a specific price change,
not a set time period.
We're used to charts where one candle equals
say, 30 minutes.
But with range bars, it doesn't matter how
long it took for the price to move - all that
matters is the amount it changed.
So one bar could mean the price moved $10,
whether that happened in 10 minutes or 1 hour.
As long as the movement was $10, that's one
range bar.
This is different than our usual time-based
charts, which will always print the same number
of candles each session no matter what else
is happening.
Range bars focus only on the significant price
action.
With range bars, the number of bars you see
each session will vary a lot more than with
normal time-based charts.
That's one of the things that takes some adjustment.
When volatility is high, you'll end up with
way more range bars printing.
The price is swinging around more dramatically
in smaller increments.
On the other hand, quieter markets with low
volatility will have fewer bars.
Less is happening price-wise, so the bars
can remain static for longer.
The specific market you trade and the defined
"range" you set also affect bar density.
A $5 range on SPY will generate a different
number of bars than $5 range on OIL, for example.
In this EURUSD example, each bar has a 10
pip range, so the high-low of each bar is
always 10 pips.
Then, a new bar starts.
Essentially, range bars only care about the
total price movement - once that predefined
threshold is hit, the bar closes and a new
one starts.
If I was watching a stock and set the range
to 10 cents, every time it moved up or down
a total of 10 cents, a new bar would print.
Again, time isn't a factor.
I hope you can see how this type of chart
could give you an edge in choppy sideways
markets or periods with very little overall
movement.
It really isolates just the significant price
action.
Now, when using range bars, getting the right
size for the price range is important.
It's not a one-size-fits-all thing.
Different markets tend to move different amounts
each day.
For example, Tesla is usually all over the
place, with daily ranges of $10-20.
Meanwhile lower priced stocks, may only move
30-40 cents.
In general, higher priced stocks are prone
to bigger swings compared to cheaper ones.
So if I look at Tesla using 10-cent range
bars, it wouldn't work well.
On a lower price stock, it makes perfect sense.
This chart looks clean and easy to analyze.
But trying to squeeze Tesla's big moves into
tiny 10-cent boxes would overload the chart
and make it a huge messy cluster.
And this shows how the optimal range needs
to match how volatile the market tends to
be each day.
Otherwise you lose the benefit of those refined
range bars.
So when choosing a range size for bars, one
thing you can do is look at how much the market
usually moves each day on average.
You can see this just from experience watching
it, or use indicators like ATR to get a better
picture.
Once you know the average daily range in dollars,
you could make the bar size a percentage of
that, like 10%, 20% or whatever you want.
It also depends on your personal style.
If you're a short-term scalper or day trader,
you probably want to see smaller moves, so
a narrow range works well.
Meanwhile, if you are a swing trader, you
need bigger ranges to highlight major swings.
For example, let's say we’re monitoring
a market that averages 50 cent daily moves.
You may go with a 10 cent range bar.
This lets you focus on the quick little fluctuations
within a session.
But a swing trader, might prefer a dollar
range bar instead.
So I can’t tell you the perfect range bar
size that works on all markets.
Paying attention to how you trade and how
much your markers typically move will really
help dial in the optimal range settings.
Range bars are really useful when viewing
how price is moving compared to normal time-based
charts.
On regular charts, if price is bouncing back
and forth in a small area for a while, it
creates a bunch of messy candles that clutter
things up.
But with range bars, all that noise gets consolidated
into just one or two bars max.
This makes it much clearer what the actual
meaningful price action is versus small meaningless
fluctuations.
Since range bars won't start a new one until
the set range is hit, it filters out unimportant
movements.
The biggest advantage for me: areas of supply
and demand or support/resistance really pop
out when you put horizontal lines on them.
Trend periods and breakouts also stand out.
I've found range bar charts to be really helpful
for scalping and day trading strategies.
The reason is because it lets you read volatility
levels better than normal charts.
Volatility simply means how much the price
is moving around.
On range bars, when price is trading in a
narrow sideways zone, it'll only make a few
bars.
This shows activity is low.
But then if it starts to break out of that
zone as volatility increases, you can watch
closely and notice changes in how often the
bars are printing.
Faster bars equals more volatility from bigger
movements.
Slower bars mean less volatility.
Carefully observing this timing and bar frequency
over time helps spot when volatility is higher
or lower.
And periods where it suddenly picks up usually
signal a new short term trend forming, creating
opportunities.
Being able to see those subtle volatility
shifts is very useful for day trading.
If you're trying to scalp the forex market
targeting let’s say 10 pips each time, then
using a 10 pip range bar chart would definitely
make more sense compared to regular charts.
When scalping those tiny moves, a 10 pip range
bar takes out the whole time element, which
isn't that important at that scale.
All that matters is seeing when the full 10
pip price swings happen regardless of how
fast or slow it occurs.
On a regular chart with candlesticks spaced
by time, like 5 minutes, it could take maybe
a long time to see a single 10 pip shift.
But the range bar would form a new box immediately
after that movement.
Cutting out noise is key for scalping, and
range bars do that perfectly by only focusing
on the important thresholds you're trading
around, not meaningless price wiggles in between.
The ability to finely tune the range size
to your strategy is a big advantage over time-based
charts.
It really lets you zero in on exactly what
your eyes need to see to catch those small
moves.
Let’s me show you how I use this chart to
trade supply and demand.
Identifying major supply and demand zones
on the charts is one of the pillars of my
strategy.
The first step is always looking at where
we are now price-wise.
Then I go back on the previous day's to investigate
past swings.
Once I spot a big move up or down, I focus
on where it started.
That area is usually a supply or demand zone,
since that's where upside or downside pressure
took over.
If it was a bearish drop, I check the last
bullish range bar before the downturn.
Then I highlight that zone up to the high
right before the move started.
Similarly, for an upswing, I look at the most
recent bearish range bar preceding it.
Then mark out the zone from there down to
the low preceding the start of the rally.
When drawing supply and demand zones on range
bar charts, it's important to consider how
"fresh" or recently used they are.
There are a few supply and demand types:
- Fresh zones, which haven't been revisited
yet, so they're untested.
- Non-fresh zones, which have seen price pull
back to them at least once.
- And used up zones, which have had price
bounce off them several times.
They're not as reliable for full swings
When marking these on a range bar chart, focus
on:
- The freshest zones, since the market impact
is most likely still there.
- The strongest zones, where price sharply
changed direction in a quick move.
These command more attention.
Paying attention to how recently zones have
been in play and how abruptly price reacted
there can help you focus your analysis on
the most influential areas.
Let’s look at this range bar chart, with
yesterday's price action on it.
First step, we mark some important supply
and demand zones from how price reacted the
previous day.
Down here near the bottom, it barely dipped
below this range before bouncing hard.
That shows strong demand.
And up at the top, price peaked then crashed
off after struggling to break through.
Clearly a strong supply up there.
Now flipping to the next day, price revisited
that bottom demand area again.
As buyers stepped up forcefully the previous
day, there’s a chance they'll protect this
level once more.
The chart structure looks ready to turn higher
from here.
This is your buy zone.
Maybe it’s placebo, but I can see supply
and demand, support and resistance level more
clearly with range bars.
These are perfect for identifying technical
areas other traders will react at from prior
days.
This was just a basic intro to the concept.
In the next videos, I want to start demonstrating
some concrete trading strategies we can actually
apply using range bars on different markets.
So, drop a like if you want that video.