Here’s my biggest advice to you: don't trade
like everyone else - the real profits in trading
come from being one step ahead, anticipating
the next move before it happens, and not by
reacting using lagging indicators.
90% of trading education is useless in today’s
market, and that’s the reality.
So let me share my discoveries and my process
to seize opportunities before others do.
Money is made in trading by anticipating what
is coming — not by waiting till it happens
and going with the crowd
In trading, being ahead of the curve is the
name of the game.
It's about anticipating the market's moves,
not just reacting to them once they've happened.
Why?
Because by the time the rest of the crowd
catches up, it's often too late to make the
most of the situation.
If you anticipate the market's 'next wave'
in advance, you can 'ride' it profitably.
But if you just stand there and let it hit
you, you will find yourself knocked over.
Consider a breakout in the market, where prices
suddenly move outside a defined range.
This could be the start of a new trend or
a market manipulation practice.
If you've done your analysis and predicted
the breakout, you can buy in early and potentially
profit as the trend takes off.
But if you're just going along with the crowd,
using lagging and outdated tools, you'll often
end up buying in too late, after the breakout
has already happened and the price has shot
up.
A similar principle applies to pullbacks – short-term
reversals in an uptrend or downtrends.
If you've done your homework and expect a
pullback, you can plan your trades to take
advantage of this temporary dip.
Buying at a discount or selling at a premium.
The key to making money in trading is anticipation,
not just blindly following some delayed signals,
like most of the crowd.
Let me repeat: trading is about anticipating
the market's next move, not reacting to what's
already happened.
It's a proactive, not a reactive approach.
If your trading strategy is 100% reactive,
you have a big problem.
Big moves start from dull, flat markets, not
from active ones.
Big moves start from flat markets, not from
active ones.
When the market is ‘going nowhere’, pay
close attention, and wait for a strong move
that is certain to eventually happen.
As I said before, the essence of trading is
anticipation.
Successful trading involves predicting the
future direction of the market based on its
current conditions.
And a common mistake is to dismiss a dull
market as unprofitable and ignore it.
Big moves in the market often originate from
these periods, not from times of high activity.
During these seemingly uneventful periods
the market is setting the stage for significant
moves.
So, when you feel the market is stagnant or
flat, don't let your guard down.
Instead, sharpen your focus and wait for the
eventual substantial move that could follow.
These are the accumulation and distribution
periods, during which smart money are planning
their next moves
During these periods you have the chance to
position yourself for the wave that's about
to come.
Successful trading relies on certain conditions,
and the most important factor is the market
volatility - the extent of price swings.
Every day prices fluctuate constantly, rising
and falling in response to various factors.
As a trader, your goal is to profit from these
price changes.
But when the market is 'quiet,' and prices
aren't moving much, there's not much opportunity
to make money.
I’m not talking about ranges, or accumulation
or distribution periods.
I’m talking about the distance price travels
during a day.
Trading during quiet, or low-volatility periods
is a common mistake.
If the price of a market is barely moving,
there's little chance to make a profit.
Let's say it costs you 5 dollars to trade.
This represents the commissions or fees you
need to pay for each trade you make.
If the stock you trade only moves around 5
to 10 dollars, you'll need to catch almost
every single swing perfectly just to break
even.
If you factor in the occasional loss, it becomes
clear why trading in a quiet market can be
a losing game.
The solution is to look for markets with sufficient
volatility - ones where prices are moving
enough to offer potential for profit.
Use the average true range or the average
daily range to determine the best markets
to be in.
With these tools, you ensure that the markets
you're trading have enough room to move.
Trading Cannot Be Reduced to Simple Rules
Trading is like playing a video game, where
each level brings new scenarios and challenges.
And here's the catch: No two scenarios in
this game ever repeat exactly.
Every new scene or challenge is different
from the last.
Financial markets are the same.
Each day in the market is a new day with different
situations and it's impossible to find two
situations that are 100% identical.
The market is always changing, evolving with
new subtleties and nuances.
Now, imagine you try to use the same strategy
for every level in your game - it's not going
to work.
Same goes for trading.
If you create a simple set of rules based
on EURUSD, it might not work on other markets.
It’s so obvious, but many traders don’t
realize this.
They take a strategy designed for certain
market conditions, and apply it in different
environment.
Most likely, it won’t work!
Your edge should be based on your own observations
If you're a new trader, instead of rushing
into the game, you need to prioritize observation.
If you focus on building a strategy before
observing the market behavior, you’re doing
it wrong.
You need to base your edge on careful observation
and understanding of market patterns and behaviors.
This is very important: if your trading strategy
isn't rooted in your observations and understanding,
you'll lack the confidence to stick to your
plan, especially when the market gets rough.
Trading requires a unique approach tailored
to your observations and understanding.
My advice?
Spend a full week observing price action.
Don’t take any trades.
Just open a chart, and look at the action
in real time.
Reflect on the market patterns or behaviors
that caught your attention.
How does the market behave before an upward
or downward trend?
What's the most reliable market behavior you've
observed?
These high-quality observations are the key
to identifying your unique edge.
They will guide you in creating a good strategy
that aligns with the market's rhythm.
Always try to take a free position
Wyckoff, the famous trader, was a firm believer
in taking free positions.
And this is something I’ve integrated in
my trading plan.
“Taking a Free Position” is a strategic
method to safeguard and secure your gains.
It’s simple.
Let's say you've placed a trade and it's going
in your favor.
To protect your profits, you move your stop
loss, following the price.
This way, even if the price suddenly drops,
you won't lose any money.
It's like setting a safety net that moves
up with the price.
Doing this helps you squeeze out every bit
of profit from the trade.
And the great thing is, as long as you don't
decide to close the trade yourself, there's
always a chance for more profit.
If you get frustrated when you close a trade
for a profit, and you see the price going
even higher, this is the answer.
Instead of setting a fixed target and calling
it a day once he hit that, you follow the
trade and adjust the stop loss according to
the price swings, going for the maximum possible
profit each time.
Consistently adjusting your stop-loss, following
the market's rise or fall, leaves room for
additional profit, whereas prematurely closing
your trade seals off any such potential opportunities.
The Holy Grail of Trading (If There Was One)
Too many traders spend excessive time constantly
tweaking their setups, playing around with
their charts, and making unnecessary modifications
every other day.
This practice isn't just time-consuming but
can also destroy your trading strategy.
Imagine you've identified your edge - your
unique understanding of market behavior that
gives you an advantage.
Your next step is to set up your charts in
a way that allows you to trade according to
your plan.
But here's the catch: make a commitment to
yourself to resist making any changes to it
for at least a month.
If you're constantly altering your charts
and setups, you won't be able to distinguish
what strategies are successful and which ones
you should avoid.
Consistency, in essence, is the closest thing
to a Holy Grail in trading.
Make a decision and have the discipline to
stick to it.
If your trading strategy varies every day,
how can you possibly evaluate what's working
and what's not?
It's ironic that many traders demand consistency
from the market but fail to apply the same
principle to their trading behavior.
The Four Foundations of Successful Trading
Jesse Livermore, the famous trader, said that
a consistent trader needs to master 4 skills:
observation, experience, memory, and mathematics.
You need good observation skills
to
Experience comes with time.
It's not just about winning or losing trades,
but understanding what worked and what didn't.
You get better as you understand the market
mechanics better.
Memory is your personal database.
It involves remembering past trades, market
patterns, and changes.
Mathematics is the analytical part.
It involves crunching numbers, analyzing charts,
and predicting market trends.
These 4 skills work together, will allow you
to evaluate the market conditions accurately.
Missing any of these elements will leave you
ineffective and likely unsuccessful.
That’s the reality!
Should you trade with a system (a set of 100%
objectively defined rules) or with discretion
(using your judgment)
Trading can seem like a binary choice between
following a system (a set of objective rules)
or relying on discretion (leveraging your
judgment).
I try to use both approaches, I’m what they
call a 'hybrid trader.'
You can have a set of rules in place (‘trading
guidelines’), without them being 100% objective.
There is room for rules as well as judgment.
However, if you're new to trading, your approach
should lean more towards systematic trading.
Systematic trading is more beneficial for
a beginner, because trading with objective
rules creates a uniform trading system, thus
promoting a coherent approach to the markets.
When trading using discretion, the chances
of committing mistakes are significantly higher,
particularly as a beginner.
So, if you're just starting, it's better to
be wholly systematic.
As you gain more experience and a deeper understanding
of the market dynamics, you can begin to incorporate
elements of discretionary judgement into your
trading strategy.
It's all about finding the balance that suits
your style and risk tolerance.
Start with Minimum Size
The art of trading is similar to mastering
a new skill or sport.
Just as a beginner doesn't start playing a
sport in the major leagues, a new trader doesn't
start by investing huge sums of money right
off the bat.
It’s a common mistake new traders make.
The safest and most effective way to learn
is to start slow and small, and then gradually
work your way up as your confidence and competence
grow.
If you've done your homework and absorbed
all the information you could find about trading
- the techniques, strategies, tips and tricks
- then it's time to apply that knowledge.
But it's best to start trading in small quantities,
with a few shares or mini lots.
This allows you to gain real trading experience
without risking a significant amount of your
capital.
Now, this approach may not seem exciting to
some, especially those who love the thrill
of gambling and want to make a big splash
right away.
But the goal here is not to gamble.
It's not about making a lot of money quickly;
it's about learning to make money consistently
over the long term.
So start small, gain experience, and gradually
increase the size of your trades as you become
more skilled and confident.
The Truth about Market Edges
So, the market you trade today is not the
market you traded yesterday and is not the
market you will trade tomorrow.
That’s because the market participants change,
as do their trading strategies
So, if you're expecting a continued winning
streak, brace yourself for disappointment.
The market doesn't work that way.
Even if you find an edge, that edge could
and in fact will disappear over time.
In my trading journey, I've found several
edges, all of which eventually faded.
You need to understand this: you cannot just
come up with a profitable system and then
use it for the next twenty years to become
insanely rich.
If your method has any edge, that edge will
change and decrease over time.
That’s what is meant when it is said that
‘there is no Holy Grail’ in trading.
I’m not trying to discourage you.
The point is, in order to succeed, you must
keep your trading strategies in sync with
the evolving markets.
If your successful strategy starts to lose
its power, you must reengineer it and adjust
it to new conditions.
What’s my personal edge?
It involves supply and demand and volume spread
analysis concepts.
If you want to know more about it, check out
this trading course, where I explain in detail
exactly how I trade.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!