a lot of Traders are using v-wop in day
trading and scalping and it's a very
useful tool because view up shows the
true average price of a market by
factoring the volume of transactions
most Traders are using daily view up but
did you know that you can also trade
based on the weekly view up
weekly view up adds more value than the
standard 50 or 200 moving average
indicators because this line reacts to
price movements based on the volume
during that period and in combination
with the RSI you can determine the trend
and momentum in just a few seconds
you know the drill like subscribe and
stick around for the full video
[Music]
you find the weekly view up here
at the anchor period you choose weekly
and will hide the bands for now we'll
just focus on the main line
for day Traders and scalpers The View up
is often used as a trend indicator for
big players and institutions it's used
as a benchmark price to evaluate the
quality of executions from their trades
weekly view app shows you the trend
depending on where the price is trading
above or below in relation to the view
upline a market trading above the weekly
view of as the line Rises indicates an
uptrend
a market trading below the weekly view
up as the line declines indicates a
downtrend
one of the simplest uses of the weekly
view up is for finding Dynamic support
or resistance view upline acts as a
support if the price is trading above it
and as a resistance if the price is
trading below it
weekly viewable also offers entry and
exit levels
one Trader support is another Trader's
resistance
for example a Trader who is long on a
market can use the view up as a Target
exit if he entered below
Traders looking to take a long position
can wait for the price to break the view
up
or wait for a pullback and a bounce off
the view up
see why the weekly view up makes for a
great entry in exit area
there are two main types of traits
breakouts and pullbacks
now from my back test I found that the
weekly view up works better when
combined with a momentum indicator like
the RSI
yes the RSI is lagging and it offers
many false signals on the lower time
frames but if you can use it correctly
with the right settings it can show you
the current momentum with decent
accuracy and no we won't use the RSI as
an overbought or oversold indicator
we'll use it 50 line instead
we'll use this indicator RSI candles
will change both values to 50.
we also change the length of the
indicator to 50.
the indicator changes the color of the
candles if the RSI is above or below its
middle line
when the RSI indicator is above 50 we
have bullish momentum and when the RSI
is below 50 we have bearish momentum
it's very easy to assess the current
state of the market price above the view
up bullish Trend green RSI candles
bullish momentum in this situation
you'll look for long signals
price below the view up bearish Trend
red RSI candles bearish momentum
now you look for cell signals
from a visual point of view you'll see
the trend and momentum almost instantly
if the trend is strong and there's also
momentum you should see something like
this
price breaks the weekly if you are blind
RSI maintains above its 50 line
so the candles remain green
and the price moves in a healthy uptrend
the same for short signals price breaks
the weekly view upline
RSI stays below its 50 line
the candles remain red
and the price moves lower and lower
these are the best market conditions
that you should trade when the RSI
candles don't change color and the price
remains above or below the weekly view
up
timing is everything in day trading and
scalping while prices may be trading
above below or at the view up you really
want to enter trades when price is about
to move away from that area
when it comes to a weekly view of
breakouts Buy Signal price moves above
the view up this can often signal that
sellers are exiting their positions or
buyers are gaining strength which moves
price above view up
now very important ideally the RSI is
already green at the time of the
Breakout
so there's polish momentum before the
weekly viewable Breakout
this is not a must-have condition but
there's something I've observed in my
back tests
and to filter signals is also good to
have a price action confirmation the
weekly view of RSI signal is stronger
and more reliable when price moves above
a previously resistance level or breaks
a trend line a Confluence which may
result in an extended price run
for a weekly view Up breakout cell
signal price moves below the view up
this time buyers are exiting their
positions or sellers are gaining
strength moving price below view up
the RSI in the best scenario is already
read at the time of the breakout there's
bearish momentum before the weekly view
Up breakout
if the candles are not red you wait
until you see the color change below the
view up
and this short signal is stronger when
price moves below a previous support
level or breaks a trend line
the second view of Entry is the pullback
one
when price is on an extended move upward
or downward and then makes a movement
towards the weekly view of line
if the RSI doesn't change its color
meaning the overall momentum is still on
this is a chance to buy or sell at the
weekly average price
if the RSI changes its color during the
pullback let's say price was below view
up RSI was red and comes back to the
weekly view up but the candles are now
green you have to rely on a price action
trigger to enter after the RSI crosses
once again below 50. again trend line
breakouts pin bars with big Wicks or
support and resistance breakouts are
valid signals
this is potion
prices below the weekly view up and the
RSI candles are red so this is a market
which favors short positions
we have this important support level
which was broken
so this is our price action trigger to
initiate a short
stop loss goes above the weekly view
upline and above this previous
resistance level
and we set a risk reward ratio of 2.
price returned once again near the view
up line
Market is making lower lows and lower
highs RSI candles are still red so if we
have a view of touch and rejection we'll
consider another short
that's unlucky price reversed before
touching the weekly view up
I prefer to enter close and very close
to the view of line I'm conservative
which means I will miss quite a few
trades if the trend is strong for a few
Pips I missed here a decent trade but if
you are not conservative you can enter
even if price isn't near the weekly view
up
let's continue again price almost
returns to the weekly view up but no
touch yet
okay now we have a breakout trade price
broke the weekly view up RSI candles
changed color before the actual Breakout
which is the ideal scenario
we also have several price action
triggers
I say this breakoff structure here
and I also see this trend line breakouts
so we enter a long position with a stop
below view up and below the swing low
we'll Target this swing High
things are easy when Market is trending
and has momentum
look at this weekly breakout trade right
here
RSI candles changed color right at the
breakout moment
the price action figure was this
trendline Breakout
under breakout trade a short one this
time
we have a breakout below view up with
RSI moving below 50 level
the trigger was the support Breakout
which is the neckline breakout of a head
and shoulders pattern
like I said when market trends it's easy
but how about when there's a range
more specifically when the RSI candles
change color often
look right here
even though price is above the weekly
view up the momentum is unclear
I have a rule to avoid getting chopped
or entering consecutive trades when the
market isn't moving
when the RSI changes its color four
times in a short amount of time you mark
the range and trade when price breaks it
so this is the job Zone with multiple
color changes
and you avoid trading inside of it
here's the signal we have a breakout to
the downside below the weekly view up
and the other side candles are red
now is the time to enter a short trade
stop goes above the view upline
and will Target the previous swing low
which offers a risk to reward ratio of
2.
I found that the weekly view up suits
the stock market better than any other
Market
stocks tend to have cleaner Trends and
seem to respect the view upline more
accurately
here's a short pullback on Tesla near
the weekly view offline
RSI candles maintained their red color
during the pullback so this is a valid
setup
we have a quite big up Gap with
consecutive candles breaking the view
upline
price is above the view up but the
candles are red so this is not a good
time to initiate any trade
now we have multiple changes in RSI
so let's mark the range
trade when we see a Breakout
[Music]
okay I'll take this short here
we have a view of Breakout
a breakout below the previous range
in the context of a downtrend as price
is making lower lows
we'll put the stop loss above view up
and will Target this previous swing low
[Music]
we had some downward momentum but now
price moved above the view upline
so we'll close the trade manually with a
small loss
another range is forming with RSI
Crossing its 50 level multiple times
again we'll mark the range and avoid
trading inside this channel
foreign
setup in the context of a larger
downtrend
will once again Target this swing low
[Music]
successful trade and I also see this
pullback trade right here a second
chance to enter if you missed the first
entry
one more aspect when you find yourself
analyzing a market which looks like this
one
with price moving above and below the
weekly view up multiple times again
don't trade
draw the channel and look for
opportunities when the trend is more
obvious
[Music]
foreign
if you want to see more videos like this
one leave us a like And subscribe
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time