today you'll discover how to think and
how to trade like market makers and
Banks and we'll cover one of their main
strategies to control the flow of orders
in the
market probably the most important
aspect of trading like a bank is to
focus on liquidity liquidity is the
lifeblood of the markets and it's a
concept that market makers and Banks
understand all too well these
institutions are like the Puppet Masters
of the trading world and they know how
to pull the strings of liquidity to
their advantage you see Banks and market
makers have a unique position in the
market they act as intermediaries
between buyers and sellers facilitating
trades and providing liquidity but they
don't do this out of the goodness of
their hearts no they're in it to make a
profit Banks and market makers have the
advantage of being able to see the order
flow the stream of buy and sell orders
coming into the market by analyzing this
flow they can evaluate the market
sentiment and position themselves
accordingly one of their main strategies
is to influence prices and create
temporary imbalances in supply and
demand here's how they do this let's say
the market is in a downtrend the price
has been falling and everyone is looking
to sell now at this point if you're a
bank sitting on a massive pile of orders
that you need to sell this might seem
like a tough situation after all who's
going to buy your positions when the
trend is so clearly pointing South well
market makers have a sneaky little trick
up their slaves they're not just going
to sit back and watch their assets
depreciate in value no they're going to
create a trap that will lure
unsuspecting Traders into buying their
positions all while maintaining the
overall
downtrend let's say the market makers
want to sell 10 million shares before
the price reaches is a certain lower
level they know that if they just start
dumping their shares onto the market
it's going to cause a panic and drive
the price down even further so they need
to be smart about this they need to
create a situation where people are
actually willing to buy even in the face
of a downtrend thus the market makers
will engineer a period of relative
stability in the price they'll start by
slowly buying up shares creating a
support a demand area that prevents the
price from falling further this buying
pressure will be just enough to
counteract the selling pressure from
other Market participants resulting in a
sideways movement in the price now
here's where the psychology comes in as
the price starts to consolidate some
Traders will begin to think that maybe
the downtrend is losing steam they'll
see the sideways movement and start to
wonder if the sellers are running out of
ammunition this is exactly what the
market makers want they're planting the
seed of doubt in the minds of other
Traders making them question their
bearish
bias as the consolidation continues more
and more Traders will start to feel like
they're missing out on a potential
reversal they'll see the price holding
steady and think that it might be a good
time to start buying it's a classic case
of fomo and the market makers are
counting on it but the market maker
aren't just going to sit back and hope
that Traders start buying on their own
no they're going to give them a little
nudge and that nudge comes in the form
of a false breakout to the upside the
market makers will strategically buy
pushing the price just above the
consolidation range this sudden burst of
buying pressure will be like a siren
song to other Traders luring them in
with the promise of a trend reversal as
the price breaks out to the upside many
Traders will interpret this as a signal
that the downtrend is over they'll start
jumping in buying in anticipation of a
major rally it's a classic bull trap and
the market makers are ready to
capitalize on it they'll start unloading
their shares into this new found buying
pressure dumping their orders onto the
market without causing the price to
Crash by creating this false breakout
the market makers have manufactured
liquidity out of thin air they've
tricked other Traders into buying their
positions all while maintaining the
illusion that the trend is reversing
it's a brilliant play and it's one that
they'll use time and time again to
manipulate the market to their advantage
and once the banks and market makers
have started to sell their shares
they'll pull the rug out from under the
buyers they'll start selling
aggressively driving the price back down
and trapping all those traders who
bought into the false breakout it's a
classic bump and dump scheme and it's
one that can leave naive Traders holding
the bag while the market makers laugh
all the way to the bank as the price
starts to fall back into the downtrend
many of the traders who bought during
the false breakout will start to panic
they'll realize that they've been duped
and will start selling off their shares
in a desperate attempt to cut their
losses this selling pressure will only
accelerate the downtrend pushing the
price lower and lower and that is how
the market makers create liquidity in a
downtrend they engineer a consolidation
lure in buyers with a false breakout and
then sell into that buying pressure
before resuming the downtrend it's a
devious little trick but it's one that
works time and time again you've
probably been a victim of it many times
before so what can you as a retail
Trader learn from this first and
foremost always be wary of
consolidations during Trends if the
price starts to move sideways after a
prolonged move don't assume that the
trend is reversing it could just be a
trap set by the market makers to lure in
unsuspecting Traders second look for
upside breakouts in a downtrend and
downside breakouts in an uptrend
especially if they occur after a period
of consolidation
these breakouts are often be signals
designed to trick Traders into buying or
selling before the real Trend resumes
this strategy of creating a liquidity is
really a masterful play that relies on
psychology and Market
manipulation in this chart the market
has been in a strong uptrend for the
past few months the buyers are in full
control and the overall sentiment is
positive however you know that Banks and
market May makers have a different plan
in mind they want to accumulate at lower
prices before the next leg up they
always look for opportunities to create
liquidity runs and sometimes you won't
see a consolidation like in the previous
example they'll start by gradually
selling pushing the price down and
creating a small pullback below a
previous minor or even major swing low
other times market makers will use this
initial selling pressure to set the
stage for a larger liquidity run they'll
engineer a period of consolidation where
the price starts to move sideways at
this point you need to be on the lookout
for false sell signals as the
consolidation continues market makers
will strategically push the price below
the lower boundary of the range this
downside breakout will trigger stoploss
orders and encourage traders to sell
thinking that the uptrend is over your
job is to Simply follow the market
makers grand plan you know they'll use
this selling pressure to accumulate at
lower prices tricking Traders into
giving up their positions once they've
accumulated enough they'll start buying
aggressively driving the price back up
and triggering a series of new buy
signals that's your cue to join the
uptrend here's another example observe
these consolidations and downward
pullbacks in the up TR all of these were
followed by liquidity runs engineered by
Banks to shake out weak hands and
accumulate at lower prices always look
for these false breakouts to the
downside especially if they occur after
a period of consolidation when you spot
a potential liquidity run you could move
to a lower time frame to pinpoint your
buy entry pay attention to upside
breakouts new higher highs or breakouts
above minor r resistance levels these
signals are your lower time frame
confirmation that the uptrend is still
intact and that market makers are back
to buying
positions just as Banks use liquidity
runs to accumulate in an uptrend they
also employ tactics to distribute in a
downtrend here we have this Market that
has been trending lower for several
weeks in this case you look for
consolidations and upward pullbacks
within the overall downtrend during
consolidation phase you need to be
patient and wait for the market makers
to strategically push the price above
the upper boundary of the range you know
that these upside breakouts triggered
new buy orders and encouraged traders to
go long Banks use this buying pressure
to distribute at higher prices
effectively tricking Traders into taking
on Long positions just before the next
leg down when you spot a potential
liquidity run in a Down Trend consider
moving to a lower time frame to pinpoint
your sell entry once the market makers
have distributed enough you know they'll
start selling aggressively driving the
price back down and triggering a series
of sell signals so you pay attention to
key sell signals such as new lower swing
lows and breaks below minor support
levels these signals can confirm that
the downtrend is still intact and that
market makers are back to selling
activities this whole process is a
masterful manipulation of Market
psychology and it's a strategy that
they'll use repeatedly as a retail
Trader your job is to stay vigilant
recognize these tactics and look for key
signals that confirm the previous Trend
you won't catch all the liquidity runs
and you won't be able to avoid all these
traps but with knowledge discipline and
a decent risk management plan you will
still find plenty of opportunities to
profit on all time frames and if you
want to learn other smart money tactics
you need to watch one of these videos
next