Let me tell you a secret: the charts
look different to professional traders!
That’s because they see the “manipulation”
candles that you don't!
These candles are the key
to understanding true market intent!
Stay till the end and I'll show you
what you've been missing!
When you place a trade,
you're full of hope and expectations.
Every time you enter, you're very
confident the market will move in your favor.
But often, almost as soon as you enter a trade,
the price starts moving in the opposite direction.
And in most cases, it all starts with
a manipulation candle.
A manipulation candle is
a price action pattern used by market makers, to
trick novice traders into taking losing positions.
These candles are designed
to create false signals,
that often lead to poor trading decisions.
Market makers, who have significant capital,
can move prices in ways that trigger
stop losses and create false breakouts.
They do this to collect liquidity from
other traders who often enter and place
their stop losses in predictable locations.
And it's not just a single candle, but a whole
sequence of price moves designed to trick traders.
So let’s talk about it, these are the most common
manipulation candles.
Candles with Big Wicks
Candles with big wicks are
some of the most deceptive and
manipulative tools used in the market.
At the core, big wicks represent areas
where the price moved significantly
in one direction, but failed to hold.
The long wick shows price rejection,
meaning it reached a point where the
market didn’t want to stay. This happens
because large players are moving the price,
to trigger certain actions from retail traders.
Big players know where most retail traders
place their stop-losses, or where
breakout traders are waiting to enter.
And by pushing the price to these
levels, they can activate these orders,
only to reverse the price and trap those traders.
The wick is the aftermath of this manipulation.
The manipulation works because most
novice traders react to price movements,
without considering the intention behind them.
The big players push the price up or down
aggressively, creating a sense of urgency.
Traders see this sudden move and think they’re
missing out on a potential
breakout or trend continuation.
The wick itself is the result of this push.
Breakout traders also enter the market,
thinking the move is real.
At the same time, traders who
had their stop losses set just beyond key
levels, get forced out of their trades.
These traders think the market is breaking out
of a range, or continuing in a strong direction.
And once the big players have triggered
enough orders and collected liquidity,
they reverse the price.
The candle closes far from
the extreme point of the wick, showing a large
rejection of that price level. Retail traders
who entered the market on the breakout are
now trapped in losing positions, while those
who got stopped out are left frustrated.
This manipulation relies on the fact that
traders tend to follow price blindly,
without understanding that the price
move was intentionally created to trap them.
Once you understand how this manipulation works,
you can use it to your advantage.
First, don’t jump into trades just
because the price moves past a key level.
Instead, wait to see how the candle closes.
If the candle has a big wick and closes near its
opening price (indicating rejection), this is a
sign that the previous breakout might be false.
You can then consider entering a trade in
the opposite direction.
Second, big wicks often
occur around major levels. These are areas
where big players know that traders have
placed their stop losses or breakout orders.
If you see a long wick forming at a key level,
it’s a sign that the big players
are hunting for liquidity.
You can use this as a signal to enter a
trade in the opposite direction of the wick.
Also, wicks are more common during
certain phases of the market.
In consolidation phases, big
players are accumulating positions,
and they use wicks to mislead traders
into thinking the market is breaking out.
Once they’ve accumulated enough positions,
they’ll move the market in the real direction,
often leaving a series of wicks
behind as a trail of manipulation.
The longer the wick, the stronger the
manipulation. A very long wick shows
that big players pushed the price far in
one direction, only to reverse it quickly.
This is a sign that they’re
actively trying to trap traders.
Shorter wicks, on the other hand, might just
be a sign of indecision or weak momentum.
If you see multiple long wicks forming
at the same level, it’s a strong sign.
The big players are repeatedly pushing
the price to that level to trigger orders,
but the price keeps getting rejected.
This is a sign that the market is about
to move in the opposite direction.
If you see this setup,
it’s a good opportunity to enter a trade
against the direction of the wicks.
Large Candles in Sideways Markets
Large candles in sideways markets are
another classic manipulation tactic.
These candles may even break out of a range,
causing traders to believe
a strong movement has begun,
only for the price to reverse shortly afterward.
When the market is moving sideways, it means
there’s a period of accumulation or indecision.
Prices are stuck within a range, bouncing between
support and resistance levels.
And big players use these
periods to build their positions.
But they also need liquidity to execute large
trades, without moving the market too much.
This is where large candles come into play.
What happens is that these big players push the
price suddenly in one direction, to create FOMO.
Reactive traders see the large candle and
enter the market, expecting the price to
continue in the direction of the candle.
This adds more liquidity for the big players,
to take the opposite side of the trade.
The large candle is essentially a trap. It
gives the illusion of a strong directional
move, but in reality, it’s a manipulation
tactic to create liquidity.
The candle may even break
outside the previous range.
This is a classic liquidity grab,
where big players need stop-loss
orders to fill their own positions.
These candles create emotional reactions in
traders. A sudden big move can make traders think
they’re missing out on an opportunity, causing
them to enter trades without proper confirmation.
This is a classic case of “Fear of Missing Out”.
I’ve personally done it dozens of times,
rushing into the market, thinking a large
candle signals the start of a new trend.
To avoid getting trapped, volume is my go-to
indicator when I’m facing a large candle.
If the candle forms on high volume but
the price quickly reverses, it’s a strong
sign that the move was actually a trap.
Big players were likely using the volume
spike to create liquidity for their own trades.
On the other hand, if a large candle forms on low
volume, it might be a sign of weak conviction,
and the breakout might not be sustainable.
Sometimes, you’ll see multiple large
candles forming in quick succession.
This is another manipulation tactic. Big
players will push the price in one direction,
then reverse it, then push it again,
creating a series of large candles.
This confuses traders, making them unsure
of whether the move is real or false.
If you see multiple large candles
forming in a sideways market,
it’s a sign that manipulation is at play, and
you should be cautious about entering a trade.
Inside Bars Followed by Weak Breakouts
Inside bars followed by weak breakouts are
one of the classic setups that
can often lead to losing trades.
An inside bar is a candle that forms completely
within the range of the previous candle.
Think of it as a sign of indecision
or consolidation in the market.
The price isn’t moving much, and traders
are waiting for something to happen.
Because the price is “stuck” within
the range of the previous candle,
traders know a breakout could be coming,
and they start preparing to enter trades,
based on whether the breakout
is bullish or bearish.
And when a series of inside bars form,
it amplifies the anticipation even more.
Traders are waiting for the
market to break out of this chop.
They know that once the price breaks out of
the range, it could lead to a strong move.
This is where the manipulation
starts to take root.
Well, during this time, big players
are building their positions.
They don’t want to reveal their hand, so
they keep the market within a tight range.
Novice traders, on the other hand,
are getting ready for a breakout.
A lot of retail traders start placing orders
just outside the range of the inside bars.
Buyers will place buy orders just above
the high of the inside bar, while sellers
will place sell orders just below the low.
This is exactly what big players want. They
are setting a trap by making the market look
like it’s ready to explode in one direction.
Then, the breakout happens. A candle breaks
out of the range of the inside bars. This
breakout candle may look extremely convincing.
It’s big, fast, and it creates a sense of urgency.
Many traders enter the market at this point. They
believe the breakout is real, and they don’t want
to miss out on the potential profits.
And this is exactly what the big players
want. They’ve lured the traders into
the market at the worst possible moment.
Then the price reverses sharply. The breakout
candle that looked so convincing is suddenly
followed by a reversal candle, and the
price moves in the other direction.
Traders who entered on the breakout
are now trapped in losing positions.
This manipulation works because it preys
on the natural instincts of traders.
Inside bars create a sense of anticipation,
and breakout candles create a sense of urgency.
When we see a large candle breaking
out of a consolidation zone,
we assume it’s the start of a new trend.
We don’t want to miss out on the move, so we
enter the market without waiting for confirmation.
This is exactly the reaction that big players
are counting on.
The key to avoiding
this type of setup is confirmation.
After the breakout candle forms, wait to see the
price reaction when it retests the breakout level.
If the breakout is real, the price will often
pull back to the breakout level, and then
continue in the direction of the breakout.
If the price breaks out and then quickly reverses,
it’s a sign that the breakout was false.
And second, a real breakout is often
accompanied by a significant increase in volume.
If the breakout candle forms but there’s no
increase in volume, it could be a sign that the
breakout is weak and likely to reverse.
Bullish/Bearish Kicker
Bullish and Bearish Kicker patterns
are also common manipulate on patterns.
These often involve a gap, followed by a strong
move in the opposite direction of the previous
trend, catching many traders by surprise.
A Bullish Kicker happens after a downtrend, right
at the New York open. The market gaps down at the
open, but instead of continuing in the direction
of the downtrend, it reverses sharply and moves
upward, forming a strong bullish candle.
A Bearish Kicker happens after an uptrend.
The market gaps up at the open, but instead
of continuing higher, it reverses sharply and
moves downward, forming a strong bearish candle.
Kicker patterns primarily occur because of
a sudden shift in sentiment in the market.
But this shift isn’t always organic.
Often, it’s manufactured by bigger players.
Just like with many other
manipulative tactics, the main goal
of a Kicker pattern is to create liquidity.
For instance, in a Bearish Kicker, traders who
are long will typically have their stop-loss
orders placed just below key support levels.
By pushing the price up and then sharply
reversing, big players can trigger those
stop-losses, creating the liquidity they
need to enter their own short positions.
Kicker patterns prey on traders’ emotions.
In a Bullish Kicker, the market may gap down,
and traders will assume that the downtrend
will continue. But when the price suddenly
reverses and moves upward, traders
get confused and start to panic.
This panic leads many traders to exit their
positions at a loss or reverse their trades,
which plays into the hands of big players.
The manipulation process in Kicker patterns
works because of a combination of
psychological and technical traps.
The first part of the
manipulation involves the gap.
This gap is designed to make traders
think the trend is going to continue.
For example, when the market
gaps down in a Bullish Kicker,
traders believe that the downtrend is still
intact and that the price will continue to fall.
So, at the market open, many
traders enter short positions.
But after the gap, the price suddenly reverses
and moves strongly in the opposite direction.
This is where the manipulation
becomes obvious. Traders who
entered short positions after the gap are now
trapped. as the price moves against them.
As the price moves in the opposite direction,
it triggers stop-losses that were placed
by sellers on the wrong side of the market.
This creates liquidity for big
players to enter their positions.
This allows them to buy at lower prices
before the price continues higher.
Big players create the Kicker pattern
to induce fear and confusion, causing
reactive traders to make emotional decisions.
Many of them will exit their positions in a
panic, while others will reverse their
trades, trying to catch the new move.
Volume can provide clues about whether
the Kicker pattern is real or manipulated.
If the gap and the strong move in the opposite
direction are accompanied by high volume,
it’s more likely that the move is legitimate.
One of the best ways to capitalize on Kicker
patterns is to trade the reversal.
Once you see that the initial breakout
was false and the price is reversing, you
can enter a trade in the opposite direction.
For example, if you see a Bullish Kicker and
the price quickly reverses after the gap,
you can enter a short position, expecting
the price to continue downwards
Spinning Top
Spinning top candles are fascinating because
they represent indecision in the market.
These candles have small real
bodies, regardless of whether
they are bullish or bearish, and they
come with long wicks on both sides.
The small body shows that there wasn’t much
movement between the opening and closing prices.
The long wicks indicate that
both buyers and sellers had their
moments of control during the period.
The result is a candle that tells us the
market isn’t sure where it wants to go next.
This candle traps both buyers and sellers,
having large wicks on both sides.
But spinning tops aren’t just about
indecision. They also present opportunities
for manipulation, especially when they
appear at key levels in the market.
So here, the market is in an uptrend,
and then a spinning top appears.
It implies that neither the buyers nor
the sellers had enough momentum to push
the price decisively in one direction.
The market is essentially “taking a
break,” reassessing its next move.
These candles often appear
at the end of a big move,
signaling that the trend might be losing steam.
This spinning top might indicate that the buyers
are getting tired, and the sellers might soon
take control, potentially leading to a reversal.
However, spinning tops are often used
as tools for market manipulation because
they play on traders’ emotions.
When traders see a spinning top,
they know it represents indecision in the market.
Many traders interpret this as a sign that
a big move is coming, especially if the
spinning top forms at the end of a trend.
They believe that the market is “pausing”
before making its next big move, and they
start positioning themselves for that move.
Beginners are taught to place buy orders above
the high of the spinning top,
or sell orders below the low.
This is where the manipulation comes
in. Big players know that novice traders
are waiting for a breakout. They use
this anticipation to their advantage.
They’ll push the price just high enough to
trigger the buy orders placed by bullish traders,
or just low enough to trigger the
sell orders placed by bearish traders.
And once the big players have triggered
these orders, they reverse the price.
For example, let’s say a spinning
top forms after a momentum up move.
Traders place buy orders above the high of the
spinning top, thinking the market will continue
higher. The big players push the price just above
the high to trigger those buy orders, then quickly
reverse the price, causing the market to drop.
The traders who entered long positions
are now trapped in losing trades.
And they rush to close their positions,
adding even more momentum to the reversal.
This is exactly what the big players want.
They’ve engineered the move to create panic
and force traders to exit their positions at
a loss, all while profiting from the
liquidity created by those exits.
Volume can confirm whether a
spinning top is likely to lead
to a real move or if it’s just a trap.
If the spinning top forms on low volume,
it could be a sign that the market is
indecisive and that the breakout will be weak.
On the other hand, if the spinning top forms on
high volume, it could indicate that there’s real
buying or selling pressure behind the move.
One of the best ways to avoid getting trapped
is to wait for a retest of the breakout level.
For instance, if a spinning top forms at the end
of an uptrend and the price breaks
below the low of the spinning top,
wait to see if the price retests that
level before entering a short position.
If the price bounces off the retest and continues
lower, it’s a sign that the breakdown is real.
If the price moves back above the level,
it’s a sign that the breakdown was false,
and you should avoid entering a short position.
And be aware of key levels. Spinning tops are
most effective when they form at
key support or resistance levels.
Sometimes, you’ll see multiple spinning tops
forming in a row. This is a sign that the
market is in a prolonged state of indecision.
While this might seem like a strong signal that
a big move is coming, be careful.
Big players know that traders are
watching these patterns, and they’ll often use the
series of spinning tops to set up a bigger trap.
If you see multiple spinning tops forming,
it’s a sign that you should be extra cautious
about entering a trade.
Weekly Candle Manipulation
On higher timeframes like the weekly chart,
manipulation tends to follow a pattern.
For example, the price opens at
the start of the week and trades
near the opening level for a few days.
Then, the price moves sharply in one
direction. Traders think this is a
real move and enter their trades.
Finally, the price reverses, trapping those
traders and completing the manipulation phase.
This type of manipulation is powerful
because it plays out over several days,
making it harder for traders to spot.
Big players use this strategy to build their
positions slowly before making the real move.
So on higher timeframes like the weekly chart,
manipulation plays out in a more
deliberate and extended manner,
making it harder for retail traders to detect.
This manipulation process occurs in distinct
phases, allowing big players to
build and distribute their positions,
while misleading retail traders along the way.
The weekly chart, in particular, is an ideal
playground for large institutions, because the
moves are more spread out, giving the illusion
of a natural price progression over several days.
At the start of the week, the price often opens
and trades near the opening level for a few days.
This is the accumulation phase. During this time,
the big players are quietly
building their positions.
The price moves within a narrow range,
often showing little volatility.
To the untrained eye, this sideways movement
may seem uneventful, but this is where the
groundwork for the upcoming manipulation is laid.
Accumulation can be deceptive because it often
looks like a period of indecision in the market.
Retail traders might interpret this as a lack
of opportunity, but in reality,
the big players are positioning
themselves for the move that’s about to come.
During this phase, large players are collecting
liquidity, by filling their orders without
causing much movement in price, which could
otherwise draw attention from other traders.
The price may oscillate slightly, but it
remains close to the weekly open, keeping
traders guessing about the next big move.
After 1 or 2 days of trading near the open,
the next phase of manipulation begins.
The price suddenly moves sharply in one direction.
This move is quick and decisive, designed to lure
traders into thinking that a breakout is underway.
For example, if the weekly candle opens and
trades near the opening level for a few
days, and suddenly the price shoots down,
most retail traders will interpret
this as a strong bearish signal.
They believe that the market is about to
go down, and rush to place sell orders.
This is exactly what the big players want.
By creating this sharp move, they trigger
sell orders from traders and, more importantly,
stop-loss orders placed by traders who were long.
This sharp move creates a liquidity pool. The
traders who enter the market after seeing the
sharp move, are providing liquidity for
the big players to execute their trades.
At this point, the big players have not
yet fully entered their desired positions.
They are using this move to mislead the market,
making other traders believe that the price will
continue, in the direction of the sharp move.
The sharp move creates a sense of urgency,
and traders often forget to wait for
confirmation before entering trades.
They see the price moving quickly and assume
that they are missing out on an opportunity.
This emotional reaction is precisely
what the big players are counting on.
Unlike shorter timeframes, where
manipulation might happen in minutes
or hours, the weekly chart stretches the
process over one or even several days.
This makes it harder for retail
traders to spot the manipulation,
because the price action seems more legitimate
when viewed over a longer timeframe.
After trapping retail traders with the
sharp move, the big players are ready
for the final phase: distribution.
This is where the real trickery
happens. The price, now reverses.
The long wick that formed on the weekly
candle is a classic sign of this reversal.
Traders who entered positions based on the
sharp move are now trapped, as
the price moves against them.
For example, as the price shot down earlier in the
week, it now creates a long wick to the downside,
and reverses, moving upward.
Retail traders who sold into
the sharp downward move are stuck in losing
positions, as the market turns against them.
Their stop-losses get triggered, or they
panic and close their positions at a loss.
The distribution phase allows the big
players to exit their positions profitably.
They had built their positions
during the accumulation phase and
used the sharp move to trigger liquidity.
Now, as the price reverses, they begin to
unwind their positions, selling to traders who are
desperately trying to exit their losing trades.
Again, if you trade on lower time
frames, you will get trapped.
One of the reasons why this type of manipulation
is so effective on higher timeframes,
is that it plays out over several days.
Traders are more likely to believe that
a move is genuine, as it unfolds slowly over
time, especially when compared to the rapid
manipulation that occurs on lower timeframes.
On a weekly chart, the manipulation doesn’t
happen in a single candle or a quick spike.
Instead, it stretches across multiple days,
making it harder to detect.
Traders might see the price
moving sharply in one direction and
assume that the momentum will continue,
not realizing that they are being led into a trap.
The longer timeframe also gives big players
more room to build, and distribute their
positions without drawing too much attention.
Additionally, the longer timeframe allows the
big players to manipulate the market in a way
that makes the move seem more believable.
A sharp move on a lower timeframe might
be dismissed as a “fakeout” by experienced
traders, but on a weekly chart, the same move
can look like the start of a legitimate trend.
This makes it easier for the big players to
mislead traders and trap them in losing positions.
Now, if you want to learn other smart money
tactics, you need to watch
one of these videos next.