many Traders get confused between the
concepts of supply and demand and
support and resistance so let's start
with that with the difference between
those two concepts
price movement is often an asymmetric
process where many opinions exchange
creating chaotic Behavior
still every so often buyers or sellers
align on the same opinion and price
which forms the supply or demanding
balance around that price thus forming a
supply or demand Zone at a specific
price location
supply and demand zones are advanced
concepts of support and resistance these
zones are the areas that show high
liquidity and pending orders at a
specific price a supply zone is a price
area above the current price where there
is strong selling interest
when the price reaches this level the
orders get filled and it moves down
this is a supply Zone where many sellers
are located
you'll find a lot of selling pressure in
this Zone
so the prices get rejected
a demand zone is a price area below the
current price where there is strong
buying interest
this is a demand Zone where many buyers
are located there's buying pressure in
the zone
so prices will likely Advance after
reaching it
a significant imbalance in price is
created when a large number of orders
are filled supply and demand zones show
unfilled orders of institutional Traders
now supporting resistance levels and
supply and demand areas are two
different trading Concepts that are very
similar they both indicate points where
the price can reverse
and you can find them everywhere on the
charts
the big difference between the two is
that support and resistance often works
on historical older and tested levels
while supply and demand especially on
Fresh levels
important resistance trading is
particularly strong in multiple touches
of the previous levels
some say that if price has responded to
a price level multiple times in the past
that level is significant
when trading support and resistance the
idea is if price reversed multiple times
from roughly the same point in the past
then it has a good chance of doing the
same in the future
so when trading based on support and
resistance you must identify where these
lines are located in the market you look
for points where multiple reversals
started from similar prices
here's a level with multiple reversals
you can see that each of the reversals
originated from prices which are quite
close to one another
so a resistance level must be found
somewhere close to where this reversal
started
and here are other reversals
again each of the reversals you see
started from similar prices
which means there is a support line
around here
trading supply and demand things are
different
if you adopt this concept you'll mainly
look for new zones a supply or demand
zone is a fresh untouched area where
price spent less time
you don't watch in the history of a
market for the validity of the zone
you don't wait for multiple retests of
the same area
several big candles and just one base
candle could make a valid supply for the
main Zone
now another difference support and
resistance trading is related not only
to best price swings round numbers
Fibonacci or again levels are also areas
of Attraction and price reversal areas
price spent a decent amount of time at
these levels every time price comes to
these levels it tends to take a reversal
or a Breakout
if price will break the support Zone
then the support will become resistance
and vice versa this is a common trading
strategy which is actually very powerful
when traded correctly but in the case of
supply and demand
this concept doesn't apply contrary to
what some may say a supply Zone which is
broken doesn't turn into a demand Zone
I would even say that all support and
resistance lines were originally
supplies and demand zones
this is how support and resistance are
created
they are essentially the confirmed
supply and demand levels
so supply and demand are fresh levels
War zones where a price has not been
determined yet
therefore these levels are valid trade
support and resistance are levels or
lines in which the price was already
determined
changed a few times
supplying them and Traders say that
support and resistance levels are
somewhat riskier than trading supply and
demand that's because having a Zone you
can use to watch for entries is much
easier than having a level
when price tests the same level the
chances for a breakout increase
probably the biggest problem when
creating support and resistance levels
is the fact that price will often fail
to turn exactly on the level itself
you know it so well you expect the
perfect Mouse a right to the people
rejection when you place your level
but oftentimes price will either move
slightly beyond the level before
reversing
or will reverse before touching the
level
this can make trading support and
resistance levels a frustrating
experience
and that's the main advantage of supply
and demand zones they offer you an area
at which the market should reverse
you don't have to find a reversal signal
forming at an exact point like it when
trading support and resistance levels
you have a whole Zone you can use to
place your trades
as long as the signal was found inside
the supplier demand Zone it's a sign
that the rejection could follow
now here's a common mistake many Traders
think because supply and demand is so
similar to support and resistance these
zones can cause multiple reversals as
support and resistance levels do
while this makes sense it's not true
supply and demand zones are a one-time
use
after price returns to a Zone and
reverses it's better to find another
area
the probability it will cause another
reversal lowers
the reason supply and demand zones only
work once is because they form from the
smart money buying and selling the whole
concept of supply and demand is centered
around finding smart money orders on a
price chart
price returns to supply domain zones
because the banks have not got all their
trades placed or they haven't take all
their profits off
so the reason why zones don't work
multiple times is that the smart money
have no reason to make price come back
after the first touch
they can get most of their trades placed
creating the Zone causing price to
return and then reverse
too many Traders put too much attention
to older Supply demand levels while the
actual strength hides within fresh
levels
some say that all supplying demand zones
have the same probability of causing a
reversal as new songs
they say that all zones perform the same
as the new zones there's no difference
between them and when you look at the
charts you may think this is true
all zones cause reversals all the time
if you go back weeks months or even
years on your charts you will find all
zones that have caused price to reverse
but let's consider how supply and demand
zones form and why they work the way
they do
so Banks cause a supply or demand Zone
to form by either placing trades or
taking profits then they cause price to
come back to a Zone because they haven't
been able to get all of their trades
placed or take all of their profits off
but why would they wait months or years
to do this
if they placed a bunch of Trades because
they want price to increase why would
they wait a few months to get the rest
of the orders placed for me it just
doesn't make sense that the banks would
wait weeks months or years or price to
come back to a Zone just to get a few
leftover trades placed
if they want to get their remaining
traits placed or take their profit
they'll make price come back to a Zone
quickly
they won't wait that long they'll do it
as soon as possible
so when it comes to supply and demand
zones and support and resistance levels
the time factor is going to have a huge
impact
order flow will reposition itself over
time that is a statistical mathematical
factor meaning that the pressure that
Supply or demand is the more likely it
is that order flow is still present in
its previous form or new Traders will
react to it much more likely compared to
any historical old price levels
so simple rule always focus on what
price structures are doing right now on
your right side of the chart and not far
back on the left side
fresh order flow will be found in the
newly formed structures
if you want to be quick in spotting
rotations that is absolutely a must to
understand
so focus on the right side over the left
side of the chart
make this a priority sure historical
price action does matter but near-term
fresh price action always should have a
priority
blotting supply and demand should be
done with some logical approach
often Traders tend to pull load charts
with 20 or 30 levels where the whole
meaning of anticipating the rejections
will lose its value
there is a low value when having a chart
completely cluttered with levels where
the trader expects that every micro move
of the price should retest some old
historical Zone and price reacting to it
when it comes to efficient plotting of
supply and demand zones on the chart
there are several variables that you
should follow
first number one rule in supply and
demand Trading
first time retrace to the base is the
strongest to enter
always make sure the zone is still fresh
which means that after the initial
creation of the zone price has not
returned to it yet
also consider the time spent at the
supply or demand level
how much time did the price spend at the
zone
the last time price spends at its own
the more out of balance supply and
demand are at that price level
this means smart money or aggressively
placing orders
you also want to analyze how far the
price moved away from the zone
look for extremely strong turning points
these are high probability price levels
and I said it before pay attention to
the most recent zones
have only the nearest ones inside and
keep your chart clean
another variable to identify the
strength of the supply or demand zone is
the volume at which price formed the
zone
the stronger the volume the more
important The Zone could be once the
price redests it
if you want to know more about volume
watch this video next to learn how to
identify buying or selling volume
check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time