Chart patterns are a crucial component of
trading.
Each chart pattern offers a unique outlook
on the potential price movement.
Today we’ll discuss one high probability
continuation formation known as the Flag pattern,
and by the end of this video, you will know
exactly how to spot the pattern accurately…and
be able to trade it confidently and profitably.
The Flag pattern is one of the best-known
continuation formations in trading, which
typically appears as a minor consolidation
between impulsive legs of a trend.
When this pattern forms on the chart, there’s
a high likelihood that the price action will
break in the direction of the prevailing trend.
The Flag pattern consists of two parts – a
flag pole and a flag.
Let’s take a closer look at each of these
two components.
The first component of the Flag chart pattern
is the Flag Pole.
It represents a trend impulse on the chart.
After creating the pole, a valid Flag pattern
will then begin to trade within a tight range,
taking on the shape of a Flag.
The Flag consists of price action with evenly
distributed tops and bottoms.
At the same time, this price action has a
corrective character on the graph.
In this manner, it is angled contrary to the
trend impulse creating the pole.
There are two types of Flag chart patterns
based on their structure and potential – a
bearish Flag and a bullish Flag.
Each of these is the absolute opposite of
the other.
The bear Flag pattern forms during bearish
trends.
The figure starts with a bearish trend impulse
and turns into a correction, which is directed
upwards.
During the correction phase, the tops and
the bottoms are evenly distributed, creating
a parallel channel.
The confirmation of the Bear Flag setup comes
when the price action breaks the flag channel
boundary downwards.
When the breakout occurs, we have the opportunity
to short the asset.
The Bull Flag pattern is the opposite of the
Bear Flag pattern in appearance.
First, it forms during bullish trends.
The pattern begins with a bullish trending
move, which then pauses and turns into a minor
bearish correction.
The tops and the bottom of this correction
are parallel as well.
The confirmation of the Bullish Flag pattern
happens with the upside breakout, and we would
prepare for a long position.
The Flag Pattern has a continuation potential
on the chart.
A valid flag pattern is likely to push the
price action further in the direction of the
Flag Pole – the trend impulse.
In addition to this, when you spot a Flag
formation on your price chart, you can measure
the approximate price target of the formation.
There are two targets related to the Flag
formation:
The first target of a confirmed Flag pattern
can be derived using the measured move technique.
The measured move target is a distance equal
to the size of the flag.
To measure the size of the flag, you would
just take the vertical distance between the
upper and the lower channel within the flag.
Then you would apply this distance starting
from the breakout point.
Your first target is located at the end of
this distance.
Target 2: Size of the Pole
The next target of the Flag formation equals
the size of the Flag Pole.
So, to get this target, you need to measure
the vertical distance between the high and
the low of the Pole.
Once you get that distance, you will need
to apply it to the pattern.
Again, as we did with Target 1, you would
apply it starting from the breakout point.
Now that we discussed some of the characteristics
of the Bull and Bear Flag, let’s create
a concrete trading strategy around this setup.
At first, I want to add two Exponential Moving
Averages, to help us identify an uptrend or
a downtrend easily.
In this case I added the 21 and 55 EMA, but
you can choose any length you prefer.
When the 21 EMA is above the 55 EMA, we consider
the market to be in an uptrend.
So we only want to start looking for the Bull
Flag Pattern when the 21 EMA has crossed above
the 55 EMA.
If the 21 EMA is below the 55 EMA, we will
look for Bear Flag Patterns.
Why this filter?
Because when the market is trading above the
21 EMA, for example, it means there is strong
momentum to the upside.
And any Bull Flag Patterns that are formed
above the 21 EMA have a higher chance of succeeding.
To enter a Flag pattern trade, you should
first obtain a confirmation signal.
The confirmation of the Flag comes with the
breakout.
If you have a bullish flag, you will buy when
the price action closes a candle above the
upper side.
If you have a bearish flag, then you would
sell the asset when you see a candle closing
below the lower level of the pattern.
One basic rule should be considered when determining
the proper stop loss placement.
If the price breaches the opposite side of
the breakout, then you should immediately
exit the trade, because the pattern is most
likely false.
The most logical location to place the stop
loss would be beyond the most extreme swing
within the Flag structure.
So, if you were trading a bullish flag, then
your stop should be placed below the lowest
bottom in the Flag.
The take profit for the Flag pattern should
be addressed using the two targets we discussed
earlier.
It is up to you which target you are going
to pursue.
However, I would suggest taking profits at
each target level to reduce risk and book
profits.
To enter into a trade using the Flag Pattern,
I also prefer to look for a candlestick pattern
that forms on the dynamic area offered by
the 2 EMAs, namely the engulfing candle and
the pin bar.
These 2 candlestick patterns are the trigger
for us to get into a trade.
If you trade a bullish flag for example, and
you have a bullish candlestick that forms
on the 21 EMA, it suggests that the EMA has
held up as a dynamic support level.
At the same time, a bullish candlestick pattern
suggests that the market has a good chance
of going up after its formation.
Basically, you want a confluence of these
elements to give you a high probability of
the trade working out.
So how do you enter into the trade once these
candlestick patterns appear?
There are 2 main entries.
The first one was to wait for a breakout,
which is a more conservative way to trade.
The second entry method is a more aggressive
entry because you do not wait for a confirmation
of the move and take a trade before the breakout,
at the close of the candlestick pattern inside
the flag pattern or at the break of the high
or low of the candlestick.
By confirmation, it means to wait for another
event to happen to give you a better indication
that the market will be going up for example,
if you trade a bull flag.
This means you don’t wait for the breakout
to happen.
With this entry, you will have a higher risk-to-reward
ratio for the same take profit level…
But the trade-off is that you will get stopped
out more often.
The ideal scenario would be a pin bar or an
engulfing candle that forms right when the
price breaks the flag, but this is rare setup.
I prefer to have a confluence of factors,
namely the price rejecting the dynamic area
formed by the 2 EMAs, the formation of a candlestick
pattern and a flag breakout.
With any trading setup, the more signals you
have supporting the direction of your trade,
the higher the chances of your trade working
out.
Here are several examples of valid trades.
If you trade stocks, many traders use volume
as an added confluence of trade signals.
What you want to look out for is for an increase
in volume when the market starts moving up
from the Bull Flag Pattern, for example.
Here, you can see that the volume has increased
when the market broke out from the Bull Flag
Pattern.
This shows that there are buyers coming in
to push the market up.
And this gives traders an added validation
that the Bull Flag Pattern has a higher chance
of working out.
As a side note, in the Forex Market, you can’t
use volume because there’s no centralized
exchange.
This means the volume you see in the Forex
market is not an accurate representation of
the total volume in the market.
You can also increase the flag pattern’s
probability with divergence.
A divergence is when the market is moving
in a different direction than your indicator.
There are a few indicators that can identify
divergence…But what I like to use is the
Stochastic Oscillator.
To identify a divergence on the Bull Flag
Pattern for example, what we’re looking
for is for the market to be forming a higher
low but the Stochastic Oscillator to form
a lower low.
This is called a hidden divergence.
Also, remember the previous confluence elements
we discussed before.
Thus, at the point where the candlestick pattern
is formed, we want the Stochastic Oscillator
to form a lower low.
Here’s an example.
We have hidden divergence, as the market is
making a higher low but the Stochastic Oscillator
is making a lower low.
The setup is even more powerful is it contains
a candlestick formation or if the price rejects
the dynamic area formed by the 2 EMAs.
So whenever you are looking for an entry,
you want to see that there is a hidden divergence
to give you the added confluence that the
Flag Pattern will work out.
Here, you can see that the market is clearly
in a downtrend.
The 21 EMA is below the 55 EMA, and the market
is forming lower lows and lower highs.
The market went down and formed the Bear Flag’s
flagpole in a few bars.
After that, the market started consolidating
and moved sideways.
If you noticed, the bars are relatively smaller
as well.
This is a sign that the market is preparing
for a possible downwards move.
Just as the price entered the dynamic resistance
area , it formed a Bearish Engulfing Candle.
At this point, you can see that the Stochastic
Oscillator is indicating a hidden divergence.
So this is a valid trade signal.
The market will give you many opportunities
to trade this setup.
However, you don’t want to make the mistake
of trading every single one of them.
You will be tempted to trade it every time
it shows up.
But if you see a Flag Pattern that doesn’t
fulfill our confluence setup, give it a miss.
Be patient and wait for the next opportunity.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.