Traders spend much of their time looking at
charts and analyzing, using technical or fundamental
analysis, or a combination of both.
While these indeed are very good things to
spend time on, not all traders take the time
to focus on, risk management, and more specific,
position sizing.
I see a lot of new and old traders or investors
which trade, only to have their accounts blown
up by taking random positions, with no plan
whatsoever.
Proper position sizing is a key element in
risk management and can determine whether
you live to trade another day or not.
Basically, your position size is the number
of shares you take on a trade.
It can keep you from risking too much on a
trade and blowing up your account.
Without knowing how to size your positions
properly, you may end up taking trades that
are far too large for your account.
In such cases, you become highly vulnerable
when the market moves even just a few points
against you.
Your position size, or trade size, is more
important than your entry and exit when trading
or investing.
You can have the best strategy in the world,
but if your trade size is too big or too small
you'll either take too much or too little
risk.
So, how do you prevent yourself from risking
too much?
How do you know the right quantity to buy
or to sell when you initiate a position?
Let’s say you have $10,000 in your account
and there’s a stock valued at $100 you like
and want to buy.
Do you buy 100 shares, 10 shares, or some
other number?
This is the question you must answer—how
to determine your position size.
If you decide to spend your entire account
balance and buy 100 shares, then you will
have a 100% commitment in this stock.
And that’s not indicated.
Also, in taking a position that represents
a large portion of your total portfolio, there
is also the opportunity cost involved.
You would have to pass up other trades that
you may have liked to enter.
Position sizing is a critical issue that a
trader needs to know beforehand and not do
on the fly.
It’s as important as picking the right stock
or currency to invest.
Newer traders or investors like to calculate
how much they could make on the upside, how
much money they could potentially make, and
focus less on how much money they could potentially
lose.
There are several approaches to position sizing,
and I will run down some of the more popular
ones.
The first one, and the most common one: Fixed
percentage per trade
Position sizing can be based on the size of
an overall portfolio.
This means a percentage of that overall capital
will be predetermined per trade and will not
be exceeded.
That could be 1% or even 5%.
This fixed percentage is an easy way for you
to know how much you are buying when you buy.
To use a simple example of fixed-percentage
position sizing, take again a $10,000 account
size and a $100 stock.
If you take a simple 1% position based on
your account size, that comes down to a single
share.
You may be thinking you are no better off
than a person with a $100 account buying one
share.
The difference is that the $100 account holder
has a 100% position size while the $10,000
account holder is putting just 1% at risk.
Which position size allows a trader to sleep
better at night?
Of course the second one.
Position sizing helps control risk.
A 1% hard limit on each trade allows you to
tolerate many losses in search of profits.
Protecting your capital is your primary job.
Your secondary job is allowing room in your
portfolio to find other trading opportunities.
The fixed percentage amount is an easy approach
to accomplish this.
The second risk management approach involves
fixed-dollar amount per trade
This approach also uses a fixed amount but
this time it’s a fixed-dollar amount per
trade rather than a percentage of the actual
portfolio.
This involves choosing a number.
Again using that same $10,000 portfolio as
an example, say you decide you won’t spend
any more than, say, $200 on any one trade.
For traders with small account sizes, this
can be an attractive approach because it limits
how much you can lose.
However, it also limits what stocks you can
buy.
You will have to rule out some securities
based solely on their price.
Of course, this is not necessarily a bad thing.
The third approach: Volatility-based position
sizing
A more complex approach but one that allows
for more flexibility is position sizing based
on the volatility of the security you plan
to purchase.
It’s more dynamic because it doesn’t treat
each stock the same.
This approach allows you to really drill down
and exercise finer control over your portfolio.
For example, growth stocks will invariably
be more volatile and that volatility will
be reflected in your portfolio.
To reduce the overall risk of your portfolio,
you would buy less of higher volatility stocks
than you would buy lower-volatility stocks.
You can measure volatility with something
as simple as a standard deviation over a given
period, say, 15 or 10 trading days.
Then, depending on the deviation, you adjust
the amount of shares you buy when you initiate
a position.
This allows lower-volatility stocks to have
more weight in your portfolio than higher-volatility
ones.
Position sizing based on this ideology lowers
overall volatility within a portfolio.
This strategy is frequently used in large
portfolios and I use it personally in my own
portfolio.
Even longer-term traders and investors face
position sizing questions.
For them, when the price of a security they
are holding goes down, it represents more
value.
Adding to their position in this case is referred
to as averaging down.
Long-term traders can decide to average down
using similar position-sizing approaches,
by risking either a fixed-dollar amount or
a percentage amount when the stock trades
down.
You can use standard deviation here as well
to help figure out that amount.
Averaging down needs to be used with caution,
because if your analysis is wrong, at some
point you’ll be in a position which is no
longer worth holding.
You don’t want to average down to zero by
buying all the way down.
Some additional common sense risk parameters
seem worth mentioning and may be incorporated
into your trade plan.
For example, to be safe, you must be able
to accept losing on any given trade and to
be able to survive taking losses on ten consecutive
trades.
And those ten consecutive losses should not
exceed a total 25 percent drawdown.
This means that no more than two percent of
the portfolio should be put at risk on any
particular trade.
Once you figured out how much you are comfortable
losing, a stop loss level for each trade should
be determined and placed in the market.
A seasoned trader will generally know where
to put their stop loss orders after having
optimized their trading plan, and chart analysis
is often performed when setting stop loss
levels.
Two rules of thumb should be followed when
you use stops to manage risk on your positions:
First…Never adjust the stop loss to arrive
at a desired position size, but instead adjust
the size of the position to meet your risk
level and desired stop loss order placement
based on your analysis.
Second…Trade using the same risk parameters
on every trade regardless of the distance
of the stop loss.
Avoid putting more money at risk to use a
wider stop, and avoid risking any less money
on a stop closer to the trading level.
Adjust your position to meet your predetermined
risk levels.
By now, I hope you realized that correct position
sizing is crucial.
You should always consider how much you buy
when you buy, and also, know how you came
up with that number.
Regardless of your account size, take the
time to come up with a consistent approach
that matches your trading style.
And then stick to it.
You can incorporate flexibility.
For example, if you are willing to take more
risk with your portfolio, you can dial up
the percentage you use.
Sound money management techniques can help
make an average trader become better, and
a good trader become great.
For example, a trader that is only right half
the time but gets out of losing trades before
the loss becomes significant, and knows to
ride winners to a substantial profit, would
be way ahead of most others who trade with
no clear plan of action whatsoever.
And you have to find the right balance because
if you risk too little and your account won't
grow, and if risk too much and your account
can be destroyed in few bad trades.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like to show your support and make
sure you subscribe and hit the bell icon to
stay notified when we upload new videos.
Until next time.