I'm about to reveal a powerful technique
you could apply right now using three
moving averages which will allow you to
read any Market with high accuracy we'll
cover multiple scenarios by analyzing
price position and the movement of
moving averages by the end of the video
you'll know exactly what is the state of
the General market structure Trend or
range the trend Direction up or down if
there are impulsive moves if there are
corrective moves if we have Dynamic
support or resistance if we have a trend
continuation or if a trend reversal is
imminent
you know the trail like subscribe and
stick around for the full video
let's look at the market which is an
uptrend
I added three moving averages the length
is not important yet
the first one is a 20 EMA the second one
is the 100 EMA and the third one is the
200 dma
this is the simplest definition of a
trend for an uptrend price is above or
at the 20 EMA which is above the 100 EMA
and above the 200 EMA
for a downtrend prices below or at the
20 EMA which is below the 100 EMA and
below the 200 one
for a valid Trend price and the moving
averages need to be aligned
if we look at this uptrending Market we
observe other key behaviors
price is pulling away from the moving
averages
the short-term moving average the 20 EMA
moves away from the medium term 1 the
100 EMA
the medium-term moving average has an
upward slope meaning it's not flat
there are no crossovers between the 100
and the 200 exponential moving averages
we also see increasing space between the
moving averages
the same for a downtrend price is
pulling away from the moving averages
the short-term moving average the 20 EMA
moves away from the medium term one
the medium-term moving average has a
downward slope it's not flat
there are no crossovers between the 100
and the 200 exponential moving averages
and we also see increasing space between
the moving averages
here's how it looks like when Market
makes a shallow pullback in an uptrend
usually price moves back to the 100 EMA
the medium term one
also price usually bounces at the 20ma
in 100 EMA and then the trend resumes
also an important note the space between
the 100 and the long term 200 EMA is not
Contracting
and here's a shallow pullback in a
downtrend price moves back to the 100
EMA
price bounces at 20 in 100 EMA and that
Trend resumes
and the space between the 100 EMA and
the long-term 200 EMA is not Contracting
here's how it looks like when Market
makes a deep retracement in a trend
price moves back to the long-term moving
average the 200 EMA
price usually bounces at the 200 EMA and
the trend resumes
the medium-term moving average will
become flat
and will even have an opposite angle but
a slope of the 200 EMA is still trending
and very important the space between the
100 EMA and the 200 EMA becomes smaller
you'll see a contraction
when the market is overextended the
trend will offer some signals that it
might reverse
first one and the most important one
price is unable to break away from the
20 and the 100 EMAs you'll see price
hanging around this area price doesn't
have the power to move
also price breaks the medium term 100
EMA in the opposite direction
when you see these two signs be ready
for a possible reversal
once the price continues to push a
larger reversal might take place
you'll see a break of the long term 200
EMA in the opposite direction
or the 100 EMA and the 200 EMA will
cross in the opposite direction
as a side note you don't trade
crossovers you are just observing the
evolution of the lines on the chart
we'll talk about this later
when a market is in a Range the angle of
most moving averages is flat
price is moving close to the medium-term
moving average the 100 EMA
this is the favorite location of the
price
medium term and long-term moving
averages are close or on top of each
other
you'll also see many crossovers between
all three moving averages
between the 20ma and the 100 EMA and the
100 EMA and the 201
so let's analyze this chart first the
trend is up
price is above the 100 EMA in the 100
dma is above the 200 EMA
here we have a pullback price is near
the medium term 100 EMA and the 100 EMA
is above the 200 EMA
here's a retracement
price is near the long-term moving
average the 200 EMA
and the 100 EMA is still above the 200
EMA
here's a reversal
price breaks the 200 EMA and the
medium-term moving average is crossing
the long-term moving average
and here's a range price stays around
the 100 EMA
and the 100 EMA is crossing the 200 EMA
multiple times
for a downtrend prices below the 100 EMA
in the 100 EMA is below the 200 EMA
here's a pullback price is near the
medium term 100 EMA
and the 100 EMA is below the long-term
one
here we have a retracement price is near
the long-term moving average the 201
and the 100 EMA is still below the 200
EMA
here's a reversal price is breaking the
200 EMA and the 100 EMA crossed above
the 200 EMA
and here's a range price stays around
the 100 EMA
and team 100 EMA is crossing the
long-term one multiple times
moving averages also show momentum first
you analyze price versus the short-term
moving average
when price is not hitting the 20 EMA
price has momentum and is showing
impulsive price action
then you look at the price versus the
medium-term moving average
if the price is not touching the 100 EMA
again price is in a strong impulsive
price action the angle of the short-term
moving average is also important a steep
angle of the 20 EMA often indicates a
strong momentum
you also need to analyze the short-term
moving average in relation to the medium
term one if the 20ma is parallel with
the 101 this indicates strong momentum
and here's a market with downward
momentum the short-term EMA the 21 is a
good indicator to read the Market's
volatility
if the 20ma stays away from the medium
term 1 then the market is very impulsive
if the angle of the 20ma is steep then
the market is showing strong impulse
and again if the 20ma is parallel with
the 101 and price is not touching that
zone this indicates strong momentum
moving averages are offering Dynamic
areas of support and resistance when
very strong momentum is present
both 20 and 100 EMA often work as bounce
areas when price is showing strong
impulse
they also offer Dynamic support or
resistance when the 20 and the 100 EMA
have an angle and are not going sideways
medium term moving averages in
particular are often bounce zones when
the moving averages have a steeper angle
also you have another area when price
reaches the 200 EMA
which is the last bouncing spot within
the current Trend Direction
the moving averages can also be breakout
spots this happens when price is
breaking the medium term moving average
the 100 EMA
this is the first warning signal
then if price is breaking the long-term
moving average this is another
indication of a possible reversal
here's another common pattern when the
price is moving sideways in a correction
or range moving averages will then have
a pool effect on price and drag price
back to the moving averages
this often creates a false Breakout and
extends the sideways price action
price tends to retrace back after a
breakout away from the 100 EMA and move
back to it
and the long term 200 EMA also tends to
be involved in the middle of the range
now I get asked a lot which moving
averages are the best
from my experience most moving averages
work well if you use them properly
whether you choose between a simple and
exponential or a different type of
moving average it really shouldn't
matter much
the difference between a 20 EMA or a 20
simple moving average is very small and
the understanding of the market will
roughly be the same
I prefer using exponential moving
averages because they Place more weight
on the most recent candles as opposed to
the simple moving average
I use the 20 100 and 200 EMA but you can
change the period as you wish
the space between the moving averages
will provide information about the trend
or lack of it if there is no space then
price is in a range and not trending
when there's no space price will have
difficulties breaking away this means
that price will often respect the
support and resistance levels of the
range
and the risk of false breakouts is
higher
no space also means that price could
also be reversing and moving into a new
trend
5100 EMA crosses over the 201 relatively
quickly then the price might changing
the trend Direction
small space also means that price might
be starting a new trend or a new
momentum could start soon after a period
of contraction an expansion one must
follow
when you see increasing space price is
showing strong or increasing momentum
minor pullbacks are often good
continuation trade setups
big space between the moving averages
but the space is flat or slightly
decreasing means that the correction
will follow
in this case you need to wait for price
to finish its consolidation and the
correction before continuing with the
trend again
Contracting space between moving
averages means that price could make a
larger and deeper retracement
or it might be ready for a full reversal
in the opposite direction
let's talk about crossovers let's say
between the 20 and the 200 EMA
ironically this is often a first
strategy that beginners use but let's be
clear crossovers are not a good strategy
for taking entries
when the 20 EMA and the 200 period
moving average are at the same price the
trend is not as clear as it should be
what you are really observing at the
crossover point is that the average of
the last 20 prices is exactly the same
as the average of the last 200 prices
if you are looking for Trends to trade
this equal relationship of the two EMAs
is not a reliable indication of a trend
here are the two main consequences when
the 20ma crosses the 200 EMA
price is either starting a period with a
larger consolidation
or price is about to confirm a larger
reversal
now the moving average analysis is just
one piece of the puzzle these are
lagging tools which means the EMAs will
move after the price moves you will have
a delay but contrary to what is said
many price action Traders do utilize
moving averages they don't rely on
moving average crossover signals instead
their focus is on understanding Market
structure and price action with the help
of moving averages
moving averages although lagging will
help you if you know how to use them if
you want a follow-up video in which
we'll combine this moving average
analysis with price action and Market
structure leave us a like And subscribe
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time