if you're a trend trader and prefer the
swing trading I'm sure that you face the
same problems I was facing when I
started trading the main struggle as
traders is to exactly pinpoint the
market entry in order to catch the next
big move but what if you developed a
simple swing trading setup that would
generate high probability entry signals
hey traders this is marios and if you
stick with me for a few minutes I will
share with you a simple and an easy
swing trading strategy that will improve
your trading results the core of this
system relies on divergences between the
price and the stochastic indicator in
the direction of the prevailing trend on
the market indicated by the 200 EMA
let's dive right into a dis strategy and
see how it works here's the first rule
of the strategy we need to spot
divergences between the price action and
the stochastic indicator if you are a
trend trader divergences should be one
of your most important tools because the
divergence signals momentum coming into
the main trend suggesting a possible
continuation in the prevailing direction
of the market as you probably know there
are two types of divergences a regular
and hidden a regular divergence involves
higher high prices and lower indicator
values during an uptrend and lower low
prices and higher indicator values
during a downtrend when this happens
that's an indication of market
exhaustion a possible sign of market
reversal or at least a short-term
correction a hidden divergence is a
visual non confirmation which involves
higher lows of the price but lower
indicator values during an uptrend and
lower highs of the price but higher
indicator values during a downtrend a
hidden divergence signals a continuation
move in the direction of the prevailing
trend that's why if you prefer to take
positions in the direction of the
main trend the hidden divergence can
generate some pretty accurate signals
for spotting divergences you can use
many tools but I prefer to use the
stochastic indicator now here's the key
to our system we don't trade all the
divergences during strong trends the
stochastic will generate divergence
after divergence and most of the signals
will probably fail you look at this
Bitcoin chart and as you can see the
price was in a strong upward trend and
the stochastic indicator generated
several divergences but most of these
signals were false that's a wrong
approach in what concerns trading the
divergences we have to be smart and
filter this technique in order to
eliminate false signals now here's the
second rule of this strategy will
establish the main trend with a 200
period exponential moving average and we
only trade divergences in the direction
of the main trend also I only trade on
the hourly on the 4 hours and on a daily
timeframes in order to reduce the market
noise and filter the bad signals
generated on shorter timeframes here's
how it takes signals with this swing
trading setup when the price trades
above the 200 EMA we consider taking
only long entries when the price trades
below the 200 EMA we consider taking
only short entries we search for
divergences between the stochastic
indicator and the price only in the
direction of the main trend indicated by
the 200 EMA if the price trades above
the 200 EMA we search for divergences on
the lower side of the stochastic and if
the price trades below the 200 EMA we
search for divergences on the upper side
of the stochastic a very important we
are not interested in trading
divergences that signal reversals
possible pull backs or counter trend
positions
here's the pound dollar on the four
hours time frame we determine the upward
trend with the 200 EMA and we start
searching for divergences on the lower
side of the indicator and we only
consider to go along on the market the
first signal was the buy entry after a
hidden divergence around 200 EMA observe
how the price was making higher lows but
the indicator was making lower lows the
second signal was the buy entry after a
classic divergence also around the 200
EMA see how the price is making lower
lows but indicator makes higher lows the
third opportunity was generated after a
classic divergence also around the same
200 EMA the fourth signal was also
classic divergence if we look at the
chart we see the price making lower lows
but the stochastic making higher lows
the fifth signal was a hidden divergence
observe how the price was making higher
lows but the indicator was making lower
lows the sixth signal was also hidden
divergence with the same setup as before
the market price making higher loss but
the stochastic generated lower loss as
you can see we ignored all the signals
offered by the divergences on the upper
side of the stochastic as we are in a
strong upward trend let's look at this
goal chart also on the four hours
timeframe we establish the downward
trend with a 200 EMA and we start
searching for divergences on the upper
side of the indicator this time the
first signal was a short entry after
hidden divergence observe how the price
was making
highs but stochastic was making higher
highs the second entry was a short
signal after a classic divergence see
how the price is making higher highs but
the indicator is making lower highs the
third opportunity was a classic
divergence around the 200 EMA the fourth
signal was also classic divergence if we
look at the chart we can see the price
making higher highs but the indicator
making lower highs the fifth signal was
a hidden divergence observe how the
price was making lower highs but the
indicator was making higher highs the
sixth signal was a classic divergence
the price was making higher highs but
the stochastic was making lower highs as
you can see we ignored all the signals
offered by the divergences on the lower
side of the stochastic as we're in a
strong downward trend the trick of the
strategy is to determine the main trend
with the 200 EMA and only take positions
in the direction of the trend so we
don't chase all the divergences that
occur on the chart we only trade the
ones with a higher probability meaning
the ones in the direction of the main
trend if you are a trend-following
trader you should train your eyes to
spot the divergences on different charts
please keep in mind that this system is
more reliable when you are using higher
timeframes a signal that is produced on
the 4-hour or on the daily chart is more
reliable than a signal produced on the
15-minute chart but divergence is more
reliable on higher time frames because
the market does not move as fast and is
easier to define trends by using higher
time frames you will see the patterns
developing and you'll have time to make
the correct decisions testy strategy on
your charts and I look forward to
hearing from you in the comment
section about your results if you got
any value from this video please
consider subscribing to this channel and
give us a like as it would help us to
grow our channel in the future until
next time
[Music]