Today is your lucky day: I got a surprisingly
simple strategy, to finally see some profits
in your account, without taking huge risks.
I’ll split this strategy into 4 different
stages, which are all price action related.
First, you need to find the levels that get
the most attention.
When prices break past support or resistance
levels on a chart, it's called a Break of
Structure.
And this matters a lot, being the first condition
in our strategy.
Break of Structure means the price has moved
significantly past a point where it used to
stop before, going in the same direction as
before.
It's simple: in an uptrend, it's when the
price goes higher than before, and in a downtrend,
it's when the price goes lower than before.
When the market keeps making higher highs
and higher lows, in an uptrend, you pick the
latest high point.
If the price keeps going up and closes above
this point for a while, that's a Break of
Structure.
But when the market's making lower lows and
lower highs in a downtrend, you pick the most
recent low.
If the price keeps dropping and closes below
this low, that's another Break of Structure.
The second condition is the development of
a change of character.
A Change of Character happens when the market
starts to go in the opposite direction, after
breaking its previous highs or lows.
It's like a sudden and big change in how the
price moves in the market.
For instance, we have this market that's been
going down, making lower highs and lower lows.
If suddenly the price breaks above its last
major high point, that's a Change of Character.
It suggests the market might be turning around,
with buyers taking over.
If the price keeps going up, making new highs
and lows, we're now in a minor uptrend.
Here, the price has been going up, making
higher highs and higher lows.
Look at the past breaks of structure, going
with the trend.
But then, after one of these breaks of structure,
the price turns around and makes a new lower
low.
This suggests the trend might be changing.
After a small pullback, the price starts making
lower lows and lower highs, showing a new
downward trend might be starting.
. The previous bullish trend has now shifted
into a bearish one.
So, to recap, first condition is a Break of
Structure, which means the market structure
keeps going in the same direction.
The second condition is a Change of Character,
which means price might be changing direction.
After you find these 2 patterns, now I want
you to take the Fibonacci tool, and apply
it from highest point of the break of structure,
to the lowest point of the change of character.
We’re interested in pullbacks to the 50%
- 61.8% Fibonacci area.
That’s the third condition.
Price tends to go back about 50% of the distance
after a big move, and even after smaller moves
too.
This happens a lot and you can see it on any
chart.
So, we’ll keep an eye out for pullbacks
to this Fibonacci golden zone, because they
often show a high chance for the price to
bounce back in the direction it was going
before.
The Fibonacci Golden Zone is a go-to gem for
finding great trades.
You’ll often find that prices get zapped
like magnets to this special area.
Big money traders watch these levels too.
It’s common knowledge that major players
like banks use these levels in their trading.
And by lining up with the big dogs, you're
ready to run with the pack.
If they want to buy or sell at the same spot,
it can push the price quite aggressively.
Very important: you might not get an instant
rejection right away, when price reaches the
zone.
Prices need to chill and regroup sometimes.
So consider this area as a memory zone.
If prices bounced there before, they'll likely
bounce again.
It’s a good area to take trades if you missed
it the first time.
Now, it's not enough for the price to just
touch the zone.
We need to see it reject off the level.
The fourth condition is a wick, rejecting
the zone, a long thin line above or below
the candle body.
Wicks show fierce rejection of that level.
When a wick spikes down, for example, but
closes back up, it demonstrates the buyers
have stepped in with force.
Wicks reveal the price "tested the waters"
at the zone before rapidly bouncing back.
Like dipping your toe in the pool before jumping
out.
A long wick into the zone combined with the
other factors screams rejection.
Of course, we need a backup plan, in case
the price goes right through the Golden Zone.
Set your stop-loss just above or below the
78% Fibonacci level.
We're looking at chart that's been in a clear
uptrend, making higher highs and higher lows
over time.
This shows strong buying pressure pushing
the price up overall.
At this point, the price breaks above the
previous high, confirming the uptrend is continuing
with a Break of Structure.
Soon after this, the price starts falling
and makes a new lower low.
This signals a Change of Character, suggesting
the uptrend may be weakening.
We take the Fibonacci tool from the Break
of Structure high down to the Change of Character
low.
This shows us the 50%-61.8% pullback zone.
We want price to pull back right into that
Fibonacci zone.
Which it did, printing a long wick before
closing back down.
This long wick into the zone shows rejection
by sellers.
We have a high probability sell setup, with
a stop above the 78% Fibonacci level and targeting
double the amount we risked.
We analyze the Crude Oil market, which was
in a clear downtrend on the 4-hour time frame,
with lower highs and lower lows, showing strong
selling pressure overall.
After a bounce up, the price makes a new lower-low,
breaking market structure to confirm the sellers
remain in control.
However, on the next days, the price rockets
up and breaks the previous lower high.
This is a Change of Character, signaling potential
weakness in the downtrend.
We draw our Fibonacci from the lower low of
the break of structure, up to the high created
on the change of character, to find the pullback
area.
We now see that price pulls right back into
that zone, and prints a long wick up before
closing back up.
The wick into the Fibonacci area tells us
buyers are rejecting that zone.
I see it as a great opportunity for a long
setup, with a stop right below the 78% Fibonacci
level and targeting double the amount we risked.
And look what happened.
I don’t know how to call it…bad luck…or
bad stop placement.
The price reached 78% level, broke slightly
below it, stopped me from the trade…and
you guessed it…went straight back up, right
to my take profit area.
Lesson learned: never put the stop loss so
close to the 78% level.
Leave the market some room for stop hunts,
market noise and others.
This would have been a home run, if I had
my stop just a bit lower!
In this chart, the market is in an uptrend,
and you can see a pattern of higher highs
and higher lows.
This is the first sign that buyers are in
control.
Now, first condition.
We're looking at a Break of Structure, with
this recent high that has been surpassed,
and the price has closed above it.
Next, we're on the lookout for a Change of
Character.
After our break of structure, the price takes
a breather and dips down, making a lower low.
With our Fibonacci tool in hand, we draw from
the highest point of our Break of Structure,
down to the lowest point of the Change of
Character.
We're interested in a pullback – we want
the price to come back up to the Fibonacci
golden zone.
When we see this long wick into the zone – combined
with our other conditions, it's our cue.
We're seeing sellers stepping back in and
it's time to make our move.
We enter a short trade, setting our stop-loss
just above the 78% Fibonacci level, to be
safe.
Here the market has been in a clear downtrend.
We see lower lows and lower highs – signs
that the sellers have the upper hand.
As we apply our strategy, we first identify
a Break of Structure to the downside.
There's a recent low that's been broken, and
the price has closed below it.
After that, the price starts to climb, breaking
past the last lower high.
It's a Change of Character, and that’s the
second condition.
The sellers might be losing their grip.
We grab our trusty Fibonacci tool and measure
from the Break of Structure low, to the Change
of Character high.
We're now watching the Fibonacci golden zone.
This is where we expect the price to retrace.
And as predicted, the price declines, with
a wick that pokes up into the zone.
It's a clear sign that the buyers aren't done
yet.
They're pushing back, and we're ready to join
them.
We place our buy trade, setting a stop-loss
just below the 78% Fibonacci level, to cover
our backs.
And we are aiming for a target that's twice
the size of our risk.
Regarding which time frame should you choose,
remember that markets are fractal.
A fractal is a pattern that repeats itself
at different scales, like little mini-versions
of the bigger picture.
Price movements form similar patterns, whether
you're looking at a 1-minute chart or a weekly
chart.
The only difference is the time frame.
No matter the time frame, the principles of
support, resistance, trends and breakouts
apply in similar ways.
We are looking for signs of strength, wait
for a change in the tide, measure our bounce
zone, and demand a clear rejection before
making a move.
This approach will keep you aligned with the
market's momentum, whether you're joining
the buyers or tagging along with the sellers.
The key is knowing which time frame to trade,
based on your style and goals.
I personally use it on higher time frames,
this is where signals are more powerful and
reliable.
And remember, it’s all about probabilities.
You will encounter losing trades.
But by following this strategy, you're stacking
the odds in your favor.
You're not guessing; you're using a methodical
approach to pinpoint high-probability trades.
And I may sound like a broken record by now,
but if you also monitor volume, you can filter
the bad signals even more.
These videos will explain how to add the volume
component into your analysis.