Today we're exploring some of
the best price action strategies.
No clutter, no indicators,
no lag…just pure price action!
Engulfing momentum candlestick
We’ll start with the engulfing
momentum candlestick.
This signal occurs when a large candle fully
engulfs the body of the previous two candles.
Basically, a big candle that completely
covers the smaller ones right before it.
This isn't just a regular occurrence—it's a sign,
a clear indicator of a strong move in the market.
This is what we call an "engulfing" pattern.
The psychology behind this pattern is all about
market sentiment and the sudden shift in
the balance between buyers and sellers.
Before an engulfing pattern occurs,
there usually is a clear trend.
This trend indicates a prevailing
direction where the majority of
market participants are either buying or selling.
At some point, the market starts showing signs of
exhaustion. For a bullish engulfing momentum bar,
this might be at a support area, or at a demand
zone where buyers believe the price is attractive
enough to start buying in large quantities.
For a bearish engulfing one, this
could be at a resistance or at a
supply zone where sellers feel the price
has peaked and it's a good time to sell.
The engulfing momentum candle
represents a strong shift in sentiment.
If it's bullish, buyers have overwhelmed the
sellers, pushing the price up and covering the
range of the previous 2 candles.
This suggests that the demand
has suddenly outstripped the supply.
In a bearish pattern, sellers have come in strong,
indicating an excess of supply over demand .
The immediate effect of an engulfing
momentum bar is to signal a potential reversal.
It shows a decisive change in market dynamics.
For bullish signals, it could mean the end of
a downtrend phase, with prices likely to rise.
For bearish ones, it could suggest the end of
an uptrend wave, with prices expected to fall.
For the engulfing momentum pattern
to be a reliable signal, it should
ideally be accompanied by high trading volume.
This volume is the evidence that a significant
number of traders have participated in
creating the candle, thereby validating
the shift in market sentiment.
And please wait for the candle
to close, to confirm the signal.
Prematurely reacting to what looks like
an engulfing momentum pattern can lead to false
signals if the candle does not close as such.
The psychology of this signal revolves around
the traders' perceptions of value and momentum.
In a demand zone, seeing a bullish
pattern might lead buyers to believe
that the market is turning in their favor,
hence they buy more, driving the price up.
In a supply zone, a bearish pattern might
scare off buyers and encourage more selling,
pushing the price down.
Breakout buildup
A breakout buildup occurs when the price action
compresses, indicating a balance or a struggle
between supply and demand, before one side
eventually takes over, leading to a breakout.
The market structures itself
around various phases,
which include accumulation and distribution.
During the accumulation phase, you often see
smart money buying up the available supply,
without causing a significant price increase.
In contrast, the distribution phase occurs after
the price has risen, and smart money begin to sell
their positions, quietly and slowly.
A breakout buildup typically forms
during these phases.
The price action during
a buildup appears as a tight consolidation
where the price moves in a narrow range.
This consolidation suggests that
neither buyers nor sellers are in
full control, but both are actively involved.
During this phase, the volume often diminishes,
which might seem counterintuitive.
However, this decrease in volume is
a key indicator of a breakout buildup.
This is because it suggests that traders
are waiting on the sidelines, watching
closely for a sign to enter the market.
In a breakout buildup, the price
action doesn't make big jumps.
Instead, it moves slowly, hugging close to a
key price level, like resistance or support.
This slow, tightening movement is often
called "coiling". And a coiled market
holds potential for a significant price move.
Traders are watching closely, but they're hesitant
to commit fully, not until a clear signal appears.
This decrease in volume and smaller price range is
a sign of weakening momentum in the current trend.
It's like the moment of silence before the storm.
The real action happens when there's a breakout
– a strong price move out of the coiling pattern.
This breakout can happen in either direction,
but it typically follows the prevailing
trend or the pressure from the dominant
market side, before the buildup started.
For example, if the buildup occurs near a
resistance level after a strong uptrend,
the breakout is likely to push
upward, continuing the trend.
However, not every buildup
leads to a breakout. Sometimes,
the price might just hover around the level and
then drift away without any significant movement.
This is why it's important to wait for
the breakout before making a trade.
Confirmation could come in the form of a price
action signal closing well beyond the level,
or an increase in trading volume that
supports the direction of the breakout.
Bull and bear trap
Bull and bear traps happen
every day, on all markets and all time frames.
They are essentially false breakouts of major and
minor levels, where the price quickly reverses.
A bull trap occurs when traders are misled into
thinking that a rising price will continue going
up after breaking above a resistance level.
However, the price reverses, and drops instead.
A bear trap happens when the price breaks below
a support level, suggesting a further
decline, but then it reverses and rises.
To find these traps, you can start by
looking for a breakout that lacks conviction.
This might manifest as a price that moves
beyond an obvious level, but with low volume.
If the breakout volume is suspiciously
low, this could be a trap.
Next, observe the price action
around these critical levels.
In the case of a bull trap, you
might see the price pushing through
a resistance level but then quickly
pulling back and closing below it.
This indicates that the buyers
could not maintain their strength,
and the sellers are taking control.
For a bear trap, it's the opposite;
the price might dip below a support
level, only to rebound and close above it,
showing that the sellers are losing their
grip and buyers are stepping back in.
Another technique is to
analyze the market structure.
False breakouts often occur in ranges or during
periods when the market lacks a clear trend.
If you notice that the price is breaking
out of a range but the overall market
conditions are not supportive of a strong
move, this could be a setup for a trap .
It's also useful to track how
often a specific level is tested.
A genuine breakout might initially
retreat back to the breakout point,
but it usually won't penetrate back through it.
If you see the price breaking a level and then
retesting it multiple times, be wary.
This could indicate that the breakout
doesn't have enough strength and might
reverse, signaling a potential trap.
Now, before we continue, let us know in the
comments what topics you’d like us to cover.
Tell us what you want to watch next!
Long wick engulfing candlestick
The long wick engulfing candlestick
is my favorite price action strategy.
This candlestick not only indicates a strong
rejection of prices, but also signals potential
momentum shift in the market direction.
This candle typically shows a large body
with a long wick that extends
far beyond the body's edges.
The 'engulfing' part means that the body of this
candle is larger than the body of the previous
candle, completely overshadowing or engulfing it.
This visual on your chart is your first clue about
a significant shift in market sentiment.
The long wick represents a point where
supply surpasses demand, pushing
the price back down, or vice versa,
depending on the direction of the wick.
Let's say the long wick is at the top of
the candle. This suggests that as the price
went up, it hit a level where sellers were
waiting to take profits or considered
the price too high, outweighing buyers.
This results in the price being pushed back
down sharply, leaving behind a long upper wick.
The rejection indicated by the long wick is
significant because it shows that a certain
price level could not be sustained.
Buyers tried to push the price up,
but the overwhelming number of sellers
at that level rejected this move.
If the candle also engulfs the previous candle,
it shows increasing selling momentum. Despite
any buying pressure that might have been
present initially, sellers took control
and managed to push the close below the open of
the previous candle, indicating strong supply .
If the wick is at the bottom, it
means sellers drove the price down,
but buyers stepped in, finding the lower price
attractive, thus pushing the price back up,
showing rejection of lower prices .
If the body of the candlestick also
engulfs the previous candle, it suggests
increasing buying momentum. Buyers were
not only able to overcome the selling pressure
indicated by the long upper wick, but were also
strong enough to close the candle higher than the
previous candle’s body, indicating strong demand.
This is a powerful price action signal.
It provides a clear signal that the
market sentiment might be changing direction.
Look for these patterns at major resistance or
support levels, because they can signal the end
of a trend or the reversal of a price direction.
A bullish long wick engulfing candle
at a key support level might suggest
a potential upward reversal, tempting buyers
to enter the market expecting future gains.
The no retest breakout
The no re-test breakout is a must-know signal.
Imagine a scenario where the market has been
trending upwards, and suddenly, a breakout occurs.
Unlike many breakouts that might retest the
breakout level, this one doesn't look back—it just
keeps powering through, with intense momentum.
This is a no retest breakout, with big momentum.
First, let’s consider the price action
psychology after, and before such a breakout.
Many traders are watching the same resistance
level. Some might be waiting to buy just
after the breakout, believing that
the price will continue to rise.
Others might be skeptical, holding
off on buying until they see a retest
of the level, to confirm it as a new support.
Now, when the price breaks through the resistance
level with strong momentum and doesn't retest, two
main groups of traders are significantly impacted:
those who missed entering at the breakout,
and those who bet against the breakout,
assuming it wouldn’t last.
For those who missed the breakout,
the pain begins as they watch the price move
further and further away from the breakout level.
They were waiting for a dip—a
retest—that never comes.
This situation creates a psychological
urgency, a fear of missing out,
prompting them to consider entering the trade at
much higher prices than they initially planned,
often pushing the price even higher.
On the flip side, consider the traders
who took a short position, betting that
the price would not sustain its breakout.
As the price climbs higher, these traders
find themselves in a losing position.
The psychological discomfort, the "point of
pain" is located at the breakout level.
The plan here is to focus on
the moment the price finally
returns to the initial breakout level,
the "point of pain", which is a critical
moment for both groups of traders.
For those who were waiting for a
retest to confirm their buy, this might be
seen as a second chance to enter the trade.
And for the traders who are trapped in
a losing position from their shorts,
this is an opportunity to exit at a
break-even point or at least minimize losses.
The return to the breakout level will
often trigger a surge in trading activity.
This can lead to a sharp price reaction.
However, the reaction at the breakout
level isn't always predictable.
If too many traders are looking to exit
their positions (both longs taking profits and
shorts covering losses), the supply might outweigh
the demand, leading to a price drop instead.
So don’t expect a major price swing at the
“point of pain”. You will see a reaction, but
it won’t be that explosive as the first one.
Multiple Rejection Wicks + Color Change
When you see multiple rejection wicks,
and candles are changing their color,
you are witnessing a strong signal.
In this example, observe these two consecutive
candles at a similar price level, where the first
is bullish with a long upper wick, followed by
a bearish one with a similar long upper wick.
This formation can tell you a lot
about what's happening in the market.
Starting with supply and demand, the first candle,
the bullish one with a long upper wick, indicates
that buyers initially pushed prices higher.
However, the long upper wick shows that as
the price reached higher levels, an ample supply
emerged, overpowering the buyers and pushing the
price down from its peak before the candle closed.
At these higher price levels, sellers are more
than willing to step in and take control .
Now, when the next candle opens, it starts
where the first one left off, but turns bearish
with a long upper wick as well. This second
candle confirms the presence of strong selling
interest at these levels. The fact that this
candle is bearish and mirrors the wick of the
previous bullish candle intensifies the signal.
The sellers are not just reacting spontaneously;
they are firmly establishing their ground,
showing that they are prepared to sell at
these prices, thus increasing the supply.
The repeated rejection at this price
level signifies that the supply has
surpassed the demand, possibly leading to a trend
reversal or at least a significant pullback.
From a psychological perspective, this
signal plays a vital role. Consider
the first bullish candle. Traders who
bought during, or just before the high,
might have expected the momentum to continue.
The subsequent price dip could lead to a change
in sentiment from optimism to concern, or
even fear. This emotional shift is crucial
as it might prompt those buyers to sell quickly
to cut losses when they see prices failing to go
higher, which adds to the selling pressure.
If this pattern appears at a known resistance
level, the message it sends is even stronger.
Traders often place their stops around these
levels, and the activation of these stops
can accelerate the price movement downward,
as the bearish sentiment takes hold.
Supply/demand
The next strategy involves choosing
the correct supply/demand zones.
During uptrends, demand levels are
respected, and supply zones are taken out.
This phenomenon occurs as buyers gain
confidence and control over the market.
This buying pressure gradually
outweighs the selling pressure,
leading to a sustained rise in price .
In this phase, when price retraces to
a lower level (a demand zone),
it finds strong buying interest.
These zones are where buyers previously saw
good value and are likely to engage again,
believing that the price will continue to rise.
The respect for these demand zones during an
uptrend is due to the traders'
psychology of "buying on dips."
They perceive these pullbacks as opportunities
to buy at a lower price in a market that
is overall ascending.
As the price reaches
new highs, it encounters supply zones.
These are levels where the price was previously
sold off, and potential resistance might exist.
However, in a strong uptrend, these zones are
often breached. This breach happens because the
ongoing positive sentiment and the buying pressure
overpower the sellers waiting at these levels.
Each time a supply zone is taken out,
it reinforces the bullish sentiment.
It's a psychological reinforcement loop - breaking
through supply zones builds more confidence among
buyers, drawing more participants into the market.
The point is, during uptrends, don’t
even try to trade supply zones. Focus
only on buying on dips, at demand zones.
During downtrends, you’ll see that supply zones
are respected, and demand zones are taken out.
When the price goes up to test a previous
high (a supply zone), it often finds
strong selling interest. Traders who
missed selling during the initial drop see
these rallies as second chances to sell.
So, supply zones gain respect; they act as
barriers preventing the price from rising further
because the prevailing sentiment is bearish.
Traders expect prices to go lower,
so these zones are defended by selling.
On the other hand, demand zones, which supported
the price on its way down, start to break.
As the downtrend deepens, each rally is weaker,
and previous demand zones fail to hold because
the selling pressure continues to mount.
The failure of these zones is due to a
shift in market psychology. The fear of
further declines becomes more dominant
than the desire to buy at lower prices.
Thus, these demand zones are
taken out, leading to new lows.
Each breach of a demand zone further demoralizes
the buyers, reinforcing the bearish trend.
So during downtrends, ignore the demand zones.
Focus only on selling at supply zones.
Over and under pattern
The over and under pattern is one
of the most effective price action strategies.
This pattern essentially signals a critical
shift in the market dynamics, hinting at a
potential weakening or reversal of a trend.
So in any trading market, prices
are driven by supply and demand.
These forces are represented by the
actions of buyers and sellers who
push prices higher or lower.
A trend, whether up or down,
continues as long as there is an imbalance
favoring either buyers or sellers.
For example, in an uptrend, buyers prevail,
consistently willing to buy at higher prices,
thus creating a sequence of
higher highs and higher lows.
The over and under pattern
comes into play when there
is a noticeable shift in this trend structure.
When the price suddenly drops below a previous
major low, and then makes a lower high,
it suggests a break in this structure.
This is the first clue that the
prevailing buying pressure is weakening.
The scenario is similar but reversed in a
downtrend. When prices push above the previous
low, but then form a higher high, it indicates
that the selling pressure is diminishing.
Let's consider the psychological
aspects driving this pattern.
In an uptrend, as the price drops to form
what initially appears as a normal pullback,
buyers are typically prepared to jump in,
anticipating another push to higher highs.
However, as the price fails to reach a new
high and instead falls below the previous low,
it disrupts the expectations
formed by the market participants.
This unexpected change often leads to
uncertainty and a shift in sentiment,
causing some of the buyers to step back and
reassess their positions, while potential sellers
might see an opportunity to enter the market.
The pivotal moment in the over and under pattern
is when the price breaches a significant level.
This action is a powerful signal because it
challenges the established market structure.
It's not just a simple breach; it's a signal
that the previous consensus is no longer valid.
This can lead to rapid shifts in supply and
demand. Buyers who were previously supporting
the price by buying at dips might pull back,
and sellers may start to dominate, pushing the
price down further in what was an uptrend.
From a supply and demand perspective, this
pattern reflects a shift in the balance.
The initial move past the previous
high increases the demand suddenly.
This failure to continue in the same direction
indicates exhaustion and a possible reversal of
roles between buyers and sellers.
The weak break of structure
Another important strategy is
the “weak break of structure”.
This signal is subtle, but powerful.
Now, a “weak” break of structure occurs when the
price marginally surpasses a previous high in
an uptrend, or a low in a downtrend, but fails
to sustain this momentum and quickly retraces.
This scenario often indicates that the market
does not have sufficient conviction to
support the new highs or lows, leading
to what we call a weak break of structure.
In any market, price movements are fundamentally
driven by the imbalance between supply and
demand. A weak break of structure typically
occurs at points where this balance
is delicate and easily disrupted.
Consider a scenario where a price level has
historically acted as resistance. As prices
approach this level, sellers begin to dominate
the market, believing that the level will hold
and prices will drop again.
Buyers, on the other hand,
push the price up, testing the resistance.
If the buying pressure is strong enough,
it might initially break the resistance level.
However, if this break is weak—meaning it only
goes slightly above the resistance level and
quickly retraces—it suggests that the buying
pressure was not truly powerful enough to
shift the market sentiment decisively.
The sellers still have substantial
influence, and the demand was not
sufficient to maintain the higher prices.
If the price cannot sustain itself above the
previous resistance, it indicates
that demand is weakening.
The price often falls back to lower levels as
sellers regain control and buyers withdraw,
waiting for more favorable conditions.
One instance of a weak break of structure
may not be meaningful.
But consecutive “weak”
breaks of structure can form a pattern that
highlights a significant loss of momentum.
For instance, if the market attempts to break a
low multiple times but each time only succeeds
marginally before retracing, it suggests a
consistent lack of supply at lower price levels.
This scenario often precedes a stronger
move in the opposite direction.
Consecutive “weak” breaks will allow you
to anticipate potential market turns.
Momentum gain vs Momentum Loss
The next strategy involves finding
instances of momentum gain and momentum loss.
Momentum refers to the speed or strength of
price movements. And this can be observed
through the lens of consecutive candles
increasing or decreasing in size,
from a supply and demand perspective.
When you see consecutive candles getting larger
and larger, this usually signals a momentum gain.
Imagine a scenario where each
candle represents a day of trading.
If each day the price moves higher than
the previous day and the size of the candle
gets bigger, it indicates strong buying pressure.
More buyers are entering the market,
willing to buy at even higher prices.
This buying pressure pushes the price
up, creating larger bullish candles.
This can often be seen in an uptrend
where each candle is getting larger and
moving a greater distance per candle,
showing a gain in bullish momentum.
The increasing size of the candles indicates
that buyers are becoming more aggressive.
Momentum loss can be found when the candles
start to decrease in size. This suggests
that the movement in price is losing strength.
For example, if you observe that after a series
of large bullish candles, the candles begin
to shrink in size, it could be a warning sign.
Shrinking candles suggest that
although the trend is still upward,
the buyers are not as aggressive as before.
The distance traveled per candle gets shorter,
signaling that the buyers are losing control
and the bullish momentum is weakening.
This shift could be due to various reasons, such
as traders taking profits after a price surge,
or simply the market running out of steam.
When buyers begin to pull back,
the supply may start to match or exceed the
demand, leading to smaller price movements.
Momentum loss is not only about shrinking candles
but also about where these candles appear.
If this pattern occurs after a prolonged
uptrend at a key resistance level,
it could be a strong indicator that the
trend might reverse or at least stall.
This is because at resistance levels, the price
has historically struggled to move higher,
and with weakening momentum, the likelihood
of breaking through these levels decreases.
The plan here is to ride the wave of increasing
buyer enthusiasm, during momentum gain phases.
On the other hand, noticing a momentum
loss with decreasing candle sizes
could signal a time to be cautious.
Volume will confirm or contradict the
momentum signals provided by candle sizes.
Increasing volume alongside larger
candles reinforces the momentum gain,
suggesting strong buyer commitment.
If candle sizes diminish and volume
decreases, this further confirms
momentum loss, indicating that the interest
in pushing the price higher is decreasing.
Now, if you liked what you saw, we have
plenty more interesting guides for you!