Banks and smart money traders are
stealing your money! Every single day!
And they use one simple trick! A trick
that turns your trades around support
and resistance into their profit machine!
Here’s a familiar scenario: price just hit
what you thought was solid support. Your
textbook told you this level would hold.
So you bought the bounce at this level. Then
boom - the market crashes right through it,
like the support never existed.
This happens because everything you
learned about support and resistance is backwards.
The traditional approach actually puts you on the
wrong side of the biggest players in the market.
I lost $5,000 learning this the hard way.
Hundreds of failed trades. All because
I believed the biggest lie in trading.
Today, you discover how smart money
manipulate every level you see. How
they trap retail traders like you and me.
And most important - how to join them.
By the end of this video, you
will think like a bank trader.
So here's what we cover. First, I show you the
massive lie about support and resistance that
every book teaches. Then, I reveal how smart
money actually thinks about these levels. Next,
I walk you through their exact
manipulation tactics. Finally,
I give you the simple system to trade like them.
Pay attention. This changes everything.
The $1 Million Lie Everyone Believes
Quick question. True or false?
The more times price tests a
level, the stronger it gets.
If you said true, you just fell for their trap.
Ask any trader about support and resistance
and they'll tell you the same thing.
"The more times a level gets tested,
the stronger it becomes." This idea shows
up in every trading course, every book.
But here's the truth - this
statement is completely wrong.
This lie costs retail traders millions
every day. Let me show you why.
Look at this chart. You see this support
level getting hit over and over. Most
traders think this makes it stronger.
More reliable. A better place to buy.
They're wrong.
Every time price hits that level,
it eats up buy orders. Think about it. Someone
places a buy order at support. Price hits it.
Order gets filled. That buyer is gone.
Price hits again. More orders
get filled. More buyers disappear.
Each test makes the level weaker. Not stronger.
Watch any forex pair during London open. See those
support levels that held during Asian session?
They get tested repeatedly because there's no
real buying interest - just small orders from
retail traders. When London banks start
trading, they blow right through these
"strong" levels to hunt for liquidity below.
Here's what really happens. Strong levels push
price away fast. No hesitation. No multiple tests.
Just pure momentum - price bounces hard and moves.
Real support doesn't mess around.
When price hits a truly strong level,
it bounces hard and fast. You'll maybe see long
wicks on the candles. Or you’ll see massive,
opposite candle colors. Price gets rejected
immediately. No hanging around, no multiple tests.
This happens because there's massive
buying interest sitting at that level.
Smart money has placed their orders there.
When price touches that zone, all that buying
power kicks in at once. Price shoots away
from the level like it hit a trampoline.
Real support acts like a steel wall. Price hits it
once and bounces violently. You see massive green
candles shooting away from the level. No second
chances. No hanging around. Just pure buying power
defending that zone with everything they have.
Watch gold market during any major crisis.
When it hits real support, the bounce is
immediate and violent. No multiple tests,
no consolidation. Just institutional money
stepping in with billion-dollar buy orders,
that send price screaming higher.
If price can casually drift around
a support level, or keep coming back to
test it, that tells you the buyers aren't
that committed. The level is weak, not strong.
When you see a level getting tested multiple
times, that's not strength. That's weakness.
That's the level getting ready to break.
Look at this example. Price tested this support
multiple times. Each test ate up more buy orders.
At the last test, there’s nothing left.
Price crashed through like tissue paper.
Same thing happens with resistance. Each
test removes sell orders. Eventually,
no sellers remain. So price breaks up easy.
I avoid buying support that gets tested multiple
times. The math is simple. More tests equal fewer
orders left. Fewer orders equal easier breaks.
Now here's what I look for instead. Price
drops to support and bounces fast. Hard.
Leaves a long shadow on the candle. That's
liquidity getting cleared out below the level.
That shadow tells me something big.
Smart money just swept up all the
stop losses below support. They grabbed
cheap prices. Now they want price higher.
That's where I buy. Not at the clean
level everyone sees. At the broken level
where smart money just loaded up.
This trade works ten times better
than buying clean support. Why? Because you're
trading with the smart money. Not against them.
Why Explosive Moves Tell You Everything
Price action leaves clues everywhere.
The biggest clue is how price leaves a
level. Slow, grinding moves away from
support show weak buying. Explosive moves
show serious money entered the market.
Think about it mathematically.
To create a massive green candle,
buyers have to absorb every single sell order
and still have enough buying power left to push
price higher. That takes serious capital.
Retail traders can't create those moves.
When I see price explode away from a level
with huge volume, I mark that zone immediately.
Someone with deep pockets made a decision
there. When price returns to that level,
the same player often defends it again.
It's all about imbalance.
When buyers and sellers are equal, price moves
sideways. Boring. Slow. No money to make.
But when one side overpowers the
other, that's when magic happens!
Picture this. Price sits at support. Suddenly,
massive buy orders flood in. Way more than the
sell orders available. Price explodes higher.
That buying pressure had to come from somewhere.
Someone with deep pockets.
Someone who knows something.
Here's the key insight. The stronger the
move away from a level, the more interest
exists there. Especially when price
didn't spend much time at the level.
So when price rockets up from support,
remember that spot. Next time price
comes back, that's where you want to buy.
Look for extreme turning points. Violent
moves. Explosive breakouts. These
show you where smart money operates.
Those levels become magnets. Price always
wants to return to where the big money played.
But here's where most traders mess up.
They wait for price to come back to the
exact same spot. That's not how it works.
Smart money doesn't buy at the same price
twice. They buy below it. In the discount
zone. Where retail traders get scared.
The Liquidity Clear-Out Secret
Here's what changed my trading forever.
Sometimes price breaks support, triggers all the
stop losses, then immediately reverses back above.
Most traders see this as a "false breakdown."
They think their analysis was wrong.
No. Their analysis was perfect.
That's exactly why it failed.
Smart money knew where every stop loss
was placed. They pushed price just below
support to trigger those stops. Each stop
loss becomes a market sell order - giving
smart money the liquidity they need to buy. Once
they fill their positions, price rockets higher.
This isn't a failed trade - it's a
successful manipulation. The support
level worked exactly as expected. Smart money
just used it differently than retail traders.
I call these liquidity clear-outs. They
happen every single day. Just watch any
major pair at the London open. Price
breaks below Asian session support,
sweeps the stops, then reverses immediately.
The candle pattern tells the whole story. You
see price pierce support with the candle body,
but it closes back above. That long wick below,
that's smart money collecting liquidity. The
close above support, that's them defending
the level after filling their positions.
How Market Makers Play You Like a Violin
Market makers run a business. They
need to fill massive orders for
clients without moving the market.
If a pension fund wants to buy $500 million worth
of Apple stock, the market maker can't just hit
the buy button. They need liquidity - lots of it.
Where do they find this liquidity? From other
traders trained to trade obvious patterns.
Here's their playbook. First, they let price
consolidate between clear support and resistance.
Retail traders mark these levels on their charts.
Everyone prepares to buy support and
sell resistance. Moving averages cluster
together. Indicators line up perfectly.
Then the market maker makes their move.
They push price just above resistance. Every
retail trader sees the "breakout." Technical
indicators confirm it. Moving averages cross over.
It's the perfect setup from every trading book.
Retail traders buy the breakout. Their buy
orders provide the liquidity market makers
need to sell their massive position at higher
prices. Once filled, the market maker stops
supporting the price. It collapses back below
resistance, stopping out every breakout buyer.
How They Manipulate You Every Day
Market manipulation isn't some
conspiracy theory. It happens every
single day. Right in front of your eyes.
It’s because smart money need stealth. They
need to spread their orders over time. They need
liquidity around support and resistance levels.
That's where all the retail orders cluster.
They know you place stop losses below
support. They know you buy when price breaks
resistance. They know exactly how you think.
And they use that knowledge against you.
Here's how the trap works. Price approaches
a key resistance level. You see the break
coming. You get ready to buy the breakout.
Price breaks through. You buy. And it feels
right. You're trading the momentum.
But look closer. Who was on
the other side of your trade?
The smart money who bought way down below. They're
taking profit at the exact spot you're entering.
You buy at the high. They sell at the high. You
think you're catching the move
up. They know the move is over.
This happens thousands of times per day.
Small traders buy the highs. Smart money
sells the highs. Retail sells the
lows. Smart money buys the lows.
The solution? Stop entering
where the pros are exiting.
Remember this phrase: "Buy
weakness, sell strength."
When price hits extreme highs, that's
strength. That's where smart money sells.
When price drops from those highs, that's
weakness. That's where smart money buys.
You want to join them in the weakness.
Not fight them at the strength.
Look at this example. Price makes a new
high. Retail traders buy the breakout. Price
immediately reverses. Retail gets stopped out.
Meanwhile, smart money waits. Price drops back
into value. Into the discount
zone. That's where they buy.
See the difference? Retail chases price
higher. Smart money lets price come to them.
The Consolidation Death Trap
Price spends most of its time
doing nothing. Just chopping
around. Going sideways.
Traders hate this. No clear direction.
No obvious trades. Just noise.
But smart money loves consolidation.
Because that's where they set their traps.
Here's how it works. Price consolidates. Retail
traders get impatient. They start drawing support
and resistance lines at the edges of the range.
Everyone sees the same levels. Everyone has the
same plan. Buy the breakout
up. Sell the breakdown.
Smart money knows this. They see the same
levels. But they have a different plan.
They want to collect all those breakout
orders. All that liquidity. So they push
price just outside the range. Just enough
to trigger the stops and breakout trades.
But here's the devious part - they don't break
it cleanly. They push price just far enough to
trigger technical signals. Moving averages cross.
Oscillators break key levels. Every retail trading
system flashes the same signal at the same time.
So obviously, retail traders see the break and
they jump in. But, as you know by now, it's
a fake break. Smart money is on the other
side. Taking the opposite position.
Using retail's momentum against them.
The break then fails and price
snaps back into the range.
This gets worse with indicators. Moving
averages bunch up during consolidation.
When price breaks out, the averages cross over.
This gives retail traders even more confidence.
But smart money set this up. They know exactly
what signals retail traders watch. They know
exactly how to trigger those signals.
By the time the indicators confirm the
trend change, smart money already made
their move. The real opportunity is gone.
The lesson is: don't trust obvious
breaks. Don't trust indicator signals
during consolidation. These are traps
designed to separate you from your money.
During consolidations, the difference between
professional and retail entries is evident.
It's completely backwards from what you'd expect.
Retail traders buy strength. They see price
breaking resistance, making new highs, and they
chase it higher. Professionals are selling into
that strength. They're distributing
positions they bought during weakness.
Retail traders sell weakness. They see
price breaking support, making new lows,
and they panic sell. Professionals are buying
that weakness. They're accumulating positions
to sell during the next wave of strength.
The psychological difference is everything.
Retail traders need confirmation. They need
to see price already moving before they
act. Professionals act on probability. They
position themselves before the move happens.
Play The Liquidity Game
Let's talk more about
liquidity. Fancy word for a simple concept.
Liquidity means orders. Buy and sell
orders. The fuel that moves price.
Smart money needs massive liquidity
to fill their huge positions.
So they create situations that make you want
to trade. They form patterns you recognize.
They trigger signals you trust. They make
you think you found a great opportunity.
But you're not finding opportunity.
You're providing liquidity.
Think about triangle patterns. You've traded
these before. Price squeezes into a tight range.
Then breaks out. So you follow the breakout.
But how many times did that work? How many times
did price immediately reverse after you entered?
Smart money uses these patterns as liquidity
traps. They know retail traders love
triangles. Love breakouts. Love momentum.
So they create fake triangles.
Fake breakouts. Fake momentum.
You see continuation. They see reversal.
You see opportunity. They see liquidity.
The key is thinking like them. Not like retail.
Ask yourself: "If I were managing billions
of dollars, where would I want to
buy? Where would I want to sell?"
You wouldn't want to buy at obvious support.
Too crowded. Too expensive. You'd want to buy
below support. Where retail traders
panic. Where you get a discount.
You wouldn't want to sell at obvious
resistance. Not enough buyers. You'd
want to sell above resistance. Where retail
traders chase. Where you get premium prices.
The Shakeout Strategy
Stop losses cluster at obvious
levels. Just below support. Just above
resistance. Below yesterday's low. Above
yesterday's high. These clusters create liquidity
pools that smart money targets deliberately.
Again, think like a market maker for a second.
You need to buy 10 million shares without
spiking the price. Where do you find sellers?
You create them by triggering stop losses.
Push price below support, trigger the stops,
buy the shares from panicking traders. Then let
price recover. You've filled your order at great
prices while retail traders nurse their losses.
This isn't illegal. It's not cheating. It's
understanding market mechanics. Stop losses are
visible to market makers through order flow.
They know exactly where the liquidity sits.
They'd be foolish not to use this information.
Smart money loves shakeouts. These are their
favorite tools. It's how smart
money are collecting cheap prices.
Once they collect enough positions, they
stop selling pressure. Price bounces back
above support. The shakeout is complete.
Small traders watch in frustration. They
got stopped out at the low. Now
price is moving up without them.
This happens every single
day. At every major level.
The solution is to trade
the shakeout, not the level.
When you see price break below
support with a long shadow,
that's your signal. Smart money just collected
liquidity. They want price higher now.
When you see price break above resistance then
immediately fail, that's your signal. Smart money
just distributed. They want price lower now.
Again. Trade with the shakeout. Not against it.
The Direction Secret
Most traders try to predict where
price will stop. They look for resistance
to sell. Support to buy. Reversal points.
This is backwards thinking.
Instead of predicting where price
will stop, trade where price wants to go.
Look at the most recent high or low. That
tells you the current bias. New high means
bullish bias. New low means bearish bias.
Trade in that direction. Not against it.
If price just made a new high,
look for pullbacks to buy. Don't look for
resistance to sell. The bias is up. Trade up.
If price just made a new low, look
for bounces to sell. Don't look for
support to buy. The bias is down. Trade down.
This simple shift changes everything. You stop
fighting the momentum. You start trading with it.
Here's what this looks like in practice. Price
breaks to new highs. Instead of looking for where
it might reverse, look for where it might pull
back. That pullback is your buy opportunity.
Price breaks to new lows. Instead of looking
for where it might bounce, look for where it might
retrace. That retrace is your sell opportunity.
You're trading the direction of the
most recent momentum. Not against it.
This keeps you on the right side of the
market. The side where smart money operates.
The Order Flow at Key Levels
If you understand the orders behind
price movement, this will change everything
about how you see support and resistance.
At every price level, limit orders wait on both
sides. Buy limits below market price. Sell limits
above. When price reaches these levels, the
battle begins. More buy orders than sell
orders means price might bounce. More sell orders
than buy orders means price might break through.
But here's what retail traders miss - smart
money can see order flow depth that you
can't. They know if support has 10,000 contracts
waiting or 1 million. They position accordingly.
The solution is to monitor the footprint
charts or Level 2 data. You can see orders
appear and disappear at key levels. A
huge buy order appears at support means
someone's defending. If that order gets
pulled, then support is about to break.
This is why the same support level might hold
five times then break on the sixth. The order
flow changed. The defender left. Without those buy
orders, support becomes just a line on a chart.
The Round Number Edge
Some of the most reliable support
and resistance levels have nothing to do with
technical analysis. They appear at round numbers
because human psychology makes them significant.
Round numbers are important
for smart money traders.
Look at any chart. Major reversals happen
at round numbers. The level ends in 50 or 100.
All this human behavior creates real
order flow at round numbers.
Smart money knows this. They know
retail traders cluster orders around these levels.
So they use round numbers as liquidity zones.
Here's how it works. Price approaches a
major round number. Retail traders start
thinking about taking profits. Or entering new
positions. Orders pile up around that level.
Smart money sees this buildup. They know they
can fill large positions at these levels.
So they push price toward the round number.
But here's what separates professionals from
amateurs - smart money positions themselves
just before the round numbers, not at them.
They'll buy Tesla at $290, knowing retail traders
are waiting to buy at $300. When price hits the
round number, retail buying provides the
liquidity for smart money to take profits.
Sometimes price stops just short. Smart money
absorbs all the selling. Then pushes price higher.
Sometimes price breaks through. Smart money
absorbs all the buying. Then pulls price back.
Either way, they get their
fills. They get their liquidity.
The key for you is recognizing these zones
early. Before the obvious action happens.
When price approaches a major round number, get
ready. Big moves often start from these levels.
But don't trade the obvious
play. Don't buy the break
above key level. Don't sell the rejection at it.
Wait for the shakeout. Wait for smart money
to show their hand. Then follow their lead.
The Complete System
Now you know how they think. How they
operate. How they trap retail traders.
Time to put it all together into
a complete system.
First, identify the
current bias. What's the most recent high or
low? That tells you the momentum direction.
Second, find the key levels.
Support and resistance that
matter. Round numbers that attract attention.
Third, wait for the setup. Price approaches
your level. Retail traders get positioned.
Orders cluster around the obvious spots.
Fourth, watch for the shakeout, the
liquidity clear-out. Price breaks the
level. Stops get hit. Retail traders
panic. Smart money collects liquidity.
Fifth, enter with smart money. Trade in the
direction they want price to go. Not where
retail thinks it should go.
Sixth, manage the trade.
Set your stop below their entry zone. Target
the next major level in your direction.
This system works because you're thinking like
smart money. You're trading with them. You're
buying their dips and selling their
rips. Taking their side of the trade.
The game is simple: smart money needs
liquidity. Novice traders provide it.
Your edge isn't fighting this reality. Your
edge is positioning yourself accordingly.
Stop trading the textbook patterns
that everyone knows. Start trading the
liquidity grabs that actually move markets.
When you see support holding multiple times,
don't buy it - wait for it to break.
When you see resistance tested repeatedly,
don't short it - prepare for the breakout.
When price spikes through a level and reverses,
don't curse your stop loss - recognize the
liquidity grab and position for the real move.
Remember this - the market doesn't care about your
technical analysis. It cares about order flow.
You now know what most traders never learn.
How smart money thinks, how they operate. And
how they profit from retail mistakes.
This knowledge changes everything.
Here's what you do next. Open your charts. Find a
recent example of each concept I showed you. The
fake breakout. The shakeout. The liquidity trap.
Study these examples. Understand how smart money
operated. See how retail traders got trapped.
Then start looking for these setups in
real time. Train your eye to spot the
manipulation. The traps. The opportunities.
Remember: every support and resistance level hosts
this battle. Once you see it, you can't unsee it!
The question is: Will you be
the victim or the beneficiary?
And If you're ready to fit this
into a full A-to-Z trading system,
that's what our Academy is for.
Link is in the description!