With every click, you're fighting a
billion-dollar institution. And on their
turf, the low time frames, you are
designed to lose. But we're not going to
fight them there. We're going to pull
them onto our turf. Swing trading on the
higher time frames. So, here is the
plan. Three brutally simple swing
trading setups fused into one 10-minute
daily routine so you can finally grow
your account without being chained to
the screen. The key to successful swing
trading is combining good tools. You
want strong reference points on the
chart so you can see where price might
pivot or pause. You want some tools that
show volatility and trend. You also want
to watch key levels that can trigger
bigger moves. Basically, you look for
confluence. Multiple tools point to the
same region. So, let's talk about it.
First swing trading approach revolves
around monthly pivots. These lines are
more influential than daily pivot lines.
For bigger moves, institutions often
watch this monthly pivot areas. They
might cluster large orders around those
lines. You will often see that price
tags a monthly pivot and then bounces or
breaks. People who trade higher time
frames rely on monthly pivots as
references. they can act as stable
levels because they do not shift each
day. If price is above the main monthly
pivot, that can signal bullish bias. If
it is below, that can signal bearish
bias. Monthly pivots often pull price
toward them. That is the magnet effect.
Traders who missed prior moves sometimes
wait for price to return to a pivot
zone, then they enter or add to
positions. So you often see price
reacting to these lines with strong
wicks or consolidation.
If you see price hold above the monthly
pivot for several sessions, that pivot
might be reliable support. If price
stays below, that pivot may act as
resistance. This can help you plan
trades. If price is above the pivot, you
can look for dips. If it is below, you
can sell rallies. Confluence is key. A
monthly pivot by itself might be good.
But if you also see that pivot align
with a demand zone or a supply zone, you
have a stronger reason for a trade. A
demand zone is a zone where buyers
showed interest before. A supply zone is
where sellers dominated. If the monthly
pivot sits right around a known support
area, that might be a prime region for a
bounce. Then you can go long. or if the
pivot is near a supply zone, you might
look for a short. You can also see
monthly pivots appear near local
structure. For instance, if the prior
swing low was around the pivot, that
line might become a stronger level. That
is how you get synergy between structure
and pivot. As a swing trader, you can
wait for price to approach that zone. If
the market prints a reversal pattern,
you step in. This helps you avoid random
trades in the middle of nowhere. In this
chart, price has been dropping for a few
weeks. You see that the next monthly
pivot line sits just below price. At the
same zone, you detect a prior demand
zone, and when price gets there, a
bullish pin bar forms. That can be your
buy signal. You set your stop loss a bit
under the pivot and demand zone. If
price bounces, you ride the wave to the
next pivot or to a prior swing high.
This is how you catch swings that last
several days. In this example, a monthly
pivot coincides with a supply zone. As
price rallies into that zone, you watch
for a reaction. Perhaps you see a
bearish pin bar or a bearish engulfing
bar. As price touches the pivot, that
can be your short trigger, anticipating
a downward swing. So, you set your stop
above the pivot and you target the next
monthly pivot line or a known support.
Candlestick patterns reinforce pivot
signals. A pin bar with a long wick
rejecting the pivot is often a sign that
price attempts to break but fails. That
can lead to a reversal. An engulfing bar
that closes back under the pivot after
testing it is also a strong sign. If the
pivot has acted as support for some
time, but you see a daily close below
it, that pivot may now turn into
resistance. Try not to jump in without a
pattern. Wait for some sign that price
is responding. Even on a 4hour chart,
you can look for a clear wick or an
engulfing candle. That evidence helps
you avoid false breaks. If price blasts
through a monthly pivot that had held
for several days, that can mean a change
in direction. Let's say a monthly pivot
was acting as support. Price slices
below it, closes below on a daily
candle, and then retests it from
underneath. That pivot might flip to
resistance. You then look for a short
entry on that retest. This approach is a
pivot flip trade. Many times old support
becomes new resistance or old resistance
becomes new support. That is a principle
you see across many time frames. With
monthly pivots, it can hold more weight.
When you see a breakout occur, you can
ride the momentum in that direction.
Some swing traders prefer breakouts if
the overall trend aligns with them. They
wait for a pivot break and enter. They
use the old pivot line as a place for a
stop or a partial stop. If the pivot
break is genuine, the next pivot might
act as a magnet. That can be your target
for a multi-day move.
Another example, price forms a demand
zone and the monthly pivot line is right
there. The candle prints a bullish pin
bar with a long lower wick showing that
sellers try to push price down. You can
go long at the next open and place a
stop-loss below the pivot. Your target
might be the next monthly pivot or a
prior swing high. If price breaks the
pivot, you might shift your plan, wait
for a retest from below, and short.
Another good swing trading approach
includes Ballinger bands. A Ballinger
band is an envelope that surrounds price
based on standard deviations from a
moving average. For this setup, you'll
use a 50 period basis, but you place
three sets of bands, one with a
deviation of one, one with a deviation
of two, and one with a deviation of
three. That way, you get a layered
effect. The middle band is your 50 SMA,
a stable average that fits swing trading
time frames. These three bands help you
see different zones of volatility. The
first band with one deviation is tight
to the average, capturing mild
fluctuations. The second band is a
broader channel that usually contains
most of the price action under normal
volatility. The third band is the widest
capturing extreme moves. When price
pushes outside the outer band, that can
show an extreme. If price closes beyond
the third deviation band, it might mean
the market is overstretched. Swing
traders often watch for a reversion or a
mean reversion. At that point, they
might look for a reversal setup.
If price stays near the middle band, it
might be trending or consolidating.
If price tags the upper band area
frequently, that might be an uptrend. If
it tags the lower band area, that might
be a downtrend. The layered bands also
help evaluate the strength of a trend.
If price keeps hugging the outer band
without snapping back, that's a strong
trend. Some traders fade extremes at the
three deviation band, especially if they
see a candlestick reversal pattern.
Others wait for a cross of the middle
band as a sign of shift. You can combine
these sidings with monthly pivots. If
you see price striking the second or
third deviation band exactly at a
monthly pivot, that's a potent
combination for a reversal.
This is how you determine the trend
stages. Price near the middle band means
a potential consolidation or transition
area. Price crossing below the middle
band means a shift from bullish to
neutral or even bearish. Price crossing
above the middle band represents a shift
from bearish to neutral or bullish. One
approach is to trade bounces off the
middle band in a trending market. For
instance, if the market is going up, you
watch for price to pull back to the
middle band. If price prints a bullish
candle there, you buy, aiming for the
upper bands as future target. Another
approach is to fade an extreme. If you
see a strong reason, suppose price slams
into the third deviation upper band,
then you spot a monthly pivot or a
supply zone, a bearish reversal candle
forms. You have multiple factors to
short, expecting price to revert back to
lower bands. Some traders prefer to
trade with the trend, buying dips near
the lower band of that trend. Others
prefer to fade extremes, shorting near
the top band or buying near the bottom
band if the market is choppy. You decide
which method suits you. A trending
environment might reward you more if you
buy dips. A range environment might
reward you more if you fade extremes at
the outer band. You can confirm whether
the market is trending or ranging by
seeing if price forms higher highs and
higher lows or if it just oscillates
around the level.
Look for a candlesticks pattern if you
plan to enter. If you see a pin bar near
a band, that might be a sign of a
potential snapback. If you see a strong
engulfing bar that breaks above the
band, that might confirm a breakout.
Evaluate the candle volume if you want
an extra glow. Sometimes price breaks
out and just keeps going. Ballinger
bands widen. The third deviation band is
not guaranteed to cause a reversal. If
the market experiences a major
fundamental push, it can ride the outer
band for days. So don't blindly jump in
just because price touches an outer
band. Pair it with additional context.
In this example, the market is trending
upward. Price keeps bouncing off the
middle band. Each time it dips to that
band, we see an increase in bullish
momentum and price resumes upward. So, a
good swing trading approach would be
buying at the middle band, taking
partial profits at the future resistance
bands. In this example, you see a market
stuck in a range. Price tags the lower
third deviation band near a monthly
pivot. A big rejection candle forms. The
correct trade is a buy one anticipating
a return to the middle band.
Another swing trading strategy involves
monitoring a channel formed by the 21
period exponential moving average. The
21 EMA is a favorite among swing traders
looking at daily charts. It reacts
relatively quickly while smoothing
short-term fluctuations.
In this setup, you create a channel
around the 21 EMA that can involve
plotting an EMA of the highs and an EMA
of the lows. So, you get two lines that
frame price. This acts like a dynamic
band of support and resistance. On its
own, this channel might not be as
reliable, but in combination with static
support and resistance level like round
numbers, this channel becomes very
important. Many traders fixate on these
levels. They often place stops or
entries around them. So price can pause
or bounce at round numbers. Sometimes
big players place large orders there,
turning them into supply or demand
zones. If the price is above the
channel, you might see a bullish
environment. So, you look for long
trades at the next round number bounce
or break. If price is below the channel,
you likely see a bearish environment, so
you aim for short trades. First, check
if price is above or below the channel.
If above, the trend is presumably up. If
below, the trend is presumably down. If
price is inside the channel, it might be
consolidating.
Then you see where the nearest big round
numbers lie. If the market is in an
uptrend, you might plan to buy a
breakout above the round number. If the
market is in a downtrend, you might plan
to sell a breakout below a round number.
The channel can also serve as dynamic
support or resistance. If price keeps
bouncing off the upper boundary of the
channel, that can confirm bullish
momentum. If it keeps failing at the
lower boundary, that can confirm a
downtrend.
Sometimes this channel acts as a
trampoline. Price will break through,
come back to test an EMA line, and
bounce away if the trend is intact. If
it fails to bounce and instead lingers,
that might signal a shift.
The first bounce is important. It proves
that the channel is being respected.
Then you look for a round number to
align with that bounce. That confluence
can yield a strong trade. For instance,
a bull trend brings price to the top of
the channel near a round number. If you
see a bullish candlestick bounce off
that zone, you jump in. You place a stop
under the channel and you target the
next round number above. If price
meanders inside the channel for more
than three candles, you might skip
trades. That indicates indecision. It's
possible the market is waiting for news
or liquidity is low. You can wait for
price to break out of the channel with
conviction before acting. If you trade
while the market is stuck, you might get
whipsaw.
That's why the strategy says to watch
for immediate rejection or bounce
behavior. You want clarity, not sideways
chop. So, here's the plan. You identify
the overall trend with the channel. You
find the nearest round numbers. You then
wait for price to approach that round
number with the channel as a guide. If
the trend is up, look for a break above
the round number or a bounce near the
channel that aligns with that round
number. If the trend is down, look for a
downside break of the round number or a
bounce from the channel's underside.
You can also trade different
combinations using all the tools and
indicators we've talked about. Some
traders run into monthly pivots that
coincide with a round number or they see
that a Ballinger band extreme lining up
with a round number. Maybe price is at a
monthly pivot at the third deviation
Ballinger band or price is in an
uptrend, holds above the monthly pivot
and sits near the 21 EMA channel. The
more confluence you have, the more
conviction you might gain. Your job is
to read the bigger story. Are we near a
strong monthly pivot or a known supply
demand zone? Do the Ballinger bands show
an extreme or a comfortable trend push?
Are we flirting with a big round number?
If multiple elements line up, you have a
potent setup.
Imagine you start your swing trading
routine on a Sunday. You check the
weekly and daily charts. You note the
monthly pivot lines. Then you switch on
the three Ballinger bands. You see that
price is currently near the middle band
slightly above it. That suggests a
bullish posture. You may notice a big
round number which may or may not align
with the monthly pivot. Then you track
the candles to see if a bounce or a
breakout occurs there.
This approach is perfect for beginners
or traders that don't have much time to
trade. You do not rely on guesswork. You
have specific levels to watch. Monthly
pivots, Ballinger bands, or the 21 EMA
channel. As a swing trader, you can
check the chart once or twice a day. You
do not need to watch every minute. You
can quickly spot potential setups, place
alerts, and plan your trades in a
structured way. Sometimes you see many
lines, the pivots, the channel, plus
multiple round numbers that can clutter
your chart. You must prioritize. If
you're aimed at a bullish trade, focus
on major support pivots or lower band,
not everything. If it sets up with a
clear confluence like the pivot plus a
round number, then that's enough. Do not
chase every minor pivot or Ballinger
band and plan your trades in advance.
Wait for price to come to your zone.
Then watch for a candlestick pattern
that confirms your direction. This
patience can help you avoid random
trades that do not align with your
strategy.
Some swing traders like to check if
there is a big economic event or an
earnings report for the market they
trade. They still rely on their pivot or
Ballinger setups for entry triggers. You
decide how much fundamentals matter to
you. Some prefer pure technical reading.
Others keep an eye on the calendar to
dodge big surprises. That is personal
preference.
Now on daily or 4hour charts, the candle
close can be pivotal. If you see price
bouncing off the pivot intraday, but the
daily close fails to hold, that might be
a warning sign. Wait until the close
might confirm the bounce is real. That's
how you filter out noise. For instance,
if price wicks below the monthly pivot
but closes above it with a bullish
candlestick, that pivot bounce is more
convincing. If price wicks above the
pivot but closes below, that is a fail.
The same logic goes for the 21 EMA
channel. If price intraday dips inside
the channel but then closes back above,
that might reinforce the uptrend. If it
closes below the channel, that might be
a shift. In practice, you can scroll
through charts from prior months. You
can see how the monthly pivot lines
shaped the market. You can spot how many
times price reversed near these lines or
how breakouts occurred. Then you can
plot your Ballinger bands and watch how
price interacts with them. Do you see
consistent bounces off the middle band?
The same goes for the 21 EMA channel.
Observe and note how often price bounces
off the top or bottom line.
Now, here are some potential pitfalls
you may encounter and their solutions.
First one, over complication. If you try
to watch too many lines, you might get
confused. So, simplify. Choose only one
dynamic support and resistance zone.
Choose between the Ballinger bands or
the EMA channel and focus on the zones
with the highest overlap or
significance.
Another pitfall is not waiting for
confirmation. Jumping in without seeing
a candle close might lead to fake outs.
Wait for that bounce or break to
confirm.
Most common problem is fading a strong
trend without care. If price is
rocketing upward, you might not want to
short just because it hits the outer
Ballinger band. Check if volume is still
surging, if the pivot is truly holding,
or if there's a supply zone. Another
problem, when swing trading, you'll have
a tendency to let your losers run. I
want you to respect your stops. If price
breaks the pivot you used as support,
let it go. The initial idea is invalid.
Sometimes you'll face a gap open or a
surprise news event that sends price far
beyond your pivot or your Ballinger
band. That can happen after weekends or
major announcements. In that case,
re-evaluate. If price already soared
past your pivot, do not chase. Wait for
a retest or a new pivot to form. Swing
trading thrives on patience. You do not
have to be in a trade every single day.
Another challenge you'll face,
especially if you are used to day
trading, is the impulse to act onto
every minimal movement. Swing trading
calls for a calmer state. You don't need
to act every day. You pick your level.
You wait sometimes multiple days for
price to get there. You see if it sets
up. If not, you skip it. That's the
discipline part. Another psychological
element is trusting your pivot or your
channel. If you set your stop under that
pivot, do not move it if price is
approaching. If the pivot fails, then
you accept the loss. That's how you keep
your risk controlled. Emotional changes
to your plan might cause bigger losses.
Handling emotional swings is another
challenge. You might see a position in
profit for a few days and suddenly the
market retraces. If you are not used to
this dynamic, you could panic. But these
swings are normal in a multi-day trade.
That is why you trust your pivot or your
channel. If it holds, you stay. If price
breaks, you exit. Many traders even set
alerts so they do not watch every
candle. they just get notified if price
hits a pivot or breaks a channel.
Another challenge will be finding the
correct exit points. One method is to
aim for the next pivot level. If you
bought near the main pivot, you might
target R1 or R2 if the trend cooperates.
If you shorted near R1, you might target
the main pivot or S1. Another method is
to use the Ballinger bands. If you fade
an extreme near the third deviation
band, you might aim for the middle band.
Keep a record of each swing trade. Write
down the reason you took it. Did it rely
on the monthly pivot plus a round
number? Did it rely on a Ballinger band
bounce? Note your stop, your target, and
the outcome. This helps you see which
setups produce the best results. Over
time, you refine your approach. And if
you're ready to fit this into a full a
toz trading system, that's what our
academy is for. Link is in the
description.