order blocks are special candlesticks
that start big price moves they're not
just any candles they're the ones big
Market players use to kick off trends
when you see a big Market move it didn't
just happen by chance it started
somewhere and that starting point is an
order Block it's where the big players
the market makers set up and get ready
to push the price around order blocks
form because of liquidity the big
players need a lot of liquidity to make
their moves and when they can't find
enough liquidity to fill their orders
they make it themselves they do this by
opening positions in both directions
creating fake counter liquidity this
lets them fill up the volume they need
and then push the price where they want
it to go there are two main types of
order blocks you need to know about
bullish order blocks which show up when
the price drops then sudden suddenly
shoots up and bearish Order blocks the
price climbs up then suddenly drops
order blocks are like pressure points in
the market they're areas where the big
players the market makers have put a lot
of their orders when the price comes
back to these areas there's a lot of
potential energy waiting to be
released think about it when a big
player wants to buy a lot of stock or
currency they can't just place one big
order that would spike the price and
they'd end up paying way more than they
want to so instead they break up their
big order into smaller pieces they might
start by selling a little bit this
pushes the price down and scare some
other Traders into selling too now
there's more Supply in the market which
is exactly what the smart money wants
they can now start buying at these lower
prices this process creates our order
block the initial selling creates the
block part the area on the chart where a
lot of orders were placed and because
this is where the smart money started
their buying we know they're likely to
defend this area if the price comes back
to it that's why order blocks are so
powerful to trade you're not just
guessing where the price might go you're
looking at where the big money has
already shown its hand this is why order
blocks will help you place better trades
they give you a solid spot to put your
own orders when you're entering a trade
this isn't just guesswork it's based on
where the big players are putting their
money you're not just picking random
points you're using levels that have
real significance in the
market now here's the reality order
blocks aren't Magic Bullets they only
work if you know how to spot real
liquidity in the market on their own
order blocks don't mean much in fact
most of them break as soon as the price
comes back to them I'll explain later
the secret to find the best areas but
for now think about this why does the
price bounce off these order blocks well
it's all about the big players average
price if the price drops below a bullish
order block or jumps above a bearish one
those big players start losing money and
trust me they don't like losing money so
they push the price back it's like
they're protecting their Turf this is
why you often see that price returns to
an order block before continuing its
main move remember this part order
blocks are based on a lack of liquidity
when smart money needs to open positions
the market makers aren't just reacting
to the market they're actively shaping
it they're creating the conditions they
need to make their moves let's say we
have a bullish order block the price has
gone up from this area but now it's
coming back down as it approaches the
order block several things might happen
first the big players who bought here
before might buy again they know this
level worked before so they're happy to
add to their position second traders who
missed the first move up might see this
as their second chance they'll start
buying adding to the upward pressure
also traders who sold short after the
first move up might start to get nervous
if the price bounces here they'll be in
trouble some of them might start buying
to close their shorts adding even more
upward pressure all of these factors
combined to make the order block a
strong support level and if the price
does bounce here it confirms the
strength of the order block making it
even more likely to work again in the
future now let's break down the anatomy
of an order block we are looking for a
specific shape here for a bullish order
block we want to see a move down then
price shooting up for a bearish order
block price climbs up then suddenly
drops now we're not just looking at a
basic reversal we want the last push the
last candle before the Big Move it's the
final gasp of the old Trend before the
new one takes over this is where the big
players make their move you're looking
for the last candle before the reversal
in a bullish scenario it's often the
last Red candle before a string of green
ones for bearish setups it's the last
green one before the red candles take
over so for a bullish order block we are
looking at a down candle but not just
any down candle we want want the lowest
red candle in the sequence for a bearish
order Block it's the highest green
candle these are our signal flares they
tell us where the action is happening
some Traders use the mean threshold for
identifying these zones it's like the
equator of order block we draw it right
through the middle at the 50% level of
the candle it's like a discount premium
zone for the order block this is where
we expect the price to behave itself if
price respects this level it's a good
sign our order block is legit it's all
about validation a strong order block
shouldn't see price dip below this
midpoint for bullish blocks or rise
above it for bearish blocks if it does
it might be telling us our block isn't
as solid as we thought for a bullish
order block to be confirmed we need to
see a more recent candle trade through
the high of our red candle marking the
zone for a bearish block we need a
candle to trade through the low of our
highest green candle and for a top-notch
bullish order block we don't want to see
price trading below the midpoint of that
candle for a bearish block we don't want
price popping above the midpoint of the
green candle now let's zoom out a bit
where do we find these order blocks we
need to look at the the highs and lows
of the market these are the optimal
reversal spots the turning points where
the smart money makes its
move now let's talk about the mitigation
of order blocks mitigation is just a
fancy word for cleaning up leftover
orders after a big player has bought
what they wanted the price often swings
back to the order block that's because
that's where those initial orders are
sitting the big player wants to close
them out ideally at break even this back
and forth creates the swings we see in
the market it's like a dance buy and
then sell create an order block then
mitigate it so how can you use this info
well it gives you a road map of sorts
when you spot an order block you can
expect price to come back to it at some
point that's your chance to hop on the
right if you see a bullish order block
you're looking for buy opportunities for
bearish ones you're thinking about
selling remember it's all about
liquidity or rather the lack of it when
the market makers need to open a
position they often face a problem
there's not enough liquidity to fill
their orders without moving the price
too much so they get creative they open
positions in both directions it's like
they're creating their own liquidity
pool they fill up the volume they need
then push the price where they want it
to go this is what creates our order
block when they do this they are left
with some positions that are now losing
money and like I said big players don't
like losing money as us retail Traders
they want to close this positions at
break even and the break even point is
right back at our order block this is
why price often comes back to test an
order block if it's not random it's the
big money trying to clean up their
positions and for us smaller Traders
this is an
opportunity here's the difficult part
not every order block gets hit and some
get blown right through how do you know
which ones to trust it all comes down to
liquidity liquidity is just a fancy word
for where the money is it's where a lot
of buy or sell orders pile up often
these are at old highs or lows big
players love to Target these spots
because that's where they can find
enough orders to fill their big
positions so when you're looking at
order blocks pay attention to nearby
liquidity if there's a juicy pool of
orders just beyond the order block
chances are good that price will come
back to hit it this is part of the
mitigation phase mitigation is when
price swings back to the order block
remember those leftover orders from the
initial move this is the time when smart
money cleaned those up they're closing
out positions getting back to even for
us retail Traders this is opportunity
knocking when price swings back to an
order Block it's often setting up for
another move in the original Direction
so if it was a bullish order block and
price comes back down to it that might
be your chance to buy some may buy as
soon as price touches the order block
others wait for signs that the
mitigation is done price action close
maybe a rejection candle or a break of a
small trend line we'll talk about the
best entries
later there's also a concept called a
mitigation Block it's like a cousin to
the order Block it's all about how price
behaves afterwards a mitigation block
forms when the market fails to make a
new high or L it's a sign that the
current move might be running out of
steam it's a failure swing here's how it
plays out let's say the Market's been
going up it hits a high pulls back then
tries to push higher again but this time
it can't quite reach the old high that's
a mitigation Block it's a hint that the
uptrend might be in trouble the opposite
can happen in a downtrend price makes a
low bounces then tries to go lower again
but it can't quite break the old low
that's a bullish mitigation block it
suggests the downtrend might be losing
steam now don't confuse these with
breaker blocks a breaker actually does
make a new high or low it breaks the old
level a mitigation block falls short and
why does this matter well it's all about
understanding what the big players are
up to a mitigation block suggests they
couldn't push price where they wanted
maybe there wasn't enough liquidity or
maybe opposing players stepped in for
you it's a heads up if you see a
mitigation block form it might be time
to start looking for a reversal now
before we continue let us know in the
comments what topics you'd like us to
cover in future videos and drop us a
like to help us with YouTube
algorithm order blocks fit into the
bigger picture of Market structure
Market structure shows the overall flow
with its twists and turns order blocks
are areas where the flow can suddenly
change direction in a bullish Market
you'll see a series of higher highs and
higher lows and each swing up is usually
kicked off by a bullish order block
these blocks are like stepping stones
marking the path of the uptrend Now flip
that for a bearish market you've got
lower lows and lower highs each drop
often starts with a bearish order block
but here's where it gets interesting
order blocks don't just go with the flow
they can signal when the flow is about
to change this is where Market structure
breaks come in a market structure break
happens when price bust through a key
level in an uptrend it's when price
makes a lower low in a downtrend it's a
higher high these brakes are big deals
they're like road signs telling you the
trend might be changing now guess what
often comes right before this breaks
that's right order blocks the market
coils up at the order block then a
structure break follows here's how it
might play out let's say we're in an
uptrend we've got those higher highs and
higher lows then then price forms a
bearish order block price drops from
there and this time it doesn't just make
a higher low it smashes right through
the previous low that's a structure
break this combo order block plus
structure breake is very powerful it's
telling you something big might be
happening the trend that's been chugging
along might be running out of steam when
you spot an order block don't just focus
on on that single level zoom out look at
the bigger picture where is this block
in relation to the overall trend if it's
going with the trend it might be a
continuation signal price could bounce
off it and keep moving in the same
direction but if it's against the trend
it could be setting up for a reversal if
price respects the block and bounces it
could be a continuation of the current
Trend but if it breaks through
especially with a strong move watch out
that could be the start of a new trend
this is where those Market structure
breaks come in if you see price break
through a significant high or low after
hitting an order block that's a big deal
it's like the market is shouting at you
that something's changing another setup
to watch for is the failed order block
this is when price comes back to an
order block but doesn't bounce off it
like expected in instead it pushes right
through this can also be a tradable
signal failed order blocks often lead to
strong moves that's because a lot of
Traders are caught on the wrong side
they were expecting the block to hold
and now they're scrambling to get out
this can fuel a big move in the opposite
direction a quick word on time frames
order blocks work on all time frames but
they are most powerful on the higher
ones an hour order block is usually more
significant than a 5-minute one but that
doesn't mean you should ignore the lower
time frames in fact you can use multiple
time frames together find the big order
blocks on the higher time frames then
zoom in the lower ones for more precise
entries it's like using a map and a GPS
together we'll talk about this
later high probability order blocks are
followed by fair value gaps
these happen when price jumps from one
level to another leaving a gap but
unlike a regular Gap there's some
trading activity in between this
imbalance signifies a sudden surge in
buying or selling pressure indicating
the presence of institutional orders
these gaps show up as big candles on
charts the candles next to them don't
touch fully to spot a fair value Gap
look at three candles in a row
in a bullish Gap the low of the third
candle is above the high of the first
for a bearish gap the high of the third
candle is below the low of the first
these gaps aren't just random they show
where big players made Moves when a
large order hits the market it can cause
a gap and the market often wants to fill
these gaps later both order blocks and
fair value gaps are about imbalances in
the market when price jumps it means one
side buyers or sellers took control fast
this quick move can leave some trades
unfilled fair value gaps are all about
speed when price moves too fast it can
leave these gaps behind and the market
wants to fill them that's why they often
act like magnets pulling price back to
them later order blocks and fair value
gaps work well together you will often
and bullish order block followed by a
fair value Gap this is like a double
confirmation of a key buy level or you
might see price move away from a bearish
order block followed by a fair value Gap
later when price comes back to fill that
Gap it might also retest the order block
this could be a high probability
setup also don't forget about the bigger
picture order blocks and fair value gaps
are just parts of Market structure they
fit into larger Trends and patterns
always keep the overall Market Direction
in
mind the best order blocks have three
key Parts a liquidity run a Breakin
Market structure and a fair value Gap
let's break this down first a liquidity
run this is when price moves fast to hit
a bunch of orders it's like a quick rate
but price shoots up or down grabbing
liquidity this move often tricks Traders
they think the trend will keep going but
it's just a setup for a reversal next we
have a break in Market structure this
means the Market's Behavior changes it
could be a shift from an uptrend to a
downtrend or a continuation in the
previous Trend or it might be a big move
after a quiet period this break shows
something new happening a new high or a
low must be formed from the order block
last the presence of a fair value Gap
when you find all three of these
conditions together you've got a high
quality order Block it's like a perfect
storm for
trading let's say price has been going
up for a while then it makes a quick
Spike higher this Spike might hit a
bunch of stop losses above the market
that's our liquidity run
right after this Spike price drops hard
it falls below recent lows this is our
break in Market structure the uptrend is
now in question as price Falls it leaves
a fair value Gap just below the order
block there's also a liquidity Zone this
whole setup the spike up the drop down
the fair value Gap and the liquidity Run
Forms our order block if price comes
back to test it later that's a decent
short
opportunity the same for a bullish order
Block it's all about reading the big
player moves the liquidity run is smart
money pushing price to an extreme
they're shaking out weak hands the
breaking structure shows their true
intent and the Gap shows how fast and
strong their move was these high quality
order blocks are rare you won't see them
in every day but when you do they are
worth paying attention
to another signal price has been falling
then it makes a quick drop lower this
might trigger a bunch of sell stops
there's our liquidity run but right
after price jumps apart it breaks above
recent highs this is our change in
Market structure the downtrend is now in
doubt as price moves up it leaves a fair
value Gap above the order block a
potential liquidity Zone this makes it a
spot to watch for future buy trades
again the liquidity run is smart money
pushing price to extremes the breaking
structure is them showing their hand and
the Gap shows the power of their move
always consider the current market
context When selecting your order blocks
prioritize those that align with the
prevailing trend Direction and fall
within the most recent price swing in an
uptrend focus on bullish order blocks
that form within the current upswing
rather than bearish order blocks from
previous
downswings and when you find these high
quality blocks it's best to wait wait
for price to come back to the block then
look for signs it's reacting maybe it
stalls there or it might make a small
move and reverse these are are clues for
potential trades and please be realist
not every order block will lead to a
good
trade a successful order block strategy
combines Trend analysis order block
identification and precise entry timing
first you need to figure out which way
the market is moving you'll want to look
at a bigger picture so use a higher time
frame chart let's say you pick the
hourly chart on this chart you are
looking for for the current order flow
in this case an uptrend now that you
know which way the market is moving it's
time to find a good spot to enter your
trade the order block should match the
overall trend as the trend is up look
for a bullish order block before the
order block forms price should have
taken out some liquidity a bunch of stop
losses sitting just below a low point in
an uptrend if price dips down and
triggers that stops before shooting back
up that's a liquidity run then the order
block should trigger a break in Market
structure this shows strength and
commitment to the move the size of the
order block candle matters to generally
the bigger it is the more significant it
might be it's like a bigger footprint it
shows that more Traders were
involved also pay attention to how price
reacts after the order block forms If It
Moves away quickly and forms a fair
value Gap even better remember not every
order block will lead to a good trade
your job is to find the best
opportunities not to trade every signal
you see another tip look for order
blocks that line up with other technical
factors maybe it's at a key Fibonacci
level or it matches up with a trend line
or a moving average the more reasons you
have to believe believe in an order
block the better once you've spotted a
promising order block on the higher time
frame it's time to zoom in for a closer
look this step is all about finding the
perfect moment to enter your trade
timing your entry so you switch to a
lower time frame chart if you were
looking at an hourly chart before you
might zoom in to a 5-minute chart this
gives you a much more detailed view of
price action your plan here is to wait
for price to come back to your
identified order block Zone first check
for realignment this means the price
action on your lower time frame should
match up with the trend you saw on the
higher time frame as the bigger trend is
up you want to see bullish signs on the
smaller time frame too look for a
smaller version of the order block you
found earlier as you're in an uptrend
you're searching for a bullet order
block on this lower time frame an order
block inside the bigger order block you
could also look for a small liquidity
grab just before your entry this is like
a mini version of the liquidity run you
saw on the bigger time frame it might
look like price dipping down to trigger
some nearby stop losses before moving in
your expected
direction another tip to pinpoint your
entry look for any patterns forming on
your lower time frame chart if you see
small double bottoms that's a decent
setup or maybe there are small change of
character price is breaking previous
swing highs and it's ready to go higher
remember the goal here is to fine-tune
your entry you're not changing your
overall view of the market you're just
trying to get the best possible entry
price the plan is to enter your trade on
the breakout of the lower time frame
order block for this buy order you place
your stop loss just below a recent swing
low and please give it enough room to
breathe don't try to be too precise with
your stop your take profit should be
ideally at least three times higher that
your risk but don't just pick a random
number look at the chart and find the
next logical High Point within the
higher time frame Trend and consider
using multiple take-profit levels you
could close half your position at your
first Target then let the rest run to a
higher
Target here's a pro tip order blocks
must have a liquidity pool to Target
identify clear liquidity pools above
your chosen order block these pools act
as magnets for price they are like a
road map for potential price movement
after the order block is triggered in
this case we see a bullish order order
block with a cluster of previous swing
highs above it this presents a clear
liquidity pool that price is likely to
Target once the order block is triggered
now if you want to learn other smart
money tactics you need to watch one of
these videos next