in this course I'm going to teach you
everything you need to know about
getting started with technical analysis
no matter if you are new to the trading
game or your intermediate or Advanced
Trader this course will help you read
any Market with precision and
consistency we'll break down technical
analysis into easy to understand
Concepts and will cover everything from
Market structure Cycles candlesticks
patterns volume and many more
so like subscribe and let's get started
Market structure must be the foundation
of your analysis the first part of any
trading plan is to establish which side
of the market is in control demand or
Supply buyers or sellers when reading
Market structure you have to pay close
attention to one thing on a chart price
price is King and will tell you all you
need to know when price is moving
influenced by supply and demand this
great strengths an uptrend also called a
bull trend is pictured by higher highs
and higher lows
the trend will continue in that
direction until a lower low is created
by the price
the trend begins to show signs of
weakness when it fails to create a
higher high
a downtrend also known as a bear trend
is the price action of lower lows and
lower highs
the downtrend will continue as long as
new lower Highs are created
once a higher high comes into the price
the trend might end the sign that the
trend may be reversing is when price
begins to print higher lows in addition
to higher highs
a sideways trend is a trend that has
approximately equal highs and equal lows
price trends in a Range during this
point of the market or better set is in
a consolidation phase and markets can
move in a period of consolidation for a
long time this trend is broken if the
price breaks out from the top or bottom
of the range
this could be the beginning of one of
the first two trends
these are the obvious Concepts regarding
Market structure now let's go deeper and
let me share the subtleties of the
market structure
the first principle is the most obvious
one for a market to be in an active
cycle its most recent structure must be
one where price creates a high that
breaks the previous high this is the
case of a bullish cycle
a down cycle will be established if the
latest swing low in the price breaks
below the most recent low
in this example you can clearly see the
market in an upcycled phase with higher
highs and higher lows
to confirm that the bullish Trend or an
upcycle is evolving in a healthy manner
not only we need to see the high created
being higher than its previous High what
we also should expect at least several
closes above that high
this is further evidence that the market
is accepting and building value above it
a failure for price to remain above that
High may translate into a false Breakout
and while this price move still
qualifies as a new high in the cycle the
momentum the speed of the move is weak
you must conduct your Market structure
analysis on multiple time frames you
must avoid the Trap of being
short-sighted by only sticking to one
time frame when conducting your analysis
it's all about finding confirmation from
higher time frames what this means is
that if you are planning to enter on the
hourly time frame for example you should
then understand what type of conditions
are dominant in the higher time frames
the most popular in this case would be
the four hour and the daily charts we'll
talk about later about how you should
analyze multiple time frames
markets don't always Trend and will come
to the point in the market structure
where the dominant Trend starts losing
momentum
while you are in an uptrend reading the
market structure is straightforward but
you must determine when you've
transitioned from a trend into a
consolidation
here's my method let's consider an
uptrend transitioning into consolidation
first you must see a failed test of a
recent High
this means that price is unable to break
the recent High
second a failed test of the most recent
swing low would confirm that we have
entered a consolidation phase which
would last until the most recent high or
low is broken
with at least several closes above or
below level
meaning price remains for a longer
period above or below that level
in this context don't forget that the
consolidation is still within the
context of an uptrend
until price manages to break and hold
below the latest valid swing low the
strength remains to the upside
the break of structure is the first sign
that the market is telling you that it's
about to get weaker or it's about
reverse
let's say we have an uptrend
higher highs and higher lows
we have a break of structure when price
makes a new lower low and a lower high
this tells you that this trend could be
weakening or it could reverse
for a downtrend the same concept lower
lows and lower highs
we have a break of structure when price
makes a new higher high
and the higher low
there's no guarantee that the trend is
over but this is a warning sign a sign
of weakness in the previous downtrend
another major sign that will help you
determine the strength of the cycle is
the type of progress made by the
Dominion side in control of the cycle
you need to ask the following question
are the new swings in the cycle
increasing or decreasing in magnitude
here despite having entered a period of
consolidation if we measure the latest
wings from the last low to the most
recent High we see that this is bigger
versus the previous wave this means that
buyers are increasing their commitment
on each new cycle High
when it comes to the distance the price
moves the magnitude is only half of the
equation the other one has to do with
the velocity of the move or the speed
was the new wave created after a fast
and impulsive move
or did price make a new lower high with
the momentum being sluggish and taking
too long to form
A good rule of thumb is to count the
approximate number of candles it took to
achieve a new leg
in this case you can see that the second
leg was created with a lower number of
candles this means faster speed
this is the simplest way of analyzing a
market the big advantage in analyzing
Market structure this way is the fact
that you keep your charts clean and
uncluttered now let's talk about Market
Cycles
[Music]
price action in the financial markets
doesn't occur randomly
it appears in a structured manner
involving distinct faces
price action follows four distinct
Cycles
accumulation markup distribution and
markdown
[Music]
accumulation is the first cycle this
phase is characterized by increased
demand for a market
it typically occurs when the price has
decreased significantly to a point where
a market appears to have sold too much
in this area buyers start accumulating
positions as they begin to take
advantage of extremely low prices
while accumulation is characterized by
buyers winning the battle against
sellers price action tends to remain
flat struggling to make any new highs
in this case the price oscillates in a
Range making lower Highs but no new
highs
even if price remains range Mount the
buying pressure dominates the
accumulation phase
before the price breaks out of the
accumulation phase it is common for
price to move below the lower level of
the range
this movement is a false breakout giving
buyers another reason to buy low
markup face is characterized by Price
breaking out to the upside
the cycle occurs as buyers gain enough
power and control to steer the price
above the upper level in the
accumulation phase
price breaks out of the upper level of
the range and starts making higher highs
and higher lows
this confirms buyers are in control and
poised to drive price to new highs
distribution phase occurs after the
price has increased significantly and
sellers attempt to regain control
as a result the price action on the
chart appears flat with a price trading
again in a Range
lower tops and flat bottoms generally
characterize the range
before the price breaks out of the range
in the distribution phase it is common
for it to move through the upper level
at the top this false breakout at the
top offer sellers another opportunity to
sell High
then price moves aggressively below the
lower level of the range
Paving the way for the next phase
a markdown phase is the last stage in
the course as sellers over power buyers
and steer prices below the lower level
of the distribution phase
cycle appears as a strong downtrend
after it breaks the lower level of the
flat range
knowing these Cycles is an important
part in your technical analysis process
this will allow you to predict price
action based on the prevailing phase
this analysis offers an edge in
recognizing upcoming price modes for
instance if you pinpoint the end of the
accumulation stage you'll enter at the
beginning of the markup stage an
opportunity to profit from prices moving
to the upside likewise you want to enter
at the end of the distribution phase and
at the beginning of the markdown thus
preparing to profit from a solid price
move to the downside
support and resistance is one of the
most widely used Concepts in technical
analysis support is an area where a
price has shown a tendency to stop
falling think of support as the floor
beneath the market
so why did this particular area become
the floor perhaps the buyers have
decided that this is a good price to
take a buy position and therefore buying
pressure emerges when the price reaches
this area preventing the price from
falling further
or perhaps the price has decreased to a
point where the sellers are no longer
comfortable selling they'd prefer to
wait in the hope of selling at a higher
price
for whatever reason the price has shown
a tendency to stop falling at this point
resistance is an area where the price
has shown a tendency to stop Rising
think of resistance as the ceiling above
the market perhaps the buyers no longer
wish to buy once the price has reached
this level and they'd prefer to see the
price drop before buying more or maybe
the sellers have determined that this is
a fair price at which to sell and their
influence Supply selling pressure at
that price
for whatever reason the price has shown
a tendency to stop rising at this point
how to draw these levels many Traders
make the process of drawing support and
resistance levels a lot more difficult
than it needs to be
there are six main rules look for
extreme swing highs and swing lows
meaning look for the highest and the
lowest points that price has reached in
the recent time
look for at least two rejections of an
area
you want the level to be obvious meaning
it jumps right out at you you should be
able to spot the level right away when
looking at the chart
the move away from the area was
significant
the level acted as both support and
resistance and it was respected from
both sides
and the level was recently respected
were formed in a recent time period
now very important you don't need all
these conditions when you draw a level
the more rules the level fulfills the
better but you don't need the level to
check all six conditions
now here's a big misconception regarding
support and resistance levels the more
times the level is tested the more valid
it is
this statement is one of the biggest
lies in technical analysis like I said
really strong support or resistance
levels immediately push price away from
them
there is enough buying pressure at
support enough buyers waiting to buy at
that level that the market is
immediately moved up and away from the
level
if price can hang out around the level
or quickly comes back to the level it
suggests a certain lack of conviction on
the part of the buyers if the market is
able to retest the level many times then
you have a potential setup for a
breakout through the level a move below
it
if you look at this example the orders
at the support level are absorbed each
time price revisits the area
until buyers lose their power
price then plunges through the Zone with
little difficulty
and also look at this resistance level
the upper Zone was tested several times
and sellers came in pushing the price
down
this resistance level was gradually
eroded as the more and more sellers had
their orders filled
eventually there were less Sellers and
price broke through
personally I avoid buying a support
which has been tested multiple times in
the past the greater the number of times
a zone is tested the more likely it is
to break
once all buyers have gone price can move
through that level to the next area
don't need to draw every level you can
find on your charts many Traders fall
into this trap and they end up taking
too long to draw on every little level
they can find
what they end up with is a really messy
chart that basically does more harm than
good
you need to learn to draw only the
significant levels on your charts then
you have a useful framework to work from
[Music]
your support and resistance levels
shouldn't be drawn across the exact
highs or lows of the price bars
oftentimes support and resistance are
more zones than exact levels
you'll see a key level that is indeed an
exact level but more often than not
price will break your line or will turn
before it touches the level
point being you don't always have to
draw the level exactly through the high
or the low of the bar
we talked about Market structure Cycles
Trends support and resistance now let's
go even deeper and talk about
candlesticks
candlesticks are basically A visual
representation of what is going on in a
market
by looking at the Candlestick you can
get information about the Open high low
and close of the price which will give
you an idea about the price movement
Candlestick analysis will help you
understand this changing psychological
factors in the market by showing you how
buyers and sellers interact with each
other
most Traders prefer to set green candles
to access bullish and red candlesticks
as bearish
a bullish Candlestick simply means the
price opened lower and closed up higher
after a certain time period which can be
one minute five minutes one hour and so
on
a bearish Candlestick simply means that
the Candlestick opens up at a higher
price and closed lower after a certain
time period
the candle body represents the distance
price has moved from the opening price
to the closing price
high is the highest price that was
reached during that time period
and the low is the lowest price that was
rich during that time period
foreign
candlesticks that are considered bearish
and bearish candlesticks that are
considered bullish
to really understand this concept you
need to understand buying and selling
pressure you see every Candlestick that
is formed tells your story about the
battle between the buyers and sellers
who dominated the battle who won at the
end and who is weakening all of this is
reflected in any Candlestick you see
the length of the body of the
Candlestick as well as the Shadow or the
wick tells you a story about the buying
and selling pressure
let's look at this green Candlestick
it's a bullish Candlestick right yes but
you can see that it has a very short
body and a very long week or a tail or a
shadow it tells you the sellers were
dominant if this Candlestick was to form
after hitting a resistance level it will
be considered a battery signal even
though it's a bullish candlestick
you can apply the same sort of logic to
all of the other candlesticks and read
the story each one is telling you if the
upper week is very long it means price
opens and got pushed Higher by the
buyers but then at the highest price
sellers got in and drove it back down
if the lower week is long it tells you
that there is a lot of buying pressure
sellers drove the price down but buyers
got in and drove the price back up
if the lower week is short it tells you
there's very minimal buying pressure
if the upper week is short it tells you
that there is very minimal selling
pressure
[Music]
and what about the length of the body of
the candlesticks a longer body of the
candle indicates a very strong buying or
selling pressure
a short body of a Candlestick indicates
little price movement and therefore less
buying or selling pressure
sometimes the candles will have no upper
or lower Shadows but with very long
bodies
these are the same as standard
candlesticks but are anyone stronger
indication of bullish or negative Market
sentiment
in the case of a bullish candle prices
never decline below the open
in the case of a bearish candle price
never traded above the old one
what Traders do is over complicate their
Candlestick trading and focus on things
that are not necessary you'll make a big
mistake if you start memorizing 40 or 50
types of Candlestick formations because
when you start analyzing a market you'll
have to consider 50 variables before
making a decision so let's simplify
Candlestick trading among the dozens of
Candlestick formations there are six
basic Candlestick types
[Music]
the long Candlestick indicates a lot of
momentum among buyers or sellers the
lack of Shadow or tail or weak indicates
exceptional strength for one side or the
other
a long Candlestick may have no Shadows
or a small one at the top or at the
bottom of the real body
the significance of the long Candlestick
relies completely on its location for
example a long green Candlestick
appearing within an uptrend could be a
strong confirmation signal but if the
same Candlestick appears after a
downtrend it could act as a potential
reversal signal
the same for a long red candle 6. within
a downtrend it tends to confirm it
and when it follows an uptrend it is
more likely to Signal or reversal
Candlestick with average or relatively
small range signals a general agreement
between buyers and sellers that the
current price is reasonable
however when short candlesticks appear
following a period of strong Trend in
either direction especially when long
candlesticks have shown up they can
indicate a struggle between buyers and
sellers and a possible reversal in the
trend or slowing down in price momentum
the appearance of a single short candle
is not meaningful by itself
when a series of short candles appear it
may show declining momentum in the
current Trend or be a symptom of
sideways movement
the candle with no real body or a very
narrow range one in which the open and
the clothes are the same represents a
significant development the fact that
price opens and closes at the same place
has greater significance when the doji
also has upper or lower Shadows or both
the longer Shadows reveal an attempt by
buyers or sellers to move price in the
desired Direction however the effort
failed when price returned to close at
the same price as the open when a doji
appears at the bottom of a downtrend and
also has an exceptionally long lower
Shadow it shows that sellers tried to
move price lower but couldn't this hints
at the likely reversal and the possible
movement to the upside
if adoji appears at the top of an
uptrend and also has a very long upper
Shadow this may indicate a possible
reversal and a possible down movement
in the first place doji candles indicate
a loss of momentum and based on the
appearance of any Shadows May provide
reversal signals
[Music]
one of the most interesting signals is
an exceptionally long Shadow or weak
appearing on both sides of the real body
when such Shadows are found in both
upper and lower ends it shows that
neither buyers nor sellers had enough
power to move price beyond the opening
and closing range
this failure of both sides to control
price movement could be a sign of a
period of consolidation
when a Candlestick is up with Long
Shadows on both sides and the current
trend has been underway it can signal
the end of that Trend even though both
sides were unable to create more
movement
[Music]
when a candle contains an unusually long
upper Shadow it signals that buyers have
lost momentum or failed in an effort to
take momentum away from sellers if this
pattern unfolds at the top of an uptrend
it's a signal that the trend may be
about to end
if it shows up within a downtrend it may
conform more established continuation
buyers try to reverse the downtrend but
failed a long upper Shadow candle often
appears at the top of a knob move and is
off on the lowest point in the downtrend
and signals a reversal point
the appearance of a Candlestick with a
long lower Shadow indicates a failure by
sellers to move price slower which leads
to the immediate conclusion that either
the current downtrend is ending or an
existing uptrend is continuing
however the pattern can have either a
bullish or a bearish interpretation
depending on where it appears
the real body may also be either green
or red without affecting the
interpretation of the candle along a
lower Shadow candle often appears at the
bottom of a Down move and is often the
highest point in the uptrend and signals
the reversal point
the multitude of Candlestick patterns
you should pay a closer attention to
engulfing candles
this Candlestick formation consists of
two bodies the first body being smaller
than the second one in other words the
second body engulfs the previous one
in the case of a bearish engulfing bar
this pattern tells us that sellers are
in control of the market when this
pattern occurs at the end of an uptrend
this indicates that buyers are engulfed
by sellers which signals a potential
Trend reversal buyers are losing control
of the market and sellers are trying to
push the market to go down
the bullish engulfing bar tells us that
the market is no longer under the
control of sellers and buyers are
gaining strength when a bullish
engulfing candle forms in the context of
an uptrend it indicates a continuation
signal when a bullish engulfing candle
forms at the end of a downtrend it
signals a potential reversal
inside bars are another formation you
should incorporate in your analysis
inside bars are either one or more
candlesticks which are contained within
a range of one candle
this Candlestick is usually referred to
as the mother candle
the second small bar is completely
contained by the first one which is the
opposite of the engulfing bar pattern
the inside bar is seen as a reversal
pattern because it indicates that the
market trend is likely to change
especially when it's located at tops or
bottoms
the inside bar formation also indicates
a period of consolidation in the case of
a bullish Trend it reflects that balls
are not buying any further on the second
candle
and this is represented by a small red
candle after a strong uptrend
bar is without a doubt one of the most
powerful and reliable price action
trading signals they are very simple
Candlestick patterns but when paired
with a solid context they can foreshadow
large Market reversals we talked about
them previously when we simplified
candlesticks a pin bar is a single
Candlestick with a long tail whose price
action demonstrates a rejection of a
price level and reversal in price
bullish pin bars form when sellers start
the candle in control but price reaches
a level that's rejected and buyers take
over and dominate the remainder of the
candle closing out near were at the high
of the candle
bearish pin bars form When Buyers start
the candle in control but price reaches
a level that's rejected and sellers take
over and dominate the remainder of the
candle closing out near or at the lows
I consider a valid spin bar a candle
that meets two conditions
the week is minimum three times the
length of the body and the weak must
stick out from all other candles and
must be very obvious
now the technical analysis of
candlesticks is not about finding pin
bars engulfing patterns or seeing if
there are more green candles than red
ones it's about observing price bars as
they form and understanding what the
market has done and is doing a candle of
the same type will have a completely
different meaning depending on where it
appears in a price trend
is it at the start of a trend or in the
middle of the trend or at the end of it
is it that support or resistance or in
the accumulation or distribution phase
candlesticks should be analyzed in the
context of the price move you should
never try and read the candle in
isolation analyzing multiple bars as a
group on several time frames offers a
lot more analytical value
the point is start reading the current
candle in relation to the previous bars
is the current Candlestick larger or
smaller than the previous ones which
recent candles are showing momentum
increases or decreases
is the size of the body meaningful or
not are you seeing a buying or selling
pressure
Candlestick patterns don't always have
to mean anything of Interest some
signals are really not signals at all
this is why confirmation is so important
confirmation is an important aspect of
Candlestick analysis it's the
observation of separate and independent
signals that verify what the Candlestick
pattern predicts
for example a Candlestick reversal may
be confirmed by tests of resistance or
support or momentum changes you need to
rely on confirmation to improve your
timing of entry and exit confirmation is
necessary because no single Candlestick
pattern is always reliable you know this
even confirmed signals May Fail however
with the use of confirmation the ratio
of successful timing improves and failed
signals are more easily spotted
a confirming indicator may also consist
of a second sign of the same type for
example an initial Candlestick reversal
may be followed by an equally strong but
different Candlestick revealing the same
potential
you may find a pin bar which is followed
by an engulfing candle at a support
level
three factors which confirm a possible
Buy trade
when this occurs the reliability of the
signal is much stronger
one of the most efficient tools to
follow a trend are trend lines trend
lines are lines that connect consecutive
higher lows in an uptrend and
consecutive lower highs in a downtrend a
trend line is most helpful when looking
for entries in the direction of the
trend on pullbacks
and in the opposite direction after the
trend line is broken
while they are relatively easy to apply
on a chart there are many trend lines
misconceptions and mistakes made by
Traders in their analysis
my first advice is to ignore the candle
wicks trend lines are only useful if
placed correctly otherwise you could
find yourself missing opportunities or
Worse trading on the wrong side of the
market drawing trend lines isn't an
exact science there are usually multiple
ways to draw a trendline but from my
experience the best trend line is
applied by using the candle bodies in
the tails in my opinion clothes are more
important and they carry more meaning
if a candle closes at a certain level
this means that market participants were
ready to accept this level as a market
balance point
as in the case of support and resistance
levels you should treat trend lines as
areas
price is a very Dynamic concept and
volatility and momentum can affect price
moves in significant ways
this is the subject of another video but
when retail Traders are trying to place
a trade at a very obvious price level
the professional Traders know this and
they will do their best to kick out the
amateurs by letting price spike through
levels
to overcome this shortcoming and to
improve your trading skills you need to
start using areas instead of just single
trend lines
by using areas you can create noise
zones and filter out a lot of Market
noise
use trend lines as zones then you don't
need to worry about drawing trend lines
along the exact highs or lows
another tip spacing between connecting
points matters the laws used to form a
knob trend line and the highs used to
form a downtrend line should not be too
far apart or too close together
the most suitable distance apart will
depend on the time frame and the degree
of price movement
if the lows or the highs are too close
together the next price reaction at the
trend line is questionable
if the lows are too far apart the
relationship between the two points
could be suspect an ideal trend line is
made up of relatively evenly spaced lows
or highs
so why it's important to measure the
time between consecutive touches we
talked about this in the support and
resistance module before a breakout
occurs the price tends to Cluster around
the supporting trend line and the time
between the consecutive touches tends to
become shorter
as the uptrend starts to lose momentum
the time between each consecutive touch
on the train line becomes shorter
finally the time between the last two
touches was very short after which the
price broke below the trend line and
started a strong downtrend buyers
weren't strong enough to defend the
trend line and sellers kept pushing the
price lower
so if the market repeatedly tests a
train line many times in a relatively
short period and the price cannot drift
far from the trend line then a breakout
will likely happen
the market will break through the trend
line and attempt to reverse the trend
of course this is not always accurate
but when I see this pattern I'm inclined
to trade a breakout rather than a
continuation
and here's another important note the
angle of the trend line matters as the
steepness of the trend line increases
the validity of the supporter resistance
level decreases
a steep trend line results from a sharp
Advance or decline over a brief period
of time the angle of a train line
created from such sharp moves is
unlikely to offer a meaningful support
or resistance level
even if the trend line is formed with
many valid points attempting to trade a
trendline breakout will often prove
difficult
once a trend has been established by a
series of trending highs and lows the
more the most profitable trades are in
the direction of the trend line until
the trend line is broken
every time the market pulls back to the
area around the trend line even if it
undershoots or overshoots the trend line
look for a reversal from the trend line
and try to enter in the direction of the
previous trend
tip after a trendline breakout the
chances are high that the area will get
tested after a pullback
depending on market conditions the test
can be followed by the trend continuing
in the initial direction in which case
you must readjust the trend line with
the new swings created
prices don't usually move in a uniform
fashion and since trend lines account
for both time and price they move along
the price and time access this means
that any acceleration or deceleration of
the trend requires adjustments to the
trend line
to decide whether a trend line should be
adjusted or whether it has been
definitely broken consider how the price
moves within a trend during an uptrend
for example the price makes higher highs
and higher lows as long as that keeps
occurring if the price moves below the
trend line it doesn't necessarily mean
the trend has ended the trend line just
need to be adjusted
and as in the case of support and
resistance levels higher time frame
trend lines are the most important lines
the longer a trend line is respected the
more important it becomes
a trend line that extends over two weeks
will always be considered more important
than a line that only extends on the
course of a trading session
to get the very best results with trend
lines use higher time frames like the 4
Hour or the daily charts
another tip is to use trendline channels
a trendline channel is on the opposite
side of the price action from the trend
line and has the same general slope
in a bull trend for example a trend line
is below the lows while a trend channel
line is above the highs and both are
rising up and to the right
a trendline channel is useful for fading
a trend that has gone too far too fast
or to take your profit if you entered a
long position around the lower trend
line
the price pattern concept is similar to
support and resistance at any one time
Market participants have one of three
choices to buy sell or stand aside as
this ratio between the three groups
change over time so thus the supply and
demand for any given market and this is
how patterns are formed most batters
fall into one of two groups reversal
chart patterns which indicate that price
is about to change direction or
continuation chart patterns which
indicate that price should continue in
its current direction
reversal patterns tend to be more
dramatic and impactful than continuation
patterns and you only need to focus on
three of them head and shoulders and the
double top and double bottom formations
The Head and Shoulders is a bearish
reversal pattern that consists of three
main parts the left shoulder The Head
and the right shoulder
the pattern begins as a series of higher
highs and higher lows the classic
definition of a trend
that sequence is altered when a low
point is formed that has the same
approximate value as the previous low
the left shoulder and the head of the
pattern are now fully formed and this is
the first sign that the changing trend
is on the horizon
the price rallies from this low point
but instead of resuming the sequence of
higher highs a lower high occurs often
this lower high is similar in value to
the prior high points on the left
shoulder then the price slides back to
the previous low for a third time
forming the right shoulder
the pattern of highs within the head and
shoulders are high higher high and lower
high
the three laws should be similar in
value and represent an area of
horizontal support this is known as the
neckline of the pattern
think of the head and shoulders pattern
as the transition point between these
two opposing trends
the left side of the pattern represents
the end of the uptrend the final higher
high and the right side of the pattern
represents the beginning of the
downtrend the first lower high
if you understand the concept of a head
and shoulders pattern the bearish double
top should be easy to follow first price
must form a series of higher highs and
higher lows the definition of an uptrend
the sequence is disrupted when the price
finally fails to reach a higher high
instead the price is only able to match
its previous High
the two highs don't have to be perfectly
symmetrical
the focal point of this pattern is the
area of horizontal support
if and when the price Falls below this
low you can use it as a signal to sell
because the next likely move is lower
[Music]
the bullish double bottom pattern is
simply the inverse of the bearish double
top one the price has formed a downtrend
consisting of a series of lower lows and
lower highs
at some point the price fails to make a
lower low instead the low price
approximately matches the previous low
again the two lows don't need to be
exactly the same
the focal point of this pattern is the
high that rests between the two lows
this area is now considered resistance
if price breaks above resistance the
pattern is completed and the breakout
has occurred
through a period of trending the market
will often pause this pause is known as
a consolidation on many occasions these
consolidations form specific shapes and
patterns known as continuation patterns
so let's take a closer look at the best
continuation formations what they are
what they mean and how you might use
them to your advantage
a triangle consists of two opposing
trend lines imagine that a series of
lower highs appears on a chart
simultaneously coexisting with a series
of higher lows
the result would be two trend lines that
move toward each other
this formation is known as a symmetrical
triangle and has no directional bias
this is because both the buyers and
sellers are demonstrating strength
the buyers are buying at consistently
higher levels and the sellers are
selling at consistently lower levels
symmetrical triangles are assumed to be
continuation patterns in other words the
price should continue moving in the
direction established prior to the
formation of the symmetrical triangle in
this cases the triangle itself is
basically a consolidation that occurs
within the trend
however the pattern itself shows that
both buyers and sellers have a similar
degree of control so the psychology
behind the symmetrical triangle seem to
say that neither of them have a
significant advantage
foreign
triangle the ascending triangle pattern
has a clear directional bias in this
pattern the buyers show their power by
forming a series of higher lows because
the buyers are willing to buy at
consistently higher prices they are
considered the aggressive side
meanwhile as the buyers push higher the
sellers are unable to create momentum in
the opposite direction
instead
form a horizontal resistance level this
indicates that the sellers are simply
trying to stand their ground as the
buyers move toward them from
increasingly higher levels
the assumption is that the aggressive
site in this case the buyers will
eventually overcome the passive Sellers
and push through resistance
this is the inverted version of the
ascending triangle in this case the
sellers demonstrate their Superior
Firepower by pushing the price to a
series of lower highs
meanwhile buyers can only form an
horizontal support level indicating a
lower level of commitment than the
sellers
the Assumption here is that the passive
buyers will eventually be overrun by the
aggressive sellers
this bearish pattern is considered more
effective when it appears within an
overall downtrend although this is not a
requirement
a bull flag pattern begins with a sharp
almost vertical bullish movement
this move indicates that the buyers are
the dominant side
this initial bullish move is known as
the flagpole this initial movement is
followed by a mild reversal which slopes
gently in the opposite direction
this second move indicates that the
sellers are unable to show a similar
response
forms a shape that is bounded by two
parallel lines resembling a flag
how to analyze this the dominant side in
this case the Bulls are expected to take
control as a result the price is
expected to continue moving higher
a bullish wedge also referred to as a
falling wedge is a continuation pattern
that slopes downward in the opposite
direction of a prior bullish trend
in this sense it's similar to a bull
flag pattern in which the flag itself
slopes in the opposite direction of the
trend while the pattern contains a
series of lower highs and lower lows
each subsequent low barely exceeds the
previous low causing a line drawn
beneath those lows to slope gently lower
this contrasts with a line drawn above
the lower highs which forms a steeper
slope the two resulting lines converge
at an angle as these lines come close to
each other a move in the direction of
the prior trend is anticipated
a bullish rectangle occurs when after
moving higher in an uptrend the price
forms a sideways consolidation which is
bounded by clear levels of support and
resistance
the area of consolidation resembles a
box in theory this consolidation is
similar to a symmetrical triangle the
main difference is the converging trend
lines of the symmetrical triangle are
replaced by the parallel lines of the
rectangle
as with the symmetrical triangle price
is taking a breather before resuming its
trend
a bearish rectangle occurs when the
price forms a sideways consolidation
after trending lower
station area is bounded by clear levels
of support and resistance and also
resembles a box
this continuation represents a pause in
the trend
and you should expect a resumption of
the downtrend
when it comes to price patterns location
is of key importance in fact it could be
said that the chart pattern is defined
not only by its shape but by the price
action that precedes it a pattern that
hints at the continuation of the current
move is useless if there is no existing
Trend that can be continued
likewise without a trend to reverse a
chart pattern that hints at the price
reversal loses its meaning
all patterns must be viewed within the
context of the price action that
preceded that patterns formation
dark patterns occur in all different
chart types in all time frames they are
just as likely to appear on an hourly
chart as they are on a daily one because
these patterns can occur in any time
period they are considered fractal in
nature and here's the main problem with
chart patterns we Traders have an
unfortunate tendency to see what we want
to see
because of this it can be difficult to
treat all charge patterns with 100
objectivity
there are even traders who question
whether the patterns we've discussed
here actually exist because we tend to
see what we want to see it might be a
good idea to avoid searching for
specific patterns
instead examine charts without
expectations looking for nothing in
particular and wait for a pattern to
reveal itself
the gold pattern should be fairly
obvious it should stand out
if it takes more than a few seconds to
identify the pattern it might not be a
useful example of the information
and remember patterns fail like any
technique nothing in technical analysis
is guaranteed the truth is that they are
easier to spot after the event but you
can still build a plan around them after
the breakout occurs another key point is
that textbook patterns are quite rare in
real time you won't find a perfect
triangle you'll see many price bikes
false breakouts you just have to observe
the relationship between the swings and
adjust your lines as the price unfolds
and another tip chart patterns are more
reliable on the higher time frames
so look at the bigger picture first
volume plays a key part in the current
and future direction of a market
trading volume is a measure of how much
a given Market has traded in a period of
time
for stocks volume is measured in the
number of shares traded for futures and
options volume is based on how many
contracts have changed hence looking at
the volume patterns over time can help
you get a sense of the conviction behind
advances and declines in specific
markets
in technical analysis volume is the
second most valuable item of data after
the price itself large volume confirms
Market activity and that market
participants are involved in the move
including smart money who bring the
highest turnover to the market
when the smart money are trading it
means they are interested in price at
certain levels and they literally push
the price up or down low volume tells us
that there are very few participants in
the market and that neither buyers nor
sellers have any significant interest in
the price
volume can help you determine the health
of a trend an uptrend is strong and
healthy a volume increases as price
moves with the trend
and decreases when price goes counter
Trend during correction periods also
known as pullbacks
when prices are rising and volume is
decreasing it tells you that the trend
is unlikely to continue
price may still attempt to rise at a
slower Pace but once sellers take
control which is usually signified by an
increase in volume prices will fall
a downtrend is strong and healthy if
volume increases as prices move lower
and decreases when the price begins to
retrace to pull back upwards
when price is falling and volume is
decreasing the downtrend is unlikely to
continue
the price will either continue to
decrease but at a slower Pace or start
to rise
when a volume spikes at certain price
levels you should know that this was an
area of high interest for Traders at
that price level
if there is a great deal of Interest it
means the level is a key one
this simple observation of volume will
allow you to identify important support
and resistance levels which could play a
significant role in the future
where volume spikes are extreme in other
words larger than any historical spikes
nearby this is generally known as a
volume climax
when this occurs you should look for
signs for the future direction of the
move from the price itself and this is
often followed by a particular candle or
a price bar pattern massive volume
spikes are often seen during fundamental
announcements on a daily basis
reversals however happen not over a
single day but over a series of days if
higher than average volume stays in the
market for several days a huge bomb
spike a volume climax will Crown a point
of Market reversal
volume can help to validate all kinds of
breakouts when the market is
consolidating on low volume a pickup in
volume can signify that a breakout is
due
I'll break out the carrying on a rising
volume is a valid Breakout
while a breakout that attracted no
interest from Traders occurring on low
volume is likely to be false
when you analyze a market you shouldn't
be looking for two points whether the
price has been validated by the volume
or whether there is a Divergence with
the price
if the price is validated then this
confirms a continuation of the price
Behavior
by contrast if there is a Divergence
then this is sending a signal of a
potential change
Fibonacci retracements are one of the
most popular technical analysis tools
used in the financial markets this
technique is based on the Fibonacci
sequence a well-known mathematical
concept but I don't want to bore you
with numbers in mathematics you just
need to know that Fibonacci retracements
are used to identify potential levels of
support and resistance during a price
trend
Fibonacci levels or simple horizontal
lines that indicate possible support and
resistance levels where price could
potentially reverse Direction
the first thing you should know about
the Fibonacci tool is that it works best
when the market is trending the idea is
to go long or buy on a retracement at
the Fibonacci support level when the
market is trending up
and to go short or sell on a retracement
at a Fibonacci resistance level when the
market is trending down
the theory is that after price begins a
new trend Direction the price will
retrace or return back to a previous
price level before resuming in the
direction of its trend
so how to draw Fibonacci levels in order
to find this Fibonacci retracement
levels you have to find recent and
significant swing highs and lows in a
market then you take the tool and for
downtrends you apply it on the swing
High
and drag the tool to the most recent
swing low
for uptrends you do the opposite you
apply the tool on the swing low and drag
it to the most recent swing High
remember there must be a visible Trend
otherwise FIB levels won't have a
meaningful impact on price movement
no matter how often you use Fibonacci
what's most important is to use it
correctly
choosing the correct price link for
placing your fibs is one of the main
problems when using it
Fibonacci is an effective method but you
must place it on the swings that make
the most sense for the current market
conditions
and remember the most important aspect
when using Fibonacci the presence of a
trend Fibonacci doesn't work well in
consolidations Corrections ranges or
sideways movements
also don't use the Fibonacci retracement
tool on very small price moves or
shorter time frames the shorter the time
frame the less reliable the retracement
level making it very difficult for you
to really pick and choose what levels
can be traded try to focus on the larger
time frames when you apply Fibonacci
levels
further if you use the Fibonacci tool on
very small price moves it may not
provide much Insight the levels would be
so close together that almost every
price level appears important
many Traders are disliking Fibonacci
because this tool is subjective there
are multiple price swings during a
trading day so not everyone will be
connecting the same two points
the two points you connect may not be
the two points others connect
that's why don't try to force the levels
the best and most helpful Fibonacci
retracements are those where you don't
have to look long on a chart
Fibonacci levels provide areas of
interest to watch for pullbacks there
are two main types of pullbacks using
Fibonacci shallow and deep retracements
if you correctly analyze the strength of
the trend you will have high probability
areas to take trades once a trend has
clearly established itself you will
often see shallow pullbacks to the 23 38
and 50 FIB levels which are very typical
before the trend continues so when the
trend is strong pay attention to these
fee levels
on the other hand price will make a deep
pullback when a trend is not yet clearly
established you will see deep pullbacks
to the 61 78 and 88 FIB levels
if the price retraces 100 of the last
price wave that may mean the trend has
failed
[Music]
when you see the price coming into a
Fibonacci support area the biggest sign
you can look for is the volume to see if
that support will hold
in this example notice how the market
had a number of spikes higher in volume
on the move up
but the pullback to support at the
retracement saw volume decreasing
this doesn't mean people are not
interested in the market it means that
there are fewer sellers pushing the
price lower this is where buyers come in
and accumulate in anticipation for the
rally higher
high volume after the rejection of a
Fibonacci level represents a very good
signal
financial markets have price movements
that repeat over and over again these
movements are called waves when you are
analyzing a market you need to answer
four key questions what direction the
price is trending how far is the trend
likely to go where can you enter a trade
with the best risk reward ratio and most
importantly at what point you are
definitely wrong Elliott wave theory
answers all these questions Elliott
weight theory is a comprehensive and
complex topic but despite its complexity
there are some elements of Elliott wave
that can be incorporated and may help
you analyze a market so I'll try to keep
this very simple and I will break down
the wave theory into small bases
Ralph Elliott a Trader who developed the
theory said that Trends in financial
markets resulted from participants
predominant psychology he found that
swings in Mass psychology always showed
up in the same recurring fractal
patterns or waves Elliot discovered that
price patterns were structured in the
same way so prices moved in impulsive
and corrective waves knowing which wave
is underway in what recent waves were
will help you to forecast what the price
is likely to do next
impulse waves are the ones that best
represent the direction of the current
Trend during an uptrend for example the
impulsive moves are those that push
prices higher this impulse movements are
often made up of large Candlestick
bodies and are typically quite
aggressive especially compared to
corrective moves
remember an uptrend keeps reaching
higher prices because the moves up are
larger than the moves down which occur
between those large up waves
on the opposite end of the spectrum we
have corrective moves or waves that work
against the prevailing trend
these counter Trend moves represent the
period of consolidation and are
typically weaker and less aggressive
than the impulse waves
the corrective move during an uptrend is
characterized by a move lower or even
sideways unlike impulse movements
Corrections are formed by a mixture of
bullish and bearish candlesticks where
the bodies are relatively small
Elliot found that when an uptrend is
underway it typically has three large
upward price moves and two Corrections
this creates a five wave pattern impulse
correction impulse correction and
another impulse
the uptrend is Then followed by three
waves lower
an Impulse down a correction to the
upside
then another impulse down these waves
are labeled a b and c
Elliot also found that these movements
are fractal meaning the pattern occurs
on both small and large time frames
[Music]
there are three rules that all Elliott
wave Traders agree on
the end of The Wave 2 cannot go past the
start of wave 1.
Wave 3 cannot be the shortest impulse
wave that means Wave 1 or wave 5 or both
must be shorter than wave 3.
and wave 4 cannot go into the price
territory of wave 2. this means Wave 2
and 4 must have some clear separation of
price
are ever stuck on where to place your
Elliott wave points always remember to
follow those three rules
so why are Elliott waves important well
knowing their location and knowing in
which wave you are potentially in they
can help you to better time the market I
advise you to trade in the direction of
the impulse waves because the price is
making the largest moves in that
direction you can use the end of the
corrective waves to enter into a trend
trade in an attempt to capture the next
bigger impulse wave
the ideal way to trade is to buy during
pullbacks or at the end of a corrective
wave during uptrends and ride the next
impulse wave as it takes the price
higher
also you sell at the end of a collective
wave in a downtrend to profit from the
next impulse wave down
[Music]
if volume represents commitment then
gaps represent excitement
a gap occurs when the price leaps higher
or
look from the previous price leaving an
empty space or gap between two prices
if you trade stocks or indices you'll
often see blank spaces which represent
times when no transactions took place
within a particular price range normally
this occurs between the close of the
market on one day and the next day is
open this space between two consecutive
days price ranges has various degrees of
significance
generally gaps below the market tend to
act as a support area
and gaps above the market suggest
resistance and an area where there will
be selling interest
there are two primary kinds of gaps up
gaps and down gaps for an up Gap to form
the low price after the market close
must be higher than the high price of
the previous day
a down Gap is just the opposite of an up
Gap the high price after the market
close must be lower than the low price
of the previous day
and these gaps happen because of an
imbalance between supply and demand
gaps are very important in my technical
analysis plan because they offer
evidence that something important has
happened to the fundamentals or the
psychology of the crowd
gaps can be classified into four groups
common gaps Breakaway gaps exhaustion
gaps and continuation gaps
[Music]
common gaps simply show a gap in price
action independent of price patterns and
usually don't provide exciting trading
opportunities these occasional gaps are
the result of normal Market forces these
gaps are usually filled fairly quickly
getting filled means that the price
action at a later time usually retraces
at the last day before the gap
this is also known as closing the gap
a common cap usually appears in a
trading range or a congestion area where
it reinforces the apparent lack of
interest in the Market at that time
this is often further intensified by low
trading volume
because common gaps are relatively small
normal and somewhat regular events in
the price action they tend to provide no
real analytical insight
Breakaway gaps occur when the price
action is breaking out of a trading
range or a congestion area
a congestion area is a price range in
which the market has traded for some
period of time usually a few days
in order to break out of these areas we
need some Market enthusiasm and many
more buyers than sellers for upside
breakouts or many more sellers than
buyers for downside breakouts
volume will and should increase
significantly not only from The
increased enthusiasm but because many
Traders are holding positions on the
wrong side of the breakouts and need to
cover or sell them
it is better if the increase in volume
doesn't happen until the Gap occurs this
means that the new change in Market
Direction has a chance of continuing
the point of the breakout now becomes
the new support if an upside breakout or
a resistance in the case of a downside
Breakout
usually this type of Gap if it happens
with good volume it won't be filled so
soon
feeling a breakout Gap might take a
longer time
it's better to go with the fact that a
new trend has taken place and trade in
that direction not against it
runaway gaps are best described as gaps
caused by increased interest in a market
runaway gaps to the upside typically
represent traders who didn't get in
during the initial move of an uptrend
and while waiting for a retracement in
price decided it was not going to happen
increased buying interest happens all of
the sudden and the price gaps above the
previous candle also a strong uptrend
can have runaway gaps caused by
significant news events that cause new
interest in the market
in this example pay attention to the
significant increase in volume during
and after the runaway Gap
runaway gaps can also happen in
downtrends this usually represents
increased sell-offs this type of Gap
occurs during strong Bull and Bear moves
and is characterized by a significant
price change in the direction of the
prevailing trend
during a trend price may experience
several runaway gaps which can help to
reinforce the transdirection
and it's not uncommon for runaway gaps
to occur after a market has experienced
a breakaway Gap
exhaustion gaps are those that happen
near the end of a strong up or downtrend
they are often the First Signal of the
end of that move
they are identified by high volume and a
large price difference between the
previous days close and the new opening
price
that they can easily be mistaken for
runaway gaps if you don't notice the
exceptionally high volume
an exhaustion Gap is a technical signal
marked by a break lower in prices that
occurs after a rapid rise in price
this signal reflects a significant shift
from buying to selling activity that
usually coincides with falling demand
for that market
the implication of the signal is that an
upward Trend may be about to end soon
in the case of an exhaustion Gap prices
Gap up with huge volume then there is a
major profit taking and the demand for
the market totally dries up
then prices drop in a significant change
in Trend occurs
exhaustion gaps are probably the easiest
to trade and profit from also don't
expect an immediate reversal in some
cases there will be several more days of
trading to the upside before the market
decrease
technical analysis makes extensive use
of various mathematical models or
studies to show various aspects of price
activity these models are generally
called technical indicators the goals in
using indicators are the same as for
better recognition to better identify
current and emerging Trends and the
points subject to trend reversals
when it comes to indicators we can
divide them into four classes Trend
following indicators momentum indicators
volume indicators and volatility
indicators
Trend indicators are designed to measure
the strength and direction of a trend
if a market is in a strong uptrend a
trend indicator should give you a Buy
Signal and if the market is in a strong
downtrend Trend indicators give you sell
signals
but here's the main problem indicators
are based on best price data so most
Trend indicators lack the price and give
trading signals after a trend has
already been established this means you
will likely miss the initial move of a
new trend until a trend indicator sends
a trade signal
most common Trend indicators are view up
and moving averages
these are the only two indicators in
this category you should learn
another popular group of technical
indicators are momentum indicators also
called oscillators
unlike Trend indicators oscillators
measure the relative strength of recent
price moves and plot a value between 0
and 100. if prices are rising strongly
an oscillator follows and reaches over
both levels
similarly if prices are falling an
oscillator is designed to reach oversold
levels oscillators work well in ranging
markets but leads to many phone signals
when markets are trending
popular oscillators are the relative
strength index the RSI the stochastic
indicator and the macd
volume indicators measure the strength
of a price move by using the information
of trading volume
while volume indicators are very popular
among stock Traders Forex Traders can
take much advantage of them since there
are no reliable measures of trading
volume in the currency Market
most popular indicators are the on
balance volume the obv the accumulation
and distribution line and the money flow
index
volatility indicators measure the rate
of price changes regardless of their
Direction
these indicators rise when markets are
fast and full when markets are slow
popular volatility indicators include
Bollinger Bands and the average true
range
so how do you combine trading indicators
while these four types of indicators are
trying to determine the same thing
whether prices are about to increase
decrease or remain stable the angle they
each offer is unique and looking at the
market for multiple different angles can
help you develop a more accurate
realistic and actionable perspective
knowing which one belongs to which
category and how to combine the best
indicators in a meaningful way can help
you analyze a market much better what
you need to realize is that while these
technical indicators are useful they
each have their own set of weaknesses
and combining indicators in a wrong way
can lead to a lot of confusion and the
wrong price analysis
the biggest problem with Traders is the
fact they use different indicators which
belong to the same indicator class and
show the same information on their
charts
if you take a look at this example I've
added three momentum indicators macd RSI
and stochastic essentially all three
indicators provide the same information
because they examine momentum in price
Behavior
you can see that all indicators rise and
fall at the same time
turn together and are also flat during
no momentum periods
so if you trade with the multi indicator
strategy that uses the RSI the macd and
the stochastic you are basically using
three types of indicators that belong in
the same class
these are all momentum indicators that
are going to display the same kind of
information in one way or the other
common mistake is using only Trend
indicators this example shows a chart
with three Trend indicators view up one
moving average and the keldner channels
again the goal of these indicators is
the same identifying Trend Direction
you can see that during a trend all
indicators are practically indicating
the same thing
at the same time during ranges they all
offer bad signals
I hope you see the problem with adding
multiple indicators showing the same
information
you will end up giving too much weight
to the information provided by these
indicators
and easily Miss other crucial things
your Mighty was two or more Trend
indicators and you might believe that
the trend is stronger than it actually
is because both of the indicators will
give you the green light and you might
miss other important Clues on your
charts
the problem with using unfitting
technical indicators is that you might
actually think that trade signals are
stronger if all indicators point in the
same direction and this is completely
wrong
the solution is simple avoid using
technical indicators that display the
same kind of information
the best strategy with multiple
indicators combine tools that show a
different type of information
and here's another common mistake using
way too many indicators
you add 5 or 6 indicators because it
looks cool on your chart
some indicators say bye While others
will say sell and by the time they all
agree price already moved a lot and it's
too late to enter I suffered from the
same problem when I started but you
don't need to clutter your charts less
is more
so limit your use of indicators to two
or three at most and don't try to filter
out your losing trades with the use of
indicators
you'll end up filtering out the good
rates as well let indicators confirm
your trade bias and don't follow them
blindly
[Music]
in your technical analysis it's better
to use a top-down approach in a top-down
analysis you start from the larger time
frames then Focus down into the shorter
ones
for example when you are looking for
trade setups you will be looking at a
large scale chart perhaps the daily or
the weekly chart
this will give you a very zoomed out
view on the market which really gives
you the scale to analyze everything in a
very macro sense
you can see certain key support and
resistance zones or long-term trends
remember relevance on higher time frames
means longevity on shorter ones
once you have found your ideal setup you
must then zoom in to shorter time frames
and analyze everything to make sure it
is congruent with your initial Theory
there are many benefits of a top-down
analysis
by always considering the big picture
first there is less noise and a more
calm approach than with lower time
frames
it's easier to see the key support and
resistance levels and easier to see the
major trends
please remember that the levels you find
on higher time frames are usually far
more important therefore it is key to
take this into account when setting up
your trades
technical analysis is complex and has
many nuances if you are striving for
perfection in trading you're going to
have a hard time
consider trend lines and support and
resistance you shouldn't expect the
price to turn right at the exact point
on a chart and base your trading
decisions on that exact line
this perfect right to the P patterns are
seen only in trading manuals
in real time price movements can be
quite messy if the price dips below a
support line it doesn't necessarily mean
that the support has been broken
remember in a market there are buyers
and sellers there is stop hunting
liquidity short squeezes momentum spikes
and shock events
[Music]
foreign
a huge argument underway between
technicians who think price action is
the best way of analyzing the markets
and the traders who think using
technical indicators is the best way to
trade price action Traders say price
action is better because it doesn't lag
behind the market action
Traders relying on indicators state that
their method is simpler because it's a
more objective trading style so which
one is better in technical analysis
first you already know that most
indicators are lagging an indicator
takes past price action and then
visualizes the result after applying a
formula to it
thus what your indicator shows you is a
result of past price action
same time price action signals can also
lag or better set can offer late signals
trading price action is not as easy as
it sounds and lots of components often
get overlooked we talked about this the
size of candlesticks and the price wings
how they compare to previous price
action the component of momentum and
volatility in weeks and bodies don't
make the mistake of trading price action
because it looks simple a Trader who
doesn't understand the nuances of price
action can easily recharge in a wrong
way
the same is true when trading with
indicators if you apply four or five
indicators and five moving averages on a
chart you can quickly clutter up your
screen
remember that trading indicators are
derived from the past price action so
they don't show you information based
off what's happening right now they show
you information based off what's
happened in the past the reality is that
traders who make their decisions using
only indicators will always be late in
reacting to changes in a market
but indicators are still useful because
they provide reference points on plane
charts they take out the guesswork by
providing information that is objective
my advice focus on price action and find
your confirmation with the help of
indicators if you are not sure your
analysis is 100 correct
but you first need to listen to what the
price is telling you who is in control
right now are buyers or sellers pushing
price up stronger how do Trend waves
relate to each other is momentum gaining
or losing strength how is price reacting
around previous highs and lows and how
does price react at key levels
those are all important signs that will
help you understand the buyer and the
seller dynamic
if you are still here and you watch the
full video I want to congratulate you it
means you're really serious about
trading and you're making a real effort
to learn and develop as a Trader if you
got any value and learn something new
show your support by leaving us alike it
goes a long way
in the next video we'll go deeper and
we'll dive into the world of smart money
trading so make sure you watch it
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time