In my first years of trading, I used to change
strategies almost every day.
I didn’t have a trading plan.
If I saw a signal, I took it.
Until I realized that when it comes to technical
trading, my job was to seek out only the high
probability entries.
Today I’ll show you an effective strategy
to increase the odds on your trades, using
VWAP and the simplest price pattern you could
find, the V top and V bottom formation.
You know the drill, like, subscribe and stick
around for the full video.
V-bottom
The V-bottom appears when price momentum switches
from aggressive selling to aggressive buying.
This is a powerful bullish reversal pattern.
Because of the nature of the aggressive buying
that takes place when a market reverses direction,
it can be intimidating to enter, after the
market increased already quite a bit.
This market shows a picture-perfect V-bottom
at the end of a bearish trend.
Price traded lower into a bottom and immediately
reversed higher with a massive increase in
momentum.
Let’s be clear: it is nearly impossible
to predict V-bottoms, we won’t try to anticipate
this swing low.
We’ll wait for price to break the neckline
of the pattern, meaning the previous swing
high before the bottom.
This is basically an interruption in the previous
downtrend.
And then we plan to enter a long position
once price retests the neckline.
But with several conformations, we’ll talk
about them in a few moments.
V-top
The V-top pattern appears when price momentum
switches from aggressive buying to aggressive
selling.
This is a bearish reversal pattern.
In a V-top, price traded higher and reversed
lower with a massive increase in momentum.
There are many ways to trade the V-top, but
the most conservative way would be to wait
for a break and close below the neckline and
to attempt a short once price pulls back to
the neckline and gets rejected.
AVWAP
Trading V tops and bottoms can be difficult
because you’ll recognize the pattern once
price breaks above or below the neckline.
And another problem is the fact you’ll see
this setup many times throughout the day.
I filter these signals using VWAP, because
on the VWAP line you won’t see changes in
length or timeframe — unlike moving averages.
Well, VWAP eliminates the confusion regarding
time frames and settings.
It doesn’t matter if you use a 1-minute
chart or an hourly chart.
There is only one VWAP line.
Flipping between time frames won’t affect
VWAPs position.
VWAP acts like a magnet, either attracting
or repelling.
For this strategy, we’ll use Anchored VWAP.
Anchored VWAP will tell you the price at which
most traders are commonly positioned.
We’ll apply it on the lowest low of a V-bottom
formation, and on the highest high of a V-top
formation.
By anchoring VWAP to these exact price locations,
you’ll find dynamic resistance and support
level.
For a long signal:
1.
Market forms a V-bottom formation
2.
The V-bottom should be at a new low point
in the market.
Meaning you can’t trade the formation if
there are recent lows below it.
3.
After you identified the V-bottom, you anchor
the VWAP on the recent lowest low
4.
If the neckline, the static support, aligns
with the Anchored Vwap, acting a dynamic support,
you buy at the re-test of the neckline
For a short signal:
1.
Market forms a V-top formation
2.
The V-top should be at a new high point in
the market.
So you can’t trade the formation if there
are recent highs above it.
3.
After you found the V-top, you anchor the
VWAP on the recent highest high
4.
If the re-test of the neckline, the static
resistance, aligns with the Anchored Vwap,
as dynamic resistance, you look to sell the
re-test of the neckline
We are trading Crude Oil on the 4-hour time
frame.
Price dropped into this low but reversed,
with momentum increasing on the way higher.
Observe that this is valid V bottom because
price made a new recent low.
When you start seeing an increase in buying
pressure, observing the price action by using
different time-frames can be very helpful.
So let’s move to the M30 time frame.
The neckline of the pattern is evident now.
The conservative way to trade would be to
wait for a break and close above the neckline
and to attempt a long position once price
pulls back to the neckline and gets rejected.
We have the breakout above the neckline, so
let’s add the Anchored VWAP, at the lowest
low of the formation.
Now we just wait for a rejection of the Anchored
VWAP and neckline.
Stop loss goes below VWAP.
And my target is the next swing high in the
price structure.
The minimum risk to reward ratio should be
at least 2.
Another target can be set above the neckline,
equal to the distance measured from the low
of the pattern to the neckline high.
We trade Apple on the H1 time frame.
I spot a potential V-bottom here.
Price made a new low and momentum switched
to the upside.
Let’s move to a lower time frame, to time
our entry.
Here’s the neckline.
We’ll wait for price to break this level
and then enter a long position once price
retests this area.
But before that, we anchor the VWAP to find
the confluence zone.
Here’s the signal.
I see a rejection of the breakout area, and
at the same time, a rejection of the VWAP.
Stop loss below the VWAP line.
And we target this swing high in price structure.
A risk to reward ratio of around 4.
Now that price consolidated above this swing
high, we remove the risk from our trade, by
moving our stop to breakeven.
Let’s trade a V top formation.
Pound dollar.
H4 time frame.
Price traded higher and reversed with an obvious
increase in momentum.
Like I said before, it is nearly impossible
to predict V-tops, and will wait for price
to break the neckline of the pattern.
Now let’s anchor the VWAP, to find our dynamic
resistance area.
Here is the signal.
We have a pin bar, rejecting the VWAP, at
the re-test of the breakout.
3 factors indicating a possible down move.
Stop loss above the VWAP and above the high
of the pin bar.
Our target is this major swing low.
If price breaks this minor swing low, I’ll
move my stop to breakeven.
Ok, now we are in risk free trade.
The main problem will be the fact that you’ll
probably see many signals.
Even with the breakout area and VWAP confluence,
you will have problems identifying the best
signals to trade, especially if you are in
your first years of trading.
So my advice is to add another filter, just
to make sure your setup is indeed worth trading.
My additional filter is the central pivot
point.
I want the pivot to offer an additional layer
of confluence.
In this example, we see a steep decline followed
by a rally to reach the top of the pattern.
The neckline would be here, the first area
of static support.
After the breakout, we add the VWAP line,
this time dynamic support.
We add the daily central pivot point.
The third area of support.
I also see this downward trendline.
Which was also broken.
This is our 4th level of support.
Let’s move to M30 time frame to pinpoint
the entry.
Here’s our signal.
A pin bar rejecting the previous levels.
This is our 5th indication that the market
wants to go higher.
Stop loss placement, below VWAP and below
the central pivot point.
And we target this swing high, a risk to reward
ratio of 3.
As price broke this swing, we remove the risk
from the trade, we move our stop loss to our
entry point.
We are looking at Exxon Mobil on M30 time
frame.
Price was in an uptrend, made a last push
higher, above the previous swing high, but
immediately reversed lower.
This looks like a liquidity clear-out, with
many orders above this area.
After price closed below the neckline, we
need to wait for a pullback to the initial
breakout zone.
That’s the first resistance level.
We add the Anchored VWAP, from the highest
high of the V top formation.
That’s our dynamic resistance, the second
component.
We add the daily central pivot, which aligns
with our previous resistance levels.
That’s the third layer.
I also see this major trend line, broken to
the downside.
Now could potentially act as resistance.
4 different elements which indicate a further
price decrease.
This candlestick, with a long wick, rejecting
our area of interest, is the signal to short
the market.
I like to see either a pin bar, or a candlestick
with an evident wick, or an engulfing bar,
forming at the VWAP – pivot point area.
Stop loss is placed above the VWAP line and
above the pivot level.
And we’ll take our profit at the next major
swing low in the price structure, which represents
a risk to reward ratio of 6.
As we broke this swing low, now it’s the
perfect time to move the stop to breakeven.
Again.
Price makes a last push higher, above the
previous swing high, and reversed lower.
Another possible liquidity clear-out.
Price closed below the neckline, which is
the first resistance level.
We anchor the VWAP, from this high.
That’s our second resistance.
We add the daily central pivot, which is resistance
number 3.
We also see a pin bar candlestick, with a
long wick, rejecting the value area, and this
is the signal to sell.
Stop loss above the VWAP line.
Take profit, as usual, either at a major swing
in the price structure, or you set a fixed
risk to reward ratio.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.