If you are a scalper, then you DEFINITELY
must try out this scalping strategy! No
indicators, no lag, just pure price action!
So… we’ll look for signals on the 1-minute
timeframe, using only price action and some basic
smart money concepts, like liquidity, supply
and demand zones, and breaks of structure.
The first setup focuses on a specific pattern:
an institutional candle followed by at least
8 inside bars, ideally 10 small candles,
forming a tight channel.
The trade is triggered when
the price breaks out of this channel range.
The institutional bar is the setup candle,
a larger price bar that sets the initial range.
Inside bars are the following smaller bars,
that form within the high and
low of the institutional bar.
When you see 8 or more inside bars,
it shows the market is consolidating.
I use this indicator to find inside bars.
Now, this setup creates a channel on your chart.
The top of the channel is the institutional
bar's high, and the bottom is its low.
The inside bars stay within this range,
making the market look calm for a bit.
The key is to wait for a
breakout from this channel.
This shows increasing momentum, that
could lead to a decent scalping move.
For a buy trade, you'd enter when the
price breaks above the channel's top.
For a sell trade, you'd enter
when it breaks below the bottom.
The scalping plan here is that
after this tight consolidation,
the market is ready to make a bigger move.
Now, this scalping approach only works in
combination with support and resistance
levels, or supply and demand levels.
These areas help you find
good spots to enter trades.
When the price breaks out of
the channel, near a key support
or demand level, it's a stronger signal.
This means you have two reasons to take the
trade - the breakout and the level itself.
And when trading this setup, you also
pay attention to the overall market context.
Is the market in a broader uptrend, or downtrend?
This can help you decide which breakout
direction is more likely to succeed.
For exits, you can use minor levels.
You look for small areas where the
price has paused, or reversed before.
These can be good spots to take profits.
This scalping setup is a classic example
of trend continuation, showing how markets
move in cycles of contraction and expansion.
Big market players use these cycles to build
positions, and profit from market moves.
The ideal signal looks like this: a strong
upward move, followed by a period of contraction
(the institutional candle and the inside bars),
ideally at a demand level, then a
breakout continuing the upward trend.
This is how smart money operates in the market.
The initial upward move (the institutional
candle) is driven by big players.
They buy steadily, pushing the price up.
But they can't buy forever without
causing the price to spike too quickly.
So they pause, creating the
contraction phase we see on the chart.
During this contraction, the institutional
candle sets the range, and the following
inside bars show decreasing volatility.
This is not random. Smart money is using
this time to continue building their
position, without alerting other traders.
The longer the contraction lasts,
the more tension builds up.
This tension is what fuels the eventual breakout.
That’s why I want at least 8 inside bars,
preferably over 10.
The contraction phase also
serves another purpose for smart money: it creates
a zone where other traders place their orders.
Breakout traders put buy orders above the range,
thinking they'll catch the move when it starts.
Short-term traders might place
sell orders, betting on a reversal.
Smart money sees all these orders
as potential fuel for the next move.
When they're ready, they push the
price up, triggering these orders.
The breakout traders' buy orders
add to the upward momentum.
The short sellers' stop losses get hit, forcing
them to buy, and pushing the price even higher.
This is the expansion phase. This is
when we enter! The built-up tension
is released, and the price moves quickly.
Ideally, the candles after the breakout are
larger, showing increased volatility.
This is the market expanding
after the contraction.
For us, scalpers, this pattern
offers several potential entry points.
You could buy the breakout when price
closes above the institutional bar's high.
Or you could wait for a slight pullback
after the breakout, which often happens
as some traders take quick profits.
The stop loss for this trade could go
below the low of the contraction phase.
If price falls below this level,
it might mean the move has failed.
As for targets, look at the size
of the move before the contraction.
Breakouts often move about the same
distance as the prior trend wave.
So to find a “sell” scalping signal on the
1 minute chart, you look for these elements:
First, identify a strong downtrend on the chart.
You want to see a series of lower highs and lower
lows, confirming the bearish sentiment.
Next, find the institutional candle,
followed by 8 or more inside bars,
creating a tight trading range.
This consolidation is basically a pause
in the downtrend, where buyers and
sellers are temporarily in balance.
Pay close attention to how price
behaves at the bottom of this range.
If it struggles to make new lows, or
repeatedly tests and fails at the lower boundary,
this could be a sign of temporary strength.
But remember, we're looking for a
continuation of the downtrend, not a reversal.
A short signal would trigger if price breaks
down, below the low of the institutional candle.
This breakdown should come with
increased volume and larger red candles.
For confirmation, you can
wait for a small pullback.
You're essentially looking for a weak attempt at
an upward move, that fails to gain traction.
This chart shows a classic buy signal in an
uptrend, with price reacting at a demand zone.
First, we see a clear uptrend, marked
by higher highs and higher lows.
The uptrend sets the stage for our
buy signal, as it's often best to
trade in the direction of the main trend.
The support zone, which can also be found
on a higher time frame, is very important here.
It was a previous resistance level, that price
broke through earlier in the uptrend.
Once price breaks above resistance,
that level often becomes new support.
Notice how price reacts at the support level.
We have our institutional candle,
followed by consecutive inside bars,
showing a contraction in volatility.
The buy signal comes when we see a bullish
candle forming above this contraction.
Considering all these factor, it means
buyers stepping in strongly at support,
during an overall uptrend. Buyers took control
and preventing prices from falling lower.
A buy scalping signal must be
strengthened by several factors:
First, it must be in line
with the overall uptrend.
It should appear at a clear
support level or demand area.
And the institutional candle must
have many consecutive inside bars.
This scalping approach aligns with the principle
that it's usually best to trade with the trend.
In an uptrend, we look for opportunities
to buy on pullbacks or corrections.
And a demand area provides exactly
that kind of opportunity.
Now, not all breakouts are real.
Sometimes, the price might make
a false move outside the channel,
and then quickly come back in.
This is called a false breakout,
and often happens with a pin bar, a
candle with a "wick" outside the channel.
This is the second variation
of this scalping approach.
When a pin bar happens, it's actually a good
chance to trade in the opposite direction.
So this chart shows a false
breakout to the downside.
The price made a quick move below the
channel, but then came right back in.
This is a signal to buy when the
price retraces inside the channel.
You see, false breakouts are often
liquidity sweeps in disguise.
Big players use false breakouts to
trap traders and create liquidity.
The institutional bar, followed by
the inside bars, create a tight range.
This range acts like a magnet for orders.
Traders place buy orders above, and sell orders
below, thinking they'll catch the breakout.
But smart money sees these
orders as liquidity pools.
When price breaks out of the range,
often times against the prevailing trend,
it's often not a real move. It's a trick.
Big players push the price just
far enough to trigger these orders.
They're not trying to start a new
trend. They're hunting for liquidity.
In this particular case, we
see an upward false breakout.
The price moves above the
range, but it doesn't stay
there. This quick move up is the liquidity sweep.
Observe the institutional candle, the inside bars,
and then the pin bar, completing the pattern.
This inducement is designed to do 2 things:
First, it triggers buy orders from
breakout traders. They see the price
rise and think a big move up is starting.
Second, it hits the stop losses of traders
who sold near the top of the range.
They thought price would go down,
but now their stops are getting hit.
All these actions create a pool of liquidity.
And that's exactly what smart money wants.
They use this liquidity to enter short
positions at good prices.
The key is waiting to see what
happens next. Price doesn't keep rising.
Instead, it snaps back into the range.
This is the "immediate retrace"
we see on the chart. It's a clear
sign that the breakout was false.
This retrace is smart money selling.
They're using all that liquidity from
the sweep to enter their positions.
Now they have the fuel they
need to push price lower.
For us, scalpers, this false
breakout is a selling opportunity.
When we see price retrace back into the channel,
after that quick rise, it's our signal to sell.
We're essentially trading with smart
money, taking advantage of all those
traders who got tricked by the false breakout.
But why does this work? It's all about order flow!
Markets need a balance of
buyers and sellers to move.
If everyone's buying, who are they buying from?
If everyone's selling, who are they selling to?
Smart money uses these sweeps
to create that balance.
Think of it like this: If smart
money wants to buy a lot of orders,
they need someone to sell to them.
But if the market looks bullish,
not many people want to sell.
So they create a scenario that
encourages selling. That's our false breakout.
Once they have these sellers, they can buy.
This concept of liquidity is crucial
in understanding market moves.
Price doesn't just move up or
down randomly. It moves to where
there are orders. These orders are liquidity.
And smart money is always looking for liquidity.
In this scalping strategy,
we're not just looking at price.
We're looking at the story behind the price.
We're trying to spot these liquidity sweeps.
When we see a tight range form, we get ready. We
know smart money might try to sweep that range.
And remember our first approach, not
every breakout is false. Sometimes,
price really does start a new trend.
That's why we wait for the retrace.
We need confirmation that the breakout
was indeed a sweep, not a real move.
This chart shows a buy signal in an uptrend,
with price reacting at a key support level.
We see a clear uptrend, marked
by higher highs and higher lows.
The uptrend sets the stage for
our buy signal, as we aim to
trade in the direction of the order flow.
The support level is crucial here. It was
a previous resistance level, that price
broke through earlier in the uptrend.
Then we see price pull back to
test this new support level.
Notice how price reacts at the level.
We see an institutional candle,
and a series of small bars
forming just above support.
These are inside bars, showing
a contraction in volatility.
The buy signal comes when we see a wick outside
the channel, followed by an immediate retrace.
This is a classic sign of a liquidity sweep.
Price briefly drops below the support level,
triggering stop losses of weak longs.
Smart money quickly buys up these
orders, at a discount.
And price immediately
retraces back into the trading range.
This price action suggests strong
buying pressure at support.
It's a sign that big players
are possibly accumulating positions,
setting up for the next move higher.
The next bar is our entry signal. This bar
closes firmly inside the trading range,
confirming that the drop below support
was just a trap for weak hands.
Any buy signal after an institutional candle and a
pin bar, must be strengthened by several factors:
First, it must in line with
the overall order flow.
Then it must be at a clear support level, with
several touches, or at an unmitigated demand area.
And the quick rejection of lower prices
must confirm the buying pressure.
Let's look at another case, a short signal.
First, we see a clear downtrend, marked by
lower highs and lower lows.
So this downtrend sets
the stage for our short signal.
And here notice this supply zone. Which
is unmitigated, has not been touched before.
We see price rally up to test this area. This
rally is normal and healthy in a downtrend.
Notice how price reacts at the supply zone.
We have an institutional candle,
then a series of small bars.
The short signal comes when we see a wick
outside the channel, and an immediate retrace.
This is the liquidity sweep we need. Price
briefly spikes above the resistance level,
triggering stop losses of weak shorts.
Smart money quickly sells into this rally,
trapping late buyers.
And price immediately
retraces back into the trading range.
This price action suggests strong selling
pressure at a supply zone.
It's a sign that big players
are setting up for the next move lower.
As the next candle closes firmly inside the
trading range, it confirms that the spike above
the channel was just a trap for weak hands.
Another signal. This short signal is valid,
because it’s strengthened by multiple factors:
It's in line with the overall downtrend,
It's at a clear resistance level
with multiple touches,
And the quick rejection
of higher prices shows strong selling pressure.
For the entry, you could short as the "liquidity
sweep" bar closes. The stop loss could go
just above the wick of the previous bar.
Now, what if you don’t have an
institutional candle to trade?
Well, another variation of this
scalping method is when you first
spot a pin bar, and then an inside bar.
So first you have a pin bar, with a long
tail and a small body, rejecting a level.
For a real pin bar, the tail must be at
least 50% of the bar's total range.
The longer the tail (or the wick),
the stronger the pin bar signal.
Candles with long wicks are great for
scalping, because they help you
spot possible market reversals.
When pin bars form, it often means
the market might move in the opposite
direction, at least for a short while.
The opportunity comes when the next
candle's range, fits inside the pin bar’s range.
So the high and low of the second candle are
completely within the first candle's range.
This is the pin bar – inside bar combo.
So you look for a candle with a long wick,
at a key support or resistance level,
You wait for an inside bar to
form right after the pin bar,
And you enter the trade when the
price breaks out of the inside bar,
in the direction of the pin bar.
Here’s a bullish setup:
The pin bar forms at a demand zone (or support).
This long lower wick shows strong buying pressure.
It's like buyers rushing in to grab a
good deal when the price dips too low.
The inside bar that follows is a pause.
Buyers and sellers are sizing each other up,
waiting to see who'll make the next move.
When price breaks above the pin bar’s high,
it implies demand has won out.
Buyers are pushing the price up,
and some sellers might be closing their
losing trades, adding more upward pressure.
For a bearish setup:
The pin bar forms at a
supply zone (or resistance level). That long
upper wick shows strong selling pressure.
Sellers stepped in when the price got too high.
Again, the inside bar is a small pause. The
market is stalling, after
that reaction at resistance.
A break below the pin bar shows
supply has taken control.
Remember, the location of the pin bar is crucial.
It should be at a level where the market
has turned before, or at an
unmitigated supply or demand.
And the inside bar adds more
strength to the pin bar signal.
It shows that the market is confirming the
potential reversal that the pin bar hinted at.
For a bullish setup:
You enter a buy order,
just above the high of the pin bar.
You place your stop loss, just below
the low of the pin bar.
And you set your target
at the next resistance level.
The same for a bearish setup:
Enter a sell order just
below the low of the pin bar.
You place your stop loss, just
above the high of the pin bar.
And you take profit at the next support level.
Now, here are some extra tips to make this
scalping setup even better:
First one is order flow alignment:
This one is obvious, you try to trade
in the direction of the bigger trend.
So check higher time frames, to confirm
the overall trend and key levels.
You also look for other price action signals
that support your trade. This could be
a trend line break, a chart pattern,
or confluence with a Fibonacci level.
And of course, volume: High volume on the
pin bar, compared to the previous candles,
will make the signal stronger.
In this specific instance, we see
an uptrend. The price moves up in a series
of higher highs and higher lows. So, buyers
are in control. We look for long trades only.
Then, the price hits a support level. A key area
where buyers have stepped in before.
At this level, we get a pin bar.
The long lower wick tail shows that sellers
tried to push the price down, but buyers had
more power. This quick reversal traps sellers
who thought the price would keep falling.
Then we see the inside bar. It fits
entirely inside the range of the pin bar.
To trade this, you'd buy when the price
breaks above the high of the pin bar.
This break shows that buyers
are taking control again.
Your stop loss would go
below the low of the pin bar.
This is the "danger point". If price
falls below here, the setup has failed.
As for target, look for the next
resistance or supply zones above.
Just remember that this
setup works best in trends.
And watch how price acts after the
breakout. A momentum move up, right away
after the breakout, is what you want to see.
If it hangs around near the breakout point,
be cautious. It might not have
the momentum we hoped for.
Here’s a short signal.
First, we'd see a downtrend. The price
moves in a series of lower highs and lower lows.
The price would then hit a resistance level.
Sellers have stepped in before, so
it might be a good area to monitor.
At this resistance, we'd get a pin
bar. This time, with long upper wick.
This quick reversal traps buyers who
thought the price would keep rising.
Right after the pin bar, we'd see the inside bar.
This combo of pin bar at resistance followed by
an inside bar is a strong sell signal.
So, we sell when the price breaks below
the low of the pin bar.
This scalping method gives
you a structured way to trade.
It combines the power of pin bars
to show potential reversals, with
the confirmation of inside bars.
And the breakout entry helps
you avoid many false signals.
By waiting for both patterns, you're being
patient and selective, which is mandatory
when scalping. You're waiting for the market
to show its hand before you commit your money.
Now, if you want to learn other scalping
methods, go ahead and watch one of these videos.