Hello guys, in the following minutes I want
to discuss the basics of the position trading,
the advantages of adopting this trading style
and we will also see 3 position trading strategies
you could implement right away.
Position trading is a trading technique which
looks at the bigger picture of the market,
usually involving a combination of technical
analysis and fundamental analysis.
When evaluating the markets, position traders
usually make their research on weekly and
monthly price charts.
I’m sure you already know that 95% of all
traders lose money and only 5% of them make
any real money.
This is due to the fact that the majority
of traders enter the markets with a “get
rich quick” mentality.
Short-term trading can be profitable, but
on the long run you’ll be safer when adopting
a position trading attitude.
When executed correctly, position trading
comes with several advantages:
The most important advantage of the position
trading eliminates market noise
Sometimes when trading on shorter time frames
you get caught up in the market price fluctuations,
rumors or the constant monitoring of the market.
That’s market noise.
Position trading on higher time frames will
help you to remove the market noise and to
extract the correct information from the price.
Another advantage is the flexibility
While day traders monitor the price action
very closely and their “screen time” is
considerably higher, position traders don’t
have to deal with such problems.
Position trading offers time away from charts.
Also, position traders execute fewer trades
and they don’t have to monitor the trades
all the time.
Another advantage of the position trading
is that you don’t over trade
Position trading keeps you away from the daily
“temptations” of entering and exiting
the market many times thought the day.
Position traders do not trade actively and
execute fewer trades.
Also, position traders don’t have to deal
with the daily stress arising from trading,
that’s because their positions have plenty
of room to survive the market volatility.
Another important advantage of position trading
is the fact that signals are more relevant
on higher time frames
Position traders often use the daily, weekly
and monthly charts.
They are not interested in analyzing lower
time frames.
This adds weight to their trading systems.
A divergence is much stronger on the weekly
chart than on a 15-minute chart.
A moving average crossover has more relevance
on the daily chart than on the 5-minute chart.
By using higher time frames position traders
improve the quality of their trades.
Now that we discussed the advantages of position
trading, let’s see a couple of strategies
used by position traders.
An efficient position trading strategy is
divergence trading on the weekly/monthly charts.
Divergences are more reliable on higher time
frames because the market does not move as
fast and it is easier to define trends.
By trading divergences, the position traders
see the patterns developing and have time
to make the correct decisions.
In this weekly gold chart, we spotted an excellent
hidden divergence opportunity.
The gold price recorded a strong upward trend
and retraced to the 23.6 Fibonacci retracement
level.
During this time, a hidden divergence pattern
developed on the stochastic oscillator.
This represented a perfect buy for a position
trader, the gold price continuing its upward
trend.
A similar pattern is seen in this aussie dollar
weekly chart.
After 4 months of price increases, the market
retraced to 38.2 fib level.
The stochastic indicator showed a hidden divergence
around that area, representing a good buy
opportunity for a position trader.
The price indeed rejected that area and continued
its upward trend for the rest of the year.
On the Apple stock chart, we found this pattern
once again.
The Apple price was in a strong upward trend
on the weekly chart.
The price retraced to 38.2 fib level.
This move, combined with the hidden divergence
on the stochastic oscillator represented a
great opportunity for a position trader.
As you can observe from these examples, the
hidden divergences represent a reliable tool
for position traders on the higher time frames,
generating high probability signals.
Another viable strategy for a position trader
is the carry trade.
The carry trade is an interesting forex long-term
strategy that is based on the difference in
interest rates around the world.
It’s a strategy through which a position
trader sells a certain currency with a low-interest
rate and uses the funds to buy a currency
with higher interest rate.
By executing a carry trade, the position trader
intends to generate profit from the difference
in interest rates between two countries.
Also, with an appropriate approach, the position
trader aims to benefit not only from the difference
in interest rates but also from the changes
in the exchange rate.
Here’s an example, the Aussie dollar/ and
the Japanese yen on the monthly timeframe.
That’s a good carry trade opportunity because
there is a big difference between interest
rates of the 2 countries, so we could make
a profit in the long term from the swap.
After we determined the main monthly relevant
support and resistance and potential price
patterns we identified a possible long position
in the direction of the prevailing upward
trend, after the price rejected the 38.2 fib
level.
A long entry on the currency pair would be
a safe entry, considering the long term.
The long position on the instrument is related
to a positive swap, and thus the profit of
such a transaction would be even greater if
the currency pair will continue to move upwards.
Another position trading strategy involves
moving averages.
The moving averages are probably the most
well-known and heavily used indicators in
technical analysis because they effectively
captures the trend of a financial market in
an easily identifiable manner.
Position traders often use moving averages
for identifying and confirming support and
resistance levels.
A crossover between 2 moving average is probably
one of the most well-known technical analysis
signal used by traders.
The strategy is simple, position traders trade
moving averages, one with a shorter period
and the other with a longer period and track
the signals when a crossover occurs.
This is the simplest position trading strategy
because moving average crossovers on higher
timeframes work better than short-term crossovers.
This is likely because they produce fewer
false signals.
However, be careful with moving average crossovers,
because this strategy works only in trending
markets.
When the market is in a range, you’ll probably
see something similar on your charts.
Despite the fact that position trading is
a long-term strategy and takes some time to
profit from markets, it’s a safer alternative
compared to the other strategies in the market.
Used it in conjunction with the long-term
trend and with a proper money management system,
the position trading might bring back the
enjoyment of trading, without having to spend
all day in front of the computer.
If you got any value from this, please consider
subscribing to our channel, share and like
this video, as it would help us a lot in the
future.
Until next time.