Renko chart is probably the most under-rated
trading concept, ignored by most traders.
Although no single tool is going to instantly
make you a great trader, Renko charts will
allow you to see the market in a different
way, and will also help you stick to your
trading plan better.
That’s why in today’s video we’ll discuss
about Renko charts and I will share how to
adjust them correctly for scalping and day
trading.
Renko charts are a new way to view the price
of an asset that filters out minor price movements.
The chart looks like a series of bricks placed
at a 45-degree angle to each other.
If you analyze these 2 two charts, you immediately
spot the striking differences between a regular
candlestick chart and a Renko chart.
You can see that those small fluctuations
on classic charts are removed, and price trends
are easier to spot on the Renko chart.
Renko charts are easier to read because the
markers on the chart—which are called bricks,
boxes, or blocks—are more uniform compared
to candlestick charts.
Traditional candlestick charts plot new bars
as time passes.
For instance, a one-minute chart will plot
a new bar every minute.
On the other hand, a Renko chart:
• Does not depend on time
• Plots a new bar only when the market moves
beyond a certain amount
Being independent of time is the defining
characteristic of a Renko chart.
So, it depends only on price action, creating
a smoothed chart with less noise.
Each brick on a Renko chart is a candlestick
with no shadows.
You need only one key parameter for Renko
charts – the brick size.
The brick size is the price range that the
market must cover before a new brick is plotted.
You can set the brick size in pips, ticks,
or cents, depending on the market you’re
trading.
And, for a Renko chart to reverse, meaning
the brick to change its color, price action
must reverse by at least two brick sizes.
Let’s say you trade Forex, and we’ll pick
the EUR/JPY pair.
It you want to set your brick size to 5 pips
for example, you just have to adjust the settings
of the Renko box size to 0.05.
If you want a ten pip box size, you set it
0.1.
I use Tradingview, by the way, to trade with
Renko bars.
For GBP/USD or EUR/USD, for a 10 pip brick
size you set the box size to 0.001.
You can set the values of the box size depending
on your trading style: scalping, day trading
or swing trading, and you can change the value
of the Renko chart to suit your trading needs.
If you trade stocks, a box size of 1, is the
equivalent of 1 dollar.
I find this value to be perfect for swing
trading and even day trading strategies.
Every time the stock moves 1 dollar, a new
brick is formed.
Since the brick size is the only parameter,
a successful Renko strategy is highly dependent
on it.
There are 2 methods used to set this parameter.
Fixed Amount
Average True Range
First, let’s talk about the FIXED AMOUNT
method.
Using a set number of ticks/pips/cents as
the brick size is the simplest method.
But unless you are already familiar with the
market, it’s challenging to arrive at a
suitable figure.
You need some trial and error here.
If you want to see more bricks plotted, reduce
the size the box size.
This approach is indicated if you prefer scalping
or day trading.
If you enjoy swing trading, increase the box
size, and in this way less bricks will be
plotted.
Be careful not to use a brick size that’s
too small.
If your brick size is too small, the Renko
chart will be volatile.
As a result, it loses its intended effect
of smoothing price action.
There is no rule that works for every currency
pair or stock.
When I use Renko, I just eyeball the chart,
and try a few different box sizes.
If it is too choppy I try increasing the box
size.
Then I try decreasing it, because maybe there
are trends to be captured within the choppy
trading.
Smaller boxes mean more trend changes and
more trades.
Big boxes mean fewer trend changes and fewer
trades.
Second approach involves the AVERAGE TRUE
RANGE (ATR) for brick sizes
The advantage of this method is that it factors
in changes in price volatility.
A typical value is the 14-period ATR.
So the brick size is based on the ATR value
at the time the chart is created.
Should the ATR value change the next day,
then this new ATR value will be used to set
the brick size.
Which one is better?
I prefer the fixed value because the ATR value
might change and can cause the Renko chart
to change significantly whenever it is updated.
That’s just my preference, but I know a
few traders that use the ATR Brick size successfully.
One characteristic of Renko charts that should
be understood is that the charts don’t show
all price points.
Consider that you are using a Renko brick
of 3 pips and price moves 5 pips in the opposite
direction.
Since that is not enough price movement to
make another Renko brick, there will be 2
pips of price that does not show on the Renko
chart.
When I first started day trading Renko day
charts, this bothered me a lot, especially
after trading with time and classic candlesticks
for so many years.
There are indicators that add ‘wicks’
to the Renko bricks to show these prices,
but these start to add some of the ‘noise’
back to the chart.
It’s up to you if you want to add or remove
the wicks on Renko bars.
So the most important step in creating a successful
Renko strategy is setting the size of the
brick.
It may be $0.10 in the stock market or 10
pips in forex market.
What you must remember is that a brick forms
on the Renko chart once the price has moved
that amount, and not before.
A candlestick chart, on the other hand, shows
the price movement over a period of time,
such as one minute or one day.
While there is a time axis along the bottom
of a Renko chart, there is no set time limit
for how long a Renko box takes to form.
It could take 4 minutes, three hours, or eight
days.
It all depends on how volatile the pricing
of the asset is and what brick size you set.
So Renko charts ignore the time aspect and
only focus on price changes.
If the brick value is set at 10 points, a
move of 10 points or more is required to draw
another brick.
Price movements less than 10 points would
be ignored and the Renko chart would remain
unchanged.
Renko charts are most useful to day traders
and scalpers for spotting trends, areas of
support and resistance, breakouts, and reversals.
The chart's simplicity can make it easier
to see those price actions and signals for
making trades.
This is because Renko charts filter the noise
by focusing exclusively on minimum price changes.
Renko bricks are not added unless price changes
by a specific amount.
Thus, it’s easy to spot important highs
and lows, and identify key support and resistance
levels.
Armed with this information, you can identify
uptrends by analyzing higher highs and higher
lows or downtrends with lower lows and lower
highs.
The stronger the trend, the more renko blocks
will be plotted.
Renko charts are particularly good at finding
support and resistance areas because they
condense long, but static periods.
This makes it easier to see where price support
and price resistance is occurring.
Renko Charts are very visual to display obvious
support and resistance levels.
With classic candlestick charts, there is
a lot of subjectivity and extra work that
goes into identifying good and precise areas
of support and resistance.
In this example, notice how simple it is to
plot the support and resistance levels.
And most interestingly, notice how price reacts
to these support/resistance levels to the
right side of the chart.
Even if you prefer to use candlesticks, using
Renko as your tool to find these price levels
will help you a lot to find the best areas
to trade from.
Also as with support and resistance identification,
chart patterns are also much easier to recognize
on a Renko chart.
This Renko chart shows several classical chart
patterns.
I can spot an inverted head and shoulders,
a double top, flag patterns, traingles and
so on.
With the bricks on a Renko chart, you can
spot price clusters quickly.
These clusters are great demand and supply
zones.
A simple guideline is to look for boxes formed
by alternating bricks within a price range.
This example shows how a Renko chart highlighted
an effective supply zone.You can notice several
renko Bricks within the same price range,
which projected a supply zone, which was respected
by the market later on.
Renko charts can also be helpful with uncovering
trends and patterns that are obscured in time-based
charts and for simplifying complicated chart
structures.
When the price is trending, Renko charts provide
a simple way to stick with the trend.
Don't exit until there is a reversal—a confirmed
box of the opposite color.
You can use typical technical analysis to
help identify potential turning points or
the start of a trend, and then use Renko charts
to stick with that trend, or you could simply
trade based on Renko.
A new box color equals a potential trend change,
but this doesn’t mean a new position must
be initiated right away.
This method can result in lots of losing trades
when the price is choppy.
Use Renko charts as an additional tool, in
conjunction with support and resistance levels.
I encourage you to use Renko only on certain
forex pairs and stocks that trend well.
Find a box size that allows you to capture
the bulk of the price moves, but also minimizes
the consolidation periods.
Unfortunately, the consolidation periods can't
be avoided...if the price is oscillating back
and forth, so will Renko charts.
For this reason, I prefer to add a moving
average to Renko charts, to keep me on the
right side of the trend.
Very important: the moving averages will be
computed using the Renko bricks, not the actual
bars.
Therefore I advise you to use shorter period
averages because the Renko technique is filtering
out most of the market noise already.
Renko charts are not perfect and have their
limitations.
A few drawbacks have already been addressed:
First, Renko charts are not so helpful in
choppy periods.
Also, the simplification of Renko charts comes
at a cost, because some price information
is lost.
A third limitation is related to fact that
price has to move quite a bit to cause a reversal.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.