Do you want to learn to anticipate a price
movement like this one?
You’re in luck because this is the video
that will change how you see and trade the
market.
Today I’m showing you how banks and professional
traders use Volume Spread Analysis, one of
the best leading strategies you could use
for trading.
And if you want to show your support, please
leave a like to help us with Youtube algorithm
and turn on the bell, so you don’t miss
when new videos are released.
Volume Spread Analysis is the study of Price
in relation to its corresponding volume.
It basically identifies the underlying reasons
behind the market behavior or movement.
If a trader anticipates a bearish or bullish
movement then there must be an underlying
reason behind it.
Volume Spread Analysis tracks down the professional
activity or the moves of the smart money.
Smart Money in this context is the Big Banks,
Hedge Funds and Large Financial Institutions
having hefty pockets to move the market the
way they want.
Volume Spread Analysis eliminates subjectivity
from trading because while price can be manipulated
by professional activity, volumes can’t.
Thereby, Volume Spread Analysis is one of
the best way to understand market psychology
and sentiments.
VSA can be used in any market like forex,
stocks, Indices, commodities, and Futures.
Many people might argue that in forex Volumes
are useless as it is decentralized market
having no real volumes.
However, Forex has Tick Volumes which is proxy
to real volumes and correlates it 90% of the
time.
And yes, VSA methodology can also be applied
to any timeframe.
Wyckoff’s VSA is one of the best methods
to analyze a market because:
• It is non subjective
• It is not prone to smart money manipulation
as the method itself is used for detecting
smart money activity.
• It figures out the underlying reasons
behind the market movements and also understands
the cause of imbalance between supply and
demand.
First, let’s see the components of volume
Spread Analysis:
1.
Spread: Spread is the difference between Opening
and closing of the price.
2.
Volume is the frequency of transaction of
the price change during a specified period
of time
3.
Bearish and Bullish Volume: Bearish Volume
is marked in Red and it shows bearish activity.
Bullish Volume is marked in green and it shows
bullish activity.
4.
Above Average High Volume: Above Average High
Volume is the Highest Volume in the current
session which is higher than the average volume.
Average Volume is the volume that coincides
with Moving Average 20 of the volume indicator.
5.
Ultra-High Volume: Ultra High Volume is the
Highest Volume in the current session.
It is higher than the previous peak volume.
There are 4 stages of VSA, based on Wyckoff
theory.
1) Accumulation: This Occurs when Supply and
Demand are in balance to each other after
a mark down move.
2) Mark Up: This occurs when Demand becomes
more than supply causing an upward bullish
rally after accumulation process
3) Distribution: This occurs when Supply and
Demand are in balance after an exhausted mark-up
move.
4) Mark Down: This occurs when Supply becomes
more than Demand causing a downward drop after
distribution phase.
Watch this video if you want to know more
details about Wyckoff method.
There are two major applications of VSA namely
tracking of SOW (Sign of Weakness) and tracking
of SOS (Sign of Strength).
SOW Sign of Weakness occurs when the Demand
is exhausted (Buyers Exhausted) after uptrend
and Supply increases (More Sellers come in).
This imbalance between supply and demand causes
the market to fall.
SOS Sign of Strength occurs when Supply is
exhausted (Sellers exhausted) after downtrend
and Demand increases (More Buyers come in).
This imbalance between supply and demand causes
the market to rise.
Now let’s talk about the different types
of Sign of Strength:
1) Down thrust:
Down thrust is the bullish pin bar or the
Doji bar having an ultra-high volume or above
average high volume.
The Spread of the down thrust bar is extremely
low meanwhile the volume is relatively high.
VSA suggests that if the spread is low then
the volume should also be low.
In this case there is a divergence between
spread and volume which signifies that there
is more demand than the supply causing price
to rise in near future.
2) Selling Climax:
Selling Climax is the high spread bearish
candle closing well off the lows, having a
noticeable downward rejection wick, projected
on ultra-high or above average high volume.
High spread rejection low volume anticipates
that the market will rise because there is
more demand than supply.
Selling Climax has a downward wick whose size
is approximately 25%-50% of the candle’s
body size.
3) Bearish Effort < Bearish Result:
This is High Spread Bearish Candle whose spread
is larger than the previous candle’s spread
but its volume is lower than the previous
candle’s volume.
VSA suggests that if there has been no effort
made then there should not be any result.
This disagreement between Price and Volume
increases demand and reduces supply causing
the market to rise in future.
An effort (volume) has not been made but there
is a result (Spread).
4) Bearish Effort > Bearish Result:
This is Low Spread Bearish Candle having spread
lower than the previous candle’s spread
but its volume is higher than the previous
candle’s volume.
In this case there is a disagreement between
volume and price resulting demand to become
more than the supply and causing price to
rise in near future.
An effort (volume) has been made but there
is no result (Spread).
5) No Supply Bar:
This is a low spread bearish candle having
downward wick whose volume is lower than the
previous two candles’ volumes.
No Supply bar means that there is lack of
supply and demand is overpowering supply causing
price to rise in future.
Please note that No Supply Bar is a continuation
signal not a reversal signal.
No supply bar is effective only if it is appears
after bullish momentum or appears after Sign
of Strength in the direction of the trend.
6) Pseudo down thrust:
Pseudo down thrust is the bullish pin bar
or doji bar having low spreads whose volume
is lower than the previous two candles’
volumes.
This suggests that there is no supply or lack
of supply.
Lack of supply means that demand will overpower
supply causing price to rise in near future.
Please also note that Pseudo down thrust is
a continuation signal not a reversal signal.
Pseudo down thrust is effective only if it
is appears after bullish momentum or appears
after Sign of Strength in the direction of
the trend.
7) Pseudo Inverse down thrust:
Pseudo Inverse down thrust is an inverse bullish
pin bar (or doji bar) having low spreads and
its volume is lower than the previous two
candles' volumes.
This suggests that there is no supply or lack
of supply.
Lack of supply means that Demand will overpower
supply causing price to rise in near future.
Again, Pseudo inverse down thrust is a continuation
signal not a reversal signal.
Is effective only if it is appears after bullish
momentum or appears after Sign of Strength
in the direction of the trend.
8) Inverse down thrust:
Inverse down thrust is the inverse bullish
pin bar or doji bar having low spreads and
projected on ultra-high or above average high
volume.
VSA suggests that if the spread is low then
the volume should also be low.
In this case there is a disagreement between
spread and volume which signifies that there
is more demand than the supply causing price
to rise in near future.
9) Failed Effort Selling Climax:
Failed Effort Selling Climax is the variation
of Selling Climax having no downward rejection
wick.
It has higher spread than the previous candles
and its volume is also higher than the previous
candle.
There is a disagreement between Volume and
Price as compared to previous candles.
However, the next candle is bullish, absorbing
the entire bearish effort.
Now let’s talk about different Types of
SOW Sign of Weakness:
1) Up thrust:
Up thrust is the bearish pin bar or doji bar
having an ultra-high volume or above average
high volume.
The Spread of the up thrust bar is extremely
low meanwhile the volume is relatively high.
VSA suggests that if the spread is low then
the volume should also be low.
In this case there is a disagreement between
spread and volume which signifies that there
is more supply than demand causing price to
fall in near future.
2) Buying Climax:
Buying Climax is the high spread bullish candle
closing well off the highs, having noticeable
upward rejection wick, projected on ultra-high
or above average high volume.
High spread rejection low volume anticipates
that the market will decrease soon because
there is more Supply than Demand.
Buying Climax has an upward wick representing
25%-50% of the candle’s body size.
3) Bullish Effort < Bullish Result:
This is a High Spread Bullish Candle whose
spread is larger than the previous candle’s
spread but its volume is lower than the previous
candle’s volume.
VSA suggests that if there has been no effort
made, then there should not be the result
(Spread).
This divergence between Price and Volume increases
supply and reduces demand causing the market
to decrease in future.
4) Bullish Effort > Bullish Result:
This is a Low Spread Bullish Candle having
spread lower than the previous candle’s
spread but its volume is higher than the previous
candle’s volume.
VSA suggests that if an effort has been made
then there must be a result (spread).
In this case there is a disagreement between
volume and price resulting Supply to become
more than Demand and causing price to fall
in near future.
5) No Demand Bar:
This is a low spread bullish candle having
upward wick whose volume is lower than the
previous two candles’ volumes.
No Demand bar means that there is lack of
demand and supply is overpowering demand causing
price to fall in future.
Please note that No Demand is a continuation
signal not a reversal signal.
No Demand is effective only if it is appears
after bearish momentum or appears after SOW
Sign of Weakness in the direction of the trend.
6) Pseudo upthrust:
Psuedo upthrust is the bearish pin bar or
doji bar having low spreads whose volume is
lower than the previous two candles’ volumes.
This suggests that there is no demand or lack
of demand.
Lack of demand means that supply will overpower
demand causing price to fall in near future.
Also, Pseudo up thrust is a continuation signal
and not a reversal signal.
So, is effective only if it is appears after
bearish momentum or appears after SOW Sign
of Weakness in the direction of the trend.
7) Inverse Pseudo Up thrust:
It is the inverse bearish pin bar (doji bar)
having low spreads.
Its volume is lower than the previous two
candles' volumes..
This suggests that there is no demand or lack
of demand.
Pseudo inverse upthrust is also a continuation
signal and not a reversal signal.
Pseudo inverse up thrust is effective only
if it is appears after bearish momentum
8) Inverse Up thrust:
Inverse Up thrust is the inverse bearish pin
bar (or doji bar) having an ultra-high volume
or above average high volume.
The Spread of the up thrust bar is extremely
low meanwhile the volume is relatively high.
VSA suggests that if the spread is low then
the volume should also be low.
In this case there is a disagreement between
spread and volume which signifies that there
is more supply than the demand causing price
to fall in near future.
9) Failed Buying Climax:
Failed Effort Buying Climax is the variation
of Buying Climax having no upward rejection
wick.
It has higher spread than the previous candle
and its volume is also higher than the previous
candle.
There is a divergence between Price and Spread
of the Failed Buying Climax as compared to
previous candles.
However, the next candle is bearish, absorbing
the entire bullish effort.
I hope you realize that that the Volume Spread
Analysis is a very powerful technique which
unfolds the true sentiment and order flow
of the market.
If you enjoyed this type of content and want
more Wyckoff and Volume Spread Analysis videos,
leave us a like to show your support and to
help us with Youtube algorithm and in future
videos we’ll go even deeper with more advanced
strategies that can be applied to day trading
and swing trading.
Until next time.