hello and welcome today i'll show you
how to perform a candle volume analysis
using wackoff method we'll cover
multiple scenarios for anticipating tops
and bottoms and they'll also reveal a
powerful strategy to follow the smart
money using a simple candlestick pattern
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
nearly a century ago richard wyckoff
began to publish his methods of
detecting supply and demand imbalances
in the market
wyckoff introduced his discovery that it
was possible to measure the force of
buying and selling pressures in any
traded market wyckof's method proved
that future price moves were
foreshadowed on the price chart because
the composite man or the smart money
must leave its trading footprint on a
price chart due to the sheer size of its
trading volume
so is the supply and demand imbalances
created by smart money that is the cause
of price movement
their activity is measured with four
simple variables
the price movement meaning the high low
and closing price
the trading volume
the relationship between the price
movement and volume and the time it
takes for the price movement to run its
course
this combined methodology is known as
wake-off candle volume analysis
in this video i will apply wipe off
candle volume analysis on a one bar
reversal pattern known as the doji you
know it very well probably
this is a candlestick batter that occurs
when the opening and closing prices are
the same or very close to each other
the shadows can be either long or short
and there can be various types of doji
bars
but for our strategy it's not important
to distinguish the type of the doji
formation it's only important to be able
to recognize what it looks like on a
chart
this formation is said to represent
marketing decision because the market
opens trades throughout the period and
then closes at or near the opening price
it represents a battle between bulls and
bears that neither one
it's widely believed that it represents
a better reversal pattern at the top of
the market then at the bottom
although you will learn that this is not
correct under the proper circumstances
by applying wike of candle volume
analysis you will learn how to
distinguish when there is no indecision
in a doji formation
the perfect doji has the same open price
and close price
however if the difference between the
open and closed prices is within a few
ticks this could also be considered a
doji
a doji candlestick suggests a lack of
control in the market either by the
bulls or the bears
the lack of direction is clear
bulls move the price higher bears move
prices lower but in the end the market
price closed exactly or very close to
where it opened
but if the doji candle highlights market
indecision it's safe to say that it
doesn't offer insight into whether
supply or demand is in control
you have to guess the market's next
direction
this is where wyckoff candle volume
analysis will make the difference
at the bottom of a market a wyckoff
technician is looking for tests of
supply in the market
a test occurs when the price is marked
down to see if greater volume comes in
at the lower price
if it does this signifies supply is in
the market
this supply must be removed before the
market can begin any substantial up move
however if the market is marked down and
no sellers emerge at this lower prices
the price will come back up to close off
the low
while volume is lower relative to the
prior candles
with no supply present in the current
price level the price should rise
the doji test bar must exhibit the
following parameters to be valid
it must have a low that is lower than
the previous candle's low
and it has to display lower volume than
at least several of the prior candles
the lower the volume the stronger the
indication of no supply being present
here's an example on the one hour chart
notice this obvious downtrend with price
starting to make higher highs and higher
lows now we are in a slight
consolidation and we don't know if the
price will go up or down
and here's our doji test bar
looking left on the chart a few candles
prior to the doji the high was here at
around two hundred and eighteen dollars
then the market dropped around eight
dollars to the low of the doji
this sets up the ideal conditions for
this formation to occur pay attention
the test candle the doji bar
makes a new recent low and if there is
reduced volume it shows that no supply
is present
so you can see that this doji is making
a new low on the chart and the volume is
lower than the previous two candles
by standard candlestick analysis
measures most traders would come to the
conclusion that this bar represents
indecision on the part of the market
participants
breakout traders would even enter short
as the doji test bar is making new laws
however when viewed from a wikov candle
volume analysis perspective it's clear
that no indecision exists here the chart
shows that there are a few sellers at
this lower price and the price comes
back to close near the open
within the next wars this market started
making higher highs and higher lows and
increased almost five dollars
with this formation it's important to
understand that the smart money which
represents a large percentage of the
overall trading volume is not selling as
lower price levels are explored this is
clearly evident and is shown by the
reduction in the total volume if the
smart money is not selling you as a
retail trader need to be aware of this
this will prevent you from selling at
market bottoms and will allow you the
opportunity to establish a long trade
into the path of least resistance
this example shows a 15 minute chart
again in the background is a pretty
strong downtrend
around 10 candles prior to the doji test
bar the high price was around
225 dollars per share
the low of this doji test bar was at 220
which represents more than a five dollar
drop in the value of the stock
once again notice how the volume gets
lower as the doji candle tests for
supply but doesn't find an increase in
interested sellers at this lower price
levels
you can see that this doji is making a
new low on the chart and the volume is
lower than the previous three candles
if there are no sellers the price should
increase
the price of this stock rose nearly two
dollars as there were no sellers present
to stop it from increasing in value
now let's look at a doji at the top of a
market
this formation is called doji demand
drawing up
at the top of a market a wykov
technician is looking for signs that
demand is diminishing
a lack of demand occurs when the price
is marked up to see if they are willing
buyers at these higher price levels but
as the price moves up trading volume
decreases
there is a telling sign that there is no
interest in higher prices from the smart
money
with no professional buying interest at
the current price level the price should
fall
the doji demand drawing up must exhibit
the following parameters to be valid
this scandal's close must be higher than
the previous candles close
and it has to display lower volume than
at least several of the prior candles
the lower the volume the stronger the
indication that the demand has dried up
here's a 30 minute chart of the smp
preceding the two dojis marked on the
chart you can see that the market has
been in an uptrend
as the market moves up to the highest
point the amount of interested buyers is
drying up
we know this because the volume is
greatly reduced compared to the previous
scandals
even though the smp is making a new
recent high
and strong markets don't behave this way
this occurs at the top of the market and
when we apply wike of candle volume
analysis the doji indicates that at
least this phase of the up move is
either close to or at the end
once again notice how the volume gets
lower as the two doji candles test for
demand but doesn't find interested
buyers at these higher price levels
you can also see that each doji is
making a new high on the chart and the
volume is at the lowest level
several candles later the market dropped
aggressively
with this formation it's important to
understand that the smart money is not
interested in supporting higher prices
this is evidenced by the reduction in
the overall volume if the smart money is
not interested in higher prices
you as a retail trader can take this
knowledge and refrain from buying the
market tops
instead you will establish a short trade
into the path of least resistance
here's an example on bitcoin
notice this aggressive up move with
price making higher highs and higher
lows
the test candle the doji bar makes a new
recent high and the volume is lower than
the previous six or seven candles
by standard candlestick analysis
measures most readers would come to the
conclusion that this bar represents
indecision
but when viewed from a wake of candle
volume analysis perspective it's clear
that no indecision exists here
the chart shows that there are a few
interested buyers at this higher price
and the price comes back to close near
the open
whenever you see a doji on low volume
that appears in the context of a bullish
uptrend this should give you some
warnings that a trend correction could
come at any time
once you identify the candlestick
pattern you will want to find a trigger
that lets you know when to enter the
trade
a simple trigger is the low of the doji
once the candle closes below this level
you can open a short position
the aggressive entry would be
immediately after the candle closes
the proper location of a stop loss is
above the high of the doji
your level of risk will vary depending
on the length of the candlestick week
ideally you want to have your reward
your take profit at least double your
risk
a first profit target equals the size or
the range of the doji candle
this would give you a roughly one-to-one
reward risk ratio
not ideal but at least you can lock in
some profits
the second profit target is double the
size of the doji this will get you
closer to a two to one reward risk ratio
[Music]
wake of candle volume analysis works in
all markets and time frames and
precisely reveals the true psychology
and the sentiment of the smart money
this technique will help you prevent
buying market tops and selling market
bottoms
i advise you however to avoid smaller
time frames like the one minute or the
five minute charts because you'll
witness many false signals and it will
be hard to see the big picture with all
that market noise
if you learned something new and want to
follow a video on this topic please hit
the like button since it really helps us
out and subscribe to stay up to date
with our latest releases
and check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time