[Music]
renko charts are a great way to analyze
the market from a completely different
perspective
if you prefer sculpting or day trading
and like to analyze price action
then ranco charts are perfect to reduce
noise and reveal key intraday levels
in this video i will share scoping and
day trading strategy involving wrinkle
charts
in a specific chart pattern and you will
learn in detail how to identify
potential signals
and the conditions needed for high
probability setups
wrinkle charts are great for sculpting
and day trading because
small noisy price movements can be
hidden to uncover the things of
importance
like trends and support and resistance
with the right understanding
wrinkle charts can produce insights that
are invisible using conventional price
time charts
ranco charts don't work in the same way
as conventional price charts
each point in a rainco chart is a block
or a brick
and the brick is plotted whenever the
price increases or decreases by a
certain amount
meaning the chart only moves forward on
the time axis
when the price changes renko charts
never move horizontally they only
advance up or down
at the same fixed rate and that's
important because when you're actively
trading the markets
scalping or day trading it's important
to have a methodology to clear out the
market noise
i won't go much in detail if you aren't
familiar with ranco charting
make sure you watch this video first to
understand exactly
how renko boxes work renko gives you a
different way to view price action
although a renkwa chart contains bricks
of the same size
predetermined by the trader there are
some boxes that contain
wicks either at the top or at the bottom
of a brick
these are the equivalent of pin bars on
classic candlestick patterns
this is the pattern we will search for
a bim bar is a chart candlestick
characterized by a long tail
that shows rejection and indicates that
the market will move in the opposite
direction
the area between the open and the close
is called the real body
and typically all beam bars have a very
small real body
and a long shadow a bullish pin bar is
known for its lower wicks
and the bearish one is characterized by
long upper wicks
the same is true for renko charts the
idea is to find
wrinkle boxes that have long wicks
now trading is a game of probabilities
that's why
you must evaluate your rank of pin bar
setups from multiple angles
to determine whether or not a rank of
bim bar is worth trading
this price action signal should respect
the following criteria
a quality wrinkle pin bar forms near a
support key level
in an uptrend and near a resistance
level in a downtrend
and the rank opinion bar formed in line
with the direction of the market
is more powerful than the one which is
formed against
the trend so the formation of this renko
pattern with the trend
makes it more effective as you can see
in this example
renko bullish pin bars that were formed
in line with the uptrend
offered good trading entries this is the
pattern we should be taking into
consideration
the bearish ones that were formed
against the trend should be ignored
the anatomy of a renko pimbar is
important as well
and you have to make sure that the
pattern is indeed a pin bar
by looking at the distance between the
box and the tail
pin bars with longer tails are more
powerful the psychology behind the
bimbar candle formation is simple
pin bars are formed when prices are
rejected
now this rejection doesn't indicate a
guaranteed reversal signal
because this price action setup can form
everywhere in your chart
the most important areas to watch when
trading pin bars
are major key levels of support and
resistance
if the rejection was near support level
for example
this is an obvious indication that the
bulls were more powerful
and they are willing to push the market
to go upward if the formation of this
candlestick occurs near a resistance
level
it indicates that the bears reject
prices and prevent the bulls from
breaking this level
so this means that sellers are willing
to push the market downward
if you understand the psychology behind
this price action pattern
you will be able to anticipate what is
likely to happen in the future
and you will make better trades based on
high probability pinbar signals
remember besides support and resistance
criteria
we aim to trade renko pinbars with the
trend
pin bars that occur in trending markets
offer good trading opportunities
with high risk reward ratio the strategy
is simple
you start by identifying a clear uptrend
or downtrend
and you wait for a pin bar to occur
after a pullback to a support or
resistance level
this example shows how this price action
signal works
if it's traded with the trend here the
price was rejected from the resistance
level
which indicates that the bears are still
in charge of the downtrend
the formation of the beam bar indicates
the end of the retracement move
and the beginning of the impulsive move
at the resistance level
in line with the downtrend this is a
high quality setup
because all the conditions are respected
the rank of pin bar is well formed
and it's in line with the direction of
the market and the rejection occurred
at a major key level which represents a
hot point in the market
a resistance level sometimes
even if the market is trending we can't
draw support and resistance levels
because prices move in a certain way
during which we are unable to identify
static key levels
if you are in this situation you can use
a moving average
which will act as a dynamic support in
an uptrend market
and a dynamic resistance in a downtrend
market
as you can observe in this example the
market was trending down
and using a moving average helps us to
identify dynamic resistance levels
and high probability pin bar setups
in this other example when prices
approach the moving average
buying pressure takes place in the
market and the price goes up
the pin bar signal is clear on the chart
because the trend is bullish
the price action setup has a bullish
structure as well
and the rejection from the moving
average is a confirmation signal to buy
the market
the entry when it comes to trading rank
or pin bars is simple
if all conditions are met we enter the
market immediately after the rank of
pimbar closes
this strategy will help you to catch the
move from the beginning because
sometimes the price goes higher
after the formation of the beam bar and
if you are not in the market the trade
will live without you
this example shows a perfect entry we
took this trade because we had three
important elements
the trend the market was trending down
in this case we look for selling
opportunities
the level here we had a support level
that becomes resistance
and the signal a renko pin bar was
formed after the retracement
back to the resistance level when you
have these three elements in the market
you just place your trade after the
appearance of the rank of pm bar
and your stop loss above the long tail
your profit target
would be the next support level in the
case of a downtrend or at least
two times the risk level as we are
scoping and day trading using this
approach
confluence is a must for a high quality
setup confluence happens when many
factors
generate the same signal this trading
concept is used to filter out entry
points
and spot high probability signals in the
market
trading with confluence will help you
focus on quality setups
rather than quantity and it will enhance
tremendously your trading performance
in our case if we are looking for a ring
of pinbar signal
we need to find other factors of
confluence to confirm
our entry so what are other factors of
confluence
first the trend is one of the most
important factor of confluence
this is the first thing that most
successful traders look for
on their charts you can't trade any
setup without identifying if it's in
line with the direction of the market or
not
next support and resistance levels and
supply and demand areas
these major levels have a significant
importance in the market
because all big participants watch the
specific areas
moving averages could represent another
conference factor
i personally add the 10 or the 20 moving
average
depending on the market i'm trading this
trading tool
acts as a dynamic support and resistance
level and it's a very important factor
of confluence in trending markets
fibonacci retracement tool is another
factor of confluence
you could use the 61 and the 50
fibonacci retracement to find the most
powerful areas in the market
to align with rank of inverse also
trendlines
drawing trend lines on your chart can
give you an idea about the market
direction
and can help you to find the most
important reversal points in the market
when you are analyzing your chart you
are not obligated to find
all these levels to determine whether
the trade is valid or not
if you can find just one or two factors
of confluence that come up together with
a good rank of pinbar setup
this is enough to make a profitable
trade in this example
we have a high probability setup with
four factors of confluence
first the trend the market is trending
up which means that we have to follow
the trend
and look for a buying opportunity second
the level
the support level is an important key
area in the market as price
broke out the resistance level that
becomes support
and pulled back to it third the signal
the formation of the renko bullish beam
bar after the retracement
back to the new support level and
another signal
the rejection of the pin bar from the
support level and the 10 moving average
that acted as a dynamic support level
all these factors work together
to give a powerful trading signal to buy
the market
this example shows four confluent levels
that indicate a powerful short trading
signal
the first factor is the bearish trend
and the second one is the support level
that becomes resistance
the third one is the 10 moving average
which represents a dynamic resistance
level
and the last factor is the rank of
pinball formation
near this level in line with the trend
if you adopted a confluence trading
concept you will completely change the
way you perceive the market
and you will start trading like a sniper
by waiting for the best trading setups
to come to you
instead of forcing your trades and
trading without any major backup
if you learned something new and found
value leave us a like to show support
subscribe to our channel and hit the
bell icon to stay in touch when we
release new videos
until next time