here's the main problem why many day
traders fail to trade effectively using
moving averages it's the false breakouts
or whipsaws that occur when price moves
back and forth crossing the line you
apply on your chart
you know the drill as the price moves
above the moving average that's a buy
signal as the price moves below that's a
sell signal but the market isn't perfect
you get one signal to move across the
moving average followed shortly by an
opposite signal
these false signals almost always result
in a small loss
the same problem happens when you apply
a crossover system for sculpting or day
trading
moving average crossovers only work when
the market trend for a substantial
period of time that is when the moving
averages you see on your charts look all
nice and pretty
only problem is that those nice and
clean trends don't always happen when
the ranging markets come and the false
breakouts start to happen the moving
average traders tend to start taking
losses as the markets tend to reverse
once the moving averages trigger an
entry
so how to reduce the false signals
because we can completely remove them
the problem is that when we apply a
moving average study we focus on the
line that appears on our charts which is
plotted based on the closing price
and that's a very small margin
instead of plotting the moving average
based on the closing price i use a
moving average channel
here's how it works we have two moving
averages forming a channel which are
applied to the bar's high and low prices
instead of the bar's close price
so instead of one moving average you'll
have two moving averages on a chart
instead of focusing on just one line
you'll have an area
this moving average channel will filter
a lot of all signals and will save you a
lot of losing trades and lost money
the moving average high low channel
tries to find trending markets and is
extremely useful for staying out of
sideways markets
the channel turns a simple moving
average into a zone of support and
resistance
in a market with a strong trend prices
may trade either above or below the
channel some traders prefer to buy or
sell breakouts above or below the moving
average high low channel
others tend to use the resistance and
support areas as zones to establish a
market position in the direction of the
dominant market trend
remember that the moving average lags
and responds to price this is why you
must analyze it together with price
action and my favorite way to trade
price action is by using hikanashi bars
when using hikanashi you can treat it
the same way as you would a traditional
candlestick chart the difference is that
prices have been smoothed out to reflect
directional bias as with candlesticks
you might use chart patterns with the
hakanashi but your view might be better
informed by the consistency in the color
coding which may indicate reversal bars
more clearly and sometimes more
accurately
so by using the moving average channel
and hiking ashy combination we plan to
remove the noise and fall signals and to
catch longer and persistent trends
trend detection is one of the main
functions of this strategy because both
high kanashii and the moving average
channel put an emphasis on persistent
trends
small corrections and consolidation are
left behind and they are very visible on
the chart you'll notice that when the
direction changes on a hikinashi graph
the price most likely starts on your
move this helps to distinguish between
the potential beginning and the end of a
trending move
with the heckiness chart you can
distinguish strong trends from weak
price action
at first glance the bullish ikanashi
trend looks like a normal japanese
candlestick trend
however you will notice that the
hakenashi trend is built primarily by
bullish candles and is absent of lower
candlewicks
when the price is shooting up the price
action creates very little to no lower
shadows
the bearish akanashi trend has the same
functions as the bullish one but in the
opposite direction
this means that is built mainly by
bearish candles also a strong bearish
trend on the hiking nation graph has
very little to no upper candle shadows
here we are using a 50 period high low
channel on a high canashi chart however
you can experiment with different
lookback periods to see which one works
best for you
higher settings tend to work well for
observing trends and the lower look back
periods are good for timing
first aspect we need to do is to
determine market direction the primary
function of this day trading strategy is
to smooth trends
when the channel is pointing up we have
a bull trend when the channel is
pointing down we have a bear trend
by the way i use this indicator on
trading view
when the moving average channel is
sloping upwards the lines are green when
it's loping downwards the channel is red
and when the moving averages are flat
the channel is gray
but the markets aren't always that
simple to analyze
to make sure that you are not trapped at
the end of a trend we need to examine
price action using high kanashii
when the high canadian price structure
aligns with the moving average channel
the market is trending
when they oppose each other the market
is slowing down and might be reversing
or retracing
for an uptrend the price is above the
moving average channel the channel is
green and the hike and ashy candles are
green
for a downtrend the price is below the
moving average channel the channel is
red
and high kanashii candles are red
[Music]
the range of the channel is related to
the look back period
fast moving averages respond quickly to
new price data and could form steep
lights
but slow moving averages are weighted
down and show more stable slopes
when the price is inside the channel i
avoid opening any position this is the
no man's land a period of indecision
where you want a clear breakout on any
side of the channel
i also avoid opening positions when the
slope of the channel changes from
upwards to downwards to flat in a very
short period of time when this happens
you can see the price breaks the channel
in both directions the market
consolidates so there is no clear trend
on the market
you must also analyze the distance
between the moving average channel and
high canada candles
in a sideways market price tangles with
the moving average there is little or no
gap between price and the moving average
channel
in a healthy bull trend the price stays
a fair distance above the moving average
channel and stays below in vertrans
in an overextended trend you'll find the
striking distance between high kanashii
candles and the moving average channel
so the strategy is very simple and very
effective at the same time
a breakout above the moving average
channel with green high kanashii candles
signals buying pressure
a breakout below the moving average
channel with red high kanashii candle
signals selling pressure
pay attention to the slope of the
channel the distance between the candles
and the channel and you'll eliminate a
lot of whole signals
[Music]
depending on your level of experience
you can add other filters to find the
best setups
here's a great one the adx indicator the
average directional index will confirm
if the market is ranging or a new trend
is likely to take place
adx is plotted as a single line with
values ranging from 0 to 100 adx is
non-directional and registers trend
strength whether price is trending up or
down
adx values will help you to identify the
strongest and most profitable signals
i personally ignore all signals if the
adx line is below 20.
adx readings above 20 suggest that a
trend is strong enough for trend trading
strategies
low atx is usually a sign of
accumulation or distribution
when adx is below 20 for more than 20 or
30 bars you will see that price enters
range conditions so ignore the signals
that we find because they will have a
low probability of working out
when adx is below 20 price will usually
move up and down between resistance and
support to find selling and buying
interest when the adx line is rising
trends trend is increasing and the price
moves in the direction of the trend
when the line is falling trend's trend
is decreasing and the price enters a
period of retracement or consolidation
here are several examples with adx
filter
[Music]
another filter is the regular divergence
i'm a big fan of combining leading with
lagging signals to confirm my traits and
one of the most powerful trading signals
that combines price action analysis with
the use of indicators is the divergent
signal
regular divergence is used to forecast
an upcoming price reversal
when you spot a regular bullish
divergence you expect the price to
cancel its bearish move and to switch to
an upward move
when you see a regular bearish
divergence you expect the price to
cancel its bullish move and switch to a
downward move
divergence trading is an extremely
effective way to confirm our strategy
the reason for this is because
divergence formations are leading
signals
this means that the divergence pattern
is likely to occur before the actual
move
this way we are able to anticipate and
enter the trade using our strategy right
at the beginning of a new emerging move
here are several examples with macd
histogram divergence s filter
[Music]
so
being a day trading and scoping strategy
you could use any time frame between one
minute and 15 minutes
and when it comes to selecting the
markets for using this strategy it's
vital to pick one that is volatile so
that you are more likely to see a high
number of moves
as always if you learned something new
and found value give us a like to show
support subscribe to our channel and
click the bell icon to stay notified
every time we upload a new video
until next time