Take a look at this.
So you see this price action sequence, you
see this trendline, you wait for the breakout
below it, and you enter when price closes
below it.
And what do you know, price returns to the
trend line and continues in the initial direction.
Sound familiar, right?
Trend lines are the simplest tools in technical
analysis, and maybe the hardest setup to trade.
Much harder than a classic support or resistance
level.
In this example, I see maybe 4 or 5 reasons
of why you shouldn’t have taken this trade
in the first place.
If you’re guilty of making the same mistake,
get ready to take some notes, because you're
about to discover the keys to mastering trendlines
and how to make the most of your trading strategies.
Like, subscribe and stick around for the full
video.
Don’t include prices that were not maintained
during a period
Drawing trendlines without wicks is, in my
opinion, a better approach, because it eliminates
noise.
A wick is the highest or lowest price that
was reached during the period represented
by that candlestick.
A rejection of price.
When you draw a trendline using the wicks
of the candlesticks, you are including prices
that were not maintained during that period,
and this can lead to more false signals, and
a less accurate trend line.
For example, if you draw a trendline using
the wicks of a bullish candlestick, the trend
line will be a bit lower than if you draw
it using the body of the candlestick.
This difference may not seem significant,
but it can make a big difference in the outcome
of a trade.
When you have a large wick on one side of
the candle, it could indicate that the price
got rejected in that level, this could be
a sign of a potential reversal, but if you
are drawing your trendline with the wicks,
you might be taking that large wick as a valid
price point, leading you to a false conclusion.
So start drawing trend lines using only the
body of the candlesticks.
A trendline connecting only 2 points is highly
unreliable
A big mistake I’ve personally made for several
years, is to focus on trend lines that connect
only 2 points.
You see 2 swings and you connect them with
a trend line.
I’ve lost far too many trades, chasing false
breakouts using this technique.
When drawing trendlines, the more connecting
points, the better.
This is because the more connecting points
a trendline has, the more reliable and robust
it becomes.
A trendline with more connecting points is
more reliable because it has been tested against
more price swings and has been able to withstand
those tests, indicating that the trend has
momentum and is likely to continue.
If you have a trendline connecting two points,
it can be considered as a weak trendline,
and let’s face it, it can be easily broken.
But if you have a trendline connecting 3 or
4 points, then you have a strong trendline.
When you see a clear breakout from a strong
trendline, it means something.
The point is: when you are drawing a trendline
with only two points, you could be seeing
a coincidence, but when you have a trendline
connecting more points, you can be sure that
the trend is real and it has been established
over a longer period of time.
Consider trend lines as noise zones
So price is constantly changing, impacted
by volatility and momentum.
This is particularly relevant when analyzing
trendlines.
Professional traders are very aware that amateurs
are likely to place trades around trendlines
and will often manipulate the market to cause
the price to spike, then change direction.
To improve your win rate, it can be beneficial
to use areas rather than relying solely on
single trend lines.
For example, when using a single trendline,
you may be hesitant to enter a trade if the
price is just slightly above or below this
trendline.
However, by using an area, you set a range
of prices where the price is likely to find
support or resistance.
Here a quick tip on Tradingview.
First you draw the trend line connecting the
swing lows, then you hold the CTRL key and
drag the line to form the area.
This can give you a bit more wiggle room to
enter or exit a trade.
By creating these so-called "noise zone",
you can filter out a significant amount of
market noise and eliminate the need to draw
trendlines precisely at the highs or lows.
A shortening time between touches can indicate
a potential breakout
The distance between connecting points is
crucial when determining the validity of your
trend line.
When forming an up trendline, the swing lows
should not be too far apart or too close together,
as this can question the validity of a future
reaction.
Similarly, when forming a down trend line,
the swing highs should also be relatively
evenly spaced.
There isn’t an ideal distance between these
points, it will depend on the timeframe you’re
analyzing.
It is important to measure the time passed
between consecutive touches on a trendline.
Here’s an important tip: a shortening time
between touches can indicate a potential breakout.
When the market repeatedly tests a trend line
over a short period and the price stays close
to the trendline, it is likely that a breakout
will occur, and the trend may be reversing.
Though this is not always the case, this pattern
can indicate a good opportunity for trading
a breakout, rather than a continuation play.
As the angle of the trendline becomes steeper,
its reliability decreases
The slope of a trendline can impact its validity
as a support or resistance level.
Let's say we have a chart with price that
has been steadily increasing over time.
As the price rises, you can draw a trendline
connecting the lows.
This trendline will have a relatively shallow
angle, indicating that the price has been
rising at a steady and consistent pace.
This trendline can be considered a reliable
support level, as it is likely that the price
will continue to find support at this level.
Now, let's say that the price suddenly experiences
a sharp and rapid increase.
If we were to connect the lows during this
time, the trendline would have a much steeper
angle.
This sudden and sharp increase in price is
not likely to be sustained, and it is less
likely that the price will continue to find
support at this level.
This trendline would be considered less reliable
as a support level.
So as the angle of the trendline becomes steeper,
the reliability of the level decreases.
In fact, a steep trendline is often the result
of a sudden and significant price movement
over a short period of time.
Such trendlines created from sharp moves are
less likely to provide a meaningful support
or resistance level.
Even if the trendline is constructed with
many valid points, attempting to profit from
a trendline break may prove challenging.
Continuation or breakout: which one you should
target
There’s a special appeal to trade a trend
line breakout.
I don’t know why, but many new traders prefer
to wait for the trendline to be breached,
then trade the potential breakout.
I’ve also been guilty of this mistake, and
now I can tell you that trading in the direction
of the trendline is a more consistent strategy
than trading breakouts.
This allows you to ride the trend and take
advantage of the momentum that is already
present in the market.
For example, let's say that you have identified
an uptrend on a chart and you have drawn a
trendline connecting the lows of the price.
It’s better to trade in the direction of
this trendline, meaning you would be buying
when the price is approaching the trendline.
You want to capture the upward momentum of
the market and not wait for a breakout, which
it may not be valid in the first place.
Another advantage of trading in the direction
of the trendline is that it allows you to
place stop losses below or above the trendline,
providing a clear level of risk management.
Not to close though, because you don’t want
to be the victim of stop loss hunting.
Wait for the first retest after breakout
Many traders are drawing a trendline, and
at the first candle close below it, they enter
right away.
But, the first retest after a trendline breakout
is a much better area to take trades from.
So why is that?
A big number of traders will place trades
in the direction of the trendline.
When the market moved below it, then all of
the traders who have placed buy trades at
the trend line are trapped in losing trades.
Their biggest desire, when the price is below
the trendline, is for market to return to
their entry level.
A lot of buyers will wait for a breakeven
chance, to close their positions.
Different traders will decide to close their
trades at different times, and the closer
the market gets to the breakout point the
higher the number of traders who will be closing
their trades.
That’s why you’ll see an immediate reaction
when the price returns to the trendline.
The losing traders had their chance to exit
their trades.
Buyers are exiting, more sell orders are coming
into the market, and this adds momentum, to
the downside.
In some cases, when you wait for the first
retest, you’ll get a better price to enter.
I personally trade only the first retest and
ignore the following tests.
I have one rule: the breakout level can only
be touched once.
When a level has been hit once, its significance
in the market decrease dramatically and the
chances of the market reacting to the level
in the same way again is low.
If the market returns to the trend line breakout
area again after already being touched, the
traders who went short on the breakout may
not be in their trades anymore.
Traders will not sit and watch as the profit
on their trades gets smaller and smaller,
they will always close their trades whilst
they still have a little bit of profit left.
At the second or third retest, you could be
facing a lack of orders present in the market.
So focus on the first re-test.
Higher time frames trend lines are less likely
to be affected by short-term volatility
Trend lines on higher time frames are considered
to be the most significant.
For instance, a trend line that extends over
a two-week period will always be considered
more important than one that only extends
over the course of a trading session.
To achieve the best results with trend lines,
it’s better to use higher time frames, it
increases the reliability of the analysis.
For example, let's say we're looking at a
chart and we've drawn a trend line on the
daily chart.
This line represents the overall direction
of the price over the past few weeks or even
months.
Now, if we switch to a lower time frame like
the 15-min chart, we may see that the price
is also following an opposite trend line.
But when you’re looking at the 15-min trend
line, you're only seeing the price action
over the past several hours.
The trend line on this chart is more likely
to be influenced by short-term factors.
Which one has more relevance?
Of course, is the higher time frame one.
There is more data, more bars that are used
to make the trend line, this makes it more
reliable, and it's less likely to be affected
by short-term volatility.
Confirm the trendline with VWAP or a moving
average
One of the main things to remember when trading
trend lines is that using an approach that
utilizes multiple confirmations is generally
the best way to go.
The more confirmations, the less chance of
a false signal.
It's always helpful to look for confluences
in your chart, which is when multiple signals
point to the same conclusion.
One example of this is when a trendline aligns
with a long term moving average.
Let's say we're looking at a chart and we've
drawn a trendline on the hourly chart.
This line represents the overall direction
of price over the past days.
If we add a moving average to the chart, we
can see that the price is consistently bouncing
off the moving average line, which also confirms
the trendline.
Another example is when the price is consistently
trading above the moving average line and
the trendline is also pointing upwards, it
gives you a better indication of the bullish
trend.
When a trendline aligns with a moving average,
it provides a level of added confidence in
the trend direction, as it confirms the trendline
and can increase the reliability of your analysis.
When these indicators give conflicting signals,
you have a warning sign, and it’s better
to wait for further price action to unfold.
So like I said in the intro, trading trendlines
is much harder than trading classic support
and resistance levels.
If you want to have the full picture, you
definitely must watch this video.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!