What moves markets?
It's a fundamental question that every professional
trader should consider.
Perhaps the shortest answer is supply and
demand.
If demand for an instrument is high and supply
is short, the price will inevitably rise.
If the converse is true, the price will fall.
But how can we evaluate what is happening
with supply and demand?
Especially in the forex market, which is de-centralized
and, not overly transparent.
One method we can utilize is to use price
data to get a handle on how money is flowing
in and out of an instrument.
And one of the more popular tools for doing
this is the money flow index indicator.
The money flow index (MFI) is a momentum indicator
that measures the flow of money into and out
of a security over a specified period of time.
It is related to the relative strength index
(RSI) but incorporates volume, whereas the
RSI only considers price.
For this reason, some analysts call MFI the
volume-weighted RSI.
The MFI is calculated by accumulating positive
and negative money flow values, then creating
a money ratio.
The money ratio is then normalized into the
MFI oscillator form.
The indicator is typically calculated using
14 periods of data and uses price and volume
and the concept of accumulation distribution,
being quite helpful in confirming trends in
prices and warning of potential reversals
in prices.
So, how to read money flow index (MFI)
• when current typical price, meaning (high
+ low + close) / 3 is higher than the previous
typical price, it is considered positive money
flow
• when current typical price is lower than
the previous typical price, it is considered
negative money flow
• positive money flow represents the sum
of the positive money over the specified number
of periods
• negative money flow represents the sum
of the negative money over the specified number
of periods.
• money flow index indicates the percentage
of positive money flow compared to the total
money flow.
MFI reading above 80 is considered overbought
and MFI reading below 20 is considered oversold.
However, if you followed by channel you probably
know by now that overbought and oversold doesn't
necessarily mean the price will reverse, only
that the price is near the high or low of
its recent price range.
The creators of the indicators recommended
using 90 and 10 levels as overbought and oversold
levels.
These levels are rarely reached, but when
they are it often means the price could be
due for a direction change.
The MFI and RSI are very closely related.
The main difference is that MFI incorporates
volume, while the RSI does not.
Traders relaying mainly on volume analysis
believe it is a leading indicator.
Therefore, they also believe that MFI will
provide signals, and warn of possible reversals,
in a more timely fashion than the RSI.
One indicator is not better than the other,
they are simply incorporating different elements
and, therefore, provide signals at different
times.
But, as it incorporates volume, the money
flow index might give you the extra edge you
need when you try to predict future price
movements.
Ok, now let’s see how to trade with the
MFI indicator.
As the money flow index (MFI) is quite similar
to RSI, the indicator can be used in a similar
way.
The MFI can offer traders several signals,
the main of them being overbought/oversold
conditions and divergences.
Moves below 10 and above 90 are quite rare.
When the MFI is above 90, the price is considered
overbought and a reversal or pullback could
potentially occur.
When the MFI is below 10, the price is considered
oversold and a reversal or pullback might
be recorded on the market.
It is important to remember that simply because
a market reaches overbought or oversold levels,
does not mean that prices will immediately
reverse in the opposite way.
During periods of strong upward trends of
downward trends, markets can and will remain
in the overbought or oversold areas for weeks
or even months.
That’s why when the MFI hits or exceeds
values of 90 or 10, signaling overbought and
oversold, you shouldn’t blindly enter counter
trend positions.
You need to pay attention to price action,
to recent market swing, to key support and
resistance levels and if you spot some sort
of confluence, then you should consider entering
into a trade.
The MFI should never be used on its own as
a trade signal, and must be used in conjunction
with other tools of analysis to make better
informed trading decisions.
Traders who use volume in their analysis often
look for divergences between volume and price.
If volume is trending one way, while price
is trending in the opposite direction, it
could be a leading indication of an upcoming
change in the direction of the market.
For example, if the price is making new highs
and the MFI fails to make new highs, or falls.
This is a bearish divergence and can be used
as a sell signal.
Alternatively, if the price makes new lows
but the MFI fails to set new lows, or rises,
this would be a bullish divergence.
Since the MFI integrates volume data into
it, a divergence between the direction of
the indicator and price could be a leading
signal.
My preference is to combine these 2 approaches
to trade the money flow index (overbought
and oversold levels and divergences) and merge
them into one signal, and further filter the
signal with a trend line breakout.
Here are the steps of this strategy:
First, the money flow index must reach an
overbought or oversold area at least once
on the chart in the recent trading period.
I use a 7-period MFI, and not the default
settings of 14 period.
The 7 period MFI will have an increased sensitivity,
to produce more signals.
The second step: a divergence between the
money flow index and the price must occur
during the recent period.
I prefer to identify the main trend with a
200-period exponential moving average and
I only take signals in the direction of the
200 EMA.
If the price is trading below 200 EMA, I plan
take only short signals.
If the price is trading above 200 EMA, I take
only long signals.
Then I search for entries once the price breaks
through a recent support or resistance level,
a trend line or channel.
As we can observe in this AT&T example, this
method offer several valid entries for buy
positions as all our conditions were met:
Here’s our first signal:
First, the 200-period exponential moving average
was pointing upward, indicating a bullish
trend, so we take only buy trades
MFI reached an oversold area
We have a divergence between the MFI and the
price.
And the buy signal was confirmed after the
trend line was broken to the upside.
The second signal appeared here, within the
same conditions.
And another signal here.
Your stops should be placed below the recent
market swing.
And here are 2 short trades on Netflix.
The first signal appeared here:
The 200-period exponential moving average
was pointing downward, indicating a bearish
trend, so we take only short trades
MFI reached an overbought area
We have a divergence between the MFI and the
price.
And the sell signal was confirmed after the
trend line was broken to the upside.
The second signal appeared here, within the
same conditions.
We have a double top in price, but lower MFI
readings, plus the overbought level and the
trend line breakout.
Here are other examples of valid trades, using
the money flow index.
Another way in which you could use the money
flow indicator is to take signals when the
oscillator crosses the 50 level.
When money flow index crosses above 50 level,
this signals buying pressure coming into the
market
When money flow index crosses below 50 level,
this signals selling pressure
A 50-level crossover using the MFI with the
default value of 14-period will offer some
good entries, but it also will generate many
bad trades.
The main problem with this method is the market
noise it generates.
And traded by itself, this system is not reliable
in the long run.
That’s why we have to smooth the indicator
by calculating it on a longer period.
If in the previous strategy i preferred to
increase the sensitivity of the MFI, by reducing
its value to 7, for this approach i prefer
to decrease its sensitivity.
And I do this by setting a 50 period for the
indicator.
We also keep the same filter for determining
the trend, namely the 200-period exponential
moving average.
Here is how it looks like.
We added a 200-period exponential moving average
to estimate the market trend and 50-period
money flow index, planning to take trades
when the indicators crosses its 50-centerline.but
don’t take my settings for granted.
Play with the periods of the MFI and even
the period of the EMA and back test yourself
on different timeframes, to find the best
settings suited for your trading style.
Here are a few trade examples of MFI centerline
crossovers.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support and don’t
forget to subscribe and to hit the bell icon
to stay notified when we upload new tutorials.
Until next time.