this is why you still haven't developed
a profitable sculpting system using
trading indicators
most important role in trading is that
indicators should deliver different type
of information about the price and
confirm each other rather than duplicate
signals i'm fixing your problem today by
showing a great combination of
indicators designed for scoping a system
using the rsi ddx and the 50 exponential
moving average and if you want to show
your support please drop a like to help
us with youtube algorithm and turn on
the bell so you don't miss when your
videos are released
the scoping strategy combines three
indicators all displaying different
information whether prices are about to
increase or decrease the angle they each
offer is different
by incorporating these two indicators we
will analyze the market from different
angles
there are four general types of
indicators offering information
regarding trend volume momentum and
volatility we will use one of each
category accepting volume information
so one momentum oscillator one trend
indicator and one volatility indicator
first we'll add the rsi as a momentum
indicator
price will often trend upwards or
downwards for long periods of time and
it's useful to know the strength of a
particular trend which is why the rsi as
a momentum indicator is very helpful
you will find that the rsi oscillates
from overbought to oversold as the price
rises and pulls
remember oversold and overbought signals
don't instantly present a change in
price direction
although it's not 100 reliable this rsi
signal generally indicates that the
trend is starting to run out of momentum
then you add ddx as a volatility
indicator
there will be times when the price is
extremely volatile and moving upwards
and downwards and there will be quieter
times when the price is barely moving at
all and is stuck in a narrow trading
range
sometimes this is obvious but it's
useful to use the adx because it will
give you a good indication of the
volatility at any given moment
now volatility is just one important
factor that can help you to
contextualize price action in any given
market
understanding the momentum using the rsi
and the volatility using the adx can
help you to anticipate price behaviors
that might otherwise surprise you
and finally we'll add the trend
indicator the 50 exponential moving
average
if a market is in a strong uptrend the
price will stay above the ema and if the
market is in a strong downtrend the ema
will be above price
so rsi for momentum adx4 trend strength
and volatility and the 50 ema for trend
direction
in the scoping setup rsi will show the
movement of price the 50 ema filters the
price fluctuations meaning the noise to
see the real picture of the market
direction and the rsi displays possible
shifts in momentum
when we're adding the adx into this
equation our goal is to watch the
direction of the market movement when
there is a sharp increase in volatility
when it comes to analyzing and measuring
volatility the adx analyzes the recent
price movements
a high atx reading implies that the
trend is strong and the low edx shows a
weak trend
used in combination with a 50 ema you
can filter those trades when there isn't
much activity in the market
the combination between the rsi as a
momentum indicator and adx as a
volatility indicator is also important
because you can confirm when the market
is turning and choose a great entry
point
now let's talk about the most important
aspect of combining these indicators the
settings and the look-back periods of
each indicator
for the rsi will change from the
standard 14 period to a three period
some of you may be familiar with the
conor's rsi using a two period rsi
connors the author of the strategy said
you should look for buying opportunities
when the two-period rsi moves below 10
which is considered deeply oversold and
four short selling opportunities when
the two period are assignments above 90.
this is a rather aggressive short-term
strategy and from my back testing this
wasn't a very successful system i never
managed to get the win rate over 50 in
any of my previous attempts
try it yourself and you'll probably
record the same results as i
but this system had some potential
so i've changed the rsi lookback period
to three i've changed not only the rsi
parameters but also played around with
the overbought and oversold readings and
found out that by using an 80 rsi
reading for overbought and 20 rsi rating
for oversold condition i get more
accurate signals
we'll pay attention when the rsi of 3
period touches the 20 and 80 level it
doesn't need to go deeper into
oversolder or but as long as the rsi
touches the lines we'll have the first
condition in our strategy the momentum
condition
the volatility condition of the strategy
is given by ddx the average directional
index is used to determine if the price
is trending or not the aex gives you a
reading that generally ranges between 0
and 50. the higher the reading the
stronger the trend the lower the reading
the weaker the trend
the edx is very useful as a confirmation
tool when you want to trade in a
trending market but will not give you
reliable buy or sell signals on its own
that's why the combination with your
assigned ema the standard settings is 14
periods but i've modified it to be in
line with our scoping strategy so i've
changed the adx parameters from 14 to 5.
and while many traders use 25 as the key
level for the adx i prefer the 30 level
the noise is greatly reduced
an adx reading of over 30 identifies a
strong trend whereas a reading of below
25 identifies a weak trend and will
avoid signals in this area
obviously the higher the score the
stronger the trend a reading between 30
and 50 signals an extremely strong trend
while a reading over 50 signals that the
trend is very strong and it could
reverse
so adx of 5 periods with 30 as the most
important level
the 50 ema the trend condition is used
to generate signals with simple price
crossovers when price action tends to
stay above the 50 ema it signals that
the price is in a general uptrend
if price action stays below the 50 ema
then it indicates that is in a downtrend
this trend filter is very important for
our scoping setup please note these two
important tips
the further price can pull away from a
moving average the stronger the current
trend is and the longer the price can
stay on one side of the moving average
without touching the moving average the
stronger the trend
here are the conditions for a buy setup
the trend condition price is trading
above the 50 ema and ideally the average
is sloping upwards
the momentum condition the three period
rsi pulls back to oversold conditions
and touches or goes below the 20 level
and the volatility condition adx must be
above 30 when the signal occurs
when we have all conditions we enter at
the high of the first green candle the
candle which pulls the rsi from the
oversold conditions
the conditions for a sales setup are the
trend condition price is trading below
the 50 ema and ideally the average is
sloping downwards
the momentum condition the three period
rsi goes to over bad conditions and
touches or goes above the 80 level
and the volatility condition the atx
must be above 30 when the signal occurs
we enter at the low of the first red
candle the candle which pulls the rsi
from the overbought conditions
here's an example on the five minute
time frame by the way this is the time
frame i use and brought me the best
results
first we identify the trend using the 50
ema
we see the trend is up as the price is
above its moving average and the ama is
sloping upwards
then after we identify the trend we look
at the rsi to identify buying
opportunities within the trend when the
rsi touches the 20 level we prepare for
a change in momentum from the downside
to the upside in line with the dominant
trend direction indicated by the moving
average
and third the volatility confirmation
from the adx as the adx has a rating
higher than 30 than the signal is valid
also look where the signal appeared
right at the previous swing low which
made it a double bottom around the 50
ema a little bit of price action
confirmation is always welcomed
we enter at the high of the green candle
that took the rsi out of the oversold
zone stop loss goes below this green
candle so very narrow stop loss
aim for one to one were a 1.5 to 1 risk
reward ratio
in this chart we found a short signal
price was trading well below the 50
exponential moving average and the ema
was sloping downwards the three period
rsi pulled back and rose above the 80
level so we expect a momentum shift to
the downside the adx stayed above the 30
level indicating that the trend was
strong so we had a volatility
confirmation we entered short at the low
of the red candle that took the rsi out
of the overbought zone stop loss above
this red candle this was a successful
two to one risk reward trade
and here's another short signal up here
this was a 50 50 signal because as price
corrected it moved slightly above the 50
ema but as this red candle returned to
the ema and the rsi moved from
overbought levels we pulled the trigger
with the four beams doubles above this
red candle
immediately we had a big red momentum
candle below the ema and after a period
of consolidation we reached our profit
target
and also observed this invalid setup
price was below the moving average the
rsi pulled back once again and rose
above 80
but the atx was below 30.
although in hindsight it was a great
signal we followed the rules and skipped
the signal
in this example a downtrend is obvious
as price is well below the 50 ema breaks
new lows and the moving average is
sloping downward
the rsi pulls up past dd level and price
pulls into a former support turned
potential resistance zone
remember even though we rely on
indicators to find our signals location
is very important
always try to take signals from levels
where price found support or resistance
as the edx was above 30. the setup also
checked the volatility condition the
entry is below this red candle and the
stop loss above it
remember that you are scoping you
operate with narrow stop-loss orders
always close a part of your position
when you reach a one-to-one risk load
ratio in this way you don't risk ending
up with nothing after having seen price
move into profits
here's an important filter to reduce
false signals by over 70 percent
pay attention
if the next candle after the signal
candle the one that pulls the rsi out of
the overbought or oversold zone doesn't
break the signal candle you skip the
signal
basically you want immediate momentum
after a signal
look at this example we had the
potential short entry price below the 50
ema
rsi rose above the 80 level and the adx
was above 30.
then we had this candle right here the
signal candle which took the rsi out of
overbought zone but look at the next
candle it didn't break the low of the
signal candle so no trade
this filter is extremely important an
entry at the close of this red candle
would have been a losing trade but with
this filter you avoided the loss
here's the filter in action avoiding
another loss
we had a price above the 50ma the rsi
moved below 20 and the adx was above 30.
a valid signal but the trigger never
came the high of the signal green candle
which took the rsi above the 20 level
was unbroken on the next scandal the
next candle was a bearish one so we
ignored the setup and avoided the loss
remember that we want immediate momentum
please be disciplined and don't ignore
this filter it will save you many many
losing trades
the second signal was valid the same
setup rsi below 20 adx above 30 priced
above the 50ma and the next candle after
the signal one took out the high of the
candle
a successful one-to-one risk reward
trade
here are several tips to increase your
win rate
never trade when the price breaks the 50
ema several times in a short period of
time you want a sloping moving average
when price moves above and below the
moving average it usually signals a
consolidation period
number two trade from levels of support
and resistance
although we rely on indicators location
is very important that's why most
trading systems fail that's because most
of them don't take into account the
basic price action
this means that you need to take trades
at or around certain price levels such
location points are usually support and
resistance supply and demand fibonacci
levels or swing highs and lows
take trades from these levels and you'll
see consistent results
number three stick to trading signals
which form during active market hours if
you're sculpting forex or main indices
these instruments are traded the most
between the time the london trading
session begins and when the us session
ends
after that the volume drops off and
there are no big orders coming into the
market to cause a significant move
and four pay attention to spreads being
a scoping setup you want narrow spreads
the aim is to exploit sudden changes in
the market liquidity for quick gains but
without low spreads your profit will
diminish the key to a successful scoping
strategy is to focus on liquid markets
with narrow spreads as this reduces
trading costs
[Music]
as always if you got any value from this
and learn something new drop a like to
help us with youtube algorithm and make
sure you click the bell icon to stay in
touch when new videos are released
until next time