One of the most difficult market conditions
is the notorious sideways market, which can
affect trading performance if you fail to
adjust accordingly.
In this video, I will share a step by step
process to help you tackle a sideways market
for potentially better trading results.
Step number one is to learn to identify a
sideways market.
This step seems intuitive and obvious but
is often ignored by traders.
A sideways market is obviously one where price
action will not roll in one definitive direction,
(up or down) but run side to side through
short bursts of movements up AND down, reflecting
major indecision in the market.
A consolidation or sideways phase in the market
may be easy to spot – even for newer traders
– when it has already formed, but can be
a real challenge to spot as it is forming
when the market is transitioning from a trending
phase to a consolidation phase.
It will usually take traders quite a few losses
before they eventually realize the market
has lost the trend and decisive direction.
Contrary to a trending market, a sideways
market will often comprise of brief periods
of strong price action in one direction that
will often reverse shortly after, usually
from short term support and resistance levels
formed recently.
As illustrated in this example, many short
term levels in a narrow range form a key characteristic
of consolidation phases themselves and can
be early indicators of a market that could
possibly be transitioning into a sideways
phase.
On the contrary, a strong trending market
will usually pack enough strength to push
through minor areas with relative ease.
Step number 2: define the range
Once you have identified that your market
is in (or is entering) a consolidation phase,
one of the first steps to take is to clearly
establish the limits or the range of the consolidation
phase itself.
Usually, these phases will have a clearly
defined upper and lower range, marked by either
side to side support and resistance levels
or angular trend lines and channels.
Identifying the range is practically marking
out your battle field, meaning how much of
a playing field do you actually possess.
And this is very important because a consolidation
phase that is too narrow, it’s not worth
trading at all.
You need ranges wide enough to allow you to
trade with caution.
The wider the range the more ‘space’ you
technically have to take and manage your trade.
In a very narrow range, as the one in this
chart, trading could be more risky as trouble
areas and potential support and resistance
levels could be grouped very close together,
making it hard to expect much from price movements.
Defining the range gives you a more clear
perspective of the bigger picture.
Knowing the upper and lower limits of the
trading range also allows you to watch the
range itself for a potential breakout to either
side.
This is especially useful when the top and
bottom levels of the consolidation phase are
defined by angular trend lines, like in a
wedge pattern that is slowly constricting
price action, leading to a possible breakout.
Step no.3: Identify the mid range and other
internal levels of support/resistance
The next step is to highlight all the areas
within the trading range that could potentially
cause price to hold as support or resistance.
They key here is to identify all levels.
Often, traders will be glued to the larger
more obvious regions, which in the case of
consolidating markets is often just the top
and lower end of the consolidation range itself.
The trick is to identify ALL levels of potential
support and resistance.
In a weak market that is struggling for sustained
momentum, even the minor areas of support
and resistance can cause the price to hold
up.
Hence all possible troubles areas – major
and minor – need to be settled into your
trade management and planning phase.
While doing so doesn’t entirely eliminate
the notorious ‘surprise’ factor of a sideways
market, it does eliminate a lot of ambiguity
around the seemingly unpredictable price action.
Of prime importance in sideways markets is
often the mid range of the area.
The mid range tends to act as a pivot for
the price as it moves back and forth from
the consolidation range.
This is basically the 50% Fibonacci level
between the range high and the range low.
Generally, above the mid range price is bullish
and below the mid range is bearish, range
high will act as resistance and the range
low will act as support.
Now, even though you may have outlined all
the possible areas on the chart that could
potentially cause trouble for the price as
it hits these regions, you need to factor
in the uncertainty that comes along with trading
in a weak non-decisive market.
Just as the price can bounce and spike up
and down the short and long-term levels within
the consolidation range, it may still be prone
to spikes or otherwise strong and sudden periods
of sharp movements in either direction off
a seemingly clear level within the range.
This likelihood calls for a safe and conservative
trading style.
Whether that involves placing conservative
stops on the chart, using trailing stops,
watching the trade live (if you day trade
or scalp the market) or taking quick profits
at brief intervals, you must take all actions
necessary to safeguard yourself from reversing
market action.
Take a look at this example of a seemingly
unpredictable bounce during sideways market
action.
Notice how price pulls back from the region
marked with this circle, even though it would
be hard to categorize the area as a clear
support and resistance level.
We are well under the top end of the range
and also further away from the midrange support
and resistance level.
It is these kinds of pullbacks that require
conservative trade management when the market
is choppy and indecisive.
You need to find a Balance between Aggression
and Conservation.
While it’s very important not to be over
aggressive when trading a sideways market,
it is also just as important not to be ultra
conservative either.
In a sideways market, because market sentiment
is weak, managing the trade too tight can
often result in a ‘suffocated’ trade as
price whipsaws within the trading range bouncing
off minor and major support and resistance
levels found internally within the range.
For example, moving the stop to breakeven
as soon as a trade moves in a sideways market
holds a very strong chance of hitting it.
The strategy could well have been intended
to safeguard against choppy price action,
but ultra-conservative trade management doesn’t
help record consistent results in a sideways
market either.
It is easy to see how several trades executed
in a sideways market – each resulting in
either a breakeven trade or a minor loss–
because of adopting ultra conservative trade
management-, would not be benefiting your
account equity much at all.
In fact, for such a trader, avoiding trading
in a sideways market altogether might actually
be a smarter move as that eliminates the risk
entirely.
But for other traders who wish to improve
their sideways market trading skills, it is
crucial to find the perfect balance between
aggression and conservation when it comes
to trade management.
Sometimes a chart can look messy and it can
be difficult to choose a range high and range
low.
It can be just as simple as picking the range
that fits the best.
Try different possibilities and see where
and how price reacts to a certain level.
Also, look for confluence.
If multiple important levels line up, it’s
more likely price will reject or bounce at
that level.
This confluence can include an important support,
resistance, or even a moving average if you
use one.
There are many ways to trade a range, but
let me share the strategies that work for
me.
The classic trade is to search for price action
patterns at the upper and lower levels of
the range, trading the bounce from that levels.
My favorite range trading strategy is fading
the breakout.
You need to search for this scenario: a low
broken after a down move or a high broken
after up move.
Next, I wait for a close back inside the range
or even for a retest.
Stop loss below/above the failed breakout,
meaning the most recent lows (or highs) and
I target range high (or low), depending on
the case.
Also, if the range is wide enough, trading
the midrange can provide high probability
setups.
Above the mid-range price is bullish, below
the mid range, price is bearish.
And here is an important tip.
Even though we are in a range, the previous
trend of an asset is obviously very important.
A trade that goes with the recent trend is
more likely to play out compared to a trade
against the trend.
I prefer to trade range setups that go with
the previous trend, so they have a higher
probability of playing out.
Trading a range can just utilize support and
resistance levels, but it can also involve
the use of indicators.
Such technical indicators, such as the Relative
Strength Index (RSI) or Stochastics can be
utilized to confirm the overbought and oversold
conditions that often follow price movements
at the top and bottom of a trading range.
Or can reveal a divergence at the top or bottom
of the range, which can be a powerful sign
that the range will hold and a trade inside
the range can be taken.
Range trading is a very useful skill to have
because most markets don’t trend all of
the time.
If you correctly identify the range, time
your entry and control your risk exposure
you can make some decent profits even if the
markets are not moving decisive in one direction.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay in touch when we release
new videos.
Until next time.