The entire SMC industry is built
on a multi-million dollar lie.
They took 80-year-old price action
concepts, gave them new names like
'order blocks' and 'fair value gaps,' and
sold them back to you as 'hidden knowledge.'
In this video, I'm going to prove it. I'll show
you the original patterns, side-by-side, so you
never have to pay for this information again.
Market structure
Market structure stands as one of the purest
forms of price reading, whether you call it
price action or smart money concepts.
The core stays the same: price makes
higher highs and higher lows in uptrends,
lower highs and lower lows in downtrends.
In basic price action, you spot a trend
by connecting these highs and lows.
A possible trend change happens
when price breaks this pattern.
Smart money concepts named this process
differently, but look at the same
thing - price breaking its previous rhythm.
This chart perfectly shows how price action
and smart money concepts describe the same
market behaviors, with different names.
Price moves up making higher highs and higher
lows, until a key point where structure breaks.
In pure price action terms, you spot a trend by
watching how price climbs in a stair-step pattern.
Each push up creates a new high,
followed by a smaller pullback
that holds above the previous low.
This forms the basic trend structure.
Notice how in both sides of the
chart, the pattern looks identical.
That's because whether you call it
"trend continuation" or "break of
structure," the price behavior stays the same.
The market continues moving higher until it hits
a point where the pattern changes.
Smart money concepts simply gave
new names to these classic price patterns.
Both methods pay special attention to these
structure breaks at key levels.
Support and resistance zones
matter in both approaches.
The market often changes
direction at these points, showing shifts
in control between buyers and sellers.
Where price action traders see a "trend reversal,"
smart money traders spot a "change of character."
Both describe that moment when price fails to make
a new high, and instead breaks below a key level.
This horizontal line on both sides
marks this key turning point.
In price action, this represents a support
level that, once broken, signals trend reversal.
Smart money concepts call the same level a "change
of character", when price shifts direction.
Look at how price builds momentum before the
reversal. It doesn't just flip instantly.
Instead, it forms a series of pushes higher,
each one showing less strength than the last.
This weakness shows up in both trading
approaches - it's just labeled differently.
Also, both methods value
higher timeframe analysis.
Structure on larger timeframes gives
context to smaller timeframe moves.
So, whether you follow price action or smart money
concepts, you watch the same price movements,
you look for the same shifts in market
behavior, and trade the same opportunities.
The renaming of these patterns
didn't change their effectiveness.
Order blocks
Order blocks represent one of
the clearest examples of how smart money concepts
simply renamed traditional price action patterns.
At their core, order blocks mark
areas where big market players enter
trades with significant volume.
In pure price action analysis,
traders always watched for strong momentum
candles that kicked off major moves.
These candles stood out because they
showed clear control, either buyers or
sellers taking charge with conviction.
Smart money concepts just gave these
candles a fancier name - order blocks.
The mechanics stay identical. A bearish
order block forms when price moves
up, then reverses down aggressively.
Price action traders always saw this as a
supply zone - where sellers overwhelmed buyers.
The bullish version shows up when
price drops, then reverses up.
This is what price action
traders called demand zones.
Smart money concepts added
specific rules about these zones.
They say the best order blocks won't
see price trade past these candle.
But price action traders noticed this too -
they just called it a strong reversal level.
The market maker angle
explains why these zones work.
When big players need to fill large orders,
they create artificial moves in both directions.
They open positions at the order
block level, making it a key
price zone they'll want to return to later.
This matches perfectly with how price action
traders always viewed strong reversal candles.
They knew these levels often got retested, because
they marked important market turning points.
The smart money framework just explains
why these retests happen.
In fact, you'll often find
order blocks at major market highs and lows.
This makes sense in both approaches - these
are the zones where big moves start
and where trading volume concentrates.
Price action traders always watched
these areas for potential reversals.
The validity rules stay consistent too.
Both methods watch how price behaves
when it returns to these zones.
A true order block, like a strong
support or resistance level, should
show clear reaction when tested.
Market structure plays a
key role in both approaches.
Order blocks matter more when
they break nearby levels.
SMC traders value a level that
breaks the market structure.
At the same time, price action traders
always gave more weight to reversal
candles that led to new high or lows.
Both methods recognize that not all
strong candles become important levels.
The surrounding market context matters most.
An order block, like any price action pattern,
needs the right market conditions to work.
I hope you understand that price
tells the same story, whether you
use smart money terms or price action language.
Order blocks simply show where big players entered
trades. Price action shows strong momentum shifts.
Both describe the same market behavior - just with
different words.
Liquidity sweeps
Liquidity sweeps form a basic market pattern that
existed long before smart
money concepts named them.
In SMC terms, you’ll know them as
liquidity sweeps or liquidity grabs.
In price action terms, these are simply
false breakouts or bull and bear traps,
where price pushes past key levels
to trap traders on the wrong side.
You'll spot these traps at
key market highs and lows.
In an uptrend, price shoots below
recent lows, triggering stop losses
and scaring traders out of good positions.
In downtrends, price spikes above recent
highs, trapping late buyers before dropping.
The mechanics work like this: Big players need
to find enough orders to fill their positions.
They push price into areas where they know
other traders place stops.
When these stops trigger,
they create instant buying or selling pressure
that big players use to enter their positions.
Smart money concepts simply
added structure to this pattern.
They look for liquidity pools - areas
with concentrated buy or sell orders.
These pools often sit just above
resistance or below support,
where traders typically place their orders.
The validation process follows simple rules.
For a bull trap, price breaks above
a recent high, then reverses sharply.
For a bear trap, price dips below
a recent low before bouncing hard.
These moves happen fast,
catching unprepared traders.
You just need to understand how
institutional traders use these sweeps.
In bullish markets, they need sell-side liquidity
below lows, to fill their long positions
This fuels the next trend move up. They create
these sweeps deliberately to find enough orders.
During bearish swings, look for price to pull up
to key levels. If no liquidity exists in previous
moves, smart money will create it through these
sweeps. They build the trap before triggering it.
So when trading bullish markets, it’s best
to place buy orders after a bear trap.
You're buying into sell stops,
just like big players do.
For bearish markets, you sell near
recent highs after a bull trap.
Whether you call this a false breakout
or a liquidity sweep, this concept works
because it exploits basic trader psychology.
Most traders expect breakouts to continue.
When price reverses instead, it forces
quick exits that fuel the new move.
Smart money concepts just explain the
institutional side of this pattern.
These sweeps often create decent reversals.
Once trapped traders realize their mistake,
they rush to exit.
This adds momentum to the new move.
The key lies in spotting potential
sweep zones before they happen.
Look for areas where traders
might cluster their stops.
Price tends to hunt these zones
during major market turns.
The more obvious the level, the
more likely it becomes a target.
Mitigation
In Smart Money Concepts,
mitigation is just another name for what
price traders call retests or pullbacks.
It’s the process of managing losses or offsetting
unfavorable positions, when the market moves
against an institutional trader’s initial entry.
Price action traders recognized this behavior but
didn’t give the institutional context behind it.
SMC just gave it a different name and explained
how big players adjust their strategies when the
market doesn't go as they expected right away.
To begin, let’s break down how
mitigation works in the context of SMC.
Mitigation happens when the market retraces
to a level where these institutions can reduce
or completely offset their losing positions.
For example, price might return to a specific
level, allowing them to close their earlier
“buy” trades at breakeven or a smaller loss,
while simultaneously entering sell positions.
Essentially, mitigation allows them to transition
from a losing “buy” position into a profitable
sell position, in the same price move.
Price action traders have always tracked this
behavior, though they described it differently.
They saw these retracements as pullbacks
or retests of previous levels.
For example, if price broke
below a key support level,
price action traders would look for the market to
return to that level, before continuing downward.
They’d call this a "retest," where the
broken support becomes new resistance.
SMC traders, on the other hand, would
call this same movement "mitigation,"
especially if they believe it’s tied
to institutions managing their risk.
Mitigation often happens because institutions
can’t execute their massive orders all at once.
Their volume is too large, and doing
so would create too much slippage,
where the price moves unfavorably
as their trades are filled.
Instead, they split their
orders into smaller chunks.
This is why you often see price revisiting
key levels before a strong continuation.
Take this example: Suppose the market is
in a downtrend, and price begins retracing
higher after a significant drop.
This retracement might test the
last bearish order block (the last up
candle before the sharp move down).
Institutions that opened sell positions
during the drop may have also opened temporary
buy positions to hedge against risk.
As price retraces to the order block,
they mitigate these temporary buy positions,
closing them at breakeven or a small loss.
At the same time, they stack
additional sell positions to
continue profiting from the downtrend.
Price action traders have always observed
this behavior, in the form of pullbacks
to resistance levels or supply zones.
For them, these levels represent opportunities
to trade in the direction of the trend after
a pause or minor correction.
Mitigation isn’t random. It follows
predictable patterns tied to market structure.
In a bullish market, institutions may mitigate
their sell trades during retracements to
key support levels. In a bearish market,
they may mitigate their buy trades during
pullbacks to key resistance levels.
These levels often align with price
action concepts like swing highs,
swing lows, or supply and demand zones.
The concept of mitigation or retest
offers a significant advantage. It
explains why price often returns to
certain levels before continuing its trend.
Let’s say you’re tracking a bearish trend,
and price breaks below a major support level.
Instead of chasing the breakdown, you wait for
price to retrace to the broken support.
This level now acts as resistance,
and the retracement offers an ideal
entry point for a continuation trade.
SMC traders would call this mitigation,
where institutions are offsetting their
earlier trades at the retest level.
Mitigation also highlights an important
truth: institutions aren’t perfect.
They don’t always get their entries right.
Just like retail traders, they deal with losses
and use retracements to manage those losses.
This understanding helps to demystify
the market. Smart money isn’t invincible.
They face the same challenges as everyone
else, but they have the tools and strategies
to manage risk effectively.
Mitigation can also explain why
some retracements go deeper than expected.
Institutions may need to push price slightly
beyond the obvious level to find enough
liquidity to close their earlier trades.
For example, if price is retracing to
a bearish order block, it might trade
slightly above the block, before reversing.
This deeper retracement occurs because the
institutions need to trigger more buy orders, more
liquidity, to close their earlier sell positions.
Price action traders might call this a "deep
pullback," while SMC traders see it as part of
the mitigation process.
Inducement
Inducement is a core principle in smart money
concepts and is what price action traders
have long referred to as "trap setups."
It’s the market’s way of luring traders
into poor positions, by creating false moves
that look convincing at first, but ultimately
work against those who fall for them.
While the term “inducement” might sound
like a fresh idea, the behavior it describes
has always been visible on price charts.
It’s just another way of understanding
how the market manipulates
participants to generate liquidity.
As I said before, smart money don’t have
the luxury of entering and exiting trades like
small traders. Their massive trade sizes require
liquidity, and they can’t execute their positions
without triggering significant price movement.
Here’s where inducement comes into play.
Institutions create false moves to attract
traders into the market, which generates the
liquidity they need to fill their orders.
These false moves often appear as breakouts,
double tops/bottoms, or other familiar patterns
that trap retail traders on the wrong side.
Take a simple example: price is trending upward
and forms a possible flag formation.
Retail traders see this resistance and
prepare to go long when price breaks
it, expecting the market to continue.
Institutions, however, see this as an opportunity.
They drive price slightly above the resistance,
triggering stop loss orders
from those who were short,
and enticing breakout buyers to enter the market.
After trapping these traders, the market reverses
sharply, leaving breakout buyers stuck in
losing positions and forcing them to exit.
Inducement is often tied to
the concept of liquidity pools.
These pools represent areas on the chart
where stop losses or pending orders cluster.
For retail traders, these are the obvious
levels, such as previous highs or lows,
equal tops of bottoms, or areas of consolidation.
Institutions target these zones, because they
know that triggering the orders in these areas
will create liquidity to support their trades.
Price action traders have always observed
this behavior, describing it as stop
hunts or false breakouts. SMC gave it a new
name—inducement—but the idea remains the same.
Consider double tops and double bottoms,
which are classic price action patterns.
Retail traders often see these as reversal
setups, expecting price to turn around when
it retests the same level.
But institutions use these
patterns to their advantage.
They allow price to form what
looks like a double top or bottom, attracting
traders who base their entries on these setups.
Then, they push price slightly
beyond the level to trigger
stop losses, only to reverse shortly after.
This is why double tops and bottoms often fail
before eventually playing out—the initial move
is an inducement designed to generate liquidity.
Breaker blocks
Breaker blocks are just a refined version
of the price action concept of role reversal.
They highlight the same behavior of support
turning into resistance, or resistance
turning into support, but with an added
focus on liquidity and institutional activity.
Price action traders have been using this
concept for years, even if they
didn’t call it a breaker block.
In SMC terms, a breaker block is basically
a failed order block causing a shift in
market structure, and acting as a level
of support or resistance for the price.
So, if price closes below the low of a
bullish order block, you can mark that
failed order block as a bearish breaker block,
which will now act as a resistance for price.
If price closes above the high of a bearish
order block, you can mark that failed order
block as a bullish breaker block, which
will now act as a support for price.
Price action traders recognized this
behavior early on and simply called
it "support turning into resistance"
or "resistance turning into support."
This transition marks a shift
in market sentiment. In price
action terms, this is called role reversal.
When price revisits these levels, it's often
a critical moment where big players show their
hand, either defending or rejecting the level.
You see these flips all the time: price is in
an uptrend and hits a key resistance level.
Price consolidates below this level
before making a strong breakout above it.
Later, when price retraces back to this breakout
level, the old resistance now acts as support.
Price bounces off this level and continues upward.
Smart money traders would call this level
a bullish breaker block.
These zones often act as
magnets for price. Big players use them to
manage their trades, either by mitigating
earlier positions or by entering new ones.
Whether you call it a breaker block or support
flip, the principle remains: these levels mark the
battleground where institutions make their moves.
Breaker blocks also tie into market structure.
They are most effective when aligned with the
overall trend.
For instance,
a bullish breaker block in an uptrend has a higher
probability of holding, than one in a downtrend.
A bearish breaker block in a downtrend
is more reliable than one in an uptrend.
Price action traders have always understood this,
prioritizing retests that align with the trend.
Fair Value Gaps
Fair value gaps are another example of how smart
money concepts are derived from price action.
In both cases, Fair Value Gaps point to
imbalances in the market, where supply
and demand are not evenly matched,
leading to sharp, directional price moves.
Price action traders have long observed
these imbalances, describing
them as gaps or inefficiencies,
left behind when price moves too quickly, to
allow for balanced trading at certain levels.
SMC formalizes this observation, defining Fair
Value Gaps within a clear three-candle sequence,
and connecting them to institutional activity.
In price action, a fair value gap is
identified as a strong imbalance between candles.
Specifically, it occurs when price moves sharply,
leaving a visible space on the chart – a gap
– between the first and third candle’s wicks,
in a three-candle structure.
This gap signals that price
moved so decisively in one direction, that the
opposing side of the trade couldn’t keep up.
This leads to a "void" or imbalance in the market,
which price often revisits at a later time,
to "fill" as it seeks equilibrium.
Consider a bullish Fair Value Gap.
Price starts with a small bullish candle, the
first candle in the sequence, then explodes upward
with a large bullish candle, the second candle.
Finally, a third candle follows, but its lower
wick doesn’t overlap with the upper wick of
the first candle. This creates a gap between
the first and third candles, signaling that during
the sharp upward move, there wasn’t enough selling
pressure to counterbalance the buying.
Price action traders see this as an area
of imbalance, while SMC traders
call it a fair value gap.
The idea is the same: this gap represents
a level that price may return to,
either to fill the imbalance or to allow
institutions to mitigate earlier positions.
A bearish fair value gap works the
same way but in the opposite direction.
This gap indicates a strong imbalance in favor
of sellers, implying that price may revisit
this level in the future, to restore balance.
Fair value gaps often contain what SMC traders
call an "institutional candle",
within the three-candle sequence.
In price action terms, these are simply strong
momentum candles with above-average volume.
They represent areas where big players
entered the market with significant orders,
pushing price sharply in one direction.
For example, in a bullish gap, the large
bullish candle in the middle of the
sequence is the institutional candle.
It’s the clearest evidence of aggressive buying
by big players, which caused the sharp imbalance.
In a bearish gap, the large bearish candle in the
middle marks where institutions
heavily sold, creating the gap.
This institutional candle helps traders identify
where smart money might re-engage with the market.
When price revisits the fair value gap, it
often reacts near the institutional candle,
either reversing or continuing its previous trend.
Price action traders might describe this as
price revisiting a "key level" or
a even a "demand or supply zone”.
When price returns to this zone, big players
might step in again to defend their positions,
causing price to bounce and resume its trend.
For price action traders, this is simply
a retracement to a support zone.
For SMC traders, it’s a revisit to
the fair value gap, where institutional
activity is likely to take place.
This is why fair value gaps
act as magnets for price.
Whether you call them fair value gaps or
imbalances, the idea is the same: these gaps are
key zones where price is likely to return
ICT Power of 3
The “ICT Power of 3” is presented as a unique
approach to decoding smart money manipulations.
It focuses on three distinct phases of
price movement: Accumulation, Manipulation,
and Distribution. While the concept might seem
innovative at first, it is actually a rebranding
of the well-established Wyckoff model.
The phases of the “ICT Power of 3” align
almost perfectly with those outlined by
Richard Wyckoff’s methodology, which has
been used to analyze market behavior for decades.
The first phase is the Accumulation. In the ICT
framework, this phase represents a period where
smart money begin to build their positions,
without causing noticeable price movement.
Price action during this phase typically
consolidates, moving sideways in a range.
This behavior is no different from Wyckoff’s
accumulation phase, where large players
quietly accumulate assets at lower prices,
in preparation for an upward move.
In the Wyckoff model, the accumulation
phase often includes a “spring,” a sharp downward
move that breaks below the established range.
This move is designed to trigger stop
losses from traders who are long,
and to encourage others to go short.
Once this liquidity is collected, price reverses
sharply and begins the mark-up phase.
In the “ICT Power of 3”,
this same behavior is labeled as Manipulation.
The mark-up phase in Wyckoff’s model corresponds
to the Distribution phase in the “ICT Power
of 3”. After institutions have completed their
accumulation and manipulated the market to collect
liquidity, they begin to push price higher.
This is where the real trend unfolds, and price
moves decisively in the intended direction.
Smart money uses this phase to
offload their positions to latecomers,
who are now chasing the trend.
In Wyckoff’s terms, this is the
"mark-up" period, where price climbs
steadily as demand outweighs supply.
In ICT terminology, this is Distribution, where
the positions accumulated earlier are sold off,
into the hands of retail traders
who missed the initial move.
So both the Wyckoff model and the “Power
of 3” recognize that large players need
to manipulate price to generate the
liquidity required for their trades.
Whether it’s labeled as a “spring,” “up thrust,”
or “manipulation,” the goal is the same:
to trap traders and create the conditions
necessary for a significant price move.
So no, the Power of 3 is not a groundbreaking
revelation. It’s just a reinterpretation of the
Wyckoff model, rebranded with new terminology.
Price action vs SMC traders
Now, price action traders and SMC traders
are often seen as two distinct groups with
different methods and perspectives.
This has led to many debates and
even a sense of rivalry between the two.
But when you strip away the terminology
and look at the core principles, it becomes
clear that they’re trading the same thing.