$100 a day from trading! Pocket change for some,
life-changing for others! If you stay till the
end, you’ll discover how to day trade using smart
money concepts, to hit this target every day!
Market structure
So when I started trading,
I had no clue what I was doing.
I thought fancy indicators
were the key to success.
I just wanted to know the
trend and find a simple entry point!
But I couldn't figure out which way
the market was going!
It was confusing because
different time frames showed different trends.
All changed when I ditched all indicators
and started reading market structure!
This the foundation of everything we do!
A bullish market is when prices keep going
up. You'll see higher highs and higher lows.
This means each time the price drops,
it doesn't go as low as before.
And when it goes up, it goes
higher than the last peak.
When price breaks through a previous
high, we call it a "break of structure".
This is a key moment. It shows
the market is getting stronger.
Now, real markets aren't perfect.
They don't move in straight lines.
That's why we need to focus on these swing highs
and lows. These are the big turns in price.
A swing low is the lowest
point that led to a swing high.
So, when you see a new high form, look back. The
lowest point before that high, is your swing low!
This might sound basic, but it's super
important and many traders get it wrong.
They zoom in too close and miss the bigger
picture. They might think the market is going
down when it's really still going up overall.
Let's say you're looking at a small part of
the chart. You might see lower lows and lower
highs. You might think the market is going down.
But if you zoom out, you might see that
this is just a small dip in a bigger
upward trend. If you sell here, you will
lose money when the price keeps going up.
That's why it's crucial to map out
your swing highs and lows correctly.
It helps you see the big picture
and trade in the right direction.
In a bearish market, it's the opposite.
You're looking for lower highs and lower
lows. The highest point that led to
a new low becomes your swing high.
And, everything between a swing high and
a swing low is just "internal structure".
It's the small moves within the bigger trend.
Don't get too caught up in these small moves.
Keep your eye on the bigger trend.
Here's another important point: After a
break of structure, always expect a pullback.
This means after the price breaks through a
previous high or low, it will usually come back
a bit, before continuing in the same direction.
Many new traders make this mistake here.
They see the price break through a level
and immediately want to buy or sell.
But the smart move is to wait for the
pullback. This gives you a better entry point.
Now, let's talk about strong and weak highs and
lows. This concept can really boost your trading.
A low's job is to make a high. A high's job is to
make a low. In a bullish market, we have a
series of strong lows. A strong low is one
that succeeds in making a higher high.
If a high fails to make a lower low,
we call it a weak high. This is important for
setting targets. In a bullish market, we like
to buy at strong lows and target weak highs.
Think about it this way: In a bullish market,
we're trying to catch higher lows. These are
the easy trades, the continuations. In a bearish
market, we're looking to catch lower highs.
This concept gives you a clean framework
for mapping structure and setting targets.
Now let's look at trend changes, also known as
changes of character. A bullish market doesn't
last forever, and neither does a bearish one.
In a bullish market, we're seeing higher
highs and higher lows. But at some point,
price will break below a strong low and form
a lower low. This is where the trend changes.
Some traders want to see both a lower low and a
lower high before they confirm a trend change.
That’s because sometimes, what looks
like a trend change can be a fake-out.
The market might grab some liquidity
below a low and then continue up.
I like to keep it simple. As soon as I see that
lower low form, I consider it a trend change.
I then look for the lower high to form
so I can trade the new bearish trend.
This links back to our strong
and weak highs and lows concept.
When a strong low is taken out, it means a lot
of money stepped in to push the price down.
This creates a strong high. We can
use this to build our trade ideas.
The same applies in reverse for a
bearish to bullish trend change.
We look for that higher high, then try
to catch the higher low that follows.
These changes of character aren't perfect.
They will often give false signals,
because we bet on a reversal.
A reversal is much harder
to spot that a continuation.
In a bullish trend, we look for that first
bearish change of character, to signal the
start of a pullback. Then we wait for a bullish
change of character to signal the end of the
pullback and the formation of a higher low.
This approach works for both continuations
and reversals.
Supply/demand
After the market structure, the next concept
you should master is supply and demand.
Supply and demand zones are key spots on
charts where big players make their moves.
These zones show where there's a big
gap between buyers and sellers.
To find them, look for quick, strong
price moves that suddenly reverse.
This shows a big imbalance
that made the price jump.
To mark these zones, find
where the big move started.
There are different types of zones to watch for.
First are the base zones: These form when price
stays in a small range for a while, then
breaks out. The edges of this range are where
orders build up. When price comes back to these
levels after a breakout, it's likely to react.
We also have pivot zones: These form at key
turning points, like swing highs and lows. They're
often marked by one or two special candles.
For a demand zone, look for a strong down candle,
where the next candle closes above its high.
This shows a shift from selling to buying.
For a supply zone, it's the
opposite: a strong up candle,
where the next candle closes below its low.
Considering the price action structure,
there are two main types of zones:
First are continuation ones:
This happens when there's a trend and price
pulls back before continuing. These are
called rally-base-rally zones in uptrends,
and drop-base-drop zones in downtrends.
The second type is reversal zones: This
happens when price changes trend direction.
These are called drop-base-rally
or rally-base-drop patterns.
Supply and demand zones aren't random. They
show where buyers and sellers are most out
of balance. Big price moves often mean there was
a mismatch between buying and selling pressure.
The key is how long price stays
in the zone. When there's a big
imbalance, price won't stay long.
It will quickly move up or down.
So, look for zones where price only stayed
for a short time before making a strong move.
The less time spent there, the more
out of balance supply and demand are.
This means a higher chance of a
good trade when price comes back.
Also focus on fresh zones
that haven't been tested yet.
When price revisits a zone, it can
use up some of the waiting orders.
This makes the imbalance less extreme.
So, the more times a zone is hit,
the weaker it gets. That's why it's important
to know the difference between an untested
zone and one that's been hit a few times.
The trading chances are very different.
To check if a zone will
hold, look for these things:
First, clear break of structure: Price
needs to make a strong move away from
the zone and break nearby swing highs or
lows. If price just hangs around the zone,
it might not be strong.
And second, inducement:
This means there's liquidity in front of
the zone that could absorb moves against it.
For a demand zone, you want to see
buy orders stacked up in front.
This could be a swing low
or a consolidation pattern.
It shows traders are waiting to buy at that price.
If there's no liquidity and price just hits the
zone, big players might not get involved.
To judge how strong a supply or demand zone is,
look at these things:
First, speed of price movement:
How fast does price move away from the zone after
it forms? Faster moves usually mean stronger
zones. Quick, big moves show a strong imbalance.
Second, time spent at the zone: How long does
price stay at the level before moving? Less
time often means it's a key turning point. If
price just touches a demand zone and starts
rising right away, it might mean big buyers
stepped in, and bought up all the supply.
Third, size of the move: How far does price go
after hitting the zone? Bigger moves usually
mean stronger zones. If price barely moves,
it's not a good sign. But a long move in
the opposite direction after testing a
zone means it's probably important.
Fourth, volume: Look for more volume
when the zone forms. This shows there's
a lot of interest at that price, and big
players might be buying or selling there.
And fifth, break of market structure: Does the
zone cause a break in the market structure? Zones
that do this are usually stronger. It takes a lot
of money to break market structure, so these
zones are more likely to hold in the future.
So when you're trading with supply and
demand zones, remember these key points:
Look for explosive price movements.
Find zones where price only stays
for a short time before moving sharply.
Focus on fresh zones that haven't been tested yet.
Check for clear breaks of structure.
Look for inducement in front of the zone.
And consider how fresh the zone is.
Liquidity
Day trading is all about understanding how the
market moves. And one key concept is liquidity,
the amount of orders in the market.
It's essentially how much supply and
demand exists at different price levels.
Liquidity is what drives market movement.
Every day, millions of traders jump
in. Many use similar strategies.
Buyers, thinking the market will go up, buy at
support. They put their stops just below it!
Sellers do the opposite. They sell at
resistance and put their stops above the highs.
Then there are breakout traders! They
set buy and sell orders around the range.
All these orders create a lot of
liquidity on both sides of a range.
And why does this matter? Well, it helps
you understand how the market moves based on
supply and demand. It's not as simple as just
buying at support and selling at resistance .
You might see a trading range after a downtrend.
Some traders, not knowing how
order flow works, might sell here.
Others might try to buy. And there are still
stop orders and breakout trades on both sides .
This is where big players come in. Banks and
hedge funds trade huge orders. They
need a lot of liquidity to do this.
Let's say a big institution wants to sell a
lot. They need to free up orders in the market.
This is done by triggering stop losses.
They might push the price up first,
hitting those stops, before selling big.
Liquidity tends to accumulate in certain
areas of the chart. These are often popular
chart patterns that many retail traders use.
First ones are old highs/lows - significant price
points from the past that stand out on the chart.
These areas are like liquidity magnets. Traders
often put their stops just beyond these levels,
creating clusters of orders. Smart
money loves to target these clusters.
Major swings, double tops and bottoms,
or any pattern with equal highs or lows,
are prime liquidity areas. Other common spots are
triangles, wedges and flags .
So when analyzing charts,
look for areas where significant buying or
selling orders are likely to be executed.
These often coincide with key
support and resistance levels,
breakouts, or areas of price congestion .
This is the simplest way to find the closest
liquidity zones. It’s all about recent
price pivots, the ups and downs in price
that stand out on a chart.
A pivot low is a low point
with higher lows on both sides.
A pivot high is the opposite - a high
point with lower highs on both sides.
And why do these matter? Well,
it's all about how traders think.
If someone buys when the price is
going up, they often put their stop-loss
order just below the last swing low.
If they're selling when the price
is going down, they put their
stop just above the last swing high.
This creates two types of liquidity:
Sell-side liquidity, where sell
stops pile up below swing lows.
And buy-side liquidity, where buy
stops gather above swing highs.
Big players in the market, the smart money,
love to hunt these areas. They place orders
to buy below the lows and sell above the
highs, hoping to trigger all those stops.
Now, let’s find the closest pivot
highs and lows on this chart.
We see a low point with higher lows on
each side - that's sell-side liquidity.
And here we spot a high with lower highs
on each side - that's buy-side liquidity.
As the market moves, these points change.
When price breaks above a swing high,
that buy-side liquidity is gone,
and we look for the next one.
Same thing when price drops below a swing low
- we find the next sell-side liquidity spot.
Sometimes, you'll see multiple
swing points close together.
These create what we call "equal highs" or
"equal lows." They're like liquidity hotspots,
where lots of stops cluster together.
Now, let's talk about some key liquidity
levels you should always keep an eye on:
First ones are previous week's high and low:
These are great for framing reversals
or as targets for price moves.
Second, previous day's high and low: These can
also frame reversals or act as price targets.
Session highs and lows: These include the high and
low from the Asian, London, and New York session.
These liquidity levels, plus the swing
pivots, give you a roadmap for the
market. They show you where big moves
might start or end. They're very useful
for planning trades within each trading day.
Smart money depend on these liquidity levels.
They often set up trades around them.
For example, if price is going up and
nearing a buy-side liquidity level, they might
get ready to sell. Because they expect a lot
of buy orders to be triggered there, which
could push price up sharply before it falls.
On the flip side, if price is dropping
towards a sell-side liquidity level,
they might prepare to buy. They're betting that
all those sell orders will create a quick drop
before price bounces back up.
Discount and premium areas
When you day trade, you should always aim to
take your trade from a discount and premium area.
Let's say you have a range.
Or you have a break of structure,
and you mark the swing low that started
the move, and the end point of the move.
Mark this range from the low to the
high using the Fibonacci tool. This
shows the middle of the range, at the 50%
Fib level. We call this the equilibrium.
Anything above the 50% is at a premium.
Anything below is at a discount.
Let's say you want to buy at the middle of
the range. If you put your stop at the low
and your target at the high, your risk to reward
is 1 to 1. But the deeper into discount you go,
the better your risk to reward gets.
The same goes for selling. If you sell
at the middle, stop at the high, and
target the low, you have a 1 to 1 risk
to reward. But as you get deeper into
premium, your risk to reward improves.
We're looking at crude oil. First, we find a
range. We have a swing low here, then price
moves up. We mark from this low to this high.
Very important, ranges expand as price moves.
So as price goes higher, we move our
Fibonacci tool up too. We keep doing
this until we see a high form.
Now, if we're looking to buy,
we want to find an entry in the discount zone.
Do we have one? Yes, there's a demand zone here.
And as price reaches into that discount
zone, it moves higher from there.
Another range, from this high down to this low.
So we mark this one out. From here, we want to see
price reach into a premium of the previous range.
We're looking for short positions, so we want
an entry in the premium zone.
Looking left, we have a supply zone.
Price reaches into here, into a
premium, and rejects the zone.
Inducement
If you want to succeed in day trading,
you also need to master inducement.
Inducement is simply a move that lures
buyers or sellers into the market,
creating liquidity pools that smart
money players use to their advantage.
Inducement can help you spot potential
reversals and entry points for trades.
Basically, you need to spot when the market's
trying to trick you. That's where inducement
comes in. It's a smart way to figure
out what the market's really up to.
So picture this: the price is
going up, and it looks like it's
about to break through a high point.
Traders who like to buy when prices
break out will be itching to get in!
And anyone who's betting on the price
going down will have their stop losses
ready to go if it breaks that high.
This is exactly when the big players, the smart
money, decide to sell. They're betting the price
will drop. This is inducement: the market shows
you one thing, but plans to do the opposite.
First, the big players gather up their positions.
That's the build-up. Then, they make it look
like the price is going one way.
That's the inducement. Finally,
they do the opposite of what everyone
expects. That's when they cash in.
So, when you're looking at a chart,
keep an eye out for these fake-outs.
If the trend's been going down, watch for
a quick jump up before it drops again.
That's your chance to sell.
If the trend's been going up,
look for a quick dip before it climbs
again. That's when you want to buy.
To find inducement, you
need to look for liquidity.
We talked before about strong highs and
lows and buy-side and sell-side liquidity.
For instance, when you see equal lows forming
a double bottom, that creates a support level.
Traders buying at this support will place their
stop losses below these lows, creating a pool
of sell-side liquidity . Smart money players can
use this liquidity to fill their own positions.
To profit from inducement, you need
to think like the big players. They're
looking to execute large orders without
moving the market against themselves.
So they use these liquidity pools to their
advantage. When you see price approaching a
strong high or low, be prepared for a potential
fake-out move before the real trend continues.
One way to use inducement in your trading
is to focus on "liquidity sweeps".
This is when price briefly moves beyond
a key level, triggering stop losses and
creating liquidity, before reversing.
These sweeps often occur just before a
significant move in the opposite direction.
When looking for inducement setups,
pay attention to fair value gaps and supply and
demand zones. These are areas on the chart where
price has moved quickly, leaving unfilled
orders. Price often returns to these areas,
creating opportunities for trades.
In this example, the price has been dropping.
Then, it tries to go lower
but can't quite make it.
There's this pivot high point nearby.
If the price breaks above that,
it could signal a change in direction.
And that's exactly what happens.
This creates what a demand zone,
and a fair value gap. It's like a magnet for
the price - it often comes back to these spots.
And watch what happens next. Before it takes
off higher, price does something tricky.
It creates a new low point, getting more
buyers interested. Then it quickly drops
below that low. This is the inducement - it's
tricking people into thinking it's going lower.
This is how inducement works
in trending markets too.
When the price is in an uptrend, look for
lows to be taken out before the next leg up.
In this particular case, we can spot several
potential entry points where the price ran
a low before continuing higher.
The key thing to watch for is how
the price closes around these old lows.
If it quickly bounces back after taking
out a low, that's a strong sign
that the uptrend is still intact.
And you need to be patient.
If you're looking at a bullish
inducement setup (where you think the price
will go up after tricking people into thinking
it's going down), wait for the price to
actually start moving up before you enter.
You might miss the absolute bottom, but
you'll also avoid a lot of false signals.
Market structure mapping will make
the difference here. I repeat,
inducement works best when it's aligned with
the overall trend or at key reversal points.
If the market's been trending up for days, an
inducement to the downside at a major demand could
signal a significant reversal.
Volume profile
In my own day trading journey, I saw immediate
improvement once I started using volume profile.
Volume profiles are one of the
most powerful trading tools.
They show how much volume
occurred at specific price levels.
This is key because it gives more useful info
than traditional volume tools, as they only
show total daily volume.
To use volume profiles,
go to the left side of your chart platform.
Look for "forecasting and measurement tools".
And add the "anchored volume profile".
Then, click on your chart where you want
to apply the profile.
The bars in the profile
show trading volume at each price level.
Bigger bars mean more volume at that price.
The middle line is the point of control
- the level with the most trading volume.
High trading volume matters because it shows
where buyers and sellers had lots of interest.
They took big action at those levels. If price
comes back to these levels in the future,
there might be interest again.
This creates potential trade
entry and exit opportunities.
But don't use volume profiles alone. Combine them
with the concepts we talked before, key points in
the market structure, or supply and demand areas.
Start by applying the anchored volume profile at
the beginning of a price move. The profile will
only calculate data after that point.
The point of control shows
where the most volume occurred.
This high-volume zone becomes an area of interest.
If price returns there, it could
present long trade chances.
Or it could be a good exit
target for short trades.
The real power comes from pairing
high-volume areas with key levels.
Zoom out and look for important
reversal points that create a key level.
If these align with your high-volume
zone, it makes that zone even stronger.
The higher quality the zone, the more likely
price will react there in the future.
Also, look for other high-volume bars
that line up with reversal points too.
These combos of volume and key levels create
high-quality zones to watch for your trades.
You can also apply the volume profile tool to
larger chart areas. This helps find the best
key zones across a wider range.
Look for points of control that
line up with multiple reversal points.
These give you key zones to focus on.
10 SMA daily chart
Now, in my first 2 years of day trading,
my biggest problem was trading the wrong trends.
I kept getting caught in false
moves and choppy markets.
One time frame would show an uptrend,
and another one a downtrend.
You might have this problem too!
Which one should you trade?
In my case, the solution was
extremely simple! I simply monitored the 10-period
Simple Moving Average on the daily chart.
If you need a simple way to filter “buy” and
“sell” trades, just use this simple method.
Price above the moving average on the daily
chart? Look for buys on shorter time frames.
If the line slopes up, it's a bullish trend.
Price below the moving average? Look for sell
trades. A downward slope means a bearish trend.
Price near or crossing the moving average
often? Wait for a clear trend or avoid trading.
It's that easy. Once you spot the daily trend with
the 10-day SMA, use this info to trade on shorter
time frames. Monitor the market structure, find
your liquidity areas, mark your supply and demand
zone and confirm these with the volume profile.
This way, you dodge false signals and choppy price
action. You only trade with the bigger trend.
This is how you day trade
using smart money concepts.
You won't get lost in a sea of
conflicting signals. Instead, you
align your trades with the main market flow. And,
you’re ready for more smart money secrets,
go ahead and watch one of these videos!