Most of the information you can find online
is usually all about retail trading.
If you look for institutional trading, you
can’t find much about it.
Smart Money trading is perhaps one of the
best kept secrets in the world of trading.
Once you discover institutional trading and
learn how Smart Money place their orders,
you can implement these concepts to your own
style of trading and see much better results.
So let me show you several smart money concepts
you must follow, in order to finally become
a profitable trader.
Indicators Lag, Price Action Leads
There is no indicator, Forex robot, or mechanical
trading system that will make you money if
you don’t understand how and why price moves.
In reality, if you rely your decisions on
indicators, you’re not really trading the
market, you’re really just plugging numbers
into a few mathematical formulas.
Indicators have absolutely no flexibility.
They are just an equation that is used over
and over again, regardless of market conditions.
Stochastics, MACD and a load of other indicators
are presenting you with lagging information.
They may look pretty on your chart, and can
help you to some degree to view a market,
but they don’t really help you predict where
the price is going in the future.
Indicators show you what has happened in the
past, but they won’t tell you what price
is going to do in the future.
Indicators used to be a powerful tool, but
those days have passed.
Stochastic was created in 1950′s, MACD in
1960′s and RSI 1970′s.
Do you see the connection?
These lagging indicators were in use before
modern computer systems took over the trading
world!
The problem is that even though computers
were invented, and people got access to technology,
they never moved away from the old way of
viewing the market.
Trading without indicators is just like eliminating
the middle man.
Instead of letting indicators to tell you
what the market is doing, you can see it for
yourself.
So, the first step, try trading for a few
weeks without indicators.
Support and resistance levels are good, but
supply and demand areas are better
Any chart is a sequence of zones where there
is supply and demand equilibrium, with supply
and demand imbalances in between.
If you are re used to trade classic support
and resistance level, I advise you to forget
about them for a second, and focus on supply
and demand zones.
Especially, the zones where the price is moving
away from with a lot of momentum.
Whenever that happens, it’s a sign that
the balance of supply and demand has shifted
in a very substantial way.
Supply and demand zones are the origins of
these price moves.
A supply zone is an area at which a lot of
sudden selling has occurred.
This resulted in an imbalance between supply
and demand, where supply greatly exceeded
demand, pushing the price down.
A demand zone is an area at which a lot of
sudden buying has occurred.
This resulted in an imbalance between supply
and demand, where demand greatly exceeded
supply, pushing the price up.
I consider supply and demand as a leading
indicator.
While traditionally, support and resistance
levels are only called as such after at least
two tests, this is not the case with supply
and demand.
You only need a supply or demand zone to be
created in order to plan a potential trade.
So use the following steps to identify supply
and demand:
1.
Find the Momentum Drive
Here you’re looking for a large price move.
Long, successive candles in one direction
work the best.
Just open any chart and it shouldn’t be
too difficult to find those.
Both the momentum (how fast is the price moving)
and the absolute distance (for far did the
price move before it stopped going in that
direction) are relevant here.
Of course, the best price moves show both
momentum and a large absolute distance.
2.
Find the Base of the Momentum Drive
After you have found the momentum drive, you
should define your base.
With the base, I mean the price area just
before the price exploded in one direction.
Often, you will see a small consolidation
before this happens and that’s the consolidation
that you’re looking for.
Especially, try to find:
• the last bearish price action before a
bullish price move
• the last bullish price action before a
bearish price move
This is the area that is responsible for the
resulting move: The base of a supply or demand
zone is where the orders were placed that
were responsible for moving the market in
such a strong way.
VSA will make the difference between a losing
and a winner trade
Volume is not difficult to understand once
the basic principles of supply and demand
are understood.
This requires you to relate the volume with
price action.
To say that the market will go up when there
is more buying (demand) than selling – and
go down when there is more selling (supply)
than buying may seem like an obvious statement.
To understand what the volume is saying to
you, you have to ask yourself “What has
the price done on a particular volume”?
Think about it, if you compare today's volume
with volume during the previous thirty bars,
it is easy to see if today's volume is higher
or lower.
But you took volume in isolation, and that’s
means very little.
Compare this volume information with the price
spread and you will then know how bullish
or bearish the market really is.
Volume spread analysis is the type of analysis
based on volumes and the spread of the candlestick.
It tries to find out the differences between
supply and demand.
The price spread is the difference between
the highest and lowest trading points reached
during the timeframe you are looking at, which
may be weekly, daily, hourly, or whatever
other timeframe you choose.
Some traders consider the actual body of the
candle, as the spread.
You decide which method you want to apply.
There are a lot of different interpretations
of the VSA, which makes it difficult to understand
it for a beginner trader.
At first, you need to get familiarized with
the most commonly used models of the VSA,
so make sure you watch this video about volume
spread analysis after you finish this one.
Smart money relies on retail traders to provide
liquidity.
Smart money will push price to an area where
retail traders place their stop loss.
In order to understand why supply and demand
zones can work as the basis of a trading strategy,
you need to understand how buyers and sellers
behave around these zones.
A lot of this comes down to finding liquidity.
Liquidity describes how easily an asset can
be bought or sold.
When there is a lot of liquidity, we say that
the orders can easily be absorbed by the markets.
It means that there are many traders willing
to take the other side of your order.
When there is little liquidity, it might be
harder to get your orders filled.
Because there might not be enough traders
to take the other side of your trade at the
price you want, you might get filled at a
worse price than expected.
This is why some institutional traders use
special techniques to get a good price for
their order.
Whenever institutional traders need to open
a position, they do so with much larger size
than the average retail trader.
In fact, their positions are usually so big
that if they were to simply enter at once,
they would move the market considerably.
So when institutional traders need to enter
a large buy order, they will do so part by
part, waiting for the price to come down before
pushing the next “slice” on the market.
This creates patterns on the chart and the
more you trade supply and demand, the more
you will “see” the underlying dynamics
of certain patterns that happen before supply
and demand momentum drives.
Another aspect is that institutional traders
understand where liquidity is accumulating.
Let’s take this chart as an example.
The institutional trader is looking for enough
liquidity to get a fill on his big order.
He wants to go long, but he needs to find
traders who want to sell their position to
him.
Below the swing low, there will be lots of
that liquidity: first, you will have the stop
losses of buy orders, which will sell on the
market once they’re hit.
Additionally, there will also be traders who
go short, again adding liquidity to the market.
This is why you will often first see a spike
in the opposite direction at the origin of
a strong price move.
The liquidity spike is the pattern that gets
created when large market participants need
liquidity and move the market in order to
get it.
Retail traders get trapped, their stops get
hit and they will often talk about “stop
hunting” while in fact, this is nothing
more than normal market behavior.
Monitor daily highs & lows, obvious swing
points and boundaries of ranges
So now you know how smart money operates and
why they operate in a certain way.
It’s time to find opportunities.
The best way to do this, is to mark out certain
levels, such as:
· Daily highs & lows
· Weekly highs & lows
· Obvious swing points
· Boundaries of ranges
By marking out these important areas of liquidity
and then analyzing what happens once the liquidity
at these areas gets triggered, you can get
a better understanding of how smart money
operates.
You can then make up rules to develop an entire
strategy around this concept.
Of course, the next step is to backtest the
rules and generate data to confirm a trading
edge.
One of the best ways to identify absorption
of liquidity by a bigger player, is to look
at candle closes & the violence of moves.
Is the high of a range being taken out, but
price quickly and aggressively falls back
into the range?
Then the buy side liquidity above the range
has been triggered and absorbed by smart money,
to fill a short order.
Waiting for confirmation is often very important.
You want to see clear triggering of the liquidity
and then absorption of that liquidity, in
order to join them.
Smart money enter the markets to fill orders,
generate liquidity and to hedge their longer-term
investments or trades
Smart money enter the markets to fill orders,
generate liquidity and to hedge their longer-term
investments or trades.
This is not how us, retail traders, trade.
This is the difference between retail trading
and institutional trading.
We try to profit from small directional moves.
So how to start trading like banks?
Start with being as prepared as possible and
treat your trading like you are running a
business.
Banks don’t just let the RSI tell them when
to enter.
Every position they take is well-calculated.
They know exactly what they need to buy, when
they need to buy it and how they need to buy
it.
They know the costs involved.
That’s how you should approach trading as
well.
You can start trading like the smart money
by following the next principles:
• Knowing your edge
• Having multiple plans
• Reviewing & learning
These are the most important points to consider
when you want to become a profitable trader.
Not by learning a concept that banks “supposedly”
use, but by approaching trading the same as
banks & professionals do.
It’s absolutely vital to know your edge.
Without an edge you will probably fail.
How do you get one?
By learning concepts that work in a market.
Then you start with building rules around
these concepts.
The next step is testing it on years of data,
followed by demo trading and live trading.
In order to be able to execute your edge effectively
and in order to improve, you need multiple
plans.
You need a pre-market plan, a plan for executing
and a post market plan.
A pre-market plan is all about how you find
the setups with your edge.
How do you need to analyze the markets & when.
Make this as clear as possible.
This minimizes the mistakes you are going
to make.
The most important thing is that you have
a clear, written down plan.
After your session, it’s time to analyze.
You will always make losing trades.
Most traders simply go to the next trade,
if you also proceed this way, this means you
wasted your money.
But if you actually take the time to learn
from your losers, that’s not wasted money
but simply a down payment for a valuable lesson.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.