If you stay, I’ll reveal the best
smart money concepts guide on Youtube!
Let’s start with the order flow. Order flow
refers to the external swing points of the market.
These are the key turning points
where price changes direction.
To identify these swing points, you need
to zoom out and look at the bigger picture.
Start by picking a higher time frame.
Now, mark out the significant
highs and lows on that chart.
These are your external structure points.
If you see that price is making lower highs
and lower lows, then the order flow is bearish.
This means that the big players in the
market, are actively pushing price down.
If you see price making a series of higher highs
and higher lows, then the order flow is bullish.
In this case, the smart money are accumulating
positions and driving the market up.
Now, these big players don't just
buy and sell randomly. They have
specific intentions and goals in mind.
This is where the concept of order flow
comes in. By analyzing the external swing points,
you can read the overall direction of the market.
The key is to trade in the same
direction as the order flow.
Don't try to fight the trend or guess when the
market will turn. Instead, focus on following the
big players and riding the big waves they create.
Now, one of the best ways to analyze order flow
is to look at multiple time frames.
Each time frame gives you a different
perspective on the market.
The higher time frames show you
the bigger picture, while the lower
time frames show you the details.
The external swing points on a
lower time frame are often seen as
internal structure on a higher time frame.
This is why it's so important to look at
multiple time frames when you read the market.
For example, you might start by looking at the
4-hour chart to get a sense of the overall trend.
If you see a series of lower highs and lower lows,
you know the order flow is bearish.
Then, you can drop down to the 15-minute
chart to look for specific entry points.
On the 15-minute chart, you'll see smaller
swings that are part of the bigger picture.
These are called internal structure points.
They're the building blocks of the larger trend.
Thus, by comparing the 15-minute swings to the
4-hour trend, you can get a sense of how
the market is behaving on a smaller scale.
You then simply look for bearish setups on the
15-minute chart that align with the overall
bearish order flow on the 4-hour chart.
Trend
Trend is all about the direction
of price over a specific period.
It's the overall movement of the market.
To identify the trend, you need to focus on
the internal swing points, on a lower time frame.
Internal swing points are the smaller highs and
lows that occur within a larger trend.
If you see that price is making a series
of higher highs and higher lows,
then the trend is currently bullish.
Each new high is higher than the previous one, and
each new low is also higher than the one before.
In a bullish trend, you'll often see strong,
impulsive moves to the upside followed by
smaller, corrective moves to the downside.
These corrections are typically short-lived
and serve as opportunities for buyers
to enter the market at a better price.
On the flip side, if price is
making a series of lower highs
and lower lows, then the trend is bearish.
In a bearish trend, you'll often see strong,
impulsive moves to the downside followed
by smaller, corrective moves to the upside.
These corrections are typically short-lived and
serve as opportunities for sellers to enter the
market at a better price.
Fractal Alignment
Now let’s talk about Fractal Alignment and how
it ties together the order flow and the trend.
So, order flow is the overall direction of the
market, determined by the external swing points,
the big picture view of where price is heading.
Trend is the current phase of that direction,
identified by the internal swing points. It's
like zooming in on a specific part of the chart.
Remember this: the internal direction
(the trend) actually makes up the
external direction (the order flow).
It's like a fractal pattern, where the
smaller parts contribute to the larger whole.
To really understand this relationship,
you need to assess order flow and trend
in relation to each other. This is where
multi-timeframe analysis comes into play.
By looking at different time frames, you can
see how the trend on a lower time frame fits into
the overall order flow on a higher time frame.
Let's say the order flow on the daily chart
is bearish, making lower lows and lower highs.
However, when we zoom in to the 1-hour chart,
we see that the current trend is actually
making higher highs and higher lows.
This is a common scenario that occurs
when the order flow is pulling back.
After a new low or high is established,
price will often gravitate to collect
more orders before continuing in
the direction of the overall order flow.
During this process, the trend on the lower time
frame may differ from the higher time frame.
As price navigates towards your points of
interest, you need to wait for trend and order
flow to align before entering the market.
So it's all about looking for
consistency between the time frames.
If the order flow on the daily chart is bearish,
we want to see the trend on the 1-hour chart
also making lower lows and lower highs.
If the trend on the 4-hour chart is bullish,
you want to see the order flow on the 15 minute
chart also making higher highs and higher lows.
When trend and order flow are aligned, the market
is more likely to continue in that direction.
Break of Structure
The next smart money
concept is the break of structure.
Looking at this price chart,
you see a series of swing highs and swing lows.
When price breaks above the most recent swing
high and closes above it, this is a
Break of Structure to the upside.
It means that the old structure, which was defined
by the previous swing high, has been broken.
Price has now created a new structure,
with a new swing high in place.
The same concept applies to the downside. If
price breaks and closes below a swing low,
it's a Break of Structure to the downside.
The old structure has been broken,
and a new one has been created.
A Break of Structure is viewed as a
continuation sign. It tells you that the buyers
or sellers have taken control, and that price is
likely to continue in the direction of the break.
So, to make it very clear, a Break of Structure
is simply a break above a previous higher
high in an uptrend, or a break below a lower
low in a downtrend.
Change of Character
The Change of Character is
another important concept.
You’re looking at this price chart,
and you see a market that has been
in a downtrend for some time. Price has been
steadily making lower highs and lower lows.
And then price suddenly breaks above
the previous major swing high.
This is a significant event, because it means that
the buyers have finally gained the upper hand.
They've managed to push price
above a key level of resistance,
and this could signal a potential trend reversal.
This is what we call a Change of Character. It's a
sudden and significant shift in the price action
of the market. In this case, the change is from
a bearish trend to a potentially bullish one.
The key is to watch what happens next. If price
continues to make new higher highs and higher
lows, then we can say with confidence that
we've transitioned into an uptrend.
In an uptrend, a Change of Character
would be signaled by a break below a previous
major swing low. This would indicate that the
sellers have taken control, and that the
trend may be reversing to the downside.
If price continues to make new lower lows
and lower highs, then we can say that we've
transitioned into a downtrend.
Premium /Discount
The Premium and Discount zones are
VERY important in smart money trading.
In this chart, the distance between a
swing high and a swing low is called
a price swing, or a price wave.
If you to measure the distance
from the top of the leg to the bottom
and you apply a Fibonacci retracement,
you can get the Premium and Discount range.
In general, anything above the 50% mark of
the price swing can be considered
Premium, while anything below the
50% mark can be considered Discount.
When price is trading in the Premium area,
it's like gravity is pulling it back down.
There's a higher probability that price
will reverse and start moving lower.
This means that selling in the Premium
area has a higher probability of success.
When price is trading in the Discount area,
there's a higher probability that price
will reverse and start moving higher.
This means that buying in the Discount
area has a higher probability of success.
Of course, you won’t use the Premium and
Discount zones as a standalone strategy.
But by combining them with the other
concepts, you can start to build a more
complete picture of the market.
In this smart money approach,
you will use the Premium and Discount concept
to help you decide when to enter a trade.
For example, if you're looking to go long,
you might wait for price to pull back into
a Discount area before entering.
If you're looking to go short,
you might wait for price to rally
into a Premium area before entering.
Supply/demand
Supply and demand zones are
one of the most important smart money concepts.
When smart money want to open a position with a
large volume, they can't just randomly
place a huge order in the market.
This would upset the balance of supply and demand,
and trigger their order at a worse price. This
could seriously eat into their potential profits.
Instead, banks split their large positions into
smaller, more manageable blocks and place
them at strategic levels in the market.
These levels are known as
supply and demand zones.
A demand zone is located at the last down candle
or series of down candles before price makes a
big move upwards. This is where the big players
are secretly accumulating their long positions,
hoping to ride the wave of bullish momentum.
When price comes back down to this demand zone,
you often see a strong reaction. That's why
demand zones act as strong support levels,
where price is likely to bounce higher.
A supply zone is located at the last up
candle or series of up candles
before price makes a big move
downwards. This is where the big players
are quietly unloading their positions,
hoping to profit from a potential price drop.
Supply zones act as strong resistance levels,
where price is likely to
stall or even reverse lower.
Mitigation
In smart money jargon,
you’ll often hear the word “mitigation”. This
term is related to supply and demand zones.
Now, in this price chart, observe
this new Demand zone forming.
Price started to rally higher from this zone.
This is what we call an Unmitigated Demand zone.
An Unmitigated zone is like a magnet for price.
It's an area that hasn't been visited before,
and it's screaming out for attention.
The big players who placed their
orders here are eagerly waiting for
price to come back and fill them.
On the flip side, here we see a Supply zone
with a reaction. Price has come back to
this level, touched it, and then fallen away.
This is what we call a Mitigated Supply zone.
A Mitigated zone is an area
that has been visited before.
The sellers that placed their sell orders at this
level have already had their fill, and they're
probably not interested in sticking around.
This is important because knowing whether a
zone is Mitigated or Unmitigated can give you
clues about what price is likely to do next.
If you see price approaching an Unmitigated
Demand zone, you know that there are probably
a lot of unfilled buy orders waiting there.
This means that there's a good chance price will
bounce off this level and start rallying higher.
On the other hand, if you see price approaching a
Mitigated Supply zone, you know that most of the
sell orders have probably already been filled.
This means that there's less resistance at this
level, and price may be able to break through
and continue falling.
Fair value gaps
Fair value gaps are used to detect
market imbalances or inefficiencies.
These imbalances happen when there is
significant buying or selling pressure.
When you look at a chart, you'll notice that
most of the time, the price tends to retrace
and leave wicks on both sides of the candles.
However, sometimes you can see candles with
no overlap on either side, which
is what we call a fair value gap.
The idea behind fair value gaps is that the
market will eventually come back to these
inefficiencies, before continuing in the
same direction as the initial strong move.
This is similar to the principle
of supply and demand trading.
For a fair value gap to develop, there must be
a set of three candles characterized by heavy
buying or selling in the same direction.
A gap will form between the first candle's
higher wick and the last candle's lower wick.
In this example, the price movement doesn't
have a Fair Value Gap, as the
previous candle's high level
balances out the low level of the third candle.
This price action is considered to be balanced.
Liquidity & Inducement
Next we need to talk about
liquidity and inducement.
In simple terms, liquidity
is just another word for money.
Liquidity refers to the amount of
money flowing in and out of the market.
Now, where does this money come from? It
comes from orders placed by traders.
And the big banks and institutions are
paying close attention to where
these orders are coming from.
You see, banks use a simple
strategy called inducement,
to lure unsuspecting traders into their traps.
They'll create artificial setups in the market,
making it look like there's a lot
of demand for a particular market.
And they do this by placing a
bunch of orders in a specific area,
creating what's known as a liquidity pool.
They want to induce traders to activate their
capital. In other words, they want you
to place your orders in the same area,
so they can take your money!
Once the banks have lured in
enough orders, they'll make their move.
They'll start buying or selling in the
opposite direction, taking out all the stop
losses and freeing up positions for themselves.
The banks don't want to fight for every move
they make. They want to be able to initiate
price in the direction they want, without
hitting any areas that could cause a battle.
That's why they build these
liquidity areas in the first place.
By inducing one side of the market
and then clearing out that liquidity,
the banks give themselves all the buying
or selling power they need to move price
wherever they want it to go.
Let’s consider a trading range.
Below the support level, there are stop-loss
orders of buyers, and above the resistance
level, there are stop-loss orders of sellers.
When the market breaks below the support level,
new sell trades are triggered by traders
expecting a continuation of the breakout.
A break above the resistance
level activates new “buy” trades.
So liquidity refers to the orders
on both sides of the trading range.
Buy-side liquidity represents new buy
orders above the resistance level,
accompanied by stop-loss orders of sellers.
Sell-side liquidity is characterized by
stop-loss orders of buyers below the support
level, accompanied by new sell orders.
By pushing the market above
these levels, smart money can
access the liquidity required to move price.
So, where else can you find liquidity? The obvious
place to look is at previous swing highs and lows.
These are areas where the market has reversed in
the past, and they're often seen as
key levels of support and resistance.
Think about it like this. If the market has
bounced off a certain price level multiple times
in the past, there's a good chance that there
are a lot of orders sitting at that level.
Another place to look for liquidity
is at equal highs and equal lows.
These are areas where the price has
reached the same level multiple times,
creating a sort of "line in the sand"
that traders are watching closely.
If the price breaks through an equal high or low,
it could trigger a wave of pending orders and stop
losses. That's why these levels are often seen
as key battlegrounds between buyers and sellers.
Trend lines are another great place to
look for liquidity. These are diagonal
lines that connect a series of highs or lows.
If the price is bouncing off a trend line, there's
a good chance that there are a lot of pending
orders sitting just above or below that line.
Chart patterns are another key area to
watch for liquidity. These are specific
formations that the price makes on the chart.
Each of these patterns has its own unique
characteristics, but they all have one thing in
common: they're often seen as key levels where
the market is likely to break out or reverse.
And where there's a potential for a big move,
there's usually a lot of
liquidity sitting nearby.
If this smart money guide helped you,
you don’t want to miss the next ones!