Heiken Ashi charts are becoming more and more
popular among traders and there are many trading
strategies build around this type of charts.
Heikin Ashi is a modified candlestick charting
technique that rearranges how the price is
displayed.
Basically, Heikin Ashi charts make candlestick
charts more readable for traders who want
to know when to stay in a trade and ride a
strong trend, and when to get out when the
trend weakens.
Although Heikin ashi has many advantages,
a lot of traders prefer to analyze classic
candlestick charts.
But what if you could combine both charts,
in order to have the classic candles and still
be able to plot Heikin-ashi candles?
We can do that by using smoothed Heiken Ashi
candles.
In today’s video, we’ll take a look at
the Heiken Ashi smoothed indicator and I’ll
show you how you can apply this tool and configure
it to your preference.
Before going further, let’s refresh our
memory with how the Heiken Ashi chart plots
prices and how traders use this type of chart
when analyzing the price of an asset.
Candles on traditional Japanese candlestick
charts frequently change their color, which
can make them difficult to read.
On the other hand, candles on the Heikin Ashi
chart display more consecutive colored candles,
helping traders to identify past price movements
more easily.
You’ll notice that Heikin Ashi charts have
a tendency for its candles to stay green during
an uptrend and stay red during a downtrend.
This is in contrast to traditional Japanese
candlesticks that alternate color even if
the price is moving strongly in one direction.
Heikin Ashi chart is much smoother looking
in terms of price action.
This is why many traders prefer to use the
Heikin Ashi candles since it reduces the noise
on the chart, and allows them to analyze trends
more clearly.
What makes Heikin Ashi different from a traditional
Japanese candlestick chart is how the price
is displayed in terms of the open and the
close.
If you look closely at the Heikin Ashi chart,
you’ll notice that each of the Heikin Ashi
candlesticks start from the MIDDLE of the
candlestick before it, and not from the level
where the previous candlestick had closed.
While Japanese candlesticks require many definitions
and flexible rules for most patterns, a heikin-ashi
chart works with only the five simple rules.
1.
A sequence of green bodies identifies an uptrend,
while a sequence of red bodies identifies
a downtrend.
2.
The uptrend gets stronger with longer green
bodies and no lower shadows.
The downtrend gets stronger with longer red
bodies and no upper shadows.
3.
The trend gets weaker with smaller bodies
and with the emergence of lower and upper
shadows.
4.
A consolidation is revealed when you spot
a series of smaller bodies with both upper
and lower shadows.
5.
A trend reversal could follow when you spot
multiple candles with small bodies and long
upper and lower shadows (doji-like candle)
or a sudden color change.
Just like any other tool used for technical
analysis, Heikin Ashi is useful but it does
have some weaknesses or limitations.
While the traditional Japanese candlesticks
are derived from the actual prices, Heikin
Ashi candlesticks are NOT.
Because the Heikin Ashi candlesticks are averaged,
they do NOT show the exact open and close
prices for a particular time period.
Heikin Ashi charts obscure actual price information.
The closing price is considered important
for many traders, but the actual closing price
is NOT displayed on a Heikin Ashi candlestick.
But we can fix this problem by using the smoothed
Heiken Ashi.
Smoothed Heiken Ashi is a modified version
of the regular Heiken Ashi candlestick charts.
While you can typically use the regular Heiken
Ashi chart all by itself, the Heiken Ashi
smoothed indicator is used as an overlay on
the regular candlestick chart.
If you have a Tradingview account, this is
the exact version I use.
As you can see, you’ll get a better perspective
of the markets.
You can see the regular candlestick chart
alongside the Heiken Ashi smoothed indicator.
This is not possible if you use the regular
Heiken Ashi chart.
The main difference between the regular Heiken
Ashi and the Heiken Ashi smoothed indicator
is that the second one plots the Heiken Ashi
candlesticks as a moving average.
The general rule of thumb is that the markets
are in an uptrend when the smoothed Heiken
Ashi indicator is bullish or green, and the
markets are in a downtrend when the smoothed
Heiken Ashi indicator is bearish or red.
Smoothed Heiken Ashi is a trend following
indicator.
In uptrends, price tends to stay above it.
In downtrends, price typically stays below
the Smoothed Heiken Ashi.
The first possibility of a change in trend
is when price crosses through the indicator.
Downtrends start to reverse when prices cross
back up and through the smoothed HA, while
uptrends show signs of reversal when price
falls through the smoothed HA, below it.
The settings for the smoothed Heiken Ashi
indicator are very simple.
You can set the values of the two moving averages
that are used.
Depending on your trading style, scalping,
day trading or swing trading, you can change
the value of the indicator to suit your trading
needs.
Here are several settings you could try:
First one: 5 period Smoothed Heiken Ashi
This is suited to scalping techiques, tracking
the strong momentum and the trend in the short
term.
The 5 period Smoothed Heiken Ashi acts as
support in the strongest trends.
This line is best used in low volatility trends
with strong momentum.
You can also use it as a trailing stop.
10 period Smoothed Heiken Ashi, which is the
default value, is a great method to keep you
on the right side of the major market trend.
It is usually the first line to be lost before
any real trouble begins, meaning any reversals
in current trend.
From my backtesting, it can be used as a standalone
signal in some stocks and markets that tend
to trend strongly in one direction for long
periods.
20 period Smoothed Heiken Ashi acts like an
intermediate term moving average.
It is generally the last line of support in
a volatile uptrend.
To me, it is the reversion to the mean in
a market when it finally pulls back after
an extended trend.
50 period Smoothed Heiken Ashi is the line
that strong leading stocks typically pull
back to.
This is usually the main support level for
strong uptrends.
Most bull markets and uptrends will usually
pull back to this level.
From my backtesting, the 50 period Smoothed
Heiken Ashi is generally a great “Buy the
dip” level.
If you enjoy swing trading or position trading,
you could use the 100 period Smoothed Heiken
Ashi, which indicate long term direction.
This is the deeper pullback level in bull
markets and uptrends.
It usually presents a great risk/reward ratio
in bull markets.
Now, how to Use Smoothed Heiken Ashi
There are 3 main ways in which you can use
the Smoothed Heiken Ashi:
• To determine the direction of the trend
• To determine support and resistance levels
• Using multiple Smoothed Heiken Ashi for
long- and short-term market trends
1.
First approach is to determine the direction
of the trend
When prices are trending higher, the Smoothed
Heiken Ashi will adjust by also moving higher
to reflect the increasing prices.
This could be explained as a bullish signal,
where traders may prefer buying opportunities.
The opposite would be true if the price was
consistently trading below the Smoothed Heiken
Ashi indicator, where traders would then prefer
selling opportunities due to the market signaling
a downward trend.
2.
Second approach is using Smoothed Heiken Ashi
for support and resistance levels
If you see the Smoothed Heiken Ashi trending
higher, you could enter the market on a retest
of the Smoothed Heiken Ashi.
Likewise, when you are long in an uptrend
market, then the Smoothed Heiken Ashi can
be used as a stop loss level.
The opposite is true for down trends.
In this chart you can see several examples
of how the Smoothed Heiken Ashi can be used
as powerful level of support or resistance.
3.
Third approach is making use of multiple Smoothed
Heiken Ashi
This allows traders to simultaneously assess
the short and long-term trends in the market.
As price crosses above or below these plotted
levels on the graph it can be explained as
either strength or weakness for the asset
you are trading.
This method of using more than one Smoothed
Heiken Ashi can be extremely useful in trending
markets.
Now, very important: when making use of multiple
Smoothed Heiken Ashi, you might have the idea
to trade when the lines will cross.
A bullish cross is identified when the short-term
Smoothed Heiken Ashi crosses above the long-term
Smoothed Heiken Ashi, while a bearish cross
represents the short-term Smoothed Heiken
Ashi crossing below the long-term Smoothed
Heiken Ashi.
Don’t use this strategy.
Heiken Ashi is considered a lagging indicator
that not only dismisses useless signals to
open the trade but also provide you with a
late signal for closing the trade.
Attempting to build a crossover strategy with
2 Smoothed Heikin Ashi lines is very bad idea.
If you don’t want to see the market slowly
destroying your profit as the trend you are
trying to trade has already changed, I advise
you to use multiple Smoothed Heikin Ashi lines
only for dynamic support and resistance levels,
and not for crossover signals.
Every Heikin Ashi trading system should include
price action rules:
• So look for Support and Resistance levels
• look for chart patterns for potential
breakouts.
• And try to enter into emerging trends
and exit on slowing trends.
Also, as you are able to see the classic candlesticks
you can combine classic price action with
Smoothed Heikin Ashi.
You will able to identify a pin bar, an engulfing
candle or a reversal pattern and at the same
time, knowing what Heikin Ashi are indicating.
With classic candlesticks, an engulfing candlestick
pattern at a support level can be a nice starting
signal, a decent entry into a beginning upward
movement.
Nevertheless, there is room for misinterpretation.
With additional smoothed Heikin Ashi candles
on the same chart, you can mitigate this danger
of misinterpretation and can help you to judge
a trend more clearly in combination with classic
candlesticks.
That’s why it’s better to use both candle
types on the same chart.
Despite the simplicity of the Heikin Ashi
approach, you must be aware that Heikin Ashi
candles, unlike classic candlesticks, are
in fact indicators.
This is due to the construction of Heikin
Ashi candles, in which the current and previous
periods are always considered.
So the Heikin Ashi Candles are not the ultimate
trading instrument.
That’s why the combination between classic
candlesticks and Heikin Ashi represents a
better and safer approach to trade.
You analyze the markets on the classic candlestick
chart, and you apply the Smoothed Heikin Ashi
to filter against false signals and background
noises.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.