Hello and welcome.
Today I’m sharing a simpler and easier way
to analyze candlesticks and I will reveal
how to use confirmation to read market structure
and trends.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
What retail traders do is overcomplicate their
candlestick trading and focus on things that
are not necessary.
For example, they start memorizing 40 or 50
types of candlestick formations and when they
start analyzing a market, they have to consider
50 variables before making a decision.
I’ve made the same mistake when I first
started trading.
You know what happens when you overcomplicate
your analysis: you start missing out on good
trade setups, you are letting your losing
positions run, and in general you are overthinking
all the time.
So let’s simply candlestick trading.
Among the dozens of candlestick formations,
there are six basic candlesticks types.
1.
Long candlesticks.
The long candlestick indicates a lot of momentum
among buyers or sellers.
The lack of shadow indicates exceptional strength
for one side or the other.
A long candlestick may have no shadows, or
a small one at the top or at the bottom of
the real body.
The significance of the long candlestick relies
completely on its location.
For example, a long green candlestick appearing
within an uptrend could be a strong confirmation
signal, but if the same candlestick appears
after a downtrend, it is more likely to act
as a potential reversal signal.
The same is true for long red candlesticks.
Within a downtrend, it tends to confirm it,
and when it follows an uptrend, it is more
likely to signal a reversal.
2.
Short candlesticks.
A candlestick with average or relatively small
range signals a general agreement between
buyers and sellers that the current price
is reasonable, especially when short candlesticks
appear in a series of sideways-moving sessions.
However, when short candlesticks appear following
a period of strong trend in either direction,
especially when long candlesticks have shown
up, they can indicate a struggle between buyers
and sellers and a likely reversal in the trend,
or a slowing down in price momentum.
The appearance of a single short candlestick
is not meaningful by itself.
When a series of short candlesticks appear,
it may show declining momentum in the current
trend or be a symptom of sideways movement.
3.
Doji candles.
The candle with no real body, or a very narrow-range
—one in which open and close are the same—represents
a significant development.
The fact that price opens and closes at the
same place has greater significance when the
doji also has exceptionally long upper or
lower shadows, or both.
The longer shadows reveal an attempt by buyers
or sellers to move price in the desired direction.
However, the effort failed when price retreat
to close at the same price as the open.
The meaning of the failure on one side or
the other, or on both sides, affects how the
current trend is viewed and what it means
in terms of likely reversal.
For example, when a doji appears at the bottom
of a downtrend and also has an exceptionally
long lower shadow, it shows that sellers tried
to move price lower but couldn’t; this hints
at a likely reversal and a possible movement
to the upside.
If a doji appears at the top of an uptrend
and also has a very long upper shadow, the
same failed attempt is shown, this time among
buyers.
This foreshadows a likely reversal and a possible
down movement.
However, just as long candlesticks indicate
exceptional strength, doji candles indicate
a loss of momentum and, based on the appearance
of any shadows, provide strong reversal signals.
Confirmation is essential to these interpretations,
but we’ll talk about confirmation later
in the video.
4.
Long upper and lower shadows
One of the most interesting signals is an
exceptionally long shadow appearing on both
sides of the real body.
When such shadows are found in both upper
and lower ends in comparison to the real body,
it shows that neither buyers nor sellers had
enough power to move price beyond the opening
and closing range.
This failure of both sides to control price
movement could be a sign of a period of consolidation.
When a candlestick is up with long shadows
on both sides and a current trend has been
underway, it can signal the end of that trend,
even though both sides were unable to create
more movement.
In general, long shadows both above and below
the real body may be better understood in
a multiple time frame analysis.
5.
Long upper shadow only
When a candle contains an unusually long upper
shadow, it signals that buyers have lost momentum
or failed in an effort to take momentum away
from sellers.
If this pattern unfolds at the top of an uptrend,
it is a signal that the trend may be about
to end.
If it shows up within a downtrend, it may
confirm or establish continuation; buyers
tried to reverse the downtrend, but failed.
A long upper shadow candle often appears at
the top of an up move and is often the lowest
point in the downtrend and signals a reversal
point.
6.
Long lower shadow only.
The appearance of a candlestick with a long
lower shadow indicates a failure by sellers
to move price lower, which leads to the immediate
conclusion that either the current downtrend
is ending, or an existing uptrend is continuing.
However, the pattern can have either a bullish
or a bearish interpretation.
The interesting thing about this pattern is
that it can be bullish or bearish, depending
on where it appears.
The real body may also be either green or
red, without affecting the interpretation
of the candle.
A long lower shadow candle often appears at
the bottom of a down move and is often the
highest point in the uptrend and signals the
reversal point.
Confirmation
So now you have 6 candlestick types to analyze.
But with all forms of candlesticks, “significance”
is a matter of market context, or market structure.
Also, candlestick patterns do not always have
to mean anything of interest.
Some signals are really not signals at all;
this is why confirmation is so important.
Confirmation is an important aspect of candlestick
analysis.
It is the observation of separate and independent
signals that verify what the candlestick pattern
predicts.
For example, a candlestick reversal may be
confirmed by tests of resistance or support,
momentum changes, or even by moving average-based
analysis.
Two or more candlestick signals may occur
in proximity, providing very strong confirmation.
A test of resistance or support, for example,
may be first made by a familiar technical
signal (such as double top or double bottom)
and then confirmed by strong reversal candlestick
signals.
Or a candlestick reversal may first appear
and then be confirmed by failed tests of resistance
or support.
You need to rely on confirmation to improve
your timing of entry and exit.
The concept is necessary because no single
candlestick pattern is always reliable.
Even confirmed signals may fail; however,
with the use of confirmation, the ratio of
successful trade timing improves and failed
signals are more easily spotted when a secondary
indicator contradicts rather than confirms
what the initial signal indicates.
A confirming indicator may also consist of
a second sign of the same type.
For example, an initial candlestick reversal
may be followed by an equally strong but different
candlestick revealing the same potential.
When this occurs, the reliability of the dual
signal is much stronger.
So the initial goal of confirmation is to
improve timing for trades.
Another value is found in how a confirming
indicator identifies and confirms a bigger
trend.
A price trend may last only a few sessions,
or extend for weeks or even months.
In my own trading, I rely on confirmation
from moving averages, volume trends, and divergences.
These are valuable in identifying the likelihood
of a trend continuing or ending.
In this respect, confirmation not only affects
the turning point in price, but it also can
anticipate an overall weakening in momentum
or development of a period of consolidation
after a strong or rapid trend has run its
course.
Confirmation is also valuable when used to
time entry and exit within the context of
existing resistance and support levels.
For example, there’s a tendency for price
to remain within the trading range until a
signal changes current conditions.
So a failed attempt to break out of the trading
range is likely to lead to a price movement
in the opposite direction.
When this occurs and separate confirmation
is found in candlestick formations, the reversal
has a better than average likelihood of taking
place.
If price does break through resistance or
support, you face an immediate decision point.
Will the trend continue and establish a new
trading range?
Or will the breakout fail and price will return
to previously set levels?
The uncertainty of the outcome of a breakout
can be clarified with confirmation, through
candlestick formations that follow the breakout
itself.
The short-term changes in price direction
and strength may further be confirmed and
tracked with the use of trend lines and other
visual tools.
Following a trend line helps identify when
a short-term trend is likely to reverse, and
if confirmed with candlestick reversal signals,
is a reliable method for tracking and confirming
price and momentum.
An uptrend is marked with a trend line drawn
under the price levels from a low point, and
it continues until it runs into price that
has reached a high and reversed.
A downtrend is marked with a trend line drawn
above the price levels starting from a high
point and continuing downward until price
reaches its low and then turns.
Confirmation comes in many forms and is applied
to short-term or intermediate trends, trading
ranges, and momentum.
Just as important as having confirmation is
the opposite theory of contradiction.
When two reliable candlestick signals do not
agree, the significance is uncertain.
You know the situation.
You get a long lower shadow candlestick after
a downtrend, you wait for confirmation, thinking
to go long, and then price forms a long upper
shadow candle, signaling a possible short
position.
2 candlestick formation that contradict.
Most traders would gamble on this scenario,
would pick a side.
In this instance, you have to choose one of
several courses of action:
1.
To seek confirmation from a new set of candlesticks.
2.
Take no action until the market direction
is clarified.
3.
To analyze volume and look for possible divergences
Or to expand the analysis for more time.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.