[Music]
hello and welcome
today we'll look at the anchored view up
we'll cover its features as well as
discuss how they're useful to trading
and additionally we'll reveal several
strategies you could apply for day
trading sculpting and even swing trading
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
i'm using trading view and you can find
the anchored view app right here
trendline tools open the menu and there
it is
you can add it to your favorites it goes
into your toolbar and it will be right
there on your chart at all times
so what is the anchored view up
indicator
the anchored view up ties view up
calculations to a specific price bar
chosen by the trader
traditional view app calculations always
start with the first bar of the day and
end with the final bar of the day
but in some situations you would prefer
to analyze the view up line based on a
less arbitrary starting point
and be able to extend that view up line
beyond the end of the trading day
anchored view up allows you to specify
the price bar where calculations begin
making it easy to see whether the bulls
or bears have been in charge since a
very specific point in time
the price level represented by the
anchored view up is important because it
serves as a benchmark when large orders
are executed by banks and large
financial institutions
they will be executed over a period of
time to minimize market impact
the benchmark price for the execution
period is the view up
banks and large traders have developed
sophisticated order execution algorithms
in order to achieve an average price
equivalent to or better than the view up
on an up trending day such algorithms
will issue buy orders when price drops
below the view up to take advantage of
prices below the average
on a down trending day
the same algorithms will issue sell
orders when the price breaks above the
view up to take advantage of the prices
above the average
anchored view up is better than the
traditional view up indicator
with traditional view up the calculation
starts with the first bar of the day and
ends with the last bar of the day
because it only incorporates one trading
day of data traditional v web can only
be used on intraday charts
with anchored view up you choose a first
bar
you are anchoring the indicator to the
and the last bar is always the most
recent bar available
you have full control you get flexible
starting and ending points
because of this anchored view up is not
limited to intraday charts
so how to trade using the anchored view
up
a good strategy is to look for key
events or turning points or moments in
the price history to anchor the view up
in this case we're looking at the chart
of netflix and this is the corona crash
we should anchor the view up to this low
price of the crash because you know
there was a massive exchange of hands
here
look at the volume spikes
at this point something really big
happened there were tons of buyers and
sellers lots of volatility
so this looks like a good point in time
to anchor
let's click the scandal the absolute low
and there's our anchor view up
and now we see a few things
for one the bulls are in control the
price traded consistently above the
anchored view up and that is a bullish
sign most of the buying on average has
occurred above the line
the most common strategy using the
anchored view up is the pullback trade
a pullback occurs when a price that's on
an extended move upward or downward
makes a small movement in the opposite
direction toward the end card view
upline pullbacks are a common price
movement especially in heavy trends
to trade a pullback setup you find an
uptrend with price making higher highs
and higher lows
price trades of course above the
anchored view up and you patiently wait
for the price to make a pullback to the
downside
returning to the view up line
this is a chance to buy the stock
another strategy is to look for moments
of euphoria where the distance between
the anchored view up and the current
price is very high
and you trade a reversion to the mean
for example let's use our price range
tool to measure the distance between the
anchored view up and the actual price
so if we measure the distance between
the anchored view upline and this high
it's 17 higher almost 84 dollars
in some cases this percentage will be
even higher generally it's best to avoid
buying when price is overextended
if you are adventurous you could try a
reversion to the mean
let's add another anchored view up at
this year's high right here starting
january till april price was traded
below this view upline
we were also in a clear trading range
so the best approach is to sell at the
top of the range and buy at the bottom
of it
when price dipped below the second view
upline
perhaps this was a time to short or to
reduce your existing positions to take
some risk off or just to reevaluate and
have some patience until price returns
to the lower anchored view up
so how to read the anchored view up
the anchored view upline can be used to
confirm trends and identify areas of
support and resistance on the chart
as you saw before the advantage of using
this line is that you can set your own
starting point in order to include only
relevant data on your chart
typically you must choose a particular
event as the starting price bar for the
overlay
these events generally must signal a
change in market psychology and the
price action prior to that change should
be excluded from the calculations since
it doesn't reflect the same market
psychology
the previous example was more of a swing
trading approach which i prefer
but what if you prefer day trading or
sculpting
in this tesla one minute chart the view
up line in blue is based on the opening
bar
while the anchored view upline in red is
set at the low of the morning
the traditional view upline includes
data for the first 30 minutes of trading
as well as the drop to the low of the
day making for a view upline that
doesn't quite reflect the price action
at the midday
the red anchored view upline includes
only data since reaching the low and
more accurately reflects the midday
market psychology
if your strategy was to buy dips at the
view upline you could see why the
anchored line was much better than the
standard one
i can see at least two buying
opportunities using the anchored view up
trades which weren't so obvious if you
use the normal view up
now as i said the starting price bar
that you choose must mark a shift in
market psychology it must be an
important event or turning point in the
market you're not going to add it in the
middle of price action
it must be in obvious places where other
traders would place it
think about it if more traders see the
same point meaning they apply the
anchored view up on the same location
the more chances you will get a reaction
when the price returns to it
so let's showcase the most important
starting points to apply the line
first the highest volume candle
high volume means there's an interest in
the asset whether it's a stock currency
pair or other market
and if it's combined with a move higher
in price then it's often used as a
signal of strong upward momentum
keeping an eye on volume will ensure
that you are on the right side of the
trade
so here's amd on the 15 minute time
frame
here's the highest volume in the
previous week
we added the anchored view up and online
immediately offered two opportunities to
buy the dip this is more of a day
trading and sculping approach you go
with the flow of the highest volume and
try to catch another swing to the upside
when price comes back to the anchored
view up
second a major swing high or low
many view of trading strategies involve
looking for the best prices to enter or
looking for value
to help us find areas of value to look
for potential traits we need to identify
potential swing highs and swing lows
these are important levels used by
traders to hunt reversal trades
but if we add the anchored view up to
them we will see some hidden support and
resistance areas which are invisible to
novice traders
look how price reacted to the anchored
view appliance
the first pullback after we applied the
line on the swing low was a perfect
bounce trade
and again when we applied the anchored
view up to the high the first pullback
to it was again a great short trade
this is useful mostly for swing trading
but you could also use this strategy for
day trading and scoping if you apply the
anchored view up on intraday swings
third anchor point
earnings report for stock trading or
non-farm payroll for forex trading
the earnings season is the most
interesting period for any stock trader
it comes after every three months when
companies release their quarterly
earnings
this is when a company tells you how
much money they earned if they beat the
estimates
this is the period when the market
sentiment can change
so we should track those periods to
apply our anchored view up
here we applied two lines on the
previous earnings
after the first one we see a clear
trading range with price moving above
and below the line although the price
dipped above and below the line it
clearly offered good support and
resistance
the view up line remained flat during
this time so no aggressive movements
happened during this period
after the second earning report the
sentiment shifted to bullish
price stayed well above the line
this technique is useful mainly for
swing trading but you could also use it
for day trading when the price is near
the anchored view upline
number 4
year to date previous month or previous
week
you can actually anchor the view up to
big starting dates it's easy if you use
trading view
you just click year-to-date down here
then you select the anchor the view up
and you apply it on the first candle
if you're a swing trader or investor you
pay close attention to this line
when price will revisit the area it can
potentially bounce off it
if you like to day trade you select one
month and you add the anchored view up
on the first scandal
look how the line offered at least two
trades during the month
one buy position here
when the price broke above the line and
retested the area
basically the first pullback after the
view up breakout
and the second one here again a first
pullback trade
price broke below the anchored view up
line quite aggressively
returned to the line and rejected the
line once again
and if you select 5 days and apply the
view up you get data from the past week
past five trading days
again you can see several by the deep
trades
around the line
i firmly believe that the anchor view up
can provide invaluable insights into the
sentiment of the market you are trading
the anchored view up is the perfect
combination of price volume and time
and you have full control you apply it
on any point you want on the chart
because of its dynamic properties the
anchored view up can be analyzed in ways
like a traditional moving average
so pay extra attention to the direction
and slope of the view up
or how far above or below price action
is in relation to the view up
so experiment with various anchor points
in your targeted markets crypto stocks
forex on different time frames and you
will immediately recognize its value
as a standalone study or in combination
with other oscillators and indicators i
think the anchor view up is likely to
become one of your favorite trading
tools
if you found value and learn something
new give us a like and subscribe this
way we'll know if you'd like to see more
videos like this one
and check out our academy program if you
want to further level up your trading
until next time