Nothing hurts worse than getting stopped out
of a trade just before it finally goes the
way you thought.
And you're left wondering - am I just unlucky?
Well, I've realized it's usually not just
bad timing.
The big banks and hedge funds actually know
how to bait normal traders like us into buying
or selling at exactly the wrong moments.
They use specific tactics to lure us into
stops, scoop up our positions, and then flip
the market to continue the move.
It feels unfair, but what I will teach you
today will save you a lot of bad trades.
Something I was shocked to learn is that markets
are actually way easier for big players to
control than we realize.
See, while it seems random to us, in reality
price action follows what a smaller group
does - the so-called "smart money".
These are huge banks, hedge funds and dealers
that make the market.
Because they see all buy/sell orders coming
in before anyone else, they have way more
power over where price will move short term.
Once you accept this reality, it totally changes
how you trade.
Instead of fighting them, you need to learn
to predict what those big players might do
next based on specific clues.
So the market may look random, but truth is
just a handful of pros control short term
price flows.
Those big players have ways of manipulating
markets that normal people like us just can't
compete with.
For one, they can see every single stop-loss
order placed, just waiting to be triggered.
Just imagine filling a huge order, then taking
all the stops below for a nice bonus.
They also have insider info before headlines
even appear.
The little guys like us never hears whispers
from the top.
Plus, with their order volumes, they can subtly
move price up or down to fill buy/sells without
moving the market against themselves.
Elite tactics we don't have access to.
When you realize how much they can see behind
the curtain, it's silly competing with the
"smart money" directly.
While we're busy day trading pennies, they
work on much bigger scales, from quick flips
to long-term positioning.
So how do we find out the intentions of smart
money?
Now let’s be real, we cannot know what they’ll
do in the future, but they do leave hints
for us in volume and price action.
Volume shows us how heavily traded a market
really is, while the actual price spread,
the difference between the open and the close,
reveals if they aim to go long or short based
on that activity.
But here's where it gets sneaky – the big
boys will do things to tip the odds more in
their favor.
Like gapping up overnight to stop people out,
shakeouts to scare people into sells, and
price tests to flush weak hands.
After reading several books about these big
players, I realized that watching volume is
key to reading what they actually intend to
do.
Remember, those whales have the power to manipulate
trends over time with their enormous positions.
When a lot of volume kicks in during a move,
you know the "smart money" is getting seriously
involved and likely intends to continue forcing
that direction.
Their collective action is what shifts markets
in the long run.
But just as important is when volume totally
dries up during an up move - because that's
a sign they aren't actually not backing the
upswing.
Known as "no demand", low volume rallies are
doomed to fail once they lose the smart money
support.
Normal traders like us opening positions have
zero impact on market flow.
So pay attention to volume surges and volume
fades – this is how you read what the big
boys are doing.
And it's unreal how the "smart money" exploits
human psychology like they do.
The big boy know most traders are torn between
FOMO and fear - and they twist that to their
advantage so smoothly.
Whenever a big news is released, smart money
always has an angle.
This is why you’ll see instances when an
economic report is released, the news are
good, the market should go up, but instead,
it decreases aggressively.
It’s a classic shakeout move.
Meanwhile the buyers who thought they were
being smart, are now getting trapped.
Smart money also like to trap sellers during
these moves.
Cashing in both ways.
While we battle emotions, these pros know
exactly what they’re doing so they profit
no matter what.
The only solution is accepting we can't beat
them.
We got to understand their moves and try to
follow their steps, their lead, instead of
trying to outsmart them.
There's more to trading than just looking
at the price alone.
See, what the big traders really don't want
us to pay attention to is the volume.
When you look at just the price, it can make
you feel nervous or excited.
But volume gives you the real facts of what's
going on.
No matter what market you look at, they all
work basically the same.
And the more people who are buying and selling
a particular market, the harder it is for
anyone to easily control it and change the
price however they want.
But with thinner markets, where not as many
orders are happening, it's easier for big
players to manipulate things.
You'll definitely see big players trying to
sway prices when trading is low.
But don't forget - they need opportunities
to make their moves too.
Things like news that causes uncertainty,
or times with less buyers and sellers around.
That's when they pounce.
As much as we don't want to admit it, people
have a natural tendency to just go with the
crowd.
And the media knows how to use that to their
advantage, whether it's talking about stocks,
crypto, or whatever.
If a bunch of news sites or shows all say
the same thing about an investment, most people
will believe it without question.
But what if they're wrong?
Then the herd gets hurt because they followed
bad advice.
The thing is, smart money see right through
us.
They know just how to steer public opinion
to serve their own interests, instead of ours.
They realize fear and greed control us more
than we'd ever admit.
And that's how they end up winning while retail
players lose money.
The lesson is simple: you really have to start
thinking for yourself and not just following
the pack if you want a fair chance at the
market.
And I know it's tempting to just want trading
strategies and tips, without understanding
the context behind why certain techniques
actually work.
But hear me out.
Understanding how big money operates and think
is the key to succeeding long run.
Otherwise you're just gambling blindly without
the full picture.
I was and I still am sometimes , when I got
start to trading emotionally.
But once I began dissecting what patterns
keep emerging, it all started clicking into
place.
Like sharp drops below clear support levels,
just enough to trigger everyone's stops, before
it rebounds as planned.
You know them so well.
You lost a lot of trades this way, didn’t
you?
We all see these tricks playing out over and
over.
So unless we accept smart money knows psychology
better than we do, we'll never stop getting
fooled.
Only in this context specific strategies like
Volume Spread Analysis really shine.
It reveals their tactics in real-time versus
getting played reactively.
I used to think it was my broker messing with
me when my trades would go bad.
But that's not really what's happening.
Unless you're using some shady offshore broker,
they probably aren't doing anything sneaky.
The real ones triggering all those stop losses
are the smart money.
You see, those huge hedge funds and banks
can't just jump into the market all at once.
That would move the price too much against
them.
What they need is liquidity, which means being
able to build positions gradually without
affecting the market.
And that's where our stop losses come in - they
give the big players a perfect way to find
good prices without causing a spike.
Let’s stay you trade stocks.
Every time one of their trades triggers a
bunch of stops, those shares flood back into
the market for the big boys to pick them up.
So we, little guys, aren't the targets - our
stops just provide the liquidity the "smart
money" requires.
I used to think some of those classic trading
rules were a sure thing, like waiting for
the "perfect" setups at obvious support levels.
But after getting caught out a few times,
I realized there's probably more to the story.
If every trader is trying to buy at the same
exact price point, like a major technical
support level, who are they actually buying
it from?
It got me thinking - if the big institutions
know everyone is watching the same levels,
don't they have an incentive to manipulate
prices a bit to find sellers?
Why wouldn't they try to trick the average
traders like us into selling just before completing
the bounce we were all hoping for?
Now it all makes perfect sense why textbook
levels get breached so often.
Smart money will bend prices exactly where
they need for maximum liquidity grabs, masked
as "breakouts".
We are acting as liquidity!
Every time I see "smart money" pull a sneaky
fake out below or above a level, it makes
total sense in hindsight.
But in the moment it's so convincing.
They know we target trend line breakouts,
bounces off support, so price suddenly pierces
right through it, like the level meant nothing.
And of course that scares weak hands into
panic selling breakouts.
Meanwhile the big banks are scooping up our
dumped positions below the supposed break,
because they arranged the whole thing.
Textbook liquidity grab.
Then to really rub salt in the wound, price
reverses perfectly back above just like we
planned from the start – only difference
is they played us to sell the bottom!
It's so slick how they manipulate stuff to
shake out one side, provide the other, then
reverse to collect winners both ways.
And we're left scratching our heads why "good"
trades never work out.
These pros truly know psychology is the name
of the game.
When a stock clearly has big support coming
at $10 but starts wobbling around $10.50 first,
you know the pros are setting their trap already.
Cause as soon as it ticks up a few cents,
FOMO takes over weak hands.
What if price never gets to $10?
I should buy now, before it takes off!
Retail traders just can't stand the idea of
missing potential gains, so they jump the
gun buying the early bounce.
Playing right into the "smart money's" cards
as expected.
Then comes the fun part where they start the
actual shakeout.
A few well-timed breaks below support have
panic sellers transforming their long positions
into losses, just in time for the big players
to pick up their shares at a true discount.
Rinse and repeat, every single time.
This is the classic pre-support shakeout trap.
So is manipulation good or bad?
Honestly both.
If we keep getting played by their tricks,
then obviously that sucks.
But once you learn to decode charts using
Volume Spread Analysis like, manipulation
becomes more of an opportunity than a threat.
I know it's easy to consider the smart money
as the bad guys.
But really, they're not "evil" or trying to
straight up steal your cash.
We have to understand, these huge companies
are in the business of making money.
They've spent a long time learning how normal
people behave in markets, as well as how markets
move overall.
To them, trading isn't personal - it's a game
they've mastered.
With their massive funds and top-notch research
teams, big firms clearly have way more info
and power than regular traders.
They are simply capitalizing on situations
to their benefit, just like we're trying to
do.
You can't really blame them for that.
It would be dumb NOT to leverage their upper
hand.
Think about it - wouldn't YOU want to scoop
up stocks for pennies before pushing them
way higher?
You can't hate the player, hate the game.
So what are some strategies we can use to
align with smart money at their own liquidity
hustles?
First, learn to trade counter to the crowd.
Look for opportunities where most retail traders
are positioned one way, and try to time your
entry in the opposite direction, once you
spot institutional activity.
This allows you to benefit from any manipulative
moves against the herd.
How do you spot institutional activity?
Use volume analysis for buying/selling signs.
Pay close attention to volume spikes and other
volume clues to identify when smart money
is accumulating or distributing shares.
Trade with them, not against them.
Third.
Set stops outside of obvious levels.
Don't stack stops right on major support/resistance,
as this invites manipulation.
Leave some buffer room to avoid stop runs.
Focus on big volume markets.
These are harder for big players to manipulate.
And always be on the lookout for liquidity
grabs.
Watch for sudden moves that trigger stops,
then reversals that benefit those who sold
into the stop run and trade against these
fakeouts.
These videos will explain more about these
strategies.