trading breakouts appeal to many forex
traders because support and resistance
levels are supposed to be price floors
and ceilings
if these levels are broken you would
expect for the price to continue in the
same direction as the breakout if a
support level is broken that means that
the general price movement is downwards
and people are more likely to sell than
buy conversely if a resistance level is
broken and the crowd believes that the
price is more likely to rally even
higher and will tend to buy rather than
sell many retail forex traders have
greedy mentalities they believe in
trading in the direction of the breakout
they believe in huge gains on huge moves
they want to catch the big trend in a
perfect world this would be true but the
trading world is far from being perfect
breakouts fail simply because the smart
minority has to make money of the
majority don't feel so bad the smart
minority tends to be comprised of big
players with huge accounts and bias sell
orders in order to sell something there
must be a buyer however if everyone
wants to buy above a resistance level or
sell below a support level the market
maker has to take the other side of the
equation retail traders like to trade
breakouts the smart minority the
institution of more seasoned traders
prefer to fade breakouts the smarter
forex traders take advantage of the
collective thinking of the crowd or
inexperienced traders and win at their
expense that's why trading alongside
with a more experienced forex traders
could be very profitable as well that's
why today I'll present you a London
breakout Forex strategy one of my most
useful and practical breakout trading
strategies the strategy is specifically
designed to benefit from a sudden spike
of trading volume near the London open
session the London breakout trading
strategy is one of the simplest training
strategies that you can use the strategy
makes use of the increased volume that
you will see during the start of the lon
training session I'm sure you know that
the forex markets are categorized into
three main trading time zones the Tokyo
session the London session in the New
York session the London session is known
to be the start of strong volatility as
London is one of the biggest capital
markets in the world
this is because the beginning of the
London session is also the end of the
Asian session right before the London
open the Asian markets are beginning to
close down and square off their open
positions and avoiding big position
trades knowing that along the open
volatility might affect their position
prior to finding its direction that's
why during the London open hours a
sudden spike in volatility occurs
causing momentum in the forex market the
main point of this trading strategy is
that you need to focus on the short-term
aspects of the price movements that
comes with this method of trading this
trading strategy is particularly suited
for traders who trade intraday or prefer
to scalp a few points from the market if
you look closely at this chart you will
see that a price action during the asian
session is quite range-bound
prices don't make any big moves during
this period this is often the case most
of the time unless there are some big
news releases during the asian session
after you identify the session the next
step is to plot auras on two lines to
establish the range from the asian
session after the start of the london
session you will wait in for the price
to break from this range here is what
you've probably been taught to trade the
london breakout so first you need to
draw a support and resistance lines
during the asian session then place a
buy stop order approximately two or five
pips above the resistance zone afterward
place a sell stop order two or five pips
below the support zone and wait for the
breakout that's a losing system with no
chance of consistency on the long term
anyone who's tried a breakout strategy
we'll know how challenging it can be to
many breakouts don't work out the way
you expect them to many breakouts that
start off strongly quickly fade and
start to track back into a range
I've personally lost a lot of trades
trying to catch London breakouts this
way until I realize that I have to think
differently that's why during London
session I don't take trades in the
direction of the breakout I fail the
breakout I won't take the normal route
with the breakout I go the opposite way
if the price breaks above I search for
short trades if the price breaks below
the Tokyo range I love to buy the
breakout that's the concept of fading in
Trading fading breakouts simply means
trading in the opposite direction of the
breakout you would fail the breakout
if you believe that a breakout from a
support or resistance level is false and
unable to keep moving in the same
direction in cases in which the support
and resistance network end is
significant fading breakouts may prove
to be even smarter than trading the
breakout keep in mind that fading
breakouts during London session is a
great short term strategy breakouts tend
to fail at the first few attempts but
may succeed eventually so how to fail
the london breakout before the London
open draw a support and resistance line
around the last candlesticks that formed
in the Asian session I usually look for
ranges in the last hour before the
London open you don't need three or four
hours of Candlestick activity you just
need a small range of few candles prior
to the London open then wait for the
price to break that range either below
or above it when this happens you simply
wait for the price to break on the other
side of the range so you don't need to
trade the breakout you fade it you want
to see trapped traders attempting to
catch that breakout
if the price returns into the range and
breaks it on the other side you can
search for crates in the opposite
direction of the london breakout I
usually place my stop loss on the other
side of the breakout and I aim for small
profits the most ideal currency pairs to
trade the london breakout system is the
jpp USD and the JPB JPY what your
choices are not just limited for these
pairs you can also trade other major
currency pairs such as the euro USD and
usd/jpy - you should not get too caught
up with which currency pairs to trade a
lot of other currencies also experience
a lot of volatility during the overlap
of these two training sessions
therefore you should firstly pick a few
currency pairs and see how they behave
during this overlap period based on this
and depending on your familiarity with a
currency pair then you can narrow down
to trading one or two currency pairs
during this time period so here is
gbp/usd on a 5-minute chart we have the
Tokyo range here the market opened with
a downward breakout at this point we
know that we want to go long when the
price returns on the other side of that
range the market returned almost
immediately on the other side of the
range offering a good rate to the upside
with a lot of traders trapped below the
range the same pattern once again we
have the range during the asian session
a false London breakout and the move in
the opposite direction this London
breakout trading system is not a
foolproof system so you will have
trading losses and days with a true
breakout you will encounter days where
the price breaks the range and trades
above it or below it for the rest of the
day and that's okay you have to do some
work and
back test to see which bears offer most
false breakouts during the London
session here are other examples of
London breakout trades the main
advantage of trading the London breakout
trading strategy is that is very simple
there is no complicated use of multiple
indicators you just need to draw
correctly the Asian range that's the
most important part of this technique
once the trade has reached the day's
profit you don't need to stay glued to
your chart and wait for other training
opportunities as mentioned when you
stick to one or two currency pairs using
the London breakout trading strategy you
can make small profits on a daily basis
as always if you learn something new
make sure to subscribe click the
notification icon and it was a like to
show support until next time