In this video, we'll unveil the
secrets of supply and demand trading,
the only strategy you'll ever
need to master the markets.
What is Supply and Demand Trading?
So, supply and demand trading is
a strategy that focuses on identifying
price levels where there's a significant
imbalance between buyers and sellers.
This imbalance creates what we call supply
and demand zones on your charts.
In the market, there are
always two competing forces:
Buyers, who represent demand.
And sellers, who represent supply.
When there are more buyers than sellers at
a certain price level, it creates a demand zone.
When there are more sellers than buyers at a
price level, it forms a supply zone.
In these zones, you often see large
unfilled orders from big institutional
traders like banks and hedge funds.
Supply and demand trading is powerful
because it allows you to trade in
line with what the institutions are doing.
These big players can't hide their massive
orders, and by identifying supply and demand
zones, retail traders like us can spot where
they're likely to be executing their trades.
The Dynamics of Supply and Demand in Market Prices
Let's talk about how supply and demand actually
influence the prices you see on your charts.
You see, the price is constantly moving up and
down, and this movement is a direct result of the
supply and demand from market participants.
When there are more buyers in the market,
they bring demand and this applies upward
pressure on prices, pushing them higher.
When there are more sellers, they bring
more supply to the market, putting downward
pressure on prices and pushing them lower.
This dynamic between buyers and sellers is
what we call order flow, and it's the engine that
actually drives price action and market movement.
Now, there are two main types of
orders that make up this order flow:
passive orders and aggressive orders.
Passive orders are limit orders placed by traders
who are willing to wait for the price to come
to their desired level. They're not in a rush.
Aggressive orders are placed by traders who
want to execute immediately at the current
market price. They're not waiting around
for a specific price; they want in, fast.
This constant battle between passive and
aggressive orders is really what causes
those explosive price movements you see on your
charts, when there's a significant imbalance
between supply and demand.
So, your job is to identify
where major imbalances are likely to occur.
Institutional Traders' Use of Supply and Demand
So, why are institutions so
interested in supply and demand zones?
It all comes down to the
massive size of their orders.
Institutions like hedge funds and investment
banks are trading huge positions that can be
worth millions or even billions of dollars.
And when you're dealing with that kind of volume,
you CAN’T just enter or exit a trade all
at once. Imagine trying to buy a billion
dollars worth of a stock without
moving the price - it's just not
possible. There's simply not enough liquidity
in the market to absorb an order that large.
So, instead, institutions have to carefully pick
their spots and look for areas on the chart where
they can gradually build or unwind a position
over time with minimal impact on the price.
And that's where supply and
demand zones come into play.
How to Identify Supply and
Demand Zones on a Chart
Now let's break down how to actually
identify them on your charts.
The first step is to look for those explosive
movements where price makes a strong push in
one direction before quickly reversing.
This could be a sharp rally followed by a
sudden drop, or a steep decline
followed by a rapid bounce back.
These movements often signal that there
was a significant imbalance between
buyers and sellers that caused price to spike.
Once you've spotted one of these big moves, the
next step is to mark out the origin of that move.
In other words, the area on your chart where that
explosive rally or decline actually started.
This is going to be your potential supply
or demand zone.
Now, there are a few
different types of zones to look out for:
First ones are base zones or range zones:
These form when price is consolidating
in a tight range for an extended period
of time before finally breaking out.
You can think of the edges of that range
as areas of supply and demand where
a lot of orders have built up. So,
when price revisits those levels after a breakout,
there's a higher probability of a reaction.
We can also have pivot zones. These form
at key turning points in the market,
like swing highs and lows, or where
you see price making a sudden change in
direction. They're often marked by one or two
candlesticks with distinct characteristics.
For a potential demand zone, you want to look
for a strong bearish candle where the next
candle closes back above its high, signaling a
shift from selling pressure to buying pressure.
For a supply zone, it's the opposite:
you're watching for a strong bullish
candle where the next candle closes below its
low, indicating a shift from buying to selling.
The key is that these pivots are
happening quickly; price isn't spending
much time in these areas before reversing.
To identify fresh zones, you also want to pay
attention to the overall structure of the price
action. There are two main types of structures
to look for: continuation and reversal.
A continuation structure forms when there's
an existing trend in place and price is just
pulling back or correcting against that trend
before continuing in the same direction.
These are your rally-base-rally
and drop-base-drop patterns.
If it's an uptrend, you'll see a strong rally,
a tight range where price forms a small base,
and then another rally continuing the uptrend.
For a downtrend, you’ll see a sharp drop, a base,
and then another drop resuming the downtrend.
Reversal structures form when price is
reversing from one trend direction to the
other. These are your drop-base-rally
and rally-base-drop patterns.
So, in an uptrend that's starting to lose
steam, you might see price drop into a base,
and then launch into a new rally,
marking the start of a reversal.
And in a downtrend that's starting to turn around,
you'd see a rally, a base, and then a strong drop,
signaling the beginning of a new uptrend.
Key Principles of Supply and Demand Trading
Now let's talk about the key principles
that make this strategy so effective.
The first thing to understand is that supply
and demand zones are not just random levels on
your charts; they're areas where the imbalance
between buyers and sellers is most extreme.
When you see explosive price movements like
huge rallies or steep drops, that's often a
sign that there was a serious mismatch between
the amount of buying and selling pressure.
What's happening in these situations is that
the aggressive orders from one side are rapidly
consuming all the available orders from the
other side, until a new equilibrium is found.
The areas on your charts where these big
clashes take place are what we call fresh,
unmitigated supply and demand zones.
One of the key things that separates
these high probability zones from
ordinary support and resistance levels,
is the amount of time price spends in the zone.
You see, when there's a major imbalance between
buyers and sellers, the price won't
hang around that area for very long;
it will quickly spike up or down.
So, when you're analyzing your charts,
one of the things to look for is zones where the
price only spent a short amount of time before
making a strong move in either direction.
The less time price spends in that area,
the more out of balance supply and demand are,
and the higher the probability of a successful
trade when the price returns to that zone.
Another key principle is to focus on fresh
unmitigated zones, rather than ones that
have already been tested multiple times.
When price revisits a zone, it can absorb some
of the pending orders that were sitting there,
making the imbalance less extreme.
So, as a general rule, the more times
a zone has been hit, the weaker it becomes.
This is why it's so important to understand
the difference between an unmitigated zone and
one that's already been tested a few times,
a mitigated one. The trading
opportunities are very different.
Now, of course, there are times when a zone
can remain valid even after being tested,
if there's still a significant order imbalance,
but generally, you want to prioritize fresh
zones when planning your trades.
So, the key things to look for are:
Zones that form after explosive price movements
Zones where price only spends a short
amount of time before spiking up or down
And fresh zones that haven't been tested
or absorbed by the market yet.
Validating Supply and Demand Zones
Now let's talk about how to actually
validate whether a zone is likely to hold.
The first thing you want to look
for is a clear break of structure.
This means price needs to make a
decisive move away from the zone
and take out any nearby swing highs or lows.
If there's no clear break of structure and price
just hovers around the zone, that's a sign that
the zone might not be as strong as it seems.
Another key concept is the idea of flip
zones. This is when a previous supply zone
turns into a demand zone or vice versa.
For example, let's say you have a strong
supply zone that's been holding price down
for a while, but then suddenly price rips
through that level and closes above it.
That's a pretty good indication that the
zone has flipped from supply to demand and could
now act as a support level for future pullbacks.
But here's the thing: in order for a flip
zone to be valid, you need to see that
initial interaction between the two forces.
Don't just assume a zone has flipped because
price moved past it. Look for that clear battle
between buyers and sellers and wait for one
side to decisively overpower the other.
Another important factor to consider is
inducement. We talk about this before. This refers
to the presence of liquidity in front of the zone
that could potentially absorb any move against it.
For example, if you're looking at a demand zone,
you want to see some buy orders
stacked up in front of that level.
This could be in the form of a swing low or a
consolidation pattern - anything that suggests
there are traders waiting to buy at that price.
If there's no liquidity in front of the zone
and price just slams into it, chances
are those big players aren't going to
be too interested in getting involved.
But if there are orders they can trade
against, they're much more likely
to step in and defend the level.
Of course, even if a zone checks all these
boxes, it's not guaranteed to hold forever.
That's why it's also important
to look at how fresh the zone is.
In general, zones that have been tested
multiple times are less likely to produce
strong reactions than those that
are being hit for the first time.
Supply and Demand Zones vs.
Support and Resistance Levels
Now let's talk about the difference between
supply and demand zones and traditional
support and resistance levels.
While they're similar concepts,
there are some key distinctions.
First off, support and resistance are
levels where price has previously reversed
or consolidated multiple times in the past.
Supply and demand zones, on the other hand,
are all about fresh, unmitigated levels.
Rather than focusing on areas that have
already been touched multiple times,
these zones represent imbalances between buyers
and sellers that have just recently formed.
The key difference is that support and resistance
trading relies on the assumption that past levels
will continue to hold in the future, whereas
supply and demand trading looks for new,
untested zones where the order flow
is likely to be more significant.
Remember this: support and resistance levels
are essentially supply and demand zones that
have already been confirmed.
Once a fresh demand zone gets
tested and holds, for example, it then
becomes an established support level.
The same goes for supply zones, flipping
to resistance after they've been touched.
So, while trading support and
resistance can certainly be effective,
especially if a level has proven
itself multiple times in the past,
the probability of a reaction tends
to diminish with each subsequent test.
This is why you should focus on fresh zones, where
the initial imbalance between buyers and sellers
is likely to be the most significant.
Optimal Entry and Exit Strategies
Now let's talk about some specific entry and exit
strategies you can use around these key levels.
One of the simplest and most effective ways
to enter a trade at a supply or demand zone is
to simply set a limit order
directly on the level itself.
This approach assumes that the zone will hold and
that price will reverse once it hits your order.
However, there are a couple of potential
downsides to this aggressive strategy.
If you set your order too far away from the
zone, you might miss out on the trade entirely
if price never quite reaches your price.
Or the second scenario, price might just
break through your zone with ease.
A more conservative approach is to
wait for a specific candlestick pattern to
form at the level, before entering a trade.
For example, you might look for a
bullish reversal pattern, like a pin
bar or an engulfing candle, at a demand zone.
The idea behind this strategy is that these
candlestick formations can give you a bit more
confirmation that the zone is likely to hold
and that price is getting ready to reverse.
Another technique you can use to fine-tune your
entries is to look for specific
structures on lower time frames.
For example, let's say you've identified a
strong demand zone on the 1-hour chart, but
you want to get more precise with your entry.
Instead of just buying blindly at the level,
you could drop down to the 15 minute chart and
look for a reversal pattern, like a double bottom
or a change of character, to form at the zone.
In this way, you can often get a tighter
entry with a better risk-to-reward ratio.
Assessing the Strength of a Supply or Demand Zone
Now let's talk about how to evaluate
the strength of a supply or demand zone.
One of the first things to look at is how quickly
price moves away from the zone after it's formed.
Generally speaking, the faster price shoots
away from a level, the stronger that level
is likely to be. Quick and significant moves
away from a zone indicate a strong imbalance.
So, if you see price just rocketing
away from a zone, that's a pretty good
sign that there's some serious order flow
happening there, and that institutions are
likely defending the level aggressively.
Another factor to consider is the amount
of time price spends at the zone,
before making that initial move.
The less time price hangs out at a
level, the more likely it is to be a
key turning point in the market.
So, if you see price just kind
of dip into a demand zone and then
immediately start rallying higher,
that's often a signal that big buyers have stepped
in, and are absorbing all the available supply.
The actual size of the move is important
too. Obviously, if price barely budges
after hitting a supply or demand level, that's
not exactly a big endorsement of its strength.
But if you see an extended move in the opposite
direction after a zone is tested, that's a sign
that the level is probably pretty significant.
Another thing to watch for is the volume during
the formation of the zone. Generally speaking,
you want to see a noticeable uptick in volume,
as price is testing a key level.
This indicates that there's a lot
of interest and activity happening at that
specific price, and that institutions are
likely absorbing or distributing there.
Another factor that can affect the
strength of a zone is whether or not
it causes a break of market structure.
A supply or demand zone that causes a
break of structure is generally stronger.
It takes a significant amount of money
to break market structure, making these
zones more likely to hold in the future.
So, if you see a zone form and then price
just starts trending in the opposite direction
and breaking through key levels on the chart,
that's often a sign that there's some serious
institutional backing behind the move,
and that the zone is likely to be
a key focal point going forward.
Avoiding Common Mistakes in
Supply and Demand Trading
Now let's talk about some of the most frequent
mistakes that traders make when it comes to supply
and demand, and how you can avoid them.
One of the biggest errors is trading
from a weak structure.
This often happens when
traders zoom in too much on their charts
and lose sight of the bigger picture.
They might see a high that failed
to break the previous one and
think it's a good supply zone to short.
But if the overall trend is actually bullish,
they're likely to get smashed trading
against that dominant direction.
So, always consider the broader context before
entering a trade. It's crucial to align your
trades with the current order flow.
Traders also tend to have the wrong
expectations of how far price will move
after hitting a supply or demand zone.
Old demand zones, for instance,
often become reaction points
for pullbacks rather than areas for new highs,
especially when order flow turns bearish.
So, if you're expecting a full trend reversal from
an area that's already been tested multiple times,
you might end up disappointed.
It's also a frequent mistake to
trade from zones with no inducement.
Inducement refers to the liquidity
that's available in front of a zone.
If there's no structural low or other
liquidity built up in front of a demand
zone, that means the only available liquidity
is actually behind the low itself.
That lack of inducement makes the
zone more prone to failure.
So, always check where the
orders are stacked in relation to your zone.
Now, if you want to take an even deeper dive
into some of the strategies we've touched on
here, be sure to check out these next videos!