support and resistance is often tght as
a beginner strategy but here's the twist
it's actually one of the most
misunderstood Concepts in trading this
is the guide you need to watch if you
really want to trade T levels like a
professional
Trader trading is all about finding
edges and support and resistance levels
are one of the most powerful edges you
can have but these invisible lines on
your charts can make or break your TR
rates basically support and resistance
are price levels where the market tends
to pause or reverse support is an area
that catches falling prices resistance
is an area that stops prices from rising
further and it's all about supply and
demand at support buyers step in they
see the price as a bargain and start
buying at resistance sellers take over
they think the price is to high and
start selling here's the key these
levels aren't exact prices they are more
like zones where interesting things
happen but why should you care about
support and resistance first they help
you understand Market structure you can
see where price is likely to pause or
reverse this knowledge is gold for
timing your entries and
exits second these levels show you where
other Traders are placing their orders
big players often cluster their orders
around support and resistance and when
you know where the big money is that's
your Edge we'll talk about that later
third support and resistance levels are
self-fulfilling Traders expect price to
react at these levels so they Place
their orders accordingly this Collective
action makes those areas even more
interesting
now let's dive into the minds of buyers
and sellers at this key price points at
support levels buyers tend to step in
seeing the price as a good deal they
believe the price is undervalued and
expect it to rise from this point this
buying pressure often causes the price
to bounce off support at resistance
levels sellers become more active they
view the price as too high and
anticipate a drop leading to increased
selling pressure this Behavior creates a
self-fulfilling prophecy as more Traders
watch these levels and act on them their
Collective actions make the levels more
likely to hold at least
temporarily Market memory plays a
crucial role in shaping these zones
Traders remember past price levels where
significant buying or selling occurred
these memories influence future trading
decision decisions the concept of
Trapped Traders also contributes to
Market memory imagine a Trader who
bought at a certain price only to see
the market drop he might be eager to
sell at a break even when the price
returns to his entry point this creates
resistance as these trapped Traders exit
their
positions support and resistance zones
often form around round numbers ending
in zero or double zeros this is partly
due to the psychological Comfort we find
in round numbers many Traders Place
orders at these levels creating natural
support and resistance the strength of
support and resistance levels can change
over time a level that's been tested
multiple times without breaking becomes
more significant in Traders minds but it
also becomes more likely to eventually
break as more Traders are watching it
and positioning themselves around it
when a support or resistance level does
break the ensuing price move can be
dramatic this is because many Traders
Place their stop-loss orders just beyond
these levels when the level breaks it
triggers a Cascade of orders
accelerating the price move this
behavior is often exploited by large
Market players who might push the price
through a level to to trigger these
stops before reversing the
move high quality support and resistance
levels have several special trades that
make them stand out on a chart one of
the most prominent features of strong
levels is the presence of sharp big
reversals these are points on the chart
where the price makes a sudden and
significant change in direction for
example if price is falling rapidly and
then suddenly bouncing is back up just
as quickly this sharp reversal could
indicate a strong support level this
dramatic price movements suggest that
there's a significant imbalance between
buyers and sellers at these levels
leading to Quick
reversals high quality support and
resistance levels often show multiple
instances of price bouncing off them
this repeated Behavior reinforces the
importance of this levels for inance
if you notice that a stock price has
bounced up from a level several times
this could be an important support level
these multiple bounces demonstrate that
Traders consistently recognize these
levels Anda on them creating a
self-fulfilling
prophecy swing highs and lows are
another important feature to look for
because they represent areas where the
balance between buyers and sellers shift
at significantly
high quality levels often demonstrate
the ability to act as both support and
resistance this characteristic known as
roll reversal happens when a broken
support level becomes a new resistance
level or when a broken resistance level
becomes a new support level this
phenomenon happens because Traders
remember these levels and adjust their
behavior
accordingly one of the key traits of
high quality support and resistance
levels is that they are visually obvious
on a chart these levels should stand out
clearly even to an inexperienced Trader
if you have to squint your eyes to
identify a level it might not be as
significant as you
think the most powerful support and
resistance levels are those that are
immediately apparent when you look at a
chart this visual prominence is
important because it means that many
Traders are like to notice and act on
these levels increasing their potential
impact on price
movements support and resistance levels
that have been recently respected tend
to be more reliable than older levels
this is because market conditions change
over time and levels that were
significant in the distant past May no
longer be relevant look for levels that
have influenced price movements in the
recent past as these are more more
likely to continue playing a role in
current and future price action round
numbers often act as psychological
support and resistance levels for
instance many Traders might set their
takeprofit orders at
$100 if a stock is approaching that
level From Below or they might set
stop-loss orders just below
$100 if the stock is trading above it
this clustering of orders around round
numbers and create noticeable support
and resistance effects the strongest
support and resistance levels typically
combine multiple traits for example a
level might be a round number have acted
as both support and resistance in the
past show multiple bounces and be easily
visible on the chart the more of these
characteristics level exhibits the more
likely it is to be a significant support
or resistance point
and when drawing support and resistance
lines on your charts remember that they
don't always need to be exact prices can
sometimes break slightly past these
levels before reversing known as a false
breakout or they might reverse Direction
just before reaching the level an
imperfect
reversal so you might need to draw a
wider Zone rather than a precise line to
capture all the relevant price action
now before we continue let us know in
the comments what topics you'd like us
to cover please tell us what you want to
watch
next now let's talk about support and
resistance flips when price breaks
through a support level it shows a shift
in power from buyers to sellers the
former support level then often becomes
a new resistance level this happens
because traders who bought at a support
level and are now facing losses may sell
when the price returns to that level
creating
resistance when price breaks above a
resistance level that level can become a
new support level as traders who missed
the initial move up may buy at the
former resistance now viewing it as a
good entry point these flips demonstrate
the psychological aspects of trading
Traders remember price levels where
significant shifts occurred and their
Collective actions around these levels
can create self-fulfilling prophecies
the strength of these flipped levels
often depends on how decisively the
original level was broken a strong high
volume break of a support or resistance
level is more likely to result in a
reliable flip than a weak break on low
volume the number of times a level has
acted as support or resistance in the
past also influences its strong strength
after a flip a level that has been
tested multiple times before breaking is
often more
significant when a support or resistance
level is broken wait for a retest of
that level before entering a trade if a
former support level holds as new
resistance or vice versa it can confirm
the
breakout sometimes a level will fail to
hold after flipping for example a broken
support level might not hold as
resistance these failed flips can lead
to strong moves in the opposite
direction as traders who were counting
on the level holding are forced to exit
their
positions when trading support and
resistance flips consider the overall
Market context in strong Trends flipped
levels are more likely to hold while in
choppy or ranging markets they may be
less reliable
volume can provide additional
confirmation high volume on the initial
break and again on the retest can
increase the likelihood of a successful
flip and it's also important to note
that not all support and resistance
levels will flip cleanly or hold after
flipping the market is dynamic and even
strong levels can be broken under the
right
circumstances one powerful aspect of
support in resistance flips is that they
often Mark the beginning of new trends
when a longstanding resistance level is
finally broken and then holds a support
it can signal the start of a significant
uptrend when a strong support level
breaks and then acts as resistance it
might indicate the beginning of a
downtrend liquidity runs at support and
resistance are a key part of how big
players move the market
these moves also called stop hunts or
liquidity grabs aim to trigger stop
losses and force Traders out of
positions the reality is that big
players need liquidity to enter and exit
large positions they often find this
liquidity clustered around support and
resistance levels that's where many
Traders Place their stop losses and
entry orders think about it if you're
buying at support where do you put your
stop loss usually just below that level
if you're selling at resistance your
stop is likely just above big players
know this and use it to their advantage
a typical liquidity run might look like
this price approaches a key support or
resistance level it briefly breaks
through triggering stop losses and
breakout entries then price quickly
reverses trapping Traders on the wrong
side these moves can be frustrating if
you're caught in them but they're not
random they serve a purpose for big
players to build positions at better
prices for example if big players want
to buy they might push price down to hit
stop losses below support this creates
selling pressure driving price lower the
big players can then buy at these lower
prices before letting price rise again
to protect yourself from liquidity runs
use wider stops don't place them just
beyond obvious levels also wait for
confirmation never enter on the first
break of a level but you can do more
than just avoid these traps you can
profit from them by thinking like the
big players instead of buying at support
wait for a potential stop run below it
then buy when price starts to recover
you're now buying at a better price
aligned with the big
players and resistance wait for a push
above the level before looking to sell
this strategy requires patience and
practice but it can lead to better
entries and less risk remember liquidity
runs often happen at the most obvious
levels previous day highs and lows round
numbers major swings and levels tested
multiple times are prime targets to spot
potential liquidity runs watch for Price
approaching a key level with increasing
momentum price action that seems to defy
logic or previous patterns unusual
volume spikes near the level quick
reversals after breaking a level unusual
Candlestick patterns with long Wicks or
does and multiple tests of a level in a
short time this pattern suggest big
players might be trying to trigger stops
or attract breakout
traders of course not every break off
support or resistance is a liquidity run
sometimes levels break cleanly the key
is to watch how price behaves after the
break in a true liquidity run price
usually reverses quickly if it continues
strongly in the breakout Direction it's
more likely a genuine move to profit
from liquidity runs you need to be
patient and disciplined don't chase the
initial breakout wait for signs that the
move is losing steam or
reversing for example if price breaks
below support but starts to form bullish
candles it might be time to consider a
long trade your stop can go below the
recent low giving you a tight risk this
approach aligns you with how big players
trade they're not trying to pick exactly
tops and bottoms they're looking to
enter after the liquidity run when
smaller Traders are getting stopped out
or chasing the move in the wrong
direction also consider the bigger
picture liquidity runs on Lower time
frames might be ins significant noise in
the context of larger Trends always
start your analysis on higher time
frames to identify the most important
levels another tip a liquidity run that
goes against the main trend is often a
good opportunity to enter in the trend's
direction if the overall trend is up a
stop run below support might be a great
place to buy as you gain experience
you'll start to see liquidity runs as
opportunities rather than
threats volume is a key tool in trading
support and resistance it's like a
secret code that reveals the strength of
these levels when you mix volume with
price action you get a powerful method
called volume price
analysis as you already know not all
levels are the same some are strong and
some are weak and how do you know which
is which that's where volume comes in
think of volume as the fuel that drives
the market when there's a lot of volume
at the price level it means there's a
lot of interest there this can create
strong support or resistance
the volume profile tool is great for
finding these key levels it shows you
where most trading happened the areas
with the most volume are often important
support and resistance zones when you
look at a volume profile focus on three
main levels first the point of control
this is where most trading occurred it's
often a strong support or resistance
level then the profile high this can act
as resistance and lastly the profile low
this can act as
support these levels matter because they
show where buyers and sellers were most
active they're like battle lines where
the big players fought over price when
price nears a key level watch the volume
closely if price breaks through with
high volume it's often a real breakout
but if it breaks through with low volume
it might be a fake out
on the flip side if price touches a
level and bounces off with high volume
that's a strong Rejection it means the
level held firm but if it bounces with
low volume the level might not be as
strong as it looks here's a cool trick
when price makes a big move away from a
level use the volume profile to see
where the most trading happened during
that move that spot often becomes a new
support or resistance level when price
returns to it later let's say you see a
big price drop you can put a volume
profile on that drop to find where the
most trading occurred that area might
become resistance when price rises again
if it does it could be a great place to
sell remember the market Moves In Waves
it trends for a while then pauses in a
congestion phase then either keeps
trending or
reverses understanding how volume works
with these moves is key to reading the
market when you're looking at a
potential trade don't just look at the
price check the volume too is it above
average that's a sign of strength is it
below average that might mean the move
is weak if you're thinking about buying
at support look for high volume as price
touches that level that show strong
buying interest if you're thinking about
selling at resistance look for high
volume there too that can mean strong
selling pressure as we already talked
false breakouts and liquidity runs are
common traps in trading when price
breaks through a key level don't just
jump in right away wait for volume to
confirm the move a true breakout should
come with above average volume and if
volume is low
it might be a fake out but here's a cool
trick sometimes a failed breakout can be
an even better trade if price breaks out
on low volume and then quickly
reverses that can be a strong signal to
trade in the opposite
direction don't forget about time frames
what looks like a breakout on a 5minute
chart might just be noise on a daily
chart always check higher time frames to
get a big picture before making your
decisions learning to read volume in
conjunction with support and resistance
takes practice but it's worth the effort
you'll see trading opportunities you
never noticed
before trading support and resistance
will differ considering if the markets
are trending or they are ranging and
most Traders don't think about this
aspect which is a major mistake in a
strong Trend support support and
resistance levels can help you catch big
moves when the market is trending up or
down with Force it's not wise to fight
it instead look for ways to join the
trend at good prices here's how to use
these levels in a strong uptrend as
price climbs it will often pause and
drop back a bit these dips often stop at
Old resistance levels which now act as
support sometimes price price will move
sideways for a while this is like a
pause in the trend it can form a small
range near a support or resistance level
watch for breakouts when price breaks
above the high of the consolidation it
can signal the trend is ready to
continue in a strong downtrend you'd use
the same ideas but in reverse look for
bounces from resistance consolidations
and breakdowns below support
ranging markets are trickier price
bounces between support and resistance
without a clear Direction here's how to
use these levels first identify the
range look for Clear areas where price
has turned multiple times wait for tests
of these levels as price approaches
support or resistance watch closely how
it acts here can tell you a lot you then
look for rejection signals if price
touches support and bounces up with
force it might be a good time to buy if
it hits resistance and drops hard
consider selling be cautious of false
breakouts price often pokes above
resistance or below support only to
reverse look for wicks or multiple Wicks
outside the range watch for
consolidations near the top or bottom of
the range a consolidation within the
consolidation if price forms a tight
range it can signal a potential
breakout of course use volume high
volume on a bounce off support can
signal a strong move low volume might
mean the move is weak in ranges you're
often looking to buy near support and
sell near resistance but be ready to
change your view if the range breaks and
a new trend starts and consider the time
frame levels on a daily chart might not
match what you see on a 5-minute chart
be clear about your trading
Horizon here are some useful tools for
finding hidden support and resistance
levels first one involves Fibonacci
retracements this use special ratios to
find hidden price levels this is how to
use them first find a big price move up
or down then draw a line from the start
to the end of this move the tool will
show you the main levels of this move
and these levels often act as support or
resistance that's because many Traders
watch them when lots of people act on
the same levels it can make them work in
an uptrend price might pull back to
these levels they could act as support
in a downtrend price might bounce off
these levels as resistance but you don't
just buy or sell at a fib level wait for
price to to show it's respecting the
level use fibs with other tools they
work best when they line up with other
support or resistance levels this is
called a
Confluence pivot Points are another
great way to find daily levels they're
based on previous days high low and
close and they can show possible support
and resistance for the current day this
is how to use pivot Points first look
for price to pause or turn at these
levels if price is above the main pivot
it might be bullish below the pivot
might be bearish use S1 and R1 for first
targets S2 and R2 for bigger moves watch
how price acts at the pivot a break
above or below can signal the day's
Direction pivot Points work well in
ranging markets and they're less useful
in strong trends remember using just one
tool isn't enough smart Traders combine
methods so look for overlaps if a fib
level pivot point and round number all
line up that's a strong level also use
multiple time frames a daily pivot might
match a weekly FIB level and add price
action watch for Candlestick patterns at
these
levels time frames play a big role in
finding and using support and resistance
effectively these levels gain strength
when they are visible on higher time
frames a level that shows up on a daily
chart is often more significant than one
on a 5minute chart this is because
higher time frame charts represent more
trading activity and longer term Market
sentiment when you spot a level on a
higher time frame it often acts as a
stronger support or resistance point
more Traders are likely watching it and
it may take more buying or selling
pressure to break through for example if
you see a clear support level on a
weekly chart it might hold even if price
dips below it briefly on an hourly chart
this is why many Traders start their
analysis on higher time frames and then
zoom in for more detail lower time frame
charts can show you more precise entry
and exit points they are also useful for
short-term price action around major
levels on Lower chart you'll see early
signs of a level breaking or holding but
remember lower time frame moves are
often just noise in the bigger picture a
level that looks important on a 5minute
chart might mean nothing on a daily
chart the solution for combining the
higher with the lower charts is a
multiple time frame analysis here's how
to use it start with a higher time frame
to get a big picture I like to use the
daily chart then move to your trading
time frame to find specific setups the
hourly chart is a good one then use a
lower time frame to fine-tune entries
and exits of course you may use other
combinations you might use a weekly
chart to find major levels a daily chart
to ident Iden ify Trend Direction and a
4-Hour chart to enter trades this is a
very important strategy it will help you
understand the overall Market context
and you'll avoid trading against a
bigger Trend plus you'll find better
entry points for your trades now if you
liked what you saw we have plenty more
interesting trading guides for you
[Music]