When you’re trading supply and demand zones,
I bet you use classic candlestick charts.
But here’s an idea: what if you used Heiken
Ashi candles?
Would it improve your results?
100% yes.
Today I’m showing you my unique way to trade
supply and demand areas, without noise, using
The only reason why price moves in any market
is because of an imbalance in supply and demand.
The greater the imbalance, the greater the
move.
A strong uptrend can only exist if buyers
outnumber sellers.
During a trend, price moves up until enough
sellers enter the market to absorb the buy
orders.
The origin of strong bullish trends is called
an accumulation or a demand zone.
Bearish trends are created when sellers outnumber
buy orders.
Then, price falls until a new balance is created
and buyers become interested again.
The origin of a bearish trend wave is called
a distribution or a supply zone.
A Demand Zone is a price area below the current
price action where there is strong buying
interest.
Looking at this chart, we can see that there
was a lot of buying interest at this demand
zone.
For this reason, when the price reaches the
level, you will notice a sharp price reaction
from the Demand Zone.
The Supply Zone is the exact opposite of the
Demand Zone.
A Supply area is located above the price action
and it typically contains a relatively big
volume of sell orders.
When the price action reaches this level,
the price reverses to the downside.
Now, let’s introduce Heiken Ashi into equation.
Heikin Ashi has proven to be one of the best
strategies to use to gain a deeper view of
the market, because with these tools it’s
easier to read candlestick charts and analyze
market trends.
Traders use the Heikin Ashi to get information
such as when to stay in a trend trade or if
it’s time to get out because the trend has
reversed.
I don’t want to insist too much on this
topic, as I have several videos on this channel
explaining how these candlesticks work.
Just remember that Heikin Ashi filter noise
and help you to see trend better.
So why trading supply and demand areas using
Heiken Ashi?
As you know, the candles on traditional candlestick
chart usually change from green to red, making
it difficult for some traders to read them
properly.
However, the candles on a Heikin Ashi chart
display more consecutive colored candles,
making it easy for traders to identify past
price movements, current trends and of course,
supply and demand zones.
With Heikin Ashi, trends usually stay green
in an uptrend and red in a downtrend.
For me personally, is much easier to find
supply and demand areas using these candles.
This isn’t the case with the traditional
candlestick charts where colors are different
even if the price is moving strongly in one
direction.
How do you mark a supply and demand zone using
Heiken Ashi?
The idea is to find the place on the chart
where demand overcame supply (for long trades)
or where supply overcame demand (for short
trades).
STEP 1: Identify current market price
STEP 2: Look left on the chart
STEP 3: Look for big green or big red Heiken
ashi candles
STEP 4: Find the origin of the big candles
STEP 5: Mark the zone around this ‘origin’
Since the Heiken Ashi candles start from the
middle of the previous candle, I had to come
up with a slightly different way to mark these
areas, compared to classic candles.
For a supply zone, I search the last BULLISH
Heiken Ashi candle before the drop.
Once you’ve done this, you need to drag
a rectangle up to the most recent high before
the drop.
For a demand zone, I look for the most recent
BEARISH candle before the up move and drag
a rectangle down to the most recent low before
the up move.
Supply and demand levels can be:
• Fresh: It means price has not pulled back
yet, it’s an untested level
• Non-fresh: Price has pulled back to it
at least once
• Used up: Price has pulled back to level
several times, and these are not good for
trading full swings, maybe some scalping trades
Plotting these areas should be done with a
logical and organized approach.
Often, supply and demand traders tend to pollute
charts with tens of levels, where the whole
meaning of anticipating the rejections loses
the value.
So try to keep your charts clean.
When it comes to efficient plotting of supply
and demand zones on the Heiken Ashi chart,
here are main variables that you should follow,
which will increase your efficiency a lot:
-focus on the freshest supply and demand zones
-focus on the strongest zones, those where
price left the zone in a quick, strong move
-focus on nearest zones, so do not plot 50
levels on charts, have only the nearest ones
in sight to keep the chart clean
-focus as much as possible on dense zones
where the price was consolidating for a while
before forming zone
The fresh zone always has priority over the
old historical supply or demand zone because
the statistical chance for order flow to be
still participating in the fresh zone is higher
than in the old historical zone.
As the time passes, the traders will slowly
liquidate positions over time, that is the
fact.
Thus the fresher the zone, the more focus
the trader should put on it.
Personally, I only draw 3 to a maximum of
5 zones on chart at most, on different time
frames, no more than that.
Now let me show you how you find the best
supply and demand Heiken Ashi zone to trade.
I look for several clues:
1.
STRENGTH OF SUPPLY AND DEMAND ZONE
First, you determine the STRENGTH OF THE MOVE.
How did price leave the level?
The stronger the price moves away from a zone,
the more out-of-balance supply and demand
are at that zone.
It means a heavy order is placed by smart
money.
Here’s an example showing different types
of zones.
The first one is the strongest, with large
bearish candles forming after the price left
the area.
The second one is a strong zone, with big
Heiken Ashi candles with no upper wicks and
a few candles having wicks.
And the third one is a weak zone, price moving
down in an unconvincing manner.
This is very powerful, so please remember
this part.
2.
TIME AT SUPPLY AND DEMAND LEVEL
How much time did the price spend at the zone?
The less time price spends at a zone, the
more out-of-balance supply and demand are
at that price level.
This means Smart money are aggressively entering.
The first example is the strongest zone, with
one bearish candle rejecting the area.
The second one is a strong zone, with several
Heiken Ashi inside the zone.
And the third one is a weak zone, with many
candles and a lot of time spent around this
area.
3.
THE MOVE AWAY FROM THE SUPPLY AND DEMAND LEVEL
Here you analyze how far did the price move
away from the zone before returning back around
the area?
The longer the distance the price moves away
from a zone before returning to that zone,
the greater the reward to risk and probability.
When price goes from selling off to a strong
bullish trend for example, there had to be
a significant amount of buy interest entering
the market, absorbing sell orders AND then
driving price higher.
Always look for extremely strong turning points;
these are the high probability price levels.
4.
FRESHNESS OF BASE
Number one rule in supply and demand trading:
First-time retrace to the base is the strongest
to enter.
If you trade of supply areas, always make
sure the zone is still “fresh” which means
that after the initial creation of the zone,
price has not come back to it yet.
Each time price revisits a supply zone, more
and more previously unfilled orders are filled
and the level is weakened continuously.
This is also true for support and resistance
trading where levels get weaker with each
following bounce.
The rules of supply and demand trading using
Heikin Ashi are simple.
You should buy when the price action approaches
a demand level and bounces upwards forming
a green Heiken Ashi candle, ideally with no
lower wick.
You expect the price to increase and you want
to trade an upcoming price swing.
And you should sell when the price reaches
a supply level and bounces downwards, forming
a red Heiken Ashi candle, ideally with no
upper shadows.
You would put a stop loss order right below
the demand area when you are long in the market.
Conversely, put your stop loss order right
above the supply area.
The most common approach is to hold your trades
until the price action reaches an opposite
level on the chart.
So, if you are trading long a demand level,
you should hold your trade until the price
action reaches the next supply zone on the
chart.
Or you could close a part of your position
after a Heiken Ashi color change.
How to define a trend using supply and demand
and heiken ashi
Since we are primarily working with supply
and demand imbalances on Heiken ashi chart,
making a higher high or a lower low does not
necessarily mean the existing trend will continue.
Here’s my PRO TIP.
1.
In an UPTREND: demand areas are being respected,
supply areas are being taken out.
So a higher high SHOULD remove previous supply
to validate the demand zone
2.
In a DOWNTREND: supply areas are being respected,
demand areas are being taken out.
A lower low SHOULD remove previous demand
to validate the supply zone.
This type of analysis will help you a lot
in defining the strongest Heiken ashi supply
or demand zones.
• In a downtrend: supply areas are consistently
respected and demand areas are taken out
• In an uptrend: supply areas are taken
out, while demand areas are respected
AS SIMPLE AS THAT.
And another tip is to look at your D1 or H4
chart and see what is going on with the supply
and demand areas in control and decide which
direction to trade.
Once you know what direction you want to go,
locate lower timeframe supply or demand areas
with a strong move away, little time at the
level and also a fresh level.
Now, it’s important to understand that there
can be several periods of accumulation during
an uptrend and several periods of distribution
during downtrends.
This means that there are supply and demand
reversal patterns and supply and demand continuation
patterns.
The Drop-Base-Rally is a bullish reversal
pattern
The Rally-Base-Drop is a bearish reversal
The Rally-Base-Rally is a bullish continuation
pattern
The Drop-Base-Drop is a bearish continuation
This is important because understanding which
phase the market is in, what is the underlying
trend and how long has it been in place, determines
which are the best demand and supply zones
to look for.
In an old trend, you will want to look for
reversals.
In a new trend you will want to look for continuations.
You search for Rally-Base-Rally zones during
uptrends and for Drop-Base-Drop during downtrends.
And remember that every timeframe has its
own trend and multiple trends coexist.
You may be trading in an uptrend on H1, but
the D1 is in a downtrend
So, the first thing you need to do is to decide
the time frames you will be using for a multiple
timeframe analysis of the trend.
You need at least 2 time frames.
When several timeframes are combined to evaluate
a market, you will easily improve the odds
of success for your supply and demand trades,
regardless of the other rules applied.
This alone lowers risk as there is a higher
probability that price action will eventually
continue on the longer trend.
As always, if you got any value from this
and learned something new, drop a like to
help us with Youtube algorithm, and make sure
you click the bell icon to stay in touch when
new videos are released.
Until next time.