I don’t know about you, but I don’t like
spending all day in front of my trading screen.
I want to have the time to do other activities I
enjoy, while having some trades in the background.
So, I’m revealing a profitable one-hour trading
strategy and I will share how I find leading
signals, how I know right at the beginning of
the day if the market is worth trading or not,
and all of this by spending
just 30 minutes in the morning.
Before we begin, if you want to show your
support, please leave a like to help us
with Youtube algorithm and turn on the bell, so
you don’t miss when new videos are released.
The speed of the markets on lower time frames
represents a big problem for many traders.
All the trading decisions you make
will have to be done much faster.
One solution to this problem is
trading the one hour time frame.
The 1 hour chart offers flexibility,
there’s considerably less noise
and it also generates enough trades so you
have lots of decent chances of making money.
This strategy involves finding trending days based
on the central pivot range, a leading indicator,
and taking trades around safe areas,
in the direction of the main trend,
using simple price action.
By the end of this video,
you’ll know right at the beginning of the
day if you are going to trade your market
and you’ll also know the
direction you’ll follow.
If I have to name my favorite
indicator, well it’s the Pivot Points.
Pivots are nothing but support/resistance,
based on the high/low/close of previous day
and offers you a framework to trade on.
By plotting Pivot Points on your chart,
it will show you boundaries, where price
is likely to face support/resistance.
Unlike lagging indicators, pivots don’t
change as you change your timeframe,
once you plot them on your chart at the market
opening, they remain there until market closes.
And one more aspect, pivots
are being used by big players.
I came to know about the Central
Pivot Range concept after reading
the “The Logical Trader” by Mark Fischer.
CPR is nothing but a range of 3 lines, one above
and one below the central pivot point of the day.
The fundamental idea behind this indicator is that
the particular day’s trading range captures
everything about the market sentiment,
so this range can be used to predict the
price movement of the following days.
How to read the price action
using the Central Pivot Range.
When the CPR makes higher highs, meaning
CPR is higher than the previous day,
that indicates that the particular
market is in an uptrend.
When the CPR makes lower lows, meaning
CPR is lower compared to the previous day,
this indicates that the market is in a downtrend.
As long as the price is above CPR, it is generally
known as bullish day, and as long as the price
is trading below CPR, we are in a bearish day
Of course, this doesn’t mean if you see price
trading above CPR you’ll go and buy it. CPR is
just a guideline, and I will show you later
how to filter and find the best signals.
The wider the Central Pivot Range, the more
difficult for the price to break the area.
This basically means that wider Central Pivot
Ranges are more powerful than a narrow width CPR.
Have a look at this chart. This was a wide
CPR day, and when price retraced to the area,
it found support and was unable to go below it.
And look what happened when the CPR was narrow.
The price broke on both sides of
the area, hunting stop orders.
And no clear trend during the day, just sideways
price movement and lots of consolidation.
So if CPR is too narrow it's unlikely the CPR
will offer a solid support or resistance area.
Whenever CPR is too narrow I don’t pay
much importance if the price comes near it,
because it can easily pierce it and break it.
So, remember, narrow CPR doesn’t
offer much support/resistance.
Also, when Central Pivot Range
is wider, often but not always,
such days are range days, where price moves
from one range to another throughout the day.
Look at this example. We had a strong move
upward, so the next day the CPR was quite wide.
We had a range day, around this
area. And remember the previous rule.
A wide range means that it’s more difficult
for the price to break the area.
Another observation is that a narrow
Central Pivot Range can lead to a big
trending day and wide Central Pivot Range
can lead to quiet and range bound day.
In this example, you can see a very narrow
range day, which lead to a huge move during
the day. Observe how the price was trending
in one direction, with lots of momentum.
And of course, after such a strong
trending day, the next day was a wide
range CPR, with sideways price action.
This an efficient way to analyze price,
quite different from the classic
price action techniques.
There’s another high probability setup,
and that is the Fresh Central Pivot Range.
If on any given day, price didn’t
touch its CPR, it will be considered
as Fresh CPR for next coming 2 or 3 days.
Here’s an example, the price made an aggressive
move downward and the next day, price action
didn’t touch its CPR. So that was a Fresh CPR,
an important area to keep an eye
on for the next several days.
Sometimes, during the trading day, you’ll
see no candlesticks inside the CPR,
but only one or two wicks entering inside the CPR.
This is also a Fresh CPR and still a
very powerful support/resistance area.
And here an interesting fact I
found out after my backtesting.
Price respects a Fresh CPR at the opening of
the session compared to mid to late afternoon.
So if the previous day was a fresh CPR, and
today at the opening, price approaches the area,
then that fresh CPR has a high chance to
work as a strong support or resistance.
If price approaches the previous day fresh
CPR after the middle of the trading session,
then the CPR isn’t likely to work as strong
support/resistance and price can easily break it.
Here’s an example.
We have a Fresh CPR on chart,
and on the next day, the market opened below
the fresh CPR, touched it, and the area acted
as resistance and price immediately reversed.
So Fresh CPR works as strong support/resistance
at opening and less powerful during
the second part of the trading day.
Plotting the CPR on your chart can give you
a great edge in your Trading. CPR is also
known as “heartbeat” of the market where price is
likely to change its direction most of the time.
CPR is a powerful support and resistance
area. So, it is not a good idea to go short
when price is above the CPR, because it
will act as a support area, and it’s not a
good idea to go long when price is below CPR
because it will act as a resistance area.
The idea of the strategy is to buy and sell the
waves of a trend. One of the best ways to buy
and sell pullbacks in a trend is to play
the bounces off the central pivot range,
which is the method many professionals use.
Essentially, each pull-back to the pivot range
is a buying opportunity within an uptrend,
and a selling opportunity in a downtrend.
How do I define a trend,
using the CPR? Very simple.
If the current day CPR is higher than the
previous one, we have a short term uptrend.
We look for long entries above the CPR.
If the current day CPR is lower than the
previous one, we have a short term downtrend. We
look for short entries below the CPR. This is an
important condition in our strategy.
So at the beginning of the day,
the first step you need to take is to analyze the
position of the CPR, relative to the previous day.
• If it’s higher, you know that during the
day you’ll be searching for long entries.
• If it’s lower, you know
you want to short the market.
If the CPR is wide, you know that the price will
most likely find support or resistance at the CPR,
but you will also be prepared
for ranging conditions.
If the CPR is narrow, you can have a
strong trending day, but at the same time,
the CPR may not offer much support and resistance.
Using the H1 time frame, you remove the noise on
the lower time frames. Just by looking at the
chart at the beginning of the trading day,
you’ll know what to expect. This is how
trading should be. Planned and organized.
Here are several techniques
I use to filter signals
and to trade only the high probability ones.
The first one is the classic trend line breakout,
which is one of the most effective
strategies if traded correctly.
Trendlines connect consecutive higher
lows in an uptrend and consecutive
lower highs in a downtrend. The idea is to
use the momentum of a trend line breakout,
to find areas around CPR area.
The strategy here is very simple:
If the price breaks a downward trendline, the
CPR is higher compared to the previous day,
and the price is testing the central pivot
range from the upper side and founds support,
then you should look for long positions.
Conversely, if the price breaks an upward
trendline, the CPR is lower compared to the
previous day, and the price is testing the
central pivot range from the lower side and founds
resistance, then you look for short positions.
Here’s the euro yen. We had a sustained downtrend,
a 3 days uptrend and a trend line breakout.
As the price broke this previous swing, it found
resistance at the lower central pivot range.
The rejection came in the form of a
pin bar. As the central pivot range
was also lower than the previous one, the
conditions were met for a short position.
Also, this is a wide range CPR, and we already had
some previous price action returning to the zone.
We know that during wide CPRs, we could witness
some ranges. So a short right below the CPR
was also in line with this, because the
price already moved throughout the day.
Stop loss goes above the CPR or above the
central pivot point (being a wide range),
and you target the next big swing or a minimum
1.5 reward, compared to your risk.
We have an uptrend, with a 4 day downtrend
correction, 4 consecutive CPR days. Here we
have the first up central pivot range,
and a double bottom around this level.
The next day was also an up CPR day, with
the price breaking above this trendline.
This time, the price managed to
reach the middle level of the range,
the central pivot point, found
support and continued its uptrend.
Always look for candlestick
formations to reveal rejection.
In this case, it was a pin
bar, forming inside the CPR.
We also had confluence with this swing high
breakout, which became support. Long above the
CPR, with a stop loss either below the pin bar
inside the CPR, or below the middle CPR line,
and you target the next swing
high, right here.
The second strategy involves
the Ichimoku cloud, but we’ll
use only the conversion line or Tenkan Sen.
The Conversion Line will help you with the
short-term price momentum and also signals
an area of minor support or resistance.
• If the market price is above the conversion
line, this indicates a short-term upward momentum,
and you would want to
concentrate on buying signals
• If the price is below conversion line,
this reveals a short-term downward momentum,
and you would want to search for selling signals
You also need to pay attention
to the slope of the line.
• An increasing conversion line,
meaning an upward slope, indicates an upward trend
• A decreasing conversion line, meaning a downward
slope, indicates a downward trend
The idea is to find zones with the
central pivot range and the conversion
line close together, areas of confluence.
So if CPR is higher compared to the previous
day, the price is testing the central pivot
range from the upper side and stays above the
conversion line, you look for long entries.
If CPR is lower compared to the previous
day, the price is testing the central pivot
range from the lower side and stays below the
conversion line, you look for short entries.
Here’s a long entry. We have an
upward CPR day, higher than the
previous day, so we look for long trades.
The CPR is wide, so we expect strong support.
We also have the conversion line
offering support. And look what happened
when price entered the zone. It touched the
conversion line, formed a pin bar and reversed.
This strategy offers a lower stop loss. You
could place it below the conversion line,
or below the pin bar rejecting the area. You don’t
need to place it all the way below the area.
And here’s a short Tesla trade.
We found a lower CPR day, price is
below the conversion line, so downward momentum.
At the opening of the session, price entered the
central pivot range, and touched to the pip,
both the upper level and the conversion line,
and immediately moved in the opposite
direction, forming yet another pin bar.
The pin bars are my go-to signals,
perfect for this strategy.
As there is clearly bearish pressure, we
took a short trade right after the pin bar.
Stop loss above the conversion line,
which is also above the pin bar and CPR,
targeting the next swing.
If and when price moves above
the conversion line, you need to be careful
and close at least a part of your position
because momentum is shifting
to the other side.
As always, if you got any value
from this and learned something new,
drop a like to help us with Youtube
algorithm, and make sure you click
the bell icon to stay in touch when new
videos are released. Until next time.