in this course I'm going to teach you
everything you need to know about
getting started with day trading we'll
break down day trading into easy to
understand Concepts from Market
structure and price action to volume
spread analysis trading indicators and
strategies we'll cover it all in a clear
and concise manner so like subscribe and
let's get started
the price chart of any Market may appear
like a random distribution but this is
not so recent studies show that around
30 percent of the time a market will be
in a definite Trend the rest of the time
price will trade more or less in a
sideways range your job is to recognize
Trends early as they emerge from
non-trends or as reversals of Prior
trends
so first you must know the basics of
Market structure and how to find Trends
on any Market Market structure refers to
the overall state of the market which
can be labeled as either an uptrend
downtrend or consolidation
identifying the current state of the
market is the first step when you want
to day trade an uptrend is characterized
by a series of higher highs and higher
lows
this means that each Peak and Valley on
a chart is higher than the previous one
indicating that buyers are in control of
the market
downtrends can be identified by looking
for lower lows and lower highs in a
downtrend each subsequent high and low
should be lower than the previous one
indicating that sellers are in control
of the market
the consolidation occurs when the market
is neither in an uptrend nor a downtrend
this means that the price is moving in a
range-bound manner with no clear
direction to determine a consolidation
look for a series of highs and lows that
don't show a clear uptrend or downtrend
a change in Trend occurs when the market
transitions from an uptrend or downtrend
to consolidation or vice versa to
identify a change in Trend look for a
series of lower lows and lower highs
that transition to higher highs and
higher lows
or vice versa it sounds basic but
understanding Market structure is
essential to any successful day trading
activity
so day trading success is quite
dependent upon being on the right side
of the trend but also executing the
trade at an optimal time the main
problem is that not all Trends are
created equal and there are multiple
Trends spread across many many time
frames that exist simultaneously
how do you determine a strong trend you
have two choices to use price action or
to use trading indicators
many day Traders especially beginners
are drawn to indicators hoping that an
indicator will show them when to enter a
trade I prefer to rely first on price
action I also use indicators in my
trading and I will show you later which
are the best ones to use but price comes
first you don't need an oscillator to
tell you if there's a trend happening
price is mainly a consensus between the
sellers and the buyers and is influenced
by human psychology and by supply and
demand now individual candlesticks will
give you a great insight into human
psychology if you learn how to analyze
them correctly I don't want to bore you
with the basics you just have to know
that each Candlestick displays the Open
high low and close of the time frame the
direction upward or downward of the time
frame and the range of the time frame
the Candlestick has a wide part called
the real body this real body represents
the range between the open and the close
price
and the long thin lines below and above
the body are referred to as wigs Tails
or Shadows
in day trading you need to have momentum
on your side momentum refers to the
sustained increase or decrease in the
price of a market it's a measure of the
Velocity at which the price changes and
momentum analysis is one of the most
important skills a day trader can learn
there are two ways of looking at
momentum the first one just looks at the
overall trend strength and a price is in
a strong or healthy Trend you can say
that the momentum is bullish or bearish
at the same time momentum also exists
when we just look at individual
candlesticks so by analyzing recent
candlesticks you can determine the price
momentum
here are the main rules for determining
the strength of a trend and its momentum
number one the market breaks its
previous swing high or low we talked
about this before a trend is generally
defined by a series of higher highs and
higher lows in the case of a bullish
trend
or a series of lower highs and lower
lows as a bearish trend that's the first
condition of a trend
number two the distance between swing
highs or lows meaning how far the swing
highs or lows are apart is a sign of
trend strength if the most recent swing
high was far above the previous swing
high that shows that the market has a
lot of buying interest and strength if a
swing High forms just barely above the
prior swing High the price may still be
in an uptrend but is not moving as
strongly
three most of the candlesticks are Trend
candles in the direction of the trend
a trend candle has a body that is
greater than 50 percent of the entire
bar range
if a candle closes above its opening
price it's a bullish Trend candle
and if the candle closes below its
opening price it's a bearish trend
candle so when you day trade and read
candlesticks search for Trend
candlesticks by analyzing the bodies if
you see many recent green Trend candles
for example you're probably in a strong
uptrend
number four there is very little overlap
of the bodies of consecutive candles
the degree of overlap with the previous
candle tells you the current market
phase and the power of the price bar in
a strong Trend there is very little
overlap of the bodies of consecutive
candles
for example in a minor uptrend many
candles have lows that are at or just
below the closes of the prior candles
some candles don't even test the clothes
of the prior bar the point is if you
find a minimal overlap between a candle
and the preceding one it implies urgency
again and this bearish down move many
bars have highs that are at or just
above the closes of the prior bar
this shows strength and it's an
important sign because the market is
unable to go higher and it keeps pushing
lower
number five there are bars with no Wicks
or small wicks in either direction this
again indicates urgency in the market
for example in an uptrend if a green
Trend candle opens and immediately
Trends up it means Traders were eager to
buy it as soon as the prior candle was
formed if it closes near its high
Traders continue their strong buying in
anticipation of new buyers entering
right after the bar closes
6 gaps between the bodies occasionally
you will find gaps between the bodies of
the candles for example the open of a
candle might be above the close of the
prior candle in an uptrend or below the
close of the prior candle in a downtrend
again a gap is a sign of urgency and a
sign of Market strength
7. Trend candles after a gap
this is even more powerful not only the
market formed a knob Gap like in this
example but it continued with a strong
Trend bar indicating the conviction of
buyers and their willingness to push
price higher
8. no retest of previous breakouts we'll
talk about breakouts later but you
probably know the classic way to trade
them you must wait for prices to retest
the breakout level a retest refers to
prices reversing Direction after a break
and returning to the breakout level to
see if it holds the tendency is for
prices to return to the break-off level
which should now act as a support and
attract buying interest but in a strong
Market you will not get a retest
the buyers are unwilling to let the
price drop lower
number nine no significant trend line
breakouts
plotting trend lines on a chart is one
of the easiest ways to get a quick idea
of a market strand or Direction
when drawing trend lines in a downtrend
you draw them above the price
connecting the high points
when you draw trend lines in an uptrend
you draw them below the price connecting
the low points
at least two swing highs or swing lows
are needed to draw a trend line in
either direction
now a broken trend line is a technical
signal that can suggest a change in
Trend but in a strong Trend you don't
experience breakouts of significant
trend lines
number 10 sideways corrections after
trendline breakouts in a strong Trend
when a trendline breakout occurs there's
no momentum behind the move
there is sideways price action a
sideways drift occurs when the price
trades within a fairly stable range
without forming any distinct Trends
price action instead oscillates in an
horizontal range or Channel with neither
the buyers nor sellers taking control of
prices
11 small Corrections and sideways
pullbacks
in an uptrend we have more green candles
than red ones this means that the buyers
have more power and are increasingly
moving the market upwards
also during a market controlled by
buyers the red candles are getting
smaller as the sellers can drive the
price down
so the corrections will be small and in
some cases the price section will appear
in a sideways range
conversely during a market controlled by
sellers the green candles are getting
smaller again Corrections will be
smaller when you compare them with
downward waves
12. breakout candles have large bodies
and small wigs when the price finds
support or resistance in its way it
usually manages the push through with a
strong candle a breakout candle that has
a large Trend body for example and small
leaks or no Wicks is a sign of strength
the larger the candle the more likely
the breakout will succeed
13 weeks below green candles during
uptrends and above red ones during
downtrends
so in a strong uptrend you will also see
a lot of Wicks below the green bars this
represents a good signal that the buyers
are in control of the market and that
are trying to push the prices upwards
you will also see a lot of Wicks above
the red bars in a strong downtrend this
shows that the sellers are in control
and that are successfully pushing the
prices downward despite the initial
reaction of the buyers
I hope you realize that candlesticks
provide a lot of information about who
is in control of the market than most
Traders realize almost every candle
offers important Clues as to where the
market is going
stay close because in a future module
we'll add the volume component for this
analysis
now I don't want to bore you with a
multitude of candlesticks used in day
trading when I'm trading I tend to
heavily rely on two special patterns as
the entry trigger the first one is the
PIN bar a pin bar is a price action
pattern which is supposed to Signal a
reversal maybe about to take place in a
market
notice of the red body of the candle is
found at the bottom of the Candlestick
and the long week is found at the top
sometimes the body of the candle will
not be found right at the bottom but it
will always be found in the bottom half
of the Candlestick in the case of a
bullish pin bar the body of the bullish
pin bar is found at the top of the
candle and most of the wick is found at
the bottom
another Candlestick which must be highly
important in your day trading activity
is the engulfing candle
firstly engulfing candlesticks begin and
end every movement in the market
whenever you see the market go from
being in an uptrend to a downtrend at
the beginning of that movement an
engulfing Candlestick is present in some
shape or form engulfing candles are the
result of big money coming into the
market usually by large Banks or other
financial institutions this is what
makes engulfing candles such a great
entry trigger the one defining
characteristic of the engulfing
candlesticks is they have a large body
which is always bigger in size than the
body of the candlesticks in immediately
before it the engulfing candle wraps
itself around the previous candle the
setup begins when we see a large bullish
candle which happens to be immediately
followed by a bearish candle the second
candle being the bearish engulfing one
notice of the body of the bearish
engulfing one is bigger than the body of
the bullish candle seen before it
if you want to increase your chances to
succeed at day trading you must align
yourself with big players in a market I
do this by using supply and demand when
I first started day trading I focused on
support and resistance levels these are
the specific price points on a chart
which are expected to attract the
maximum amount of either buying or
selling a support is a price area at
which you can expect more buyers than
sellers
a resistance is a price area at which
you can expect more sellers than buyers
but over the last years I've slowly
Incorporated supply and demand in my day
trading plan this trading approach takes
the best of support and resistance and
adds the concept of Supply instrument
news events speculation and General
market action caused different groups of
traders to place buy and sell positions
resulting in changes to the supply and
demand in a market these changes
manifest visually as the Rises declines
and consolidations you see on your
charts when you see price Rising it
means demand outweight Supply
when you see a price following Supply
alt weights demand now changes in Supply
and demands happen when the banks and
other big players decide to enter their
positions we retail Traders can cause
price to rise or fall because we don't
have enough money only the smart money
with their high buying and selling power
can make price move and the banks never
Place their full positions all at once
their positions are very large so they
must break them into smaller pieces and
place each trade individually around a
similar price to avoid pushing price
away and potentially forcing the entry
at the bad price
in day trading it is all about finding
points where the banks have initiated
positions and then jumping into trades
when the price returns to the supply or
demand area
supply and demand trading is a method
where the idea is to find points in the
market where the price has made a strong
Advance or decline and Mark these areas
as supply and demand zones demand zones
form when Banks place a large number of
buy positions this creates an imbalance
and results in the price aggressively
moving higher these are the support
levels of supply and demand Trading
Supply zones are points where the banks
place a significant number of cell
positions resulting in price
aggressively moving lower
these are the resistance points where
price could fall
and if price returns to a certain Supply
or demand Zone it has a high probability
of rejecting these areas
so how to identify the best supply and
demand areas do they trade here's my
process in the first place you look for
Sharp Rises and the coins in price these
are the first signs that smart money are
active you can call them Market
imbalances big price shifts in One
Direction
to find the main zones you look for fast
impulse up moves keep an eye on big
green candles Trend candles we talked
about them in the previous modules
the long bodies and with little to no
wicks
once you have identified a fast impulse
move it becomes a lot easier to find the
base of the zone you find the most
recent red candle before the impulse
move and place a line at its high price
and another line at the most recent
swing low that formed at the source of
the move
some may choose to place the first line
at the open price and the second one at
the most recent low you can choose any
method you want
to find Supply Zones look for fast
declines again yellow 4 Trend red
candles with long bodies and little or
no wicks
you then find the most recent up candle
before the sharp down move and place a
line at its low price and another line
at the most recent swing high that
formed at the source of the move
in theory price has a high probability
of reversing once it returns to the
source of the decline
before you start day trading supply and
demand there are two key rules you need
to understand to find the right zones on
the chart and to trade them correctly
using your entry method
first rule is that all zones rarely work
a big misconception is that the longer
the market has been away from a supply
or demand Zone the better chance the
market has of reversing when it
eventually reaches the Zone this is
wrong recent zones are far more
important supply and demand areas which
have been created recently are far more
effective than zones which were created
a long time ago
second rule is to trade only fresh on
touch zones another big misconception is
the idea that supply and demand zones
have the power to cause reversals more
than once like support and resistance
levels too again this isn't true supply
and demand zones are one-time use when
price hits a Zone and reverses the Zone
loses its power the probability it will
cause another reversal in the future is
lower
foreign
ERS get confused between the concepts of
supply and demand and support and
resistance so let's talk about the
difference between these two concepts
supply and demand zones are advanced
concepts of support and resistance they
both indicate points where the price can
reverse the big difference between the
two is that support and resistance often
works on historical older and tested
levels while supply and demand
especially on Fresh levels
support and resistance trading is
particularly strong in multiple touches
of the previous levels when you day
trade based on support and resistance
you mainly look for points where
multiple reversals started from similar
prices
here's a level with multiple reversals
you can see that each of the reversals
originated from prices which are quite
close to one another
so a support level must be found
somewhere close to where this price
movement started now when trading supply
and demand things are different if you
want to day trade using this concept
you'll mainly look for new zones
a supply or demand zones is a fresh
untouched area where price spent less
time you don't watch in the history of a
market for the validity of the zone you
don't wait for multiple retests of the
same area
another difference if price will break
the support Zone then the support will
become resistance and vice versa this is
a common day trading strategy which is
actually very powerful when traded
correctly we'll talk about this later
but in the case of supply and demand
this concept doesn't apply a supply Zone
which is broken doesn't turn into a
demand Zone
I would even say that all support and
resistance lines were originally
supplies or demand zones
this is how support and resistance were
created they are essentially the
confirmed supply and demand levels
so supply and demand are fresh levels or
zones where a price has not been
determined yet therefore these levels
are valid to trade
support and resistance are levels which
are already confirmed
probably the biggest problem when
trading support and resistance levels is
the fact that price will often fail to
turn exactly on the level itself you
know it so well you expect the perfect
bounce when you place your level but
oftentimes price will either remove
slightly beyond the level before
reversing all will reverse before
touching the level
and that's the main advantage of supply
and demand they offer you a bigger area
at which the market should reverse you
don't have to find an entry at an exact
point
you have a whole Zone you can use to
place your positions
now there are four types of supply and
demand considering how the price
approach the supply and demand Zone and
how it left the Zone again I've labeled
them into continuation structures and
reversal structures continuation price
structures include the drop base drop
and the rally base rally patterns and
the reversal price structures are the
drop base rally and the rally based drop
patterns
the rally base rally is a type of demand
Zone which forms during an up move
being a continuation pattern the market
structure is very simple we first have a
rally then a consolidation or the base
and finally another rally which creates
the demand Zone
a rally based rally will always form a
demand Zone it can never create a supply
Zone
the drop based drop is a type of Supply
Zone which forms during a down move also
being a continuation pattern
so a drop based drop will always form a
supply Zone a Zone which if the market
returns to should push the price back in
the direction of the movement that
created the zone
the drop base rally is a structure which
forms a demand Zone in a market these
zones differ from the first price
structures mainly because of their
location in the market if the rally
based rally and the drop based Drop
Zones only formed during trending
movements the drop-based rally zones
will only be found when the market
changes from moving down to moving up
it's a reversal pattern
the rally based Drop Zones form when the
market reverses from moving higher to
moving lower when they are completed a
supply Zone will have formed in a market
which should cause the market to fall
again A reversal structure
understood the basic principles of
supply and demand your next step is to
learn to read the volume well volume
spread analysis is the study of price in
relation to its corresponding volume it
tries to find out the differences
between supply and demand in day trading
VSA is very important because it tracks
down the professional activity the moves
of the smart money
first you need to know the components of
the volume spread analysis first is the
spread the spread is the difference
between the opening and closing of the
price volume is the number of
transactions during a time interval
then we have bearish and bullish volume
bearish volume shows bearish activity
bullish volume shows bullish activity
then we have above average high volume
this is the highest volume in the
current session Which is higher than the
average volume and then we have the
ultra high volume it's the highest
volume in the current session
this indicator tells you whether the
volume is ultra high high low or average
it's called the volume spread for VSA
it's very easy to read volume using it
red means ultra high volume
yellow means high volume
green is average volume and blue is low
volume
now VSA can seem difficult but I'll try
to keep it as simple as possible there
are two major applications of VSA namely
sign of strength and sign of weakness
sign of strength occurs when the supply
is drying up after a downtrend and
demand increases
meaning more buyers come in and there
are less sellers in the market
this imbalance between supply and demand
causes the market to rise
sign of weakness occurs when demand is
drying up after an uptrend and Supply
increases in other words more sellers
come in and there are less buyers in the
market this imbalance between supply and
demand causes the market to fall
when I'm day trading I'm looking for
different signals of sign of strength or
sign of weakness
VSA goes hand in hand with a well-known
analysis method developed by Richard
Wyckoff Wyckoff stated that changes in a
market price are the result of an effort
which is represented by the trading
volume
so effort volume versus the result price
if the price action is in harmony with
the volume there is a good chance the
trend will continue
but if the volume in price diverged
significantly the market trend is likely
to stop or even change direction
based on this here are the best sign of
strength volume patterns for day trading
first is the downfrost the downtrust
appears as a bullish pin bar or a doji
bar having an ultra high volume or above
average volume
spread of the down frostbar is extremely
low meanwhile the volume is relatively
High
VSA implies that if the spread is low
then the volume should also be low but
in this case there is a Divergence
between spread and volume so there is
more demand than Supply potentially
causing price to rise in the near future
then we have the selling climax the
selling climax appears as a high spread
bearish candle having a noticeable
downward rejection week but on ultra
high or above average high volume
the signals that the market could rise
in the future because there is more
demand than Supply
the selling climax signal could have a
downward Wick whose size is around 25 to
50 percent of the candle's body size
then we have bearish effort lower than
the bearish result
this appears as a high spread bearish
candle whose spread is larger than the
previous candle spread but its volume is
lower than the previous scandal's volume
an effort meaning volume has not been
made but there is a result the spread
this disagreement between price and
volume increases demand and reduces
Supply causing the market to potentially
rise in the future
next is the bearish effort higher than
the bearish result
disappears as a low spread bearish
gamble having spread lower than the
previous Scandal spread but its volume
is higher than the previous candle's
volume
an effort has been made but there is no
result
in this case there's a disagreement
between volume and price which might
rise in the near future
we have also done no Supply bar this
appears as a low spread bearish candle
having a downward wake whose volume is
lower than the previous two candles
volumes
no Supply bar means that there is a lack
of Supply causing price to rise in the
future
an all Supply bar is a continuation
signal and is effective only if it
appears in the direction of the trend
there are other VSA sign of strength
signals but from my experience these are
the most effective ones to incorporate
in your day trading strategy
now let's talk about the different types
of sign of weakness
first is the up thrust the up Frost
appears as a bearish pin bar or doji bar
having an ultra high volume or above
average volume
the spread of the up thrust bar is
extremely low while the volume is
relatively High
in this case there's a disagreement
between spread and volume which
signifies that there is more Supply than
demand potentially causing price to fall
in the near future
next is the buying climax the buying
climax appears as a high spread bullish
candle having a noticeable upward
rejection week projected on ultra high
or above average high volume
this signals that the market could
decrease soon because there is more
Supply than demand buying climax could
also have an upward week representing 25
to 50 percent of the candle's body size
then we have the bullish effort lower
than the bullish result this is a high
spread bullish candle whose spread is
larger than the previous candle spread
but its volume is lower than the
previous scandal's volume
VSA states that if there has been no
effort made then there should not be the
result
these Divergence between price and
volume increases Supply and reduces
demand causing the market to decrease in
the future
then we have the bullish effort higher
than the bullish result
this is a low spread bullish candle
having spread lower than the previous
candle spread but its volume is higher
than the previous candle's volume
VSA suggests that if an effort has been
made then there must be a result
in this case there's a disagreement
between price and volume resulting
Supply to become more than demand and
causing price to fall in the near future
and then we have the no demand bar this
is a low spread bullish candle having
upward week whose volume is lower than
the previous two candles volumes the no
demand bar means that there is a lack of
demand and Supply is overpowering demand
causing price to fall in the future
no demand is a continuation signal and
not a reversal signal and is effective
only if it appears after bearish
momentum in the direction of the trend
there are other VSA patterns you could
follow but for now stick with this
if you want to learn more about VSA
check out this video after you finish
watching this one analyzing VSA was a
really game-changing moment in my day
trading it will be hard at first but
with time you'll see the volume patterns
more clearly volume spread analysis is
one of the most powerful day trading
strategies which reveal the true
sentiment in the order flow of the
market
most day Traders are using lagging
indicators in their analysis and their
lagging signals can only be known after
the event don't get me wrong this
doesn't make them useless they can
clarify and confirm your bias but
leading indicators or signals are the
ones you should consider adding in your
technical analysis leaning indicators
give signals when the trend is about to
start whereas lagging indicators are
those which follow price action my
favorite leading indicator is the volume
we talked about it in the previous
module because it communicates the
involvements of smart money
volume spread for VSA indicator became
an important tool in my day trading
routine supply and demand concept is
another leading tool
from the multitude of lagging indicators
I also use a couple of them but the most
important one is the view up so let's
talk about it
the volume weighted average price gives
you the average price a market has
traded throughout the day based on both
volume and price and this tool is
important especially in day trading the
viewer appears as a single line on
intraday charts similar to a moving
average view up is a simple indicator
the price is either above it or below it
that's why it's an easy measurement on
whether a market is cheap or expensive
on the day
you can use it to help you pinpoint
intelligent entry and exit points for
your day trades and at the same time it
can help you to determine Trend changes
often quicker than a moving average
for day trading you can read The View up
to generate buy and sell signals this
can be simply done by comparing the
relationship between view up and the
current market price
if the current market price exceeds a
rising view up this suggests the Buy
Signal if the price Falls below a
falling view up it suggests a sell
Signal View up can also be used to
detect Trends and changes in price if
price action stays above the view up
this signals that the price is in a
general uptrend if price action stays
below the view up they signals a general
downtrend and using v-wop to identify
support and resistance levels can be
another useful function in day trading
you can use view app to identify dynamic
levels and buy when price retraces
testing the level
and sell when price rejects a dynamic
resistance area
mostly Traders are using the daily view
up but you can also day trade based on
the weekly and even monthly view up
weekly view up shows you the trend
depending on where the price is trading
above or below in relation to the view
upline
again one of the simplest uses of the
weekly view up is for finding pullback
opportunities
view outline acts as a support if the
price is trading above it and as a
resistance if the price is trading below
it
[Music]
anchored view up is another variation
which has an edge over the default
version
I'm using trading View and you can find
the anchored view up in trendline tools
the anchored view obtains its
calculations to a specific price bar you
choose
evolved view up always starts with the
first bar of the day and ends with the
final bar of the day but in some
situations you would prefer to analyze
the view of line based on another
starting point and be able to extend
that view of line beyond the end of the
trading day
anchored v-wop allows you to specify the
price bar where calculations begin
making it easy to see whether buyers or
sellers have been in charge since a very
specific point in time with anchored
view up you choose a first candle you
are anchoring the indicator to that bar
you have full control and you get
flexible starting and ending points
so how do they trade using the anchored
view up a good strategy is to look for
key price swings or turning points in
recent price action to Anchor The View
up
you basically Place The View up on these
key levels
the most common strategy using the
anchored view up is the pullback trade
a pullback occurs when the price that's
on an extended move upward or downward
makes a small movement in the opposite
direction towards the anchored view up
line
to trade a pullback setup you find an
uptrend with price making higher highs
and higher lows then you anchor The View
up on a key pivot
price trades of course above the angle
view up and you patiently wait for a
price to make a pullback to the downside
returning to the view of line This is a
chance to buy the market in this Zone
you can find a demand area or a VSA
pattern as an entry
look how price reacted to the anchored
view upline the first pullback after we
applied the line was a perfect bounce
rate
another day trading strategy is to
Anchor The View up on the highest volume
candle
I said it before high volume means
there's an interest in the market and if
it's combined with a move higher in
price then it's often used as a signal
of strong upward momentum
in this example we identified the
highest volume we added the anchored
view up
and the line immediately offered several
opportunities to buy the dip
you go with the flow of the highest
volume and try to catch another swing to
the upside when price comes back to the
anchored view up as a standalone study
or when viewed with other oscillators
the anchored view up is a must use tool
in day trading
pivot Points are my favorite day trading
indicators pivots are fixed support and
resistance levels based on the high low
and close of the previous day unlike
lagging indicators pivots don't change
as you change your time frame once you
plot them on your chart at the market
opening they remain there until the
market closes and one more important
aspect pivots are being used by big
players
in recent years I focused on the central
pivot range I came to know about the
central pivot range concept after
reading the logical Trader by Mark
Fisher
CPR is a range of three lines one above
and one below the central Pivot Point
the fundamental idea behind this
indicator is that a particular trading
range captures everything about a market
sentiment thus this range can be used to
predict the price movement of the
following days
so how to read the price action using
the central pivot range when the CPR
makes higher highs meaning the CPR is
higher than the previous day that
indicates that the market is in an
uptrend
when the CPR makes lower lows is lower
compared to the previous day this
indicates that the market is in a
downtrend
as long as the price is above the CPR
it's generally known as a bullish day
and as long as the price is trading
below the CPR we are in a bearish day
The Wider the central pivot range the
more difficult for the price to break
the area this basically means that wider
Central pivot ranges are more powerful
than a narrow waist CPR
have a look at this chart this was a
wide CPR day and when price retraced
that area it found support and was
unable to go below it
happened when the CPR was narrow the
price broke on both sides and no clear
Trend during that day just sideways
price movement and lots of consolidation
so if the CPR is too narrow it's
unlikely it will offer a solid support
to resistance area
also when the central pivot range is
wider often but not always such days are
range days where price moves from one
range to another throughout the day
look at this example we had a strong
move upward so the next day the CPR was
quite wide we had a range day around
this area and remember the previous rule
a wide range means that is more
difficult for the price to break the
area
another observation is that the narrow
Central pivot range can lead to a big
trending day and the wide Central pivot
range can lead to quiet and range bound
days
in this example you can see a very
narrow range day which lead to a huge
move during the day observe how the
price was trending in One Direction with
lots of momentum and of course after
such a strong trending day the next day
was a wide range CPR with sideways price
action this is an efficient way to
analyze price quite different from the
classic price action techniques
and there's another high probability day
trading strategy and that is the fresh
Central pivot range if on any given day
price didn't touch its CPR it will be
considered as a fresh CPR for the next
coming two or three days
here's an example the price made an
aggressive move downward and the next
day price action didn't touch its CPR so
that was a fresh CPR day an important
area to keep an eye on for the next
several days
CPR is a powerful support and resistance
area essentially each pullback to the
pivot range is a buying opportunity
within an uptrend and the selling
opportunity in a downtrend
at the beginning of the day the first
step you need to take is to analyze the
position of the CPR relative to the
previous day
if it's higher you know that during the
day you'll be searching for long entries
if it's lower you want to short the
market
if the CPR is wide then the price will
most likely find support or resistance
at the CPR but be prepared for ranging
conditions
if the CPR is narrow you can have a
strong trending day but at the same time
the CPR may not offer much support or
resistance
[Music]
as I said before a lot of day Traders
are using lagging indicators and then
they complain that day trading is hard
if you use RSI stochastic or macd and
try to find overbought and oversold
signals then I agree you won't enjoy day
trading much I also focused on this
lagging indicators when I started a day
trade no shame in that but nowadays when
I'm analyzing a lagging tool I mainly
look for divergences because they offer
leading signals
I use the stochastic indicator but you
can replace it with any oscillator you
prefer
in day trading divergences should be one
of your most important tools because
they signal momentum coming into the
main Trend or indicate a possible
reversal when the trend is nearly over
again leading signals
a Divergence occurs when the price and
the indicator provide conflicting
signals by moving in opposite directions
there are two types of divergences
regular and hidden a regular bearish
Divergence appears during an uptrend
when the price is making higher highs by
the indicator the stochastic indicates a
lower high that's an indication of
Market exhaustion and a possible sign of
Market reversal or at least a short-term
correction
a regular bullish Divergence appears
during a downtrend when the price is
making lower lows but the oscillator
records higher lows thus the regular
bullish Divergence suggests a possible
Market reversal or a short-term
correction
in a bullish hidden Divergence the
oscillator makes lower lows but the
price makes either a higher low or a
double bottom low
this type of pattern occurs mainly
during uptrend Corrections
in this example the price was in a very
strong upward Trend and recorded an
important correction the price failed to
record new lows enclosed higher than the
previous downward swing if we look at
the oscillator it recorded a lower low
thus forming a hidden Divergence and
signaling that a possible upward
movement is on the cards
in a bearish hidden Divergence the
oscillator makes higher Highs but the
price makes either lower price or double
bottom highs
this type of pattern occurs mainly
during downtrend Corrections in this
example after a strong uptrend the
recent price action indicated a downward
momentum with price making lower highs
the oscillator recorded higher highs
thus forming a hidden Divergence
with regular divergences the oscillators
indicate momentum shift and thus points
toward the reversal of the trend this
implies that the regular Divergence
warns that the end of the trend is
expected
hidden divergences signal momentum
coming into the main Trend suggesting a
possible continuation in the main
direction of the trend
the reason why so many day Traders fail
when taking Divergent signals is because
they take counter Trend signals they
spot a regular Divergence and
immediately think the market will
reverse a smarter way to trade
divergences is to identify the main
Trend maybe with price action maybe with
a view up or the CPR indicator and find
divergences that go along with the trend
in the case of an upward Trend you
ignore bearish regular divergences those
appearing on the top of the oscillator
and search for bullish regular
divergences
you also look for bullish hidden
in the case of a downtrend you ignore
bullish regular divergences and search
for bearish regular divergences and
bearish hidden divergences
and this way you have a higher
probability of a successful Divergence
trade
[Music]
the location of the Divergence is very
important adding the filter of location
can usually enhance the quality of your
Divergent signals instead of taking
trades just because of a Divergent
signal you'd wait for the price to move
into a previous Supply or demand Zone
and only then look for divergences and
Trend shifts to time your entries
in this example you see an uptrend with
two divergences
however the first one completely failed
and the second one resulted in a massive
winner
what was the difference if we analyzed a
big picture we see that the first
Divergence happened in the middle of
nowhere
and the second Divergence formed at the
demand area
as a day trader you must first identify
your support and resistance zones or
supply and demand areas and then let
price come to you
such an approach will impact your
performance in a big way
volume brings many advantages and could
be of tremendous help when it comes to
analyzing divergences
if the price is rising in an uptrend a
Divergence is visible but the volume is
reducing it may show that there is
little interest in a market and the
price May reverse
similarly when the price is rapidly
declining and forms a Divergence but the
volume is low it could mean that the
institutional Traders are not interested
in the price Direction
so the price might soon reverse to the
upside
a high volume after the Divergence
usually indicates more interest in the
market and the presence of institutional
Traders
a Divergence confirmed by a rising
volume represents one of the safest
trades I hope you see how supply and
demand volume and divergences are
interconnected I know that many day
Traders are dismissing Divergent signals
but from my experience combined with
other leading tools they can offer very
reliable day trading setups
breakouts can be a very powerful tool in
your day trading Arsenal allowing you to
capitalize on strong Market movements
first let's start with the basics a
breakout occurs when the price breaks
through a key level of support or
resistance this can be a bullish
breakout where the price breaks through
a resistance level or a bearish breakout
where the price breaks through a support
level
now not all breakouts are created equal
one of the biggest challenges of trading
breakouts is avoiding false ones
a false breakout is when the price
temporarily breaks through a key level
only to quickly reverse and Retreat back
into its previous range this could be
caused by a lack of follow through from
the buyers or sellers or by market
manipulation this can be frustrating for
day Traders as they lead to losses and
missed opportunities so the Big
Challenge in day trading is knowing how
to avoid false breakouts one key
strategy is to wait for confirmation
this means waiting for the price to
close above or below the key level or
waiting for a strong search in volume to
confirm the Breakout
another tip most Traders when looking to
trade a retest will Mark the point where
a breakout has occurred using horizontal
lines and this is one of the reasons why
you fail at Trading retests a far better
way of marking the points is using areas
by marking the breakout Point as an area
instead of a line you give yourself the
benefit of not having to guess the
breakout point
if there are several highs for example
and you mark the level using a line then
you won't be able to know which highs
the market is going to return to
by having a Zone you can cover multiple
highs it's much easier this way
additionally it can be helpful to look
at indicators to confirm the Breakout
so analyze the view up and the central
pivot range
on the other hand a valid break of the
curse when the price breaks through a
key level and continues to move in the
same direction to identify a valid
breakout look for a significant surge in
volume and price momentum as well as
confirmation from the same indicators
one popular strategy for trading
breakouts is the break and read test
technique this involves waiting for the
price to break through a key level then
waiting for a retest of the level before
entering a trade in the direction of the
Breakout
in this example the initial move higher
and through the resistance level must be
followed by a strong and Rising volume
it takes effort for the market to move
away the same applies here and you
should see this move reflected in the
volume of the next few bars
if you don't see this then you know it's
either a trap set by the smart money or
there is simply no interest from Market
participants to take the market higher
at this stage
if it's a valid move then the volumes on
the initial break will be well above
average and Rising
at this stage you want to see the market
pull back to test the former resistance
level but very important this should be
followed with low or falling volume
since we are now developing a bullish
Trend higher and expect to see rising
market with Rising volume
so very important you want to see strong
and Rising volume on the breakout and
low volume on the pullback then at the
retest level you want to see another
increase in volume
it isn't enough to Simply see the market
touch a broken level as a new supporter
resistance when the market revisits a
level after breaking it you want to see
some sort of confirmation that the
previous support level turned into
resistance and vice versa a previous
resistance turned into support
a simple method to enter into trades at
a retest of the breakout level is by
using price action more specifically
using Candlestick patterns such as
engulfing candles or pin bars we talked
about them in a previous module
here we have a breakout area when you
see a market breaking a support level
see if there are any Candlestick
patterns you can use as an entry into
the trade here we can see that when the
market reached the area a bearish
engulfing candle formed volume confirmed
a move high volume on the breakout and
low volume during the pullback
so a valid short signal
the beam bar is one of the most powerful
price action signals during retests and
the signal rely the most in my trading a
pin bar signals that a reversal may be
about to take place in the price action
trading pinball signals with support and
resistance and volume confirmation is
perhaps one of the most effective ways
to day trade the very best pinballs
stick out at the retest level the bigger
the rejection and the bigger the pin bar
the more powerful the signal the best
beam bars are the large and obvious
candles that as soon as you flick over
to your chart you notice them
high probability pin bar at the retest
level needs to have the weak sticking
out from all other candles and above
average volume to confirm the active
participation at the retest
risk management and trading discipline
usually rank very low on the priorities
list of most day Traders you shouldn't
neglect this topic let me share my best
tips that will help you improve your
trade and risk management first tip is
the most obvious one you must be aware
of the risk you will take on each trade
and the reward you will receive prior to
the trade execution this means knowing
where to place your stops and your
profit targets a trade should only be
placed when the anticipated reward from
the trade matches or exceeds the risk
being taken
assessing the risk factor should be easy
you basically determine a portion of
your Capital to be risked on each trade
a fixed percentage of your capital for
example one or two percent per trade is
decent based on this percentage you
determine the invalidation point of the
trade the point at which your assumption
has been proven wrong this is the
location to place your stop loss and
again if you risk one percent of your
Capital your reward must be higher than
this
second tip is to stop closing trades
without a good reason have you ever
exited a trade due to a fear of giving
back unrealized profits only to see the
market continue in your intended
Direction I'm sure you have this is
something everyday Trader has to master
the ability to control emotions in a way
that allows you to trade based on pure
technical analysis one way to keep your
emotions in check if you feel the urge
to close a position early is to Simply
ask yourself why am I causing this
position if your answer is anything
other than a technical one you are
likely making a decision based on
emotions
another tricky component to risk
management is the ability to control
exposure with correlated traits when it
comes to money and risk management this
means that trading instruments which are
positively correlated will lead to
increased risk
let's say you trade Forex you spot a
demand Zone on pound dollar and you
decide to enter a long position
at the same time you also see a bullish
Divergence on the pound Yen and you also
decide to take the trade
when these trades are opened then you
will have two correlated traits that
could either double your win potential
if the bond keeps rallying or double
your losses if the bond suddenly sells
off
this is why it's essential to avoid
opening positions for highly correlated
instruments
another important tip understand the
impact of Leverage on your risk
management
Leverage is simply a way of trading with
more money than you actually have in
your account now using leverage can
maximize gains however it can also
increase losses too
if you are leveraged and you make a
profit your returns are magnified very
quickly but at the opposite side losses
will erode your account just as quickly
and too many people have lost their
entire trading accounts just because of
their High Leverage
remember the greater the amount of
Leverage on the capital you apply the
higher the risk that you will assume if
you are conservative and don't like
taking many risks or if you are still
learning how to trade a lower level of
Leverage like five to one or tenth one
might be more appropriate
keeping your position small and limiting
the amount of capital for each position
is a good start to learning the proper
way to manage Leverage
another tip keep a journal and review
your trades most Traders will never look
at their trades again after they have
caused them they will just move on to
the next trade and forget about what
they did before giving a trading journal
offers two potential benefits
first it provides a place where you can
come back to and revisit all your best
trades to see what you have done wrong
and how you developed over time
and second it will keep you from making
mistakes during your trading sessions
at the end of each week and month go
back and see what you did notice common
problems and spot your strengths these
observations can help you exploit your
strengths and highlight the areas you
need to work on
another tip is to give your stop-loss
room to breathe most day Traders
misunderstand what the stop loss really
is
at its core it's the price where your
trade idea is no longer valid but
placing stops too close too close to the
current price is one of the most common
mistakes day Traders make how many times
have you been right about the Market's
Direction your trade signal was right
but you still lost money somehow
this keeps happening to you because your
stop loss is too small
when your day trade the market can move
unpredictable and if you place your stop
too tight there is a high chance that
you will be stopped out before the price
continues to go in your direction
position sizing also plays an important
role in this equation my advice lower
your position size and slightly increase
your stop loss to give the price enough
room to breathe
when you day trade you must have a
trading rules checklist but checklist
must State all your entry criteria
underneath each other
and every time you are about to enter a
trade you revisit your checklist and
check off the things you can see on your
charts
with a checklist it becomes obvious
right away if a trade really matches
your criteria or not
again if you can visually see that the
trade that you are about to take is
breaking your rules you are most likely
to avoid those painful mistakes
here's a simple example of a day trading
checklist is the market trending or
ranging is there a significant level of
support or resistance or Supply or
demand nearby do you have a clear entry
trigger do you have validation from the
volume is there a confirmation from The
View up or the central pivot range do
you see a Divergence do you have a
decent risk to reward Ratio or do you
have the proper mindset to trade
another tip is to have realistic take
profit targets many day Traders put way
too much emphasis on having higher take
profit levels and don't understand that
this doesn't tell you anything about the
quality of your strategy you'll end up
setting unrealistic profit targets far
away from your interests thinking that
by using a wider take profit you can
increase your risk to reward ratio using
a wider take profit means
device won't be able to reach the level
as easily and if your stop-loss strategy
isn't on point you will most likely see
a decline in your win rate you need to
be able to determine a suitable profit
Target one that gives you a realistic
profit Target but also gives you a
sensible risk reward
this is one of the biggest lessons in
day trading
find Confluence on your charts the more
technical tools that validate the price
move or simply confirm the significance
of a price level the stronger that level
is confluences when there is more than
one signal coming together at the same
point in a market
when you find the setup that has the
same signal from multiple methodologies
you have found a high probability
trading opportunity and there is a high
chance of the trade working out
successfully conference can be found
when you combine the different elements
we've discussed price patterns view up
pivots support or resistance supply and
demand and volume
when some of these tools meet at a
single location on the chart it is
considered a point of confidence in this
way you are combining more than one
trading technique to increase your odds
of winning on your trades
when they trading there are too many
markets to keep track of too many
strategies to backtest and you need to
narrow it down when I first started
trading Forex I used to have a template
with over 20 currencies and I tried to
monitor all of them you know the outcome
many missed trades which resulted in
many poor trades taken out of
frustration or fomo so you need to
narrow it down follow three markets at
most you have a lot of things to cover
when day trading Market selection and
preparation pattern recognition risk
reward indicators volume position size
entry level price action trade
management it's easy to become
overwhelmed again narrow it down
and you don't need to trade the entire
day there is enough money to be made
trading only a few times each day and
you should come up with a suitable
trading schedule that caters to your
needs and trading goals you don't need
to sit in front of the screen all day I
know that there's a tendency to try to
squeeze every dollar out of the trading
day so you don't miss any profit but
when you have reached your profit Target
or you stop seeing setups simply stop
Trading
I now have a simple role when I'm day
trading I must close my positions at the
end of the day even at all
you should never turn a day trade into a
swing trade and hold it overnight
you know the feeling you open a trade
hoping for a quick profit and instead of
closing it you find yourself justifying
staying in a bad trade the second day
this is one of the deadliest scenes a
day trader can make you need to change
your mindset think about it you can
always get back in but it's hard to
recover from a big loss so if you're
wrong take the loss and come back when
the timing is better
in my first years I used to average down
on losing trades imagine you buy 10
shares of a company at fifty dollars in
the anticipation of selling them at
around 60 dollars instead the price
breaks the support level and drops to
forty dollars you have lost the trade
and you should have been stopped out but
instead of accepting the loss and moving
on you buy another 10 shares at forty
dollars it's unlikely that the price
will hit your initial Target of 60
dollars but now you're hoping the price
will rally back to 45 or 50 at 50
dollars you sell all of your shares and
you even recorded some profits it's very
tempting to average down on a losing
trade with the hope of getting out that
break even but you shouldn't do it
averaging down or losing trade is a
recipe for wiping out your account
ninety percent of the time maybe you
will profit when you average down but
that 10 of the time you are wrong you
will blow up your account
another common mistake is to day trade
low conviction trades because you can't
find anything better
if you take more trades than your
strategy dictates because you can't find
high probability setups that's a warning
sign this is often a result of boredom
or a lack of discipline
since this trades occur outside of your
trading plan they are less likely to
perform well
trade only what your strategy dictates
if the market is quiet or the trade
entry conditions are not there just wait
out
this is one of the most important tips
don't believe anything you heard until
you have tested and try it out for
yourself
what used to work two years ago on Forex
Market may not work today on the stock
market a strategy I use on the 15 minute
time frame on Amazon may not work for
you on a 5-minute chart of Euro USD
that's a common mistake among day
Traders they don't understand that
different strategies work on different
markets you only find out what works for
you by rigorous testing and Analysis
back testing is the most underutilized
weapon in day trading it allows you to
witness how your plan would have
theoretically performed had you been
trading it for the past months with this
information you can objectively confirm
whether or not your trading plan will
make you money in the future
so don't ignore back testing and forward
testing
now let's be clear day trading can be
profitable but it isn't a get rich quick
scheme day trading can be simple but
don't make the mistake of thinking it's
that easy
I know that there are many websites that
try to tell you differently that you
just have to read about it for a couple
of days and then magically you'll become
a day trader so let's be realistic you
won't become an instant millionaire
overnight in this course I wanted you to
learn the correct Foundation facts
secrets and the concepts that actually
work in day trading but in order to make
the most out of this trading course you
have to adapt and adjust these Concepts
to what you might already know making
money with day trading is possible but
it requires some time discipline effort
and commitment on your part
if you watch the full day training
course and learn something new please
show your support by giving us a like it
goes a long way and if you haven't
watched our previous trading course
about technical analysis you definitely
must watch it either and check out our
Academy program if you want to further
level up your Trading
until next time