in day trading there are many
conflicting Concepts
trend lines are broken Fibonacci is
irrelevant chart patterns don't work
support and resistance trading is broken
if you are new to the game it's quite
hard to know which concepts are indeed
profitable and what is the best approach
you should take to make money trading
I'll tell you what worked for me
Confluence conference is when there is
more than one signal coming together at
the same point in the market
the more technical tools that validate
the price move or simply confirm the
significance of a price level the
stronger that level is
today I'm sharing a very simple strategy
to day trade and swing trade using
critical price levels and two moving
averages
so like subscribe and stick around for
the full video
[Music]
when you find a setup that has the same
price signal from multiple methodologies
you have found a high probability
trading opportunity and there is a high
chance of the trade working out
successfully
finding a Confluence is key and could
eliminate noise when it comes to
validating a signal Confluence can be
found in all forms of the markets price
patterns moving averages pivots support
and resistance levels trend lines or
Fibonacci levels
when some of these tools meet at the
single location on the chart it is
considered a point of confluence
conference trading is basically
combining more than one trading
technique or charge pattern or analysis
to increase your odds of winning a trade
[Music]
I always pay close attention to support
and resistance areas these are price
structures which show previous reaction
points and are usually used to find
turning points or breakouts in a market
there are many price levels that you can
trade from Major Market boundaries to
smaller price structures forming swing
lows and highs to huge zones where price
comes back regularly
the break and retest pattern is
especially important in our strategy
this is where price changes from using a
level as support first and after a
breakout it uses the same level as
resistance
and when a resistance level becomes a
support
[Music]
moving averages are another useful
Confluence tool because they are very
versatile
you can use them as entry filter and
only take trades in the direction of the
moving average
the time entries on a retest of a moving
average during a pullback plus they also
serve as Dynamic support and resistance
lately I've stopped using moving
averages which are applied to the close
price
I prefer to use two moving averages with
the same period in this case 200.
the first one is a moving average
applied to high prices
and the second one is applied to low
prices
this creates a channel which is much
better than a simple line
so the more trading techniques you have
indicating a certain direction the
higher the probability of the market
price going in that direction
strategy consists in finding areas where
critical price levels and the EMA
Channel converge one static support and
resistance level and a dynamic one
aligning on the same area on a chart
we trade Euro Yen on the 15 minute time
frame
price is below the 200 EMA Channel So
the plan is too short the currency pair
when price bounces off the channel
I also see a triple top here and a
breakout the breakout happened at the
same time with the breakout below the
channel
this area is an important one it was a
support Zone turning into potential
resistance
which aligns with the EMA Channel
so we found our value Zone
if price comes to this Confluence area
we'll enter a cell position
topless above the EMA Channel
and we target the next swing low in the
price structure
that's a risk to reward ratio of 3 which
is the minimum Target you should aim
[Music]
if you want to maximize profits when
price breaks an important level in the
price structure
you move your stop loss to lock in
profits
[Music]
I suspect this pullback to our
conference area also aligns with the
Fibonacci level
[Music]
foreign
just as I thought it was the 50
Fibonacci retracement
another layer of confidence
we moved to Nvidia on the five minute
time frame
this is a strong downtrend with price
making lower swing lows lower swing
highs
I also see this major swing low
again a firmware support potentially
turning into resistance
foreign
zone is more evident now
it's right here where the 200 EMA
Channel and the resistance area meet
if price reaches the Zone we'll go short
stop loss above the channel
and for our take profit we'll Target the
previous swing low in the price
structure a very good risk to reward
ratio of 5.
foreign
excellent trade and as in the previous
example let's add the Fibonacci
retracement
what do you know Fibonacci golden Zone
offered additional resistance
we change markets once again and we
trade the X index on the 30 minute time
frame
I see a strong uptrend
higher swing highs higher swing lows
price above the 200 EMA channel so
market conditions favor long trades
price broke this resistance level and
now we expect it to hold and act as a
new support
[Music]
price hit the moving average channel in
a conference area at this support level
when in doubt add a few retracement
[Music]
once again Fibonacci golden Zone
perfectly aligns with the other
Confluence vectors
so stop loss below the channel
and will aim for the minimum risk to
reward ratio of 3.
here's how to manage the trade once
price breaks an important swing in the
price structure remove the risk from the
trade and move your stop to break even
now we can't lose money we are in a
risk-free trade
in this chart I see a potential long
trade
we have an accumulation Zone after a
downtrend
and now price broke the upper side of
the range
and it also broke the 200 EMA Channel
around this area we have our potential
long trade
stop loss below the channel
take profit at the next swing High
okay this time we lost the trade
the conference zone wasn't strong enough
but let's continue maybe we'll find
another opportunity
route right here
which tells me this Market wants to go
higher
price breaks the EMA Channel once again
and makes a new high
let's see if the market will offer us a
pullback to the EMA Channel
here it is we have a support level and
dma Channel
nd151 round number which is another
conference Factor
stop goes below the 200 EMA Channel
and we'll set the take profit a few
points below the swing High
foreign
zone is part of a chart pattern
in this example I see a head and
shoulders
and a Breakout
we have the neckline here and the entry
point would be at the retest of this
resistance for more support
the 200 EMA Channel also offers Dynamic
resistance
this would be the sweet spot for an
entry
placed above the 200 EMA Channel
and let's target the swing low
a bigger price move
we'll monitor each swing low in the
price structure
[Music]
okay we broke the swing low I'll move my
stop to break even and now we removed
the risk from the trade
[Music]
here's another common chart pattern a
double bottom
which was broken to the upside
but the interesting thing was the fact
that the breakout occurred at the same
time with the breakout above the 200 EMA
Channel
I also see a major trendline breakout my
intuition says this Market wants to go
higher
this is the conference zone where
different signals are indicating the
same thing
foreign
goes below the channel
this swing high is our final Target
a risk to reward ratio of 5.
price broke they swing high this is the
moment when we eliminate the risk from
our trade
here I see a double tap
and a Breakout
there's also a breakout below this upper
trend line
so chart pattern Traders see a potential
down move
moving average Traders also see a
possible bearish Direction
trendline Traders also expect further
price decrease
all of these independent forms of
analysis indicate a similar price
movement
stop loss placement above the 200 EMA
Channel as usual
and take profit at this major support a
risk to reward ratio of around 3.
we remove the risk from the trade right
here as price broke this important swing
low
[Music]
here I see a double top
and a breakout below the support line
which now will possibly act as a
resistance
price also broke below the 200 EMA so
further price fall is expected
this would be our Confluence Zone
if we apply a fib retracement
we also observe this aligns perfectly
now let's wait for price to retest the
breakout Zone
[Music]
okay that's unlucky we anticipated a
further price decrease but the
retracement to our Confluence Zone never
came we only had a minor retracement and
price went straight down
it's important to remain disciplined and
patient and don't get frustrated or
angry
you will see many similar setups and you
will wait for a retracement to your
Confluence Zone but sometimes you'll
miss the opportunity
[Music]
foreign
thank you thank you
[Music]
if you found value and learned something
new leave us a like this way we'll know
if you'd like to see more videos like
this one
and check out our Academy program if you
want to further level up your Trading
until next time