When a market makes a strong move on volume,
this means that the price movement is confirmed
by a simultaneous rise in volume.
So volume means strength.
Volume must increase as the trend develops,
whether it is a bull or bear market.
But what if you combine a moving average and
the volume in order read the market momentum
or to analyze a breakout strength.
Would this tool help you make better decisions
when trading or investing?
Sure it can, and this tool is called volume
weighted moving average.
So today we’ll talk about the volume weighted
moving average, you’ll learn the importance
of using it and I’ll show you how to use
it in a trading strategy.
Before we continue, if you are new to my channel,
make sure you subscribe, turn on the notifications
and leave a like to show your support.
The volume weighted moving average is a moving
average indicator which includes volume in
its calculation.
This moving average places more importance
on the closing prices which had a higher volume.
It incorporates not only the last number of
periods of price into its calculation but
also the average volume during those periods.
The volume-weighted moving average (VWMA)
emphasizes volume by weighting prices based
on the amount of trading activity in a given
period of time.
Prices with heavy trading activity get more
weight than prices with light trading activity.
This is very important information because
you can make better decisions when you add
volume into your trading strategy.
You could read the volume weighted moving
average in a similar manner to other moving
averages.
Its main use, however, arises when it is used
in conjunction with a SMA.
So, let’s analyze a chart with a 50 SMA
and a 50 volume weighted moving average.
At a first glance, you will see that they
pretty much follow the same trajectory.
However, on further analysis, you will notice
the averages don’t mirror each other exactly.
The reason for this, as I previously said,
is because the volume weighted ma emphasizes
volume, while the SMA only factors the average
of the closing price per period.
So, if you pay attention at the volume at
the bottom of the screen you will notice that
when we have a big volume candlestick, the
volume weighted moving average starts moving
away from the trajectory of the simple moving
average.
Then, when we have lower market volumes, the
simple moving average and the volume weighted
moving average are very close in value.
When the volume is stronger, the volume weighted
moving average will follow price more closely,
and when volume decreases, it will mimic a
simple moving average.
When the 50 volume weighted moving average
is between price and the 50 simple moving
average SMA(50), then volume confirms we are
trending in that direction.
Look at this example.
At the exact moment of the breakout, the volume
weighted moving average was well above the
SMA already, showing us that volume confirms
the uptrend.
The retrace even bounced off from the volume
weighted moving average instead of the SMA
as support.
So, how do you read the volume weighted moving
average?
A volume weighted ma moving below an simple
moving average indicates bearish conditions.
So, if the volume weighted moving average
crosses below the simple moving average, this
implies that a bearish move is on the horizon.
This could lead to a weakening in the bullish
trend or a possible reversal.
If the price is able to break through both
the volume weighted ma and the SMA a bearish
trend is confirmed and you can start searching
for short positions.
A volume weighted ma above an SMA indicates
bullish conditions.
So, if the volume weighted moving average
moves above the simple moving average, a bullish
trend change is likely.
Once the price is able to break both the volume
weighted ma and the SMA to the upside, you
can start searching for long opportunities.
Separation between a volume weighted ma and
the simple ma indicates a trending market.
In other words, if the volume weighted moving
average is between the chart and the simple
moving average, then we have a signal for
a trending market.
Keep in mind that sometimes the volume weighted
moving average will test the simple moving
average as a support and resistance, depending
on the primary direction of the traded instrument.
These tests can be considered as potential
trend reversals.
It doesn’t mean that the market will reverse,
it may continue its direction, like in this
example, you just have to pay attention to
possible turning points.
Both moving averages closer together might
suggest an exit point.
This signal is pretty much the opposite of
the previous one.
You look for a contrary signal to the primary
trend.
For example, you have taken a long position
and you notice no separation between the volume
weighted ma and the simple ma.
This is the moment where you might want to
consider exiting the market and to collecting
your profits.
Now, let’s see how you could use the volume
weighted ma by its own, without the simple
ma
First, to identify and confirm market trend
If you want to trade in the direction of the
prevailing trend on the market, a volume weighted
ma can offer some important clues.
However, don’t forget that a moving average
is a lagging indicator, so it doesn’t predict
new trends, just confirms the market trends
once they have been developed.
So how you find and confirm trends with the
volume weighted ma:
A possible uptrend is when the price is above
a moving average and the slope of the moving
average is upward
A possible downtrend is when the price is
below the moving average and its slope is
downward
The slope of volume weighted ma is simply
the direction of the moving average plotted
on the chart.
Another way to trade using volume weighted
moving averages is to look at them as dynamic
support and resistance.
They are referred to as dynamic because they
are not like the traditional support and resistance
lines on the chart.
They tend to change as price changes.
Being so common and followed by so many people,
we can often see on charts that the price
often stalls or bounces when hitting popular
moving averages.
Although volume weighted moving averages are
not like the normal support and resistance,
they tend to behave the same way.
As price stays below the volume weighted moving
average several times, it shows high selling
pressure in the market.
As the price finds it hard to break through,
it means that the sellers are stronger than
buyers.
The volume weighted moving average above the
price becomes a resistance and price is likely
to bounce back offering short opportunities.
Likewise when price stays above at the volume
weighted moving average, it becomes a support
and therefore is likely to bounce back, offering
buy opportunities.
Like any other support and resistance level,
price cannot hold forever, and sometimes these
levels are violated and price breaks through.
You can also take advantage of a strong break
below or above the volume weighted moving
average to trade a breakout.
A classic way to trade a break out is to wait
for a price retest after the break, to avoid
a fake out.
Another strategy for overcoming the problem
with false signals is to wait a certain number
of candles after the moving average line has
been crossed by the price before you enter
your trade.
This way, you filter out a lot of the choppy
price movements during times when the market
is not showing any clear direction.
Volume weighted moving average helps a lot
to smooth out price action.
What you need to know is that the longer the
moving average, the smother it becomes and
the slower it gets to reacting to price movements.
Also, the shorter the moving average the choppier
it gets and the quicker it reacts to price
movements.
In a fast-moving trend, you will want to use
a faster moving average, in a slow-moving
trend, a slower moving average sometimes works
better.
You can set the length of the moving average
to suit your trading style.
Just remember that prices with heavy trading
activity get more weight than prices with
light trading activity.
The volume weighted moving average is suited
to trend following strategies, because this
indicator performs best in trending markets.
You can also use the volume weighted moving
in combination with other signals and techniques,
to get a more comprehensive analysis of the
market.
Now, if you got value from this this video
or learned something new, make sure you subscribe,
turn on the notifications so you don’t miss
future uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.