One of the best ways to consistently make
money trading is to understand the facts and
nuances about the market structure.
Today we’ll cover an important pattern,
the “over and under” break of structure
pattern.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel
and stick around for the full video.
What is a break of structure?
Market structure is simply the support and
resistance levels on your charts, determined
by swing highs and lows.
These are levels on your chart that attract
the most attention.
When the market is in a bullish trend and
buyers are controlling the market, you will
see higher highs and higher lows.
There is strong buying pressure.
This results in the upward movement of price
with time.
The formation of consecutive lower lows and
lower highs in the price is referred a bearish
trend.
This indicates strong selling pressure.
This results in a downward movement of price
with time.
Now, the over and under pattern represents
a break of structure in the market.
The break of structure is the first sign that
the market is telling you that it's about
to get weaker or it's about to reverse.
Let’s say we have an uptrend.
Higher highs and higher lows.
We have a break of the structure when the
price makes a new lower low and lower high.
This tells you that this trend could be weakening
or it could reverse.
For a downtrend, the same concept.
Lower Lows and lower highs.
We have a break of the structure when the
price makes a new higher high and a higher
low.
There's no guarantee that the trend is over,
but this is a warning sign, a sign of weakness
in the previous downtrend.
The over and under pattern
We can distinguish two types of patterns:
• Bullish break of structure, which appears
at the end of a downtrend.
• Bearish break of structure, which appears
at the end of an uptrend.
Here’s how to easily find a bullish over
and under pattern, after a previous downtrend.
• Price creates a lower low
• Price creates a lower high
• Price breaches the previous low and creates
a new lower low
• Then price breaks the previous high as
well and forms a higher high
When price returns to the zone created by
the 2 previous lows, you look to enter into
a long position.
For a bearish over and under pattern, after
a previous uptrend.
• Price creates a higher high
• Price creates a lower high
• Price breaches the previous high and creates
a new higher high
• Then price breaks the previous low as
well and forms a lower low
When price returns to the zone created by
the 2 previous highs, you look to enter into
a short position.
Now, you might be inclined to believe that
this break of structure pattern looks similar
to the Head and Shoulder pattern.
The main difference between the over and under
pattern and the Head and Shoulder pattern
is the left leg (second valley) of the over
and under formation, which is much lower than
the right leg (first valley).
And this is a more common pattern than the
classic head and shoulders, because it involves
2 traps set by the smart money, for both sides.
The second major difference between the two
reversal patterns is the entry point.
Usually, the point of entry for the HS pattern
is the break of the neckline, but with the
over and under pattern, we look for a much
earlier entry near the left wave, which offers
a bigger profit potential.
We’ll talk about this later.
Break of structure & liquidity hunt
So why is this break of structure pattern
important?
For big institutions with a need to fill large
orders, finding pockets of liquidity is absolutely
essential.
When these big players take positions in the
market, they obviously aim to be filed at
the best possible price.
However, given the size of their positions,
they need to find enough counter-forces to
fill their orders, with the minimal amount
of slippage.
If a big player were to enter the market at
an area of low liquidity, the volatility it
would create would have a negative impact
on the average price it gets.
Lower liquidity usually results in a more
volatile market and will cause prices to change
drastically.
So, where do we find these levels?
Where stop-loss orders are placed.
Where do you think the concept of “stop-loss
hunt” comes from?
From the necessity that large players have
to enter the market in areas of liquidity
as they aim to accumulate major positions.
These areas will always attract interest because
that’s where pockets of liquidity exist.
Now very important: the creation of a liquidity
level comes as a result of an initial imbalance
of supply/demand, which forms what we know
as a swing high or swing low.
As more players take positions in the market,
these are levels where market participants
will use as a historical reference to place
their stops.
In a bearish over and under pattern, the highest
high in the formation, represents the liquidity
hunt.
Lot of traders had their stops places above
the previous swing high.
Smart money pushed the price above the previous
high, grabbed the liquidity and moved price
back down.
I always like to see a clear rejection that
leads to a structure breakout.
And not only the previous higher high was
broken.
We also have a breakout of the previous lower
high.
Another liquidity hunt, because the price
is then moved upward, toward the previous
higher high.
As a retail trader, it’s very hard to make
money in this context, if you don’t know
what you are doing.
How to trade the break of structure setup
The best time to trade the break of structure
pattern is after a significant rally or sell-off
no matter the time frame used (you can use
this on the daily chart down to the 1-minute
chart).
Here are the rules for a short signal, during
a bearish break of structure.
• A prevailing uptrend needs to be visible
– series of HH followed by a series of HL.
• Break in the market structure – price
starts to make a lower low LL.
• You plan to enter at the zone between
the right wave and the highest high
• You place the protective stop-loss above
the last higher high HH.
• Take profit near the first valley, at
the low of the first down leg.
And the second target at the area of the lower
low.
For a bullish break of structure, meaning
for buy signals:
• A prevailing downtrend needs to be visible
– series of LL followed by a series of LH.
• Break in the market structure – price
starts to make a higher high HH.
• You plan to enter at the zone between
the right wave and the lowest low
• You place the protective stop-loss below
the last lower low LL.
• Take profit near the first peak of the
pattern.
And the second target at the area of the higher
high
Break of structure & supply and demand strategy
The break of structure don’t always result
in a reversal.
That’s why you need to find other confluence
factors, to increase the odds in your favor.
Because, with this pattern, I’m basically
trying to align my positions with the smart
money, using supply and demand zones is a
great way to find entry locations.
So the plan is to find the break of structure
pattern, we’ll wait for a retracement back
to the first wave, and we’ll try to find
a supply or demand zone for an entry, to execute
the trade with a greater accuracy.
Here, a significant drop has occurred.
The market makes an obvious low, followed
by a lower high.
Then after making a lower low, it shoots up
and breaches the previous high, to make a
higher high.
The space between this low and the second
low is considered as a strong demand zone
itself.
But what if you want even more accuracy.
What if you are seeing the pattern on the
Hourly chart and you want to time your entry
on the 15 min time frame or on the 5 min time
frame?
You need to find a demand zone for an entry.
First, you need to take a look at the left-hand
side of previous low, where the strong rally
has started.
Now you need to find out the origin or the
start point of that strong rally.
Remember that demand zones are found when
the market makes a large move up from a single
candle or from a base.
You always draw the demand zone from the last
BEARISH candle before the up move.
When price returns to the zone, you can open
a buy position, with stops below the lowest
low.
Here’s our first target.
And here’s our second target.
Of course, anticipating a much bigger break
of structure, you can leave a portion of the
trade open, in the case the reversal is much
more aggressive.
Here’s another break of structure pattern,
a bearish one.
The price is forming a new high level, declines,
then forms a temporary low.
Prices then rally again to exceed the previous
high (making a higher high).
The price then falls to form a new lower low.
This is our first sign that we might have
an over and under pattern.
Prices rise again to the initial high level,
so we need to find a supply area.
You look at the left side of the previous
high where the previous strong down move started.
After that, you need to find out the origin
of the strong down move.
Remember, supply zones are found when the
market makes a large down move from a single
candle or from a base.
You draw the supply zone from the last BULLISH
candle before the down move.
This is price area that could represent the
entry trigger.
Stop level can be placed above this higher
high, while partial profits can be taken at
this low and at this low.
Over and under divergence strategy
Another effective way to trade the break of
structure is by using indicators, more specifically
to find divergences between an indicator and
the price.
If that coincides with a supply or demand
zone, it gives you even a better indication
of which way the price will go.
Divergence is when the direction of a technical
indicator, usually some form of oscillator,
MACD, RSI, Stochastic, ‘diverges’ from
the overall price trend.
In other words, the indicator starts moving
in the opposite direction to the price and
the trading oscillator signals a possible
trend reversal.
Coupled with the initial break of structure,
you have 2 indications that something will
happen in the market.
Bullish divergence is when the price is moving
lower but the indicator turns and points up.
Bearish divergence is when the price is moving
higher but the indicator points down.
The logic behind divergence to analyze the
market is that the indicator is showing a
slowdown in price momentum.
Price momentum will often change before the
price itself.
That’s a leading signal.
So the plan is to find a break of structure,
we wait for the price to return, to trap new
traders, and we want to find a divergence
at the third wave in the structure.
Here’s a bearish break of structure with
a Stochastic divergence confirmation.
Price makes a new high, declines and makes
a new low.
Price then rallies above the previous high
to mark a new higher high.
Price then falls quite aggressively to form
a new lower low.
This is our break of structure.
Price then rises towards the initial high,
but does not make a new higher high.
And during this up move, after the break of
structure, we have a bearish divergence on
the Stochastic.
This bearish divergence signifies a potential
down move, because prices rally to a new high
while the oscillator refuses to reach a new
level.
In this situation, bulls are losing their
grip on the market.
So a sell entry here is a high probability
trade, with an excellent risk to reward ratio.
The protective stop-loss above the last higher
high HH.
And take profit near the first valley and
the second target at this low.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.