The Andrews pitchfork indicator, commonly
referred to as 'median lines' is one of the
most versatile trading tools available.
Andrews’ pitchfork consists of a median
line at the center and two parallel equidistant
trend lines, where the outside trend lines
represent areas of support and resistance.
Traders often look for buying or selling opportunities
as the price approaches the ends of these
channels.
In this chart, for example, the price remains
largely within the bounds of the indicator
with the exception of several short false
breakouts.
The Andrews pitchfork works in any time frame.
This, of course, can range from tick charts
to monthly.
This allows the indicator to work well for
day trading and long-term investing.
The indicator can also work on any security.
So, whether you like to trade forex, futures
or stocks, you can incorporate this versatile
tool in your analysis.
The Andrews pitchfork indicator is created
by selecting three points on a chart:
A beginning point that represents the start
of a trend.
(We’ll call this point A)
A reaction high coming after the beginning
point.
(Point B)
A reaction low coming after the beginning
point.
(Point C)
The selection of these points is somewhat
subjective, but it’s a good idea to experiment
with different reaction highs and lows to
find what works best.
In some cases, you may want to plot multiple
Andrews’ pitchforks on the same chart to
provide an indication of where support or
resistance may be strongest.
You may also look at different timeframes
to determine long-term and short-term support
and resistance levels for a given security.
You need to identify the right points in your
analysis, because the success or failure of
interpreting signals depends largely on how
you plot the median lines.
In most cases, drawing the median lines is
rather subjective, but with practice, you
can develop the confidence required.
A rather simple method is after pivot points
are identified, tweak the median lines to
encapsulate price action with the greatest
level of accuracy.
If you master how to use Andrews pitchfork
, you will have a competitive advantage ahead
of the market, because you will know the dynamic
support and resistance levels in advance.
Now, not all three trend lines that make the
Andrews pitchfork react the same.
They offer different levels of support and
resistance.
The Andrews pitchfork indicator has three
lines.
Each line starts from the pivot.
We have ml (median line), the uml (upper median
line) and lml (lower median line).
But, they don’t have the same importance.
By far, the most important one is the median
line.
It has one big advantage: it attracts price.
As such, it acts like a magnet.
Because of that, traders use it to adjust
their trading strategies.
There are many ways to use this powerful trading
tool.
Some traders use it as a single indicator.
Others integrate the pitchfork with other
trading tools.
In any case, there’s not one Andrews pitchfork
strategy that works all the time.
The classical way to use this trading tool
is to look after support and resistance levels.
As you know, when we analyze a price chart,
we can find classic and dynamic support/resistance
levels.
With this tool however, the dynamic ones are
more valuable.
The bigger the time frame, the more powerful
the reaction from the levels will be.
The idea is to integrate the dynamic support/resistance
rules with Andrews pitchfork power.
Pay attention at this example.
The three pivots (a, b, c) give the angle
and the shape of Andrews pitchfork.
The resulting lines act as future dynamic
support/resistance levels.
As always, once a level gets broken, resistance
turns into support.
And, the other way around.
Judging by the current prices, the outlook
looks bullish.
The key here is the medial line.
Many traders misinterpret how to use Andrews
pitchfork’s ml.
While it attracts the price, it doesn’t
offer any support.
Nor resistance.
Just the fact that it pierces it is enough
for a strong trend.
Strong trends see the ml guiding the price
action.
Eventually, the price will pierce it multiple
times.
As a rule of thumb, while the price stays
within Andrews pitchfork lines, the trend
will keep going.
The fact that it pierces the ml multiple times
shows strength.
Hence, you must not use this as support or
resistance.
Here is another example, to make it very clear.
We identified, the A point as the start of
the move.
Next, the B is the end of the first drop.
Finally, the C point is the end of the first
swing higher.
The resulting Andrews pitchfork shows a very
strong downtrend.
Even if the price gets above the upper ml,
the bearishness is overwhelming.
On top of it, the ml attracts the price on
a constant basis.
Furthermore, the upper ml and lower ml act
as strong support and resistance levels.
Using Andrews pitchfork this way gives dynamic
support and resistance levels.
But, this is valid only for the upper median
line UML and lower median line LML.
For the median line ML, multiple piercings
simply show how strong the trend is.
In this case, very strong.
However, how do we know when the trend ends?
When should bulls consider a bottom is in
place?
The way to answer these 2 questions is to
use the Schiff line.
Few traders know about the Schiff line’s
existence.
This is a line that connects the a point and
c point.
As such, traders know in advance where the
Schiff line is.
In strong trends, the price has a strong tendency
to move away from it.
As a rule of thumb, a bearish trend keeps
going as long as the price stays below the
Schiff line.
Of course, the opposite happens in a bullish
trend.
Here’s the Schiff line on the previous chart.
It shows when the bearish trend ended.
In fact, it shows when bears should not consider
selling anymore.
Because the Schiff line gets broken, it means
bulls will step in on any future pullbacks.
Now, based on the median lines and the Schiff
line, the two most common strategies falling
under the s/r umbrella include:
Buying/selling the bounce.
Traders may buy when prices hit the bottom
of a channel, but only in an uptrend and sell
when prices hit the top of the channel only
in a downtrend.
In these cases, it’s important to wait for
confirmation that the price is responding
to these levels.
Here are several examples of buying the bounce.
The second strategy involves, buying/selling
the break.
Traders may buy when the price produces a
breakout from the top of a channel or sell
when price breaks from the bottom of the channel.
In these cases, it’s important to look for
a clean break to avoid false breakouts.
My favorite way to use the Andrews pitchfork
is to look for divergences between the pitchfork
and RSI.
If you followed by channel, you know that
i consider the divergence one of the most
powerful leading signals you could get.
So I look to buy or sell the breakout from
the pitchfork, only when i see a divergence
on the RSI.
This is powerful stuff, and let me demonstrate
it.
In this first example, you can see how the
bearish divergence was formed with price making
a higher high while the relative strength
index was seen making a lower high.
Following this, price eventually broke down
through the lower median line following the
price failure.
In the next example, you can see that while
prices posted a lower low, but the RSI signaled
a higher high, which indicated a bullish divergence
in price.
This leading signal suggested that price would
be reversing upward shortly.
Following the breakout from the upper median
line, we can see that a long position resulted
in a profit as price continued to push higher.
I strongly encourage you to search for this
pattern on your charts.
Here are other trades based on RSI divergences
and Andrew’s pitchfork breakouts.
Andrews’ pitchfork is a great price action
indicator to use when determining areas of
support and resistance.
While it’s not perfect in every scenario,
the indicator provides a good indication of
where prices may be headed.
The downside is that picking the main three
points is a largely subjective process that
requires experience to master.
The Andrews pitchfork as a trading tool has
a bit of mystery for retail traders.
While everyone knows to use it in a trend,
few know how to master it.
The key stays with the main 3 pivot points.
If you learn to draw them correctly, the Andrews
pitchfork indicator works like a charm.
Here’s one last important tip: a great way
to use this tool is to perform a top/down
analysis (meaning to study all timeframes).
Start from the biggest one (monthly) and continue
with the weekly chart, daily and the four-hour
one.
A multi-timeframe analysis with Andrew’s
pitchforks will result in a better understanding
of market conditions.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, don’t forget to subscribe,
click the bell icon to enable notifications
for new uploads and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.