When the market has a clean breakout, it often
likes to revisit that breakout point before
continuing in the breakout direction.
And I bet you’re actively looking for these
retests as valid opportunities.
There’s nothing new here.
But here’s the thing.
The strategies in most trading books don't
really match what big smart money traders
are actually doing.
There’s a big difference between where smart
money sees a technical support versus our
retail support levels.
Breakout retests happen because the big boys
are still trying to enter or exit positions.
When the market breaks past certain levels,
it attracts a bunch of new buyers and sellers.
After breaking a high or low, the price will
often swing back to where it started.
This is so smart money can fill more orders
from traders betting on the breakout.
Before it happens, many traders place pending
orders, waiting to join the move.
Once the breakout goes through, it triggers
all those orders.
And then some smart money traders will start
taking profits since they got in early before
the move was obvious to us.
Their profit-taking causes the market to retrace
back to the original breakout point.
It gives late traders a second chance to hop
in, while also letting smart money lock in
their gains.
That's why breakout retests tend to provide
trading opportunities - big players are still
moving in and out!
Also, there’s another reason why breakouts
tend to retrace after a big move.
It's because many traders start closing their
positions too early!
When the price breaks past a level, breakout
traders will jump in, hoping the price keeps
running.
But as it comes back down towards where they
got in, their profits start getting smaller
and smaller.
Most people probably panic seeing their gains
decrease.
So they bail while there's still a little
profit left.
The closer it trades to the breakout point,
more and more traders will close out of fear.
This creates a pile of sell orders that smart
money can use to their advantage.
Big institutions enter by picking off the
orders of stopped out retail traders.
Then once they build their positions, the
retrace will end and the move continues.
It helps to see retests differently than just
a retracement.
They're actually the market's way of resetting
itself after a big move.
By "resetting", I mean it gets rid of weak
positions held by traders who can't handle
the volatility.
These are usually retailers like us who bail
too early before the move really takes off.
Either we panic seeing our profits erode,
or trade really short timeframes just looking
for tiny gains.
Either way, when a retest happens, it tends
to shake these weak hands out before the next
wave up.
After the reset, there's less resistance at
that level.
And now smart money have a chance to buy more
at cheap prices, from the stopped out traders.
At the retest point, the big boys are free
to drive the move further without as much
selling pressure.
When a drop happens, you can see the zone
where a ton of traders had sell orders set
beforehand.
Once the downward breakout goes through, the
market will usually keep falling for a bit
as momentum carries it lower.
And then the big money players start locking
in profits on their short trades.
As they close positions, it pushes the price
back up towards the original break point.
As price moves higher, trapped sellers are
bound to bail and exit, scared of losing more
money, flooding the market with buy orders,
their stops.
Then smart money swoops in to fill all these
reversing orders on the way back up.
If you think about it, no wonder retests tend
to be so strong - they're capitalizing on
multiple trader types repositioning themselves!
This is how the big players manipulate these
patterns.
Another reason why so many people struggle
trading breakout retests – it’s because
the way they're marking these levels is all
wrong!
Most people just draw a single line where
the breakout happened.
But with how messy charts can be, that forces
you to guess exactly which point price will
revisit, which is basically impossible.
And no wonder so many retest trades end up
as losses.
I said it many times before, start using areas
instead of lines and it will made a huge difference.
If there's a cluster of highs or lows in the
breakout zone, I'll highlight the whole region
rather than a specific price.
That way, no matter where it comes back to
within that area, my analysis still applies.
This takes the guessing game out of figuring
out the exact retest level.
As long as price re-entries your highlighted
region, you can take the trade.
Making this simple adjustment has made trading
breakouts much more reliable.
In this chart, you can see there were two
highs close together that triggered breakout
buys.
In the moment, you wouldn't know which exact
high the price might drop back to test.
That's why it's way better to highlight the
whole zone between the highs instead of just
drawing a line.
That way, whether it hits the first or second
high on a retest, your area still covers it.
By outlining a broad region instead of trying
to pinpoint one level, you take out lots of
guesswork.
Marking breakdowns and breakouts as trading
ranges just makes so much more sense than
rigid lines.
It builds in more wiggle room for when the
price retraces.
Now very important: when trading these breakout
retests is all about reading each market’s
individual tendencies.
What works on one market may fail totally
for another one.
There's no formula that instantly makes you
a pro - it comes down to watching price action
over time so you get a feel for how each one
behaves.
The more markers and consolidations you witness,
the better calls you'll make.
Also, for a breakout to be legit, look for
two signs.
First there needs to be a noticeable gap in
the close price through the level, not just
a wick.
That shows commitment.
Second, check volume.
If it spikes on the candle that clears the
zone, that validates buyers/sellers are stepping
up.
Low volume breaks are suspect.
When looking for valid breakouts, volume is
key.
For the move to have strength, you need to
see rising volume on the initial push through
resistance.
This shows real buying pressure forcing the
break.
But then volume is just as important on the
retracement - it should be lower than the
breakout.
If volume stays high as it pulls back, that
tells you sellers are still in control and
it may just be a trap.
You want evidence of buying demand strengthening
again.
Ideally at the retest zone, volume will start
to pick up too.
That confirms buyers are defending that area
again.
Without that validation from volume swings,
it's risky to bet on the breakout continuing.
Reading these volume clues is so helpful for
discerning real strength versus smart money
traps.
The moves need to fit the typical patterns
- break on rising volume, pullback on falling
volume, then rising again at retest.
This is the framework for analyzing potential
breakouts.
Breakouts that start downtrends follow the
same pattern.
It doesn't matter if it's continuing bearish
momentum or reversing from bullish.
The only difference is it breaks below support
instead of above resistance.
But volume should be high on the drop through
the zone to confirm selling pressure breaking
it.
Then, we want a return back up to test that
new area.
And again, falling volume validates buyers
aren't in control here yet.
Most importantly, declining markets need rising
volume too.
As it extends lower, increasing selling volumes
prove real downward strength.
Once the buyers can't keep pace at the retest,
look for volume to spike as the sellers take
control.
Those volume inflections confirm healthy breakdowns
versus fake traps.
When looking to enter a retest trade, it's
not enough for the price to just touch the
old support/resistance zone.
That's barely a retest at all.
You want to see some confirmation that smart
money are genuinely treating it as a new level.
For me, the best way is through candlestick
signals at the zone.
An engulfing candle that swallows up the previous
one shows a reversal underway.
Or a pin bar wick rejection off the area is
a solid sign too.
That's a much stronger indication that the
new level is holding, and it’s not hovering
there without conviction.
Just waiting for a simple touch isn't enough
evidence for me.
But catching those engulfing or pin bar signals
right at the old break point, level ups the
odds the move will continue in my direction
after the retest.
One thing that's helped improve my breakout
retests is taking advantage of patterns on
smaller timeframes.
Like this chart - I mainly trade the H4.
But zooming into a 30min view, I spotted an
engulfing candlestick forming right at the
support zone break point.
Volume was also validating the move with high
volume on the drop and low on the pullback.
So with that bearish engulfing candle plus
volume check, this would have been a pretty
decent trade.
Now for the stop, you have 2 main areas: above
the engulfing candle.
Or you simply set the stop a few points above
the whole resistance zone.
So using patterns on lower timeframes for
entries, but keeping the stop based on the
broader zone, can be a much safer retest strategy.
One of the most reliable signals I see at
retest zones is a big pin bar candle.
It literally screams that buyers or sellers
are stepping up to defend that area.
A pin bar shows up as a small body with a
long upper or lower wick.
This rejection at the retest shows traders
are fighting over that price.
Catching strong pin bars precisely where the
market breaks out of a range gives such a
high-probability entry.
The bigger the pin, the more force was in
that rejection.
Plus, the volume needs to be above average
too.
That confirms heavy volumes swapping hands
as buyers and sellers are battling there.
For me, these obvious pin bars that pop out
at a retest zone are just begging to be traded.
As soon as I see one, I'll enter in with the
expectation the rejection holds and the move
continues.
The combination of pin bars with volume spikes
at a retest point is one of my go-to strategies.
And I know it can be tempting to jump in right
away when a big breakout happens.
But being disciplined and waiting for a retest
is so important.
Even if you miss a few trades that keep running,
that's better than entering early before letting
the market reset itself.
Those premature entries are riskier.
By waiting, you get to see how volume behaves
on the break compared to the pullback.
You can also watch for solid candlestick patterns
showing buyers/sellers stepping up again at
the old level.
Most importantly, it allows weak positions
from nervous traders to get flushed out first.
Then you enter with stronger footing once
the area has reset as support or resistance.
I know it's boring to sit on your hands at
first sometimes.
But patience at retests creates a much firmer
base for the move to continue.
Don't compromise on this rule just because
FOMO bites!
The initial retest after a breakout is often
the most important one for me.
When price first returns to a newly established
support or resistance zone, that sets the
tone for what's likely to follow.
If it holds and bounces back in the direction
of the original move, it confirms that level
is now significant.
But the moment it violates that zone twice,
the likelihood of a new wave decreases a lot.
Traders will be less inclined to defend an
area if it fails as a new boundary once already.
The impact is lessened.
That's why I put extra focus on how the market
interacts with freshly broken levels the first
time it re-encounters them.
That initial test often makes or breaks the
whole pattern.
Often times, a second retest of a breakout
zone usually isn't as strong as the initial
one.
Here’s why.
When price first comes back to that area,
any traders who entered on the initial breakout
would still be in their positions.
But if it tests again after that?
They would've closed out already.
So during a second retest, there's less buy/sell
orders stacked up from the original breakout
traders still chasing gains or protecting
stops.
Smart money already collected those first
retest trades, so they're less motivated to
defend it again.
They're not hunting for as many stops or liquidity
anymore either.
In this chart you can see it clearly - price
bounced perfectly off the zone the first time
back.
But on the second touch?
It cleanly broke through with ease.
Support was weaker.
So for the best odds, focus on trading that
crucial first retest.