for many years I've always looked at CH
patterns thinking they provide clear buy
and sell signals things like triangles
flags and head and shoulders seemed very
simple as long as the price formed the
right shaped on the chart you knew a
move was coming at least that's what all
the trading books told me but over the
past years I've started to realize chart
patterns may not be as reliable as they
are made out to be in fact I'm beginning
to think many of the classic patterns
retailers like myself look for on the
charts are intentionally set up by the
smart money specifically to trap retail
Traders when I first started trading I
would eagerly scan charts looking for
well-defined triangles Flags double tops
or bottoms anything that resembled a
textbook pattern as soon as I spotted
one starting to form I would plot my
entry and exit levels based on the
target markets described in most trading
books more often than not the price
would promptly reverse against me
leaving me scratching my head wondering
what went wrong and at first I blamed it
on my inexperience but it kept happening
over and over with different markets no
matter how perfectly the pattern
appeared as soon as I took the bait the
move fell flat I started to suspect the
big players must be aware of this common
retail strategy and we're deliberately
setting traps to liquidate our
positions it was around this time I
first came across the idea of orderflow
manipulation I discovered how
institutions monitor retail order flow
to see where we concentrated then the
engineer fake outs in the opposite
direction to flush us out and at first I
didn't want to believe such a thing was
possible sounded like a conspiracy but
the more examples I saw saw the more it
started to make sense and if you're
being honest to yourself you know that
retail J patterns seem to not be as
effective as they once were these big
institutions have immense resources and
Technology on their side is it really
that far-fetched that they manipulate
prices to profit at our expense the
answer lies in the subtle yet powerful
influence of the smart money and how it
manipulates the market it might sound
bit harsh but I believe this is an
ongoing reality in the financial markets
the rich keep getting richer and the
poor stay poor and why does this happen
it's often due to Market
manipulation so let me ask you do you
keep all your life savings in physical
cash chances are you don't your money is
sitting in various Banks or large
institutions the banks are the ones who
control the mass amounts of money in
Banks just like any other business are
out to make a profit so it's safe to say
that we and them have the same goal but
here's the thing it takes a substantial
amount of money to influence the market
and these banks are the actual ones with
the power to shape and steer prices as
they see
fit a smart money has a few tricks up
its sleeve one of these tricks is stop
plusus hunting so let's consider this
double bottom almost all Traders set a
stop loss below the pattern which
automatically exit their position if the
price reaches a certain level but if
enough people have stop losses set
around the same price and the smart
money can push the price down to this
level all the stop losses will trigger
at once causing a rapid drop in price
the smart money can then scoop up these
cheap prices before the market rebounds
then there are Market traps this is is
when the smart money purposely creates a
chart pattern like a flag or a triangle
knowing that retail Traders will see it
and start buying or selling once the
retail Traders have taken the bait the
smart money goes the other way causing
the price to move in the opposite
direction of what the retail Traders
were
expecting one of my most common mistakes
was placing too much faith in Char
patterns and a lot of years I've ignored
other key factors like volume market
news or fundamentals and I was instead
relying solely on patterns to guide my
trading decisions and at first I wasn't
aware of liquidity runs the main
strategy used by smart money to quickly
buy or sell large quantities of a market
they do this by pushing the price to
levels where they know lots of orders
are waiting like the stop losses we
talked about earlier triggering them all
at once
and creating a sudden surge in demand or
Supply that allows them to execute their
large orders without drastically
affecting the
price in fact one of my biggest losses
came after a Char pattern few years ago
I noticed Apple was forming a pretty
obvious symmetrical triangle on its
daily chart over the course of about 3
weeks as the pattern developed the stock
was bouncing consistently between the
upper and the lower trend lines to me it
was a textbook so I bought the next day
the price broke out and within a couple
of days without any clear news the stock
abruptly reversed its direction and
plunged back below the breakout level by
the following week it had completely
negated the whole triangle move and
thinking back in hindsight this was a
liquidity run based on a classic retail
pattern big players likely noticed the
buildup of long retail positions from
people like me reacting to the confirmed
triangle breakout once our buys were
established based on the pattern they
started selling into our stops trapping
us all with losses in the process and
with their vast Financial capabilities
such an orchestrated price decrease
wouldn't be hard to engineer and would
yield massive profits at our expense
after seeing so many textbook patterns
fail me in similar fashion over time
I've became increasingly skeptical that
chart Reading Alone provides any real
Edge whatsoever at my retail level of
course technical analysis still has
Merit but this strategies relying purely
on pattern recognition seem hopelessly
naive when factoring in the reality of
orderflow manipulation by the bigger
players like I said looking back I was
repeatedly taken for a soccer anytime I
followed one of these textbook retail
setups to the letter lons learned the
hard way one of the patterns I got
burned on repeatedly was The Head and
Shoulders it's supposed to be a very
reliable reversal indicator yet they
would form only to promptly get
invalidated by a big spike in the
opposite direction soon as I entered I
clearly recall entering short position
multiple times as prices would break
below the neckline only to mysteriously
reverse Direction and move right back
above it in no
time and another mistake I've made was
not validating the breakout with the
volume most breakouts below the neckline
happened on low volume these apparently
staged fake outs strongly suggest the
pattern was deliberately engineered to
attract our counter Trend shorts only
only to be violently flushed out for a
loss flags were other chart formations I
used to consider based on textbook
continuation patterns but much like the
others they fooled me too many times the
signals seem so Cut and Clear price
pauses horizontally consolidating its
gains before resuming the prior Trend
yet time and time again as soon as I
entered assuming the breakout the price
would often reverse Direction against me
often on relatively light
volume like I said those were valuable
lessons I've learned while retail
Traders like myself are busy scanning
the charts looking for textbook setups
based purely on price the bigger players
are no doubt leveraging their much
richer Intel and experience to
manipulate against our positions with
access to order information sentiment
readings and many other data streams
they can pinpoint exactly where waterers
are concentrated and engineer fake moves
to liquidate those positions the reality
is that our trading activity is
completely transparent to them and this
allows them to set off liquidity runs
with these conditions where temporary
imbalances lead to Sharp irrational
moves that defy any chart
logic so knowing this how can we retail
Traders compete with the smart money are
we doomed to lose every single time the
key is understanding how market prices
move prices tend to gravitate toward
levels where a significant number of
unexecuted orders are waiting these
orders can be located either below or
above the current market price or
sometimes both the type of orders I'm
referring to are buy stop sell stops
stop losses and trailing stops in my
personal approach to trading I now
prefer to identify general areas where
these orders might be clustered on my
charts and when I notice a notable
reaction from one of these areas it
often presents an opportunity for me to
enter the
market once pending orders have been
triggered and liquidity dries up in a
specific price area it often leads to a
reversal from the current levels these
reversals can frequently Mark the low or
high point of a trend and finding your
entry into the market can set you up for
potentially significant gains with
minimal risk while this phenomenon can
occur across various time frames it's
more noticeable on smaller time frames
compared to larger ones and from my
experience this tends to happen most
frequently during the London Trading
session in the overlap between the
London and the US
session you have to ditch the retail
mentality the conventional approach of
the retail trading presented in most
trading books me personally I seek
buying opportunities where others are
getting stopped out instead of following
the crowd I now prefer to take a
contrarian approach from my experience
markets often Pro the crowd wrong
especially at price streams therefore
aligning your position against the
prevailing consensus can often lead to
more favorable outcomes my new mindset
when I see a textbook pattern is that
many stop-loss orders exist just below
the market and I know that smart money
will try to run the market down to take
out or activate the stops and then run
the price back up again with this new
perspective on the market I encourage
you to go back to your own charts and
observe what happens in real Market
scenarios for those of you who felt the
frustration of being stopped out just
before the market moves in your favor
despite correct analysis you now have an
explanation for why this
occurs now you might ask should we
abandon chart patterns altogether not
necessarily while it's true that smart
money manipulation can lead to fail
patterns this doesn't mean that chart
patterns are useless they can still
provide some insights into market trends
however it's crucial for us as retail
traders to be aware of these tactics and
not to rely solely on chart patterns
when making our trading decisions we
need to remember that trading isn't just
about recognizing shapes on a chart it's
a complex game involving numerous
factors we need to be flexible adaptable
and and always ready to learn
understanding how smart money operates
will help us become better Traders so
keep an eye on those Char patterns but
don't let them be your only
guide so technical analysis still has
value but textbook chart patterns might
be doing naive Traders like my past self
a great disservice signals that worked
for decades are now intentionally
manipulated precisely to bait and flush
out unassuming ril positions classic
moves like triangles flags and wedges
have all personally failed me too many
times to plausibly assign them the same
credibility as for myself I aim to
evolve Beyond pure pattern Reliance
going forward combining traditional
chart tactics with orderflow monitoring
sentiment analysis and volume analysis
for potential liquidity events has
become my quest to level the playing
field against smart money so here are my
key takeaways going forward trading
isn't as simple as searching and
recognizing different shapes if it were
everyone would be rich markets can and
will be manipulated to trigger stop
orders retail Traders don't have control
over the price movements but liquidity
runs executed by smart money can present
trading opportunity is for us retail
Traders and always remember that prices
tend to gravitate toward levels where a
significant number of unexecuted orders
are
[Music]
waiting