If you're waiting for a green candle to buy here,
you've already lost. This is just one of the
mistakes you make daily, why you're always late,
and why your best trades turn into stop-outs.
Your losses aren't random. They're a system.
This video gives you the rules to break it.
First scalping tip is to mark the previous
day's missed pivot or untested pivot.
You basically check if price ever touched
that pivot as the day unfolded. If not,
that pivot becomes a missed or untested pivot.
Many traders ignore it and move on because they
assume a new session pivot is all that matters.
That assumption might cause them to miss subtle
clues about potential price magnets. When price
fails to visit a pivot, it can remain like a loose
end. Sometimes on a later day, the market will
wander back to settle that unfinished business.
If the pivot stayed untouched, place a small
horizontal marker there. If you see that the
market is drifting in that direction or
if momentum picks up, you might sense that
price is gravitating to that leftover pivot.
That's the moment to plan a possible trade.
If the main trend aligns with that directional
push, you can jump in with more confidence. If
there is a strong counter-trend wave, be more
careful. Untested pivots are worth watching,
especially when the new day is quiet and
no massive fundamental shift is in place.
Now, a big trending wave can ignore these missed
pivots entirely. That's why you don't chase the
pivot idea blindly. Instead, treat it as a clue.
If the market looks indecisive, that missed pivot
can become a prime target. If price gets close,
you often see volume accelerate. That's because
others expect a reaction at that hidden zone.
Sometimes price bounces off it. Other times,
it pierces through. But this approach can
provide a short-term scalping opportunity.
In a slow session, scanning for untested pivots
can highlight pockets of volatility. If you see
that yesterday's pivot was never reached, you
can note that level. If the market creeps in
that direction, you can plan a scalp or short
swing if it lines up with your usual signals.
For example, if you trade candlestick patterns,
you might watch for a simple break above a micro
resistance that points to an approach toward
that pivot. You ride that wave in hope that
the pivot is indeed acting as a magnet.
You might notice a missed pivot from a few
days back that can remain relevant if the market
is in a broad range or if it's drifting aimlessly.
The concept of untested pivots matters in
both trending and ranging markets. It might
not be the only tool you use, but it's an
extra lens to spot hidden magnet levels.
Conventional wisdom says wait for confirmation.
I've said it countless times in my previous
videos, but many new traders interpret
this as "watch for a green candle to close,
then buy on the next candle." Well, in fast-paced
sessions, you might miss the best entries. If you
wait for a green candle to go long, you often
might be too late. The price has already moved.
An alternative tactic is to set your own zone
first, then enter if price hits that zone,
regardless of candle color. You focus on the
level, not the candle. This means you need to
plan your trades in advance. The color can mislead
you because short-term price flips happen often.
If you wait for that extra candle close, you might
lose half the move. Your plan could revolve around
the support or resistance, supply or demand,
or a pivot level. And if price hits this spot,
you already know what to do. You don't care if the
candle heading there is red, green, or has a doji
shape. You rely on a structure-based approach.
The reason for ignoring candle color is that
many real intraday moves start abruptly.
If you wait for the perfect green bar,
the entry might be on candle number three after
a breakout. Meanwhile, the best reward-to-risk
ratio might have occurred on the first touch
of the zone. That's why more advanced scalpers
often jump in while the candle is still forming.
Focusing on pre-planned price zones also keeps
your mind clear. If you stare at each candle, you
might interpret random wicks or small color flips
as a signal to do something. Instead, mark your
zone before the market opens or during quieter
times. Base it on a pivot, a prior day's high, or
any other support or resistance zone. Then wait.
If price charges into that zone with a giant red
bar, don't be afraid to buy. If your rules say to
buy that zone, you can take it even as the candle
is printing red. You trust the level. If it fails,
your stop is triggered. If it bounces,
you catch the reversal at the best price.
Many scalping guides revolve around 1-minute
or 5-minute charts, and that's a reasonable
approach. But for those seeking an even sharper
look, second-based charts can be a game-changer.
A 15-second or 30-second chart creates new
candles more frequently, so you see subtle pulses
in price. If you trade a fast-moving stock like
Tesla or an index future, those micro shifts can
reveal entry or exit moments with more precision.
Another advantage is that second-based charts can
give you a sense of momentum stalling. If you see
a rapid series of green bars on a 10-second chart,
then suddenly a red bar forms and pushes price
back more than half of that previous wave,
that's a quick sign the momentum may be fading.
On a one-minute chart, that might all appear in
the same single candle, making it harder to
interpret the shift. Scalpers who want tight
risk management can react faster. They might
exit or reverse if that micro structure breaks.
Stocks with high volume can be ideal for
second charts. If the stock is illiquid,
second charts might show a bunch of gaps and
weird prints. So, choose actively traded names
or markets. Some scalpers keep a second chart
side-by-side with a 5-minute chart. They might
confirm the bigger pattern on the 5-minute, then
time their entries or exits using the 15-second
chart. The 5-minute chart shows broader direction.
The second chart helps with the accuracy.
One caution is whipsaw. Second-based
charts can produce many false starts.
If the market is choppy, you might see
a tiny wave up, then a tiny wave down,
all within a minute. If you chase every small
move, you could get in trouble. That's why second
charts must be used with a clear plan. Maybe
you only trade in the bigger trend direction,
or you only act when volume spikes above a
threshold, or you wait for a certain breakout
that aligns with the 5-minute structure, then
zoom down to the second chart for the best fill.
Scalpers often trade the same level multiple
times. If price dips into a support zone,
they might try to buy each bounce, and sometimes
that works. But advanced scalpers sometimes do the
opposite. They attempt one strike at the level
and if it fails, they move on. This rule can
help avoid repeated losses. If your first attempt
at that support zone fails, maybe it's not truly
strong support. The logic is that the best trades
often work soon after you enter. If it doesn't,
the level might be weaker than you thought.
Picture a scenario. You see a pivot line or
some narrow range support. Price dips there once
and you buy. Suppose it doesn't bounce quickly.
Instead, it breaks below or consolidates under
that support. You exit and vow not to re-enter
that same zone again soon. The zone might still
hold eventually, but you skip further attempts.
You wait for a brand new sign of strength or
a pivot shift. This method can keep your mind
fresh. If you keep banging your head at the same
level, your frustration can lead to mistakes.
Think about it. If it's truly a strong bounce
zone, it often shows energy right away. If price
hovers or creeps lower, that's not the decisive
bounce a scalper wants. If you see no real
follow-through within a few candles, you simply
exit. Then refrain from repeating the same trade.
You can modify the rule for breakouts, too. If you
see a resistance level that you expect to break,
you might go long on the first push above it. If
it fails quickly, you exit. Instead of jumping in
again, you consider that a false breakout and you
move on to another setup. Many new traders keep
re-entering or doubling down, hoping the level
eventually holds or breaks. And this is a sure
way to obtain other losses. So pick your best
zone, wait for price to test it. If you see a
fast rejection or bounce that you expected, good.
You trade it. If the level is truly significant,
it often yields a decent reaction on the first
test. If you prefer building positions or letting
trades develop, you might skip this tip. But
for pure scalpers who hate watching multiple
retests, this method can be a robust filter.
Markets often have a typical daily range. That
range might be 80 pips for a currency pair or $2
for a stock. This average changes over time, but
many traders track the 10-day or 20-day average
true range to get a sense of typical volatility.
If you notice that your market has already
hit or exceeded that average range by midday,
it might be overextended. If the market has barely
moved half its usual range and the session is half
over, you might anticipate more movement ahead.
Let's say you trade a currency pair whose average
daily ADR is around 100 pips. By noon, if you see
the high-low range of the day is already 110 pips,
you're above the normal daily range.
That doesn't guarantee a reversal,
but it signals the market might be close to a
rest phase. Of course, there can be extraordinary
days that double that range, but on an average
day with no groundbreaking news, the odds of
more huge moves may be smaller. So be careful
about chasing further breakouts at that point.
Now let's flip that scenario. Suppose by noon
it's only moved 30 pips. That's far below the
100-pip norm. There's more to come, possibly
after a news release or a session overlap. You
might expect a bigger push if something triggers
momentum. This doesn't mean you blindly enter,
but you stay prepared knowing the market often
covers more ground on an average day. If a
catalyst appears, it can travel a good distance.
Checking the daily range can stop you from
over-scalping in a market that's already had
its big run. Combine it with your pivot or zone
analysis. If a missed pivot lines up with
the idea that a day has no space to move,
that synergy can enhance a reversal trade.
Many scalpers love to trade news. It's one of
the fastest ways to gain quick profits. Imagine
a day with big NFP news to be announced. The
numbers are released and they look bullish. You
expect price to rise and price does spike up,
but then it stalls and sinks back below the
starting point. You've seen this hundreds of
times. That's a failed reaction. If the market
couldn't hold a bullish push on good news,
it implies hidden selling or a lack of real
buying interest. So, you fade the move. You
do the opposite of what a naive approach might
suggest. This is a contrarian fade tactic.
Many traders chase the news direction. They
see a bullish headline, so they buy. If that
move can't stick, they get trapped. Meanwhile,
contrarians see the failure as a sign the market
wants to go the other way. This method applies to
economic releases, corporate earnings for a stock,
or even a technical breakout that gets
reversed quickly. This is the basic premise:
If the market had every reason to continue
in that direction and still couldn't,
that reveals underlying weakness
or strength on the opposite side.
Suppose a company reports excellent earnings.
The stock gaps up at the open but can't hold.
Within minutes, it's back below the
pre-gap level. Contrarians might short,
reasoning that if the good news isn't fueling
sustained demand, maybe big holders are selling.
If you see that price is returning below a
daily pivot or a missed pivot after good news,
that's an added sign the bounce is failing.
One advantage is that you often find a good
risk-to-reward ratio. The failed breakout or
the failed reaction sets a clear line. If you're
shorting, you can place a stop just above that
day's high or the initial spike. If the market
retakes that high, maybe the fade was early. If
it continues lower, you might catch a good move.
Now, the contrarian fade is triggered only when
you see a robust failure. The news or event gave
the market every chance to keep going. If it
can't, that's the trigger. Big players might
have used the good news to unload. They wait for
retail or momentum traders to buy. Then they sell
into strength, capping the rally, and once the
buy orders dry up, price collapses. The contrarian
fade method tries to profit from that dynamic.
You can refine this with volume analysis. If
you see a surge in volume on the initial spike
but no follow-through volume on the next bar,
that can be a clue. Alternatively, if
you see huge volume on the reversal bar,
it might confirm big money selling. The concept
stays the same: Watch how price reacts to a
bullish or bearish catalyst. If that fails to
sustain direction, consider the opposite trade.
Most traders always set a strict take-profit
level, and there's nothing wrong with this.
But a small minority skip the price target step,
aiming for bigger wins. They let the trade run
until the market knocks them out by hitting a
trailing stop or a structure break. This can be
effective for catching big moves that go farther
than expected. If you always place a target at,
say, 20 pips, you might never see those 100-pip
surges. By removing or loosening your target,
you allow chance for a home run. That is
the logic behind skipping fixed targets.
This style needs a clear risk plan. You can't
just hold indefinitely. You still define an
initial stop-loss. Maybe you base it on a
pivot low or a certain percentage from your
entry. But on the profit side, you remain
open-ended. As price moves in your favor,
you might trail your stop to protect some
gains, but you let the trade keep running.
When you skip the target, you have to handle
the psychological strain of watching unrealized
gains fluctuate. Suppose you're up 20
pips. Price dips to only 10 pips profit,
so you worry. With no fixed target, that doubt
will often creep in. A mechanical trailing stop
can help. You set a rule such as "move the stop
to break even after X distance" or "trail below
the last swing low." This prevents you from
giving back everything on a random pullback.
Those who can't handle the emotional roller
coaster might prefer partial profit taking.
You could close half at a set target, letting
the other half run. This tactic works well if
your market produces big trending moves.
If you're trading choppy conditions,
you might get stopped out often before price
ever truly runs. And that's normal. But if you
know the market environment is supportive, those
momentum sessions can spark extended moves, which
is where skipping a fixed target might pay off.
Some days you'll pass up certain exit points.
Then the market reverses and you exit with a
smaller profit than if you had a fixed target.
That's part of the trade-off, but on other trades,
you'll get a much better exit level. The biggest
mistake with this method is letting a winning
trade come all the way back to your initial
stop because you refuse to exit. That's not the
intention here. You want to preserve gains while
allowing for more upside. The main idea is to
give yourself the possibility of a larger trade.
An overlooked step is to revisit the chart
after the trade is done. What happened to the
price after you closed the trade? Did it continue
another 50 pips after you exited? Did it reverse
shortly where you got out? Over time, you'll
notice patterns in how you manage exits. I bet
many times you'll discover you exit too soon.
Price hits your small target, then marches on.
You might discover that you repeatedly bail out
of winners at the first sign of a small pullback,
then the market resumes upward. If that's
the case, maybe using a micro trailing stop
or partial exit could improve results.
And if you're ready to fit this into a
full A to Z trading system, that's what our
academy is for. Link is in the description.