the divergence is one of the most
effective ways to try the financial
markets divergence as the name suggests
forms when the oscillator and a price
action failed to converge if you analyze
price action in a chart you'll notice
that the price moves up and down forming
peaks and valleys these are the
expansions and contractions or trusts
and retracements for an experienced
trader trading based on price action
alone might already be profitable
however many other traders also prefer a
secondary confirmation for their setups
so they use indicators some applied on
price chart while others are oscillating
indicators on a different window on
their platform usually at the bottom of
the main charts under normal conditions
price action and the oscillator tend to
move in the same direction when price
makes a new high the oscillator is also
prone to make a new high likewise
when a price makes a new low the
oscillator is also prone to make a new
low when this converge fails what you
basically get is a divergence the
divergence is a leading indicator of
price action in other words when you see
a divergence there is a high likelihood
that price action will potentially make
a reversal there are many different
types of divergences available the
divergences are categorized into regular
and hidden divergences while the regular
divergence is easy to spot hidden
divergences are less rare and require
some practice to spot them within the
hidden divergence you have the bullish
and the bearish divergence if you look
closely at this chart you'll notice how
the MACD indicator moves up and down
corresponding to price movements however
if you also look closely you would also
notice instances where the peaks and
valleys height and depth would differ
from that of the price chart these are
what we call divergences it is basically
a disagreement in the height or death
the price charts and the indicators
peaks and valleys this disagreement is
telling me that even though the price
chart has already formed a low
that might not be that deep
mathematically the indicator is showing
that the retracement is already deep
enough this indicates that price is
ready for a sharp reversal this type of
divergence is called a hidden divergence
which usually signifies a reversal of a
short retracement were better said a
continuation of an existing trend so
remember this hidden divergences usually
correspond with short-term retracements
how does the hidden bullish divergence
work a hidden bullish divergence works
based on the concept of the lows in
price and the lows in the oscillator
while a trade with divergences that are
regular indicates a reversal of training
price action hidden divergence is an
indication that the trend will continue
I like to consider a hidden divergence
as the end of a pullback in order to
identify a divergence you basically need
an oscillator any type of oscillator
works in this case the most commonly
used oscillators on the relative
strength index the stochastic oscillator
and the MACD the custom oscillator and
money flow index are also great
indicators to spot hidden divergences
this example you have the basic
illustration of the hidden bullish
divergence in this chart you can see
that the price makes a higher low
compared to the initial low however
every sign indicator makes a lower low
relative to the previous low this
example shows another hidden bullish
divergence
using the stochastic indicator in a
clear uptrend
as you can see comparing the lows in the
price and the lows in the oscillator the
hidden bullish divergence is formed
after the formation of the higher low in
price price then surges to a new high it
should be noted that the hidden bullish
divergence can form anywhere in a trend
typically though the hidden bullish
divergences are usually found in an
uptrend
it forms close to the highest in the
price action
portrayed with hidden bullish divergence
signals there is a strong probability of
price continuing the uptrend also pay
close attention to the higher lows
formed at the end of the pullback price
action candlestick patterns can serve as
great confirmation tools for the
continuing trend the next type of trade
with divergence is the hidden bearish
divergence in a bearish hidden
divergence the price makes lower highs
but you'll see later makes higher highs
this type of pattern occurs mainly
during downtrend Corrections in this
example we see that while prices have
continued to go lower in formed lower
highs the arrow psy oscillator made
higher highs this is what we called
hidden bearish divergence divergence
Theory tells us that there is a strong
probability that the Down trend will
continue basically a hidden bearish
divergence pattern means that the trend
is continuing to the downside
and here's another hidden divergence
this time which is stochastic recent
price action indicated a downward
momentum with the price making lower
highs however despite the fact that the
price was making lower highs the
stochastic recorded higher highs thus
forming a hidden divergence and
signaling that Bears were in a strong
position to enter the market of the two
types of divergence regular and hidden
the hidden divergence represents the
higher probability pattern this is based
on the fact that the hidden divergence
is a trend continuation leading signal
now that we identified the main types of
hidden divergences how do you trade them
the hidden bullish divergence method can
be used in a number of ways due to the
fact that the hidden bullish divergence
is a leading indicator it can
potentially tell you what could happen
next in price generally speaking when a
hidden bullish divergence is formed you
can take long positions
and when you spot the hidden bearish
divergence be prepared to search for
short trades the oscillators are used in
the previous examples were the RSI
stochastic and the MACD these are
probably the most common oscillators for
detecting divergences but there are a
substantial number of oscillators very
useful to trade divergences now from my
experience the most ideal place where a
hidden bullish divergence can occur is
at the end of a downtrend near the
bottom end of the downtrend a hidden
bullish divergence can be a powerful
trading signal in this example we have
the hidden bullish divergence that is
formed near the bottom end of the
downtrend if you closely observe what
you first see is a minor collection in
price this leads to a higher low in
price at the same time the relative
strength index indicator forms a lower
low this divergence then leads to an
uptrend one of the ways to trade the
hidden bullish divergence is to wait for
the error side to cross it's 50 level
also pay attention to candlestick
formations pin bars and engulfing
candles are great confirmation patterns
that bulls are prepared to push price
higher also trendline breakouts and
breakouts of a key resistance on a lower
timeframe are also very strong signals
that the hidden divergence could prove
to be successful after the entry of the
trade the stops are placed at the higher
low in price
following this aim for a one to one what
I wanted to risk/reward setup as you can
see in this example the price action
eventually reached our target however
not all hidden bullish divergences are
successful you can find many examples of
a failed hidden bullish divergence the
most common mistake that inexperienced
traders make would be mistaking false
hidden divergences scenarios as a green
light to get started with trading for
instance in this example looking at a
downtrend
you will spot that a hidden divergence
starts much
earlier than the official top that's why
when you spot the inception of a hidden
divergence
don't enter the market blindly you need
confirmation from price action first and
from the oscillator second a hidden
bullish divergence can fail when the
price fails to make new highs that's why
you should constantly pay attention to
price action this example shows a failed
hidden bullish divergence here
although price action jumped higher
after posting the higher low prices
failed to maintain the gains sure if you
entered early at the stochastic
crossover this trade would have brought
some profits following the swing high
that is formed price action barely tests
is high and then drops off this leads to
a downside correction in price as you
can see while this looks like a failed
hidden bullish divergence you can see
that a failure of the swing high leads
to prices posting or your purse all to
the downside price is king that's why
you need to let it guide you so the big
point to remember is that when the
hidden bullish divergence forms near the
top end of the rally
you can expect to see a topping pattern
being formed if the hidden divergence
pattern fails you can expect to see
reversal on the lower side here are
other examples of successful hidden
divergence patterns the hidden
divergence is an exceptional market tool
that can pinpoint areas to enter the
market and eliminate some of the
guesswork created by false trading
signals divergences although not perfect
are very powerful techniques to use
since hidden divergences usually occur
on minor retracement the probability of
a successful trade is higher since
chances are you are still trading with
the trend and not against it if you
learn something new and found value give
us a like to share support and make sure
to subscribe and click the bell icon to
stay in touch when we upload new videos
until next time