Hello and welcome.
Today I’m sharing my trading experience,
what trading is all about, some of its complexities
and how your approach should be when day trading.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
Technical indicators are inherently lagging
so they cannot be relied upon on their own.
Most new traders start with indicators.
That’s the first step in day trading.
In my first 2 years in trading, price action
didn’t matter to me because I was relying
on a random set of lagging indicators to make
decisions for me.
The truth is I was being lazy, hoping that
I’d stumble across some magical combination
of indicators that would make me wealthy.
I was just making decisions because a few
dots and lines said it was time to buy or
sell.
But to rely 100% on them without first learning
how to read price action is a major mistake.
Don’t get me wrong.
I’m not saying all indicators are bad or
that traders who use them are wrong to do
so.
I also use trading indicators, but price action
comes first.
Before you apply any indicator to the chart,
you first need to understand price action.
Even If you feel that indicators are the way
to go, that’s okay.
Just be sure to spend some time learning how
to read price action.
It’ll help you in the long run even if you
decide to use an indicator-based strategy.
If a trade doesn’t let you sleep, you are
not trading correctly
A simple rule you should apply is to think
about your sleep.
If you are able to place a trade, set the
appropriate stop loss and take profit orders
in your platform, and then go to sleep, this
is the trade size that fits your risk profile.
If, however, when you place a trade you find
it difficult to sleep, you find that you are
always thinking about the trade while away
from your computer, that you feel the urge
to constantly check your smartphone, then
the trade is too big.
That’s a common mistake.
When people are new to trading, they tend
to feel pressure throughout the day and especially
when a trade is open.
You need to reduce your trading to the sleeping
point, the point at which you can place a
trade, accept the risk, and have a peaceful
state of mind.
Although trading risk is important, your emotional
and mental health risks are more important.
The first and most important way to control
stress levels with regards to trading, is
to control your position sizes.
You will find yourself remarkably less stressed
if you keep your percentage at risk on each
trade lower.
Always watch more than one time-frame.
Zoom out to see the bigger picture.
Day trading is considered a riskier alternative
to the more traditional investing or swing
trading.
When trading short timeframes, it is not enough
to simply analyze one time frame.
Sometimes there is very little time to catch
the perfect moment to enter and if you are
late even a little bit, you won’t be able
to take advantage of the price movement.
If you see a good trade on an M15 chart, see
how it looks on the hourly chart and H4 too.
Zoom out to see the bigger picture.
Sometimes an opportunity may be less obvious
on a smaller chart timeframe and more obvious
if you zoom out and look at the bigger picture,
and vice versa.
Sometimes a move on a 10-minute chart can
look so scary; but when you step back, it’s
very minor when viewed on a daily time frame.
Evaluating a market on different timeframes
will help confirm a trend and make a better
informed decisions.
Never make a trade, change your mind for little
to no reason and take it off
Here’s a familiar experience.
You analyze a chart for some time, you see
a decent trade, you pull the trigger, confident
that your analysis will pay off, and after
5 minutes, when you’re down a few points,
you close your position.
When day trading, emotions will come from
market noises coming your way.
Whether markets are in an uptrend or downtrend,
you will witness a lot of noise.
And noise can impact your trading strategy
and decisions.
So, you must filter it to keep your emotions
under control.
The lesson is to always give your trades enough
time to come good.
If you often engage in emotional exits, this
will only destroy your confidence and eat
into your profits
This doesn’t mean you can’t change your
mind when new information comes in.
If a support level is broken for example,
or a huge pin bar forms on high volume.
This should all be considered in your plan.
Always question yourself as to whether your
decisions are emotionally driven or are backed
by technicals or fundamentals.
Learn all you can about the Kelly Formula.
This is the mathematical answer to how much
you should risk on a trade.
The reality is that even a wildly profitable
system will go bust if your risk is too big.
The Kelly criterion is an advanced money management
tool that helps you work out how much money
you can risk on each new trading position,
based on how well you have done with similar
trades in the past.
Calculating the Kelly criterion is relatively
simple and relies on two basic components:
your trading strategy's win percentage probability
and its win to loss ratio.
These will help you arrive at a number called
the Kelly percentage.
This gives you a guide to what percentage
of your trading account is the maximum amount
you should risk on any given trade.
Kelly formula is probably the best money management
tool for judging position sizes and risk tolerance
in trading.
You don’t need to trade.
If the market is quiet or behaving strangely,
just wait it out.
If you find yourself jumping into low conviction
trades because you can’t find anything better,
the most likely reason is that you need to
do more work.
Spend less time looking at charts and more
time researching, reading, back testing and
analyzing.
If you take more trades than your strategy
dictates, that’s a warning sign.
This is often a result of boredom or lack
of discipline.
Since these trades occur outside of your trading
plan, they are less likely to perform well.
So trade what your strategy dictates.
If the market is quiet or the trade entry
conditions are not there, just wait out.
A new opportunity always comes along.
You only need a few big trades to have a green
week.
Learn to plan and structure every trade so
that you know what to do in any eventuality.
You need to make a specific plan regarding
when you’ll enter and exit a trade.
Decide which signals will be your green light
to enter.
Consider what you’ll do if a trade starts
going against you.
What’s your stop loss?
When will you get out if things don’t go
your way?
How much of your portfolio should you risk
on one trade?
What you’ll do if the market doesn’t move
and you’re stuck in the trade.
What you’ll do when you’re in profit?
You need to plan and structure every trade
so that you know what to do in any scenario.
Your trading plan should be complicated enough
to be effective, but simple enough to make
snap decisions.
If you have 20 conditions that must be met
and many are subjective, you will find it
difficult (if not impossible) to actually
make trades.
More hours does not mean more profit.
Sitting in front of a screen for many hours
can lead to diminishing returns and burnout.
Sitting in front of a computer screen all
day, watching the price action, might sound
like fun, but I have found it can also be
a detriment to my performance.
There is no another job in the world that
will take money from you by trading your time.
You can make thousands of dollars in a few
seconds.
But you can also trade for 7 hours and lose
a lot of capital.
The market doesn’t care how much time you
are trading for.
Day trading is often chaotic and full of stress.
It’s so easy to lose your ability to concentrate.
You can be highly motivated to day trade and
have a decent strategy, but if you lack concentration,
you’ll have big problems.
When day trading, it’s essential that you
learn to concentrate while executing a trade
and monitor the market action during a trade.
It’s useful to remember that concentration
takes psychological energy and your energy
has its limits.
If you want to maintain your focus, you must
be rested and relaxed.
Four hours of concentrated trading or research
is usually the limit for most people.
Don’t overdo it.
More hours does not mean more profit.
Value your time.
You don’t have to spend all day trading.
Don’t quit your job to become a full time
trader.
Don’t start with the intention of trading
for regular income.
Day trading is not something that should be
taken lightly.
It takes years of building up knowledge and
experience.
I get triggered when I see influencers on
different platforms telling people to quit
their jobs to day trade stocks or crypto,
showing off their expensive cars and luxurious
life style.
You can’t simply walk out of your day job
to start trading.
There are many traders that are successful
and have full-time jobs.
Remember, in trading, you do not have a set
salary.
The market owes you nothing, your winning
strategy might stop working in a year.
And your mistakes have big consequences in
trading.
You don’t know how much money you will make
or lose before any given trading day.
This is the most important piece of advice
I can give to 9-5 traders.
Do NOT give up your primary source of income.
In general, you don’t want to lose streams
of income.
The more streams of income you have, the more
stability you have.
Better income stability will allow you to
trade better, as you view the market with
less emotional attachment to money!
Keep your job as long as you can while you
build up your trading skill-set.
Don’t rush the process.
Don’t believe anything you read until you
have tested and tried it out for yourself.
What used to work ten years ago, on a certain
market, may not work today.
A strategy I use on the H4 time frame on Tesla
may not work for you on a 5-min chart of Bitcoin.
That’s a common mistake amongst new traders.
They don’t understand that different strategies
work on different markets.
You only find out what works for you by rigorous
testing and analysis.
Back testing is the most under-utilized weapon
in trading.
Many traders find it to be boring, difficult,
and even pointless.
But back testing allows you to witness how
your plan would have theoretically performed
had you been trading it for the past months.
With this information you can objectively
confirm whether or not your trading plan will
make you money.
Backtesting is like a mirror to reality.
You might have the best trading idea, but
if you backtest it over the past few months
and it’s not profitable, chances are this
strategy isn’t going to suddenly start working
now.
Likewise if you come up with a clever idea
that you think probably doesn’t work, you
may surprise yourself to discover through
your back testing that it in fact does work.
Of course, the past is never an indication
of the future, or at least not a consistently
reliable one.
But without back testing you are essentially
trading blind.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.