Let me ask you: do you feel overwhelmed by
the constant stress and pressure of trading?
You're not alone.
Today we'll take a deep dive into the mental
health issues faced by traders and we'll explore
the importance of prioritizing mental health
in the fast-paced world of trading.
So, like, subscribe and stick around for the
full video.
The prevalence of mental health issues among
traders
Mental health issues, including stress, anxiety,
and even depression, are very common among
traders.
The high-pressure nature of trading can take
a toll on your mental health, and you may
face significant financial and professional
risks on a daily basis.
This can lead to a range of mental health
problems, such as difficulty sleeping, anger,
and difficulty concentrating.
In severe cases, you may also suffer from
burnout, a physical and emotional exhaustion
and a lack of accomplishment.
If left unchecked, these mental health issues
can seriously impact your ability to trade
effectively and may even lead to more serious
problems.
The impact of cognitive bias in trading
A cognitive bias is a fancy word.
Think at it as a mental shortcut that your
brain takes in order to simplify processing
information.
These biases can lead to irrational decision-making,
and they can be problematic in the context
of trading, where the ability to make sound
decisions is critical.
There are many different types of cognitive
biases that can affect you, you face them
every day.
Confirmation bias is one of them.
That’s the tendency to seek out information
that confirms your preexisting beliefs.
You want to short a market, and you look for
signs that agree with our existing beliefs
and you’ll ignore information that contradicts
it.
You see this breakout, and you ignore the
other signs indicating that this might not
be the best trade.
Loss aversion bias is another one.
It refers to the tendency to prioritize avoiding
losses over maximizing gains.
It’s when you decide whether to close a
buy position you opened.
The price has been performing poorly, and
you are concerned that you could lose more
money if you leave it open.
However, you are also aware that there is
a chance that the price could bounce back
and that you could close it for a higher price
in the future.
Because of your loss aversion bias, you may
be more likely to close the trade right away
in order to avoid the possibility of further
losses, even if this means giving up the chance
to potentially make more money in the future.
I still suffer from this.
It’s one of my biggest struggles in trading.
To avoid loss aversion bias, take a long-term
perspective: rather than focusing on the potential
for short-term losses, try to consider the
potential rewards over the long term.
Also, use risk management strategies.
Implementing different strategies, with different
stop-loss orders can help to mitigate the
potential for losses and can make it easier
to manage risk.
The importance of setting boundaries and taking
breaks in trading
As a trader, it is important for you to set
boundaries and take breaks from trading in
order to maintain your mental health.
Trading is a demanding and stressful activity,
and it's easy to get caught up in the grind
without taking breaks.
However, this can lead to burnout and will
negatively impact your performance.
When I first started, I was trading 10-12
hours per day.
Even when I was watching a movie, I’d still
thinking about it.
Setting boundaries in trading is very important.
This involve setting limits on the amount
of time you spend trading and analyzing a
chart, as well as establishing clear lines
between this and your personal life.
This involves setting specific times for trading,
and, mandatory, staying aside certain hours
or days that are designated as "off limits"
for trading.
Taking breaks is also essential for maintaining
a healthy work-life balance.
By making time for yourself and your personal
life, you’ll be able to maintain a fresh
perspective to your trading and stay focused
and motivated.
Strategies for building resilience and coping
with setbacks in trading
As a trader, it is important to build resilience
and develop strategies for coping with setbacks
and losses.
Here are a few things that I try to do to
stay resilient and bounce back from losses:
First is to maintain perspective.
So you lost a trade on EUR/YEN.
It can be very easy to get caught up in the
moment and lose sight of the bigger picture
when you lose a trade.
I try to remind myself that losses are a natural
part of the trading process and that every
trade is just one small piece of the puzzle.
It's important to remember that trading is
just one part of your life and you shouldn’t
let it consume you.
It’s imperative to make time for other interests
and activities outside of the screen.
I also try to stay positive.
It's easy to get down on yourself after you
made a mistake and took a bad trade, but I
try to stay positive and focus on the things
that I did well in the process.
Seeking support is another step.
If you’re struggling to cope with a setback
in trading, maybe try to reach out to friends,
family, or other traders for support.
It can be helpful to talk with someone who
can offer a fresh perspective.
Of course, learning from your mistakes is
another step, I’ve talked about it many
times.
After a setback, try to take a step back and
analyze what went wrong.
The link between mental health and risk-taking
in trading
From my trading journey, I’ve learned that
there is a strong link between my mental health
and my risk-taking behavior.
When I am feeling anxious or stressed, I tend
to be more risk-averse and taking on too much
risk.
I might use bigger stop losses, I might double
my exposure, trying to recover some losses.
On the other hand, when I am feeling confident
and in control, I know how to manage my risk.
I have also learned that my mental state can
affect my ability to make good decisions.
When I am feeling overwhelmed or emotional,
it is harder for me to think clearly and analyze
data objectively.
This can lead to poor decisions that will
expose you to unnecessary risk.
Revenge trading is the immediate result, when
you try to "get back" at the market and try
to recover a trade that didn't go your way.
So to manage the link between mental health
and risk-taking in your trading, try to pay
attention to your emotional state.
This might involve setting time to relax and
de-stress, or avoiding making important decisions
when you’re feeling emotional.
The impact of technology and screen time on
mental health
As a trader, you spend a lot of time in front
of screens, whether you’re analyzing data,
executing trades, or tracking the markets.
This can and will have a negative impact on
your mental health.
As I said before, prolonged screen time was
my number one problem.
I used to stay in front of the screen for
hours.
The constant flow of information and the pressure
to make quick decisions was overwhelming,
and it was hard to disconnect from trading
when I was always connected.
To mitigate the negative effects of screen
time on your mental health, again, take breaks
from trading whenever possible.
Making a conscious effort to look away from
the screen and focus on something else you
enjoy.
Try to make time for activities that don't
involve screens.
My solution was to move to swing trading,
and spend less time day trading.
Nowadays, I spend 2, maximum 3 hours per day
to trade, sometimes even less.
The impact of impulsive or reckless behavior
Impulsive or reckless behavior in trading
is another cause which will affect your mental
health.
This refers to making trades without a careful
consideration of the potential risks and rewards,
or disregarding risk management strategies.
This type of behavior will lead to significant
losses and is mainly caused by your desire
for quick profits, or a lack of understanding
of the markets.
One way to avoid impulsive or reckless behavior
in trading is to develop a trading plan and
stick to it.
This plan should include a clear set of rules
for entering and exiting trades, as well as
risk management strategies such as always
using stop-loss orders.
It is also important to maintain a long-term
perspective and resist the temptation to chase
after quick profits.
So what you lost 2 trades today.
Markets will open tomorrow, and the next day,
and there are plenty of other opportunities.
Be aware of your own emotional state and recognize
when it might be affecting your decision-making.
And it is also important to continuously educate
yourself about the markets and to stay up
to date on latest events that can impact the
markets.
This will help to ensure that trading decisions
are based on a sound understanding of the
markets rather than on impulsive or reckless
behavior.
Dealing with the ups and downs of trading
and maintaining a positive attitude
It is natural to feel upset or discouraged
after a trading loss, and it’s challenging
to maintain a positive attitude in the face
of such setbacks.
I know it’s hard to be happy when you just
lost $1000 on a single trade.
But if you want to remain in the game for
the long term, it is important to try to maintain
a positive attitude and to keep things in
perspective.
Reflect on each losing trade and rather than
dwelling on the negative, try to objectively
evaluate what happened and what could have
been done differently.
Also, set small, achievable goals: Rather
than trying to double your account in one
month, try setting small, achievable goals
for yourself.
Go for a 5-10% increase.
This can help to give you a sense of control
and can increase confidence in your trading
abilities.
The impact of social isolation on mental health
in trading
Trading can be a solitary task and this can
lead to social isolation and a lack of social
support, which can have negative consequences
for our mental health.
I’m an introvert, and I don’t mind this
time alone with myself.
But prolonged trading hours can lead to feelings
of loneliness and isolation, which can lead
to other dangerous mental health problems
such as anxiety and even depression.
To mitigate the negative impact of social
isolation on mental health when trading, it
is important to make an effort to stay connected
with other traders and seek out social support.
This might involve joining a trading community
or networking group, spending time with friends
and family, or participating in activities
outside of trading.
The fine line between trading and gambling
There’s a fine line between trading and
gambling.
Both involve taking a financial risk in the
hopes of achieving a profit, but there are
some key differences between the two.
When you trade, you’re making informed decisions
based on market analysis, risk management,
and a clear strategy.
It is a form of investment that requires discipline,
skill, and knowledge.
Gambling, on the other hand, is mostly based
on chance and is not backed by any form of
analysis or strategy.
And it can be highly addictive.
When these 2 concepts are not clear, your
mental health will suffer.
You must know the difference between trading
and gambling, and it is important to be aware
of your own motivations and goals.
If you’re making informed and rational decisions
based on a clear strategy, then you’re engaging
in trading.
However, if you’re trading based on emotions
or a desire for quick profits without a clear
plan, then you crossed the line into gambling.
The danger of trading addiction
Trading addiction refers to a compulsive need
to trade, even when it is not in your best
interest.
This can be fueled by a variety of factors,
including the belief that you can get rich
quickly through trading, the thrill of the
markets, or maybe a desire to escape from
other problems.
If you’re feeling an urge to trade constantly,
if you’re neglecting other responsibilities
in order to trade, if you’re continuing
to trade even when it is causing financial
or personal problems, if you’re feeling
anxious or stressed when unable to trade,
then you may have problems with trading addiction.
These are the most dangerous problems you
could face when trading, and it is important
to seek professional help.
I had a friend that lost his house because
of this.
It’s so easy to be caught up in this spiral,
and at the same time, it’s hard to get out,
if things go out of control.
Trading is demanding and it’s very important
to be aware and recognize the warning signs.
These signs may include changes in mood, difficulty
sleeping, anxiety and difficulty concentrating.
If you are experiencing any of these symptoms,
there’s no shame in seeking some professional
help.
Trading should not take control over your
life and your mind.
If you enjoyed learning about the role of
psychology in trading, be sure to check out
our next video on improving your trading psychology.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!