This scalping signal happens three to
four times per day. All you need three
specific conditions, a zone, a line, and
a liquidity sweep move. Here's the first
one right now. Let me ask you a
question. Have you ever noticed those
levels on your chart? Price hits them
and instantly reverses. Most scalpers
call it support and resistance, but they
are missing the real story. You see,
smart money doesn't guess. They use
algorithms. These algorithms are
designed to build positions in very
specific zones, creating the supply and
demand areas you see on your chart. But
here's the part most traders will never
understand. Institutions can't just dump
millions into the market. They'd move
the price too fast and hurt their own
entry. So, what do they do? They break
their orders into tiny pieces, creating
those tight consolidation zones you see
right before a major move. Watch this.
See this tight compact area right before
the explosion? That isn't random noise.
That is a footprint. It's the signature
of smart money quietly building their
position before the next phase of their
attack. Once you learn how to read this,
you will never look at the market the
same way again. Now, most traders get
this next part wrong. They think
institutions only care about the daily
chart. Wrong. Smart money algorithms are
active on all time frames, scalping
right alongside you. They just have
bigger size and far better information.
And this brings us to the single most
important insight of this video. Retail
traders use stop- losses. Institutions
don't. They use something far more
powerful, hedging. They'll hold long and
short positions at the same time. And
when one side moves in their favor, they
have to come back to unwind the losing
hedge. This creates what we call
mitigation zones, areas where price is
almost guaranteed to return so they can
balance their books. This is why you get
stopped out. You are busy analyzing
micro patterns and lagging indicators.
Meanwhile, smart money is orchestrating
fakeouts to hunt your stop-loss before
they make their real move. You just
learned the fundamental truth of the
market. It isn't random. It's
algorithmic. And algorithms have rules.
They leave footprints. And once you know
what to look for, they become
predictable.
Let me show you how to identify the
exact zones where these algorithms
operate. Forget everything you've been
taught about support and resistance. On
the scalping time frames, we're looking
for something much more specific. I call
them footprint zones, areas where smart
money has left unmistakable evidence of
their activity. The mistake most
scalpers make is marking every level
where price bounced. Do that on a one
minute chart and you'll have 50 zones by
noon. It's useless noise that will
destroy your decision-m.
Here's what actually works. A valid
scalping zone must meet one
non-negotiable condition. It must cause
a break of structure or change of
character. This isn't some arbitrary
rule. It's the exact moment where
trapped traders realize they're wrong
and start covering their positions. Let
me break this down. In an uptrend,
you're looking for areas where price
breaks above the previous high. In a
downtrend, you need price to break below
the previous low. This structural break
is smart money signature, their way of
announcing that they've gathered enough
liquidity to push price in their
intended direction.
See how this demand zone caused an
immediate break above the previous high.
That's not retail buying. That's
algorithmic execution pushing price
through resistance.
So how do you mark these zones? First
find the explosion, the break of
structure. Then trace it back. Find the
single candle that started it all. The
last candle that moved in the opposite
direction. That is your zone. But here's
where most traders mess up the
execution. They think these zones work
forever. Wrong. On the scalping time
frames, you have a small window of
opportunity. Here's a rule that will
save you from countless bad trades.
Write this down. These zones have an
expiration date. The highest probability
setups happen when price returns within
just 2 to 4 hours. After that, the
footprint is stale. The money has moved
on. Think about it logically. Smart
money creates these zones by taking
large positions or closing existing
ones. They bring price back to these
areas because they have unfinished
business, more orders to fill or hedge
positions to mitigate. But why would
they wait days or weeks to complete
their operations? It makes no sense for
them to wait around when they have the
power to move price whenever they want.
The newest zones represent active
institutional interest. The oldest zones
represent completed operations that
smart money has moved on from. Focus
your attention on the areas where the
smart money is still active, not where
they used to be. This single insight
will improve your win rate more than any
indicator.
Now, let's add the second layer that
transforms good setups into great ones.
Pivot points. Most scalpers completely
ignore pivots, and that's a massive
mistake. These levels represent
mathematical zones where big players
expect price to react. Here's how they
use these levels. As price approaches a
pivot point, their algorithms increase
activity. If price comes from below, the
pivot acts as resistance. If price comes
from above, it acts as support. But
you're not trading the pivot alone.
You're looking for confluence with your
supply or demand zone. When a pivot
point aligns with your footprint zone,
you found a high probability scalping
setup.
Let me show you why this works. Banks
are not using secret formulas. They're
using standard pivot points and other
common levels. The difference is they
have better execution and size. When you
align your zones with their reference
points, you're essentially frontr
running their next move. That's the edge
that separates profitable scalpers from
the rest. Pay attention to this zone.
The demand area aligns perfectly with
the S1 pivot point. This isn't
coincidence. This is institutional
precision at work. The key insight is
this. Pivot points don't guarantee price
reactions, but they increase the
probability when combined with footprint
zones.
Now, we get to the part that makes or
break scalpers. Reading liquidity runs
is what separates those who consistently
profit from those who get chopped up by
market noise. Every time you place a
stop-loss, you're adding liquidity to
the market. Multiply that by thousands
of traders and you create concentrated
liquidity pools at obvious technical
levels. Smart money algorithms are
programmed to identify these pools and
run them before executing their real
moves. This is why traditional chart
patterns fail so often in scalping. The
obvious levels are traps. Here's what to
look for. Look for areas where traders
would naturally place stops above
obvious resistance, below obvious
support, beyond trend line breaks. These
are liquidity magnets. You want to see
price spike beyond an obvious level
where stops would be placed then quickly
reverse back into your zone. This spike
and reversal is the liquidity run. The
beauty of this pattern is that it traps
traders on the wrong side of the move.
If you're looking for a buy setup, you
want to see a liquidity run that traps
sellers. If you're looking for a sell
setup, you want to see a liquidity run
that traps buyers. Watch this carefully.
Price approaches our demand zone, spikes
below it to grab the stops, then
immediately reverses higher. Those
sellers who got stopped out are now
watching price rocket away from them.
Their forced buying becomes fuel for
your trade. This is optional but
powerful. Not every setup will have a
clear liquidity run. But when you can
identify one, it dramatically increases
your win rate. Think about the
psychology. You're entering exactly
where other traders were forced to exit
at a loss. Their pain becomes your gain.
This isn't cruel. It's simply how
markets work.
You now have all the pieces. The
footprint zones, the pivot point filter,
and the liquidity pattern. This is your
step-by-step process for finding trades
on the 1 minute and 5-minut charts.
First, scan for footprint zones. These
must be compact consolidation areas or
single candles that caused immediate
breaks of structure. Mark only the
freshest ones that haven't been touched
in the last 2 to 3 hours.
Second, check for pivot point
confluence. Your zone should be near a
daily pivot level. This adds
institutional confluence.
Third, identify potential liquidity
runs. Look for areas where other traders
would place obvious stops. Then wait for
price to run those levels before
returning to your zone. When all three
conditions align, you have a complete
setup. For buy setups, place your entry
at the top of the demand zone. Your stop
loss goes slightly below the zone. Your
target is the next major supply level,
recent swing high or opposing pivot
point.
For sell setups, enter at the bottom of
the supply zone. Stop loss slightly
above the zone. Target the next major
demand level, recent swing low, or
opposing pivot point. You now have the
ability to see what most sculbers miss
entirely. You can identify institutional
footprints, confirm them with pivot
confluence, and enter with the backing
of big players.
Let's walk through a complete long trade
using this system. I'm looking at the
5-minute chart of gold market during the
London session. First, I spot a demand
zone. Here's a tight candle
consolidation followed by a strong
bullish breakout that smashes through
the previous swing high. This qualifies
as a break of structure. So I mark the
last bearish candle before the surge.
Second, I check for pivot confluence.
Perfect. The demand zone sits right at
the S1 pivot point. This gives me two
layers of institutional support. Third,
I wait for the entry trigger. Price
retraces back to my zone over the next
hour. As it approaches, I see a classic
liquidity run. Price spikes below this
zone, triggering stops and reaches our
confluence zone. This is my signal. I
enter long at the top of the demand
zone. My stop loss sits just below the
zone. My target is the next resistance
level, giving me a good risk-to-reward
ratio. The trade worked exactly as
planned because I waited for all three
conditions to align.
Now, let's look at a short setup. I'm
analyzing the 3minut chart of pound
dollar during the New York session.
First, I identify a supply zone. Here's
a tight consolidation at the highs
followed by a violent breakdown that
breaks below the previous swing low.
This is a clear change of character from
bullish to bearish. Then the pivot
confluence check. The supply zone aligns
perfectly with the R1 resistance level.
Step three. As price approaches my
desired zone, I see a liquidity run.
Price spikes above the supply zone,
grabs the breakout buyer stops, then
immediately reverses lower. Those
trapped buyers are now forced to sell at
a loss. Their selling pressure becomes
fuel for my short trade. So, I enter
short at the bottom of the supply zone.
My stop-loss sits just above the zone
and my target is the next support level.
The beauty of this approach is its
consistency. You're simply identifying
where institutional money is active and
joining them.
Now, I need to show you something
crucial. Even with perfect setups, you
will have losing trades. I found what
looked like a perfect demand zone on the
2minute Euro Dollar chart. tight
consolidation, break of structure, pivot
confluence, and a liquidity run. Price
returned to the zone, and I entered
long. But price didn't hold. It sliced
through my zone like it wasn't there and
stopped me out for a 10 pip loss. This
happens, and it's normal. Here's what I
learned. The zone was created during
light volume hours. Institutional
footprints are strongest during high
volume sessions. London open, New York
open, session overlaps. These are when
smart money is most active. But here's
the more important lesson. Risk
management is everything in scalping.
You can't control when you lose. You can
only control how much you lose. My rules
are simple. Never risk more than 1% of
my account on any single scalping trade.
If I have a $10,000 account, my maximum
loss per trade is $100.
You now possess a complete scalping
system that works. You can identify
footprint zones where smart money has
left their signature. You understand how
to use pivot points as confluence
filters. You know how to wait for
liquidity sweeps that provide maximum
fuel for your trades, but more
importantly, you understand the
progression. You find the zones with
structural breaks. You add pivot
confluence for increased probability and
you wait for the liquidity pattern. The
entry decision comes down to reading
price action in real time. Look for
rejection candles, liquidity runs, or
other signs that institutional money is
defending the level. Your exit strategy
is equally important. Take profits at
logical levels. Don't get greedy. In
scalping, it's better to take consistent
small wins than to hope for home runs.
This system works because it's based on
market structure, not indicators. You're
reading the actual language of
institutional activity. And if you're
ready to fit this into a full a toz
trading system, that's what our academy
is for. Link is in the description.