The market is speaking to you through
price action, but you're not listening!
And THIS is costing you money!
So let’s change that! These
strategies will show you how to day
trade with nothing but price and volume,
using some basic smart money concepts!
BOS – CHOCH – FLIP Strategy
The first price action strategy relies on market
structure and institutional trading behavior.
This is the model we’re looking for. So
let's break down a buy signal, step by step.
The first thing to spot is a break of structure.
This happens when price moves decisively
through a previous significant low.
In the case, we see a downward trend
that breaks below a previous low.
This break of structure signals
a potential continuation in the overall trend.
It shows that sellers have overcome the previous
support and may be gaining control.
After the break of structure,
we look for a change of character. This is
when the market behavior shifts noticeably.
In our example, the price moves up strongly
after breaking the previous structure.
The change of character is critical
because it confirms that the break
of structure was just a fake-out.
It shows that there's real strength
behind the move, but on the upside!
At this point, traders who were short
start to realize they might be on
the wrong side of the market.
Then we identify the last area of
supply, before the change of character.
This area becomes significant because it's
the last place where sellers were in control,
before the buyers took over.
In the chart, this area is
marked as "a possible new demand zone".
This is a key price action concept - an
area of supply (meaning selling pressure)
has now flipped to become potential demand
(meaning buying pressure).
Big players often use these
areas to enter trades.
The final step is to wait for
a pullback to the area we’ve marked, and
then enter when we see a bullish candle
with higher volume than the previous candles.
The higher volume is our setup confirmation.
It implies that there's strong interest
from buyers at this level, increasing
the chances that the upward move will continue.
The psychology behind this is simple: the pullback
allows traders who missed the initial move to
enter. And the increase in volume on the bullish
candle suggests that institutional traders might
be entering, or adding to their positions here.
So this price action strategy is mainly
based on simple market structure movements.
It assumes that large institutional traders move
the market in ways that often trap retail traders.
The initial downtrend and break of
structure can be seen as a "stop hunt".
Large players push the price down,
triggering stop losses of buyers.
This allows them to enter long
positions at better prices.
Once they've stored their positions,
they push the price up sharply
(resulting in the change of character).
This catches many traders off guard,
especially those who just entered short
positions thinking the downtrend would continue.
The pullback to the "last supply" area
could be considered as another trap.
Many will see this as a chance to enter
short positions, thinking the uptrend was
just a temporary move. However, smart money uses
this pullback to add to their long positions.
This strategy works because it aligns
you with the movements of smart money,
and also takes advantage of market psychology.
The break of structure and change of character
creates a fear of missing out among
traders who missed the initial move.
This often leads to a strong trend,
as more and more traders pile in.
And the pullback to the "last supply" area
provides a relatively low-risk entry point.
The stop loss can be placed just below this area.
Here’s another signal.
The first step is
spotting a break of structure.
This happens when price pushes
through this previous low, signaling
a possible continuation in trend.
Next, we look for a change of character. This is
when the market really starts to show its hand.
Again, you need to understand
the psychology behind this setup.
Many traders get caught on the wrong side
when the market suddenly changes direction.
The third step is key. We mark the last
supply area before the change of character.
This area is special because it's the last place
sellers were in control, before buyers took over.
In price action terms, this area flips from
being supply, to potential demand. Potential,
because we don’t know yet. The price
might break to this zone in many cases.
That’s why the pullback to
this newly marked demand
area must fulfill the most important condition.
The entry signal comes only if we see a bullish
candle with higher volume than previous candles.
This increased volume means there’s strong
buyer interest, hinting that big
players might be getting involved.
Now let's break down the steps for a short signal.
The first aspect to spot is a break of structure,
but now we're looking for a break to the upside.
So we need to see that price moves upward,
through a previous significant high,
signaling a potential trend continuation.
It's like the market is testing the waters,
seeing if it can continue its previous direction.
This time, the break catches
buyers off guard, those who were
betting on the continuation of the uptrend.
After the break of structure, we need a change
of character, but now in a bearish direction.
This is when the market behavior shifts to
the downside, breaking a major swing low.
This price action movement confirms that
the break of structure was actually a
fake-out, a trap for buying traders.
And also shows that there's real
strength behind the downward move.
At this point, traders who were long start
to realize they’ve entered at a bad time.
And this can lead to some panic selling
as they try to exit their positions,
further fueling the downward move.
Next we identify the last area of demand,
before the change of character.
This area becomes significant
because it's the last place where buyers were
in control, before the sellers took charge.
Again, this is an important concept -
once an area of demand has been broken,
it flipped and became a potential supply
(so, a possible zone with selling pressure).
And we already know that big players often
use these areas to enter short trades.
The final step is to wait for a pullback
to supply, and then enter the short
position when we see a bearish candle with
higher volume than the previous candles.
The higher volume is your confirmation
that there's strong interest from sellers
at this level, increasing the likelihood
that the downward move will continue.
The increase in volume on the bearish candle
basically means that smart money might be
entering or adding to their short positions here.
You’ll see this pattern every day, multiple times,
on all markets, and all time frames.
The final break of structure
can be seen as a "stop hunt".
Large players push the price up, triggering
stop losses of sellers. This allows them to
enter their short positions at better prices.
Once they've absorbed all the
liquidity, they push the price down
sharply (resulting in the change of character).
As I said, this catches many traders off guard,
especially those who just entered long
positions thinking the uptrend would continue.
And the pullback to the "last demand"
area can be seen as another trap.
Many will see this as a chance to
enter long positions, thinking the
previous downward movement was just temporary.
But the smart play here is to use this pullback
to find a short signal.
Another example.
First, we're seeing a break
of structure to the upside.
We see price moving above a previous significant
high, indicating a potential continuation.
When price breaks above these levels,
it triggers a cascade of new buy orders.
At the same time, the stop
losses of sellers are hit.
And this creates liquidity for
smart money to engineer their plan.
After the break of structure, we see a
change of character in a bearish direction.
This is when the market
behavior shifts to the downside.
The price moves down strongly after
breaking the previous structure.
It confirms that there's real
strength behind the downward move.
Next you look for the last area of
demand before the change of character.
The last place where buyers were in
control before the sellers took over.
So this previous area of demand has now
flipped, and then became a potential supply.
We wait for a pullback to our new supply
zone, and then enter the short trade when
we see a bearish candle with higher
volume than the previous candles.
It’s the confirmation of strong
interest from sellers at this level.
This is a low-risk entry for a short trade.
Now, very important: when you spot a setup like
this one, consider the larger context of the
market. This setup - the break of structure,
change of character, and the flip of supply to
demand - could very well be part of a larger
uptrend, marking the end of a pullback.
Trading this setup as a continuation
of the previous trend, rather than a
reversal, is often the smarter move!
Trends tend to persist due to market momentum.
When you trade this setup with the trend,
you're aligning with the order flow.
So, at the end of a pullback, this setup is
actually a continuation trade in the direction of
the main trend. The overall trend shows where the
big money is flowing, and it's usually safer to go
with the current trend, rather than against it.
In this example, the market has been in an
uptrend for some time. We’re seeing higher
highs and higher lows. Then, we see a pullback.
This pullback might look significant on a smaller
timeframe, but in the context of the
larger trend, it's just a retracement.
Toward the end of this pullback,
we see our setup unfold:
First, the Break of Structure:
Price breaks below a previous low.
Then the Change of Character: a strong move
up. It signals that the pullback might be
over and the uptrend is ready to resume.
Then we have the flip from Supply to Demand:
The area just before the Change of
Character, which was previously supply,
now becomes potential demand. This is our
key level to watch for potential entries.
As price pulls back to this demand zone,
this is where we look for our entry,
confirmed by a bullish candle with higher volume.
So by entering here, we're not trying to
catch a reversal. Instead, we're joining a
trend that's already in place. We're essentially
betting that the larger uptrend will continue
after this retracement.
Rejection block strategy
The “rejection block” strategy is the
second price action method, capitalizing
on the behavior of large institutional traders.
So let's break down this strategy step by step.
The first key element of this method
is spotting a "2 wicks rejection."
If there are more wicks, even better.
This occurs when we see at least two
consecutive candles with long wicks
extending in the same direction.
These wicks represent failed attempts by
the market to move prices higher or lower.
In the context of a downtrend trend, we're looking
for minimum two candles with long upper wicks.
These wicks show that buyers
tried to push the price higher,
but sellers came in with enough force to reject
those moves, pushing the price back down.
The psychology behind this is simple:
These rejection wicks often form at
significant price levels where large
players have placed sell orders.
As the price moves up into this area,
it triggers these large sell orders,
causing the quick rejections we see as wicks.
The next crucial element is the presence of
high volume on the candles containing these
rejection wicks. Volume is the best indicator
to see the level of participation and
interest in a particular price move.
High volume accompanying these rejection
candles suggests that there's significant
selling pressure at this level.
It's not just a few traders
causing these rejections - there's
substantial market interest here.
So basically, high volume on rejection candles
often indicates that smart money is active.
These large players typically need high
volume to execute their large orders
without causing dramatic price spikes.
For many traders, seeing high volume can
be misleading. They might interpret it as a
sign of strength in the most recent trend,
not realizing that in this context, it's
actually showing strong selling pressure.
Once we've identified the 2 wicks
rejection and confirmed high volume,
we can define the "rejection block".
This is the price range encompassing
the wicks of these rejection candles.
The rejection block represents a zone where
selling pressure has overwhelmed buying pressure.
It's an area where the market has shown
it's not yet ready to accept higher prices.
Those who bought near the top of this range
are now potentially sitting on losses,
creating a pool of traders who may be eager
to sell if the price returns to this level.
For traders who missed the initial move down,
this rejection block becomes a potential entry
area for short trades on any future retests.
And after the initial rejection and the
subsequent move lower, we often see price
return to retest the rejection block.
This retest will invalidate or confirm
the strength of the resistance,
and potentially entering a short trade.
The retest happens for several reasons:
Traders who missed the initial move down see
this as an opportunity to enter short positions.
Some bullish traders still believe in the
uptrend, and try to buy what they see as a "dip."
Smart money often uses these retests
to add to their short positions,
or to trap more retail traders into long
positions, before pushing the price lower.
Look for signs of rejection at this level,
such as bearish candlestick patterns or
another push lower, on high volume.
Entering at this point allows you
to ride the next wave of selling pressure.
You place your stop loss above the rejection
block. This level has already shown
strong selling pressure, so a move
above it might indicate that the setup has failed.
For take profit, you can use previous areas or key
technical levels below the current price.
Let’s look at another signal.
First, we're looking for a
rejection of higher prices.
And here, the market tries to
move up but gets pushed back down,
showing potential selling pressure.
We spot several candles with long upper wicks.
These wicks show where buyers tried
to push the price up, but sellers
stepped in and pushed it back down.
This means there’s strong selling
interest at this price level.
Next, we want to see high volume
on these rejection candles. High volume means
lots of orders were placed. It's not just a
few random trades - it's a big group of
sellers saying "No" to higher prices.
When we see big volume bars with these
rejections, it adds weight to our idea
that this price level is important.
After we spot the rejection wicks
and confirm high volume, we mark the
rejection block, containing the wicks.
This rejection block will be our
key resistance level where sellers
have shown they're ready to jump in.
Now comes the waiting game. You could enter
after the rejection candles. There’s nothing wrong
with this trade, if the rejection block happens
at a resistance, or a previous supply zone.
But let’s say we missed this initial trade.
We then have to wait for the price to move away
and then come back to test this level again.
This retest is important. It shows us if
sellers still think this level matters.
While we wait, we're watching to see how
the price acts near this level. Does it
start to slow down as it approaches?
Do we see little hesitation candles?
These are signs that traders remember
this level and are getting ready to act.
When price comes back to test the rejection
block, we pay close attention. We're looking
for signs that sellers are still interested.
This might look like another rejection wick,
a series of small bearish candles,
or a sharp drop off the level.
If we have this confirmation, we short the market
when price retests the rejection block and shows
signs of respecting it.
Let’s talk a bit about
the mechanics behind the pattern
To really get this strategy, you need
to understand what's happening in the market.
First we have resistance: The rejection block
acts as a resistance level. In price action
trading, resistance is where selling pressure
overcomes buying pressure.
Then we have Market Memory:
Traders often remember important price
levels. When price returns to a level
where it previously turned around, many traders
will be watching to see if it happens again.
Then we have Order Flow: The rejection
wicks and the subsequent drop implies
that there are large sell orders placed
at this level. These orders absorb the
buying pressure and push the price back down.
And finally, there’s the Trend Continuation:
Often, these rejection blocks form during bounces
in a larger downtrend. By entering on the retest,
you're trying to catch the
next wave down in the trend.
This rejection block strategy taps
into how traders think and feel:
First, there’s the Fear of Missing Out: As
price approaches the rejection block again,
traders who missed the first drop may be eager
to enter, adding to the selling pressure.
And we have the Pain of Regret: Buyers who
got stopped out on the initial rejection
may be hesitant to buy again at this
level, reducing buying pressure.
Another trade.
We notice two candlesticks
with long upper wicks near a recent high.
These wicks stand out because they're much
longer than the wicks on nearby candles.
Then we check the volume for these candles
and see it's significantly higher than the
average volume of the past few candles.
Next, we draw our rejection block, as
price moves lower, away from this level.
As price approaches the rejection block, you
notice it starts to slow down. The candles
get smaller, showing hesitation.
Then price touches the rejection
block and immediately forms a bearish
candle with another long upper wick,
similar to the original rejection candles.
So the play here is to sell as the bearish
candle closes, placing your stop
loss just above the rejection block.
The same for a buy signal.
The first step is to spot two
or more candles with long lower wicks.
Sellers tried to push the price down,
but buyers stepped in and pushed it back up.
This action reveals strong buying interest
at this price level.
Buyers were ready and
willing to defend this price zone.
Also, we want to see high volume
on these rejection candles.
Again, when we see big volume
bars with these rejections, it adds weight to
our idea that this price level is important.
After spotting the rejection wicks and confirming
high volume, we draw the rejection block.
This area will act as a key support zone where
buyers have shown they're ready to jump in.
Then we wait for the price to move away and
then come back to test this level again.
This retest will shows us if buyers
still think this level matters.
While we wait, we're watching to see
how the market acts near this level.
Does it start to slow down as it approaches?
Do we see little hesitation candles?
These are signs that traders remember
this level and are getting ready to act.
Basically, we're looking for signs that buyers are
still interested. Maybe another rejection wick,
a series of small bullish candles,
or even a sharp bounce off the level.
If you see signs of rejection,
you enter a buy trade.
Another buy entry.
We found two candlesticks
with long lower wicks near a recent low.
These wicks stand out because they're much
longer than the wicks on nearby candles.
Then we check the volume for these candles
and see it's significantly higher than the
average volume of the past few candles.
Then we draw our horizontal lines at
the bottom and top of these wicks,
marking the rejection block.
As price approaches the
rejection block, it starts to slow down.
The candles get smaller, showing loss of momentum.
Then price touches the rejection block
and immediately forms a bullish candle.
This candle has a higher volume than
the previous candles, so once again,
this is a sign of strength.
So the play here is a long trade
as the bullish candle closes, placing your
stop loss just below the rejection block.
Now, when trading rejection blocks, you need
to know that price movements aren't always
perfect. Sometimes, the market might briefly
dip below your identified rejection block
before bouncing back up. But this doesn't
necessarily invalidate your trade setup.
Market Noise is a major factor for this.
Short-term price movements can be influenced
by big orders or algorithmic trading. These can
cause brief dips below your rejection block.
There’s also stop hunting: You know
that big players like to push the price
below obvious support levels to trigger
stop losses, before reversing the move.
A short break below a rejection block could
simply be a "shake-out of weak hands."
And sometimes, the market
needs one last push lower
to confirm that buyers are still
interested at these levels.
To deal with these situations, instead of entering
as soon as price touches the rejection block,
wait for a candle to close above it.
And keep in mind that a true breakout of
the rejection block often comes with high volume.
If you see price moving below your rejection block
but volume is low, it might be a false move.
And maybe you should check multiple timeframes:
A break on a smaller timeframe might
not mean much if the larger timeframe
still shows a strong trend in your favor.
That’s why, when you place your trade,
consider adding a buffer, below their rejection
block. Instead of placing you stops right below
the block, you might place them slightly
below, to account for these brief dips.
Now, if you’re ready for more smart
money and price action methods,
go ahead and watch one of these videos!