Renko charts can be your biggest edge in scalping
or day trading, if you know the right strategy!
Well, this trading guide rewrites the rules,
giving you the ultimate Renko strategy to
dominate any market.
Renko charts present
a distinctive way of plotting price movement.
Instead of using time-based candles, they rely
on discrete price increments, forming bricks.
This process strips away a good deal of noise,
since each Renko brick forms only after
price has moved a set amount up or down.
You will very soon find that Renko charts
highlight trends and consolidations more clearly.
To illustrate, imagine you decide
on a brick size of $1 per brick.
If the market is steadily climbing, each
time the price advances $1 beyond the most
recent completed brick, a new brick prints.
If the price fails to move in that increment,
no new brick appears.
This helps you identify
well-defined waves in the market.
On a regular candlestick chart,
each bar prints at fixed intervals (like every
five minutes), even if price is relatively flat.
With Renko charts, nothing updates unless the
market accomplishes a full brick’s worth of
movement. This means that in an extremely
thin or sideways market, you might see a
slow pace of brick formation, whereas in a highly
volatile environment, the chart can move rapidly.
Renko method accentuates straightforward
patterns like higher highs or lower lows.
A series of consecutive bricks of the same
color (and direction) clearly reveals patterns
of momentum, while color flips serve as
direct signals of a potential reversal.
Because each brick has the same size,
a cluster of bricks all pointing in the
same direction can reflect a robust trend.
Any deviation from this pattern can be a
cautionary sign that momentum is changing.
Renko’s fundamental purpose is to simplify.
Instead of drawing a candle every X minutes,
you see a brick only if price justifies it.
That can be helpful for those
who want to identify direction
quickly or who prefer mechanical systems.
Of course, some nuance remains. If brick size
is set too small, you might get a choppy chart
that prints bricks on minimal fluctuations.
If it’s set too large, you might fail to
capture subtle intraday turning points.
Thus, picking a suitable brick size is crucial.
That’s a key principle we’ll explore later.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 2 – ADVANTAGES AND LIMITATIONS
Renko charts offer several unique advantages
for reading market direction.
One of the primary benefits is
the filtering of minor market fluctuations.
A standard time-based chart often shows you
every tick or bar, leading to “noise” that can
affect your interpretation of price movement.
By contrast, Renko bricks appear only if
the market moves beyond a certain threshold,
effectively smoothing out small, random wiggles
that do not add meaningful information.
This smoothing effect can be invaluable
when attempting to see the overall trend.
For instance, if you are scanning for a consistent
uptrend, a Renko chart can reveal it through a
stacked run of green or upward-pointing bricks.
Another key advantage rests in how well Renko
illustrates clear support and resistance zones.
Because the chart does not print new bricks for
every price tick, it often forms
distinct patterns, where price has
trouble rising above or dipping below.
Suppose you see a region where multiple
bricks top out at roughly the same level,
forming an obvious horizontal boundary.
You might interpret that boundary as a robust
area of supply or resistance, where sellers have
repeatedly stopped further upside attempts.
Also, you may also see zones where several
bricks bounced near the same price,
signifying strong support or demand.
Once again, the Renko process of printing
bricks only on significant moves can make
these levels more apparent than on
a traditional candlestick chart.
However, there are limitations. One major
caution is that the “timeless” structure means
you cannot see how long a move took to develop.
Rapid fluctuations might produce multiple bricks
in a short time, while a slow, meandering market
might barely print any new bricks for hours.
Also, selecting the wrong brick
size can undermine Renko’s benefits.
If your brick size is set
too small in a choppy market,
you can get frequent flips in brick
color, generating false signals.
If your brick size is too big, important moves
may remain hidden behind the large threshold.
Thus, calibration is crucial, taking into account
average true range, typical daily price movement,
or your personal style.
For day trading and scalping,
you might might select a very small
brick size to capture intraday swings.
A swing trader looking at multi-day moves may
pick a larger brick size for a wider lens.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 3 – RENKO CHART CONSTRUCTION
To trade using Renko, you first must
understand how these charts are constructed.
By default, many charting programs let you
specify a fixed brick size.
Suppose you set 10 pips for
a currency pair or 1$ for a stock.
That means a new “up” brick draws
if the price climbs 10 pips (or $1)
above the previous brick’s high.
A “down” brick forms if it declines that
same threshold below the prior brick’s low.
Because the threshold is absolute, you ignore
time-based intervals such as 5-minute or daily
bars, focusing purely on price increments.
Most platforms automate all these mechanics,
so your main choice is the brick size.
Some traders prefer a fixed size.
For example, for a stock that
usually moves $1 to $2 intraday,
you might pick a $0.10 or $0.20 brick.
For a currency pair, you might choose 5
or 10 pips, depending on typical volatility.
Again, if you pick an excessively small setting
and the market is jumpy, you will see
bricks flipping up and down constantly,
which defeats the smoothing advantage.
If your brick size is too large,
you risk losing detail in your analysis
A widely adopted Renko approach is to use
Average True Range for determining brick size.
ATR is a measure of volatility, typically
taking an average of recent true ranges
(the difference between high and low).
By tying brick size to the
market’s current volatility,
you allow the chart to adapt dynamically.
For instance, if a currency pair becomes
more volatile, your ATR-based brick size
might increase, so it still filters out
small random movements, but captures the newly
expanded price fluctuations more systematically.
In a quiet environment, brick size shrinks so
that you do not end up with a motionless chart.
This approach can be more stable, as the
brick size adjusts to new conditions.
A purely fixed size might be workable
for day trading, but if that instrument’s
volatility changes drastically, you
might have to keep manually adjusting.
When adopting an ATR-based approach,
you also have to accept that the renko
chart might shift as ATR changes.
That is, if ATR was 10 pips for a
currency pair last week, but then rose
to 15 pips this week, your new bricks
might appear somewhat differently.
Now, you could also choose to see
the wicks on Renko charts.
Wicks appear as thin lines
above or below each brick.
These small lines might reveal
sudden pushes or quick rejections
during the formation of each brick.
Some prefer clean bricks without wicks,
because they want to remove all small noise.
Others want to see every flicker of
price, believing that wicks hold big
clues about supply or demand shifts.
A wick can mark a moment when buyers
or sellers took charge for a
short span, then lost their grip.
That is why wicks can show
dominance on a smaller time scale.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 4 – PRICE ACTION STRATEGIES
Renko charts resonate strongly with price
action traders who want to focus on raw movement.
One fundamental technique is to look for a series
of consecutive bricks of the same color,
which can signal a trending condition.
For example, if you see four or five green
bricks in a row with no interruption,
that might reflect a strong bullish push.
If you identify a well-defined uptrend, you can
look to buy on small pullbacks, anticipating
that the primary direction will continue.
Another method is identifying breakout points.
Because Renko charts clarify support and
resistance, you might mark horizontal
lines where price repeatedly failed
to surpass a certain brick level.
Suppose you spot a zone where multiple
bricks reversed to the downside around the same
price area. On a candlestick chart, that might
have been a choppy region, but on Renko, it
looks like a distinct “ceiling” of bricks.
If the price eventually breaks above
that ceiling, you interpret it as a
breakout with less noise to distract you.
Additionally, some price action traders watch
for color flips to identify potential reversals.
If you have a streak of red bricks forming a
downtrend, and then you see the creation of
a green brick that might be an early sign the
market is flipping bullish on the short term.
If you prefer more confirmation, you could
wait for two or three consecutive
bricks of the opposite color.
The beauty of Renko is that each
brick is uniform in size; thus,
a color shift literally indicates that price
has moved enough to overcome that threshold.
Another valuable dimension is
analyzing sideways conditions.
Sometimes the market stalls, creating an
alternating pattern of up and down bricks,
but staying within a certain horizontal band.
You might identify a “box” or “range” by
marking the highest up-brick and the
lowest down-brick within that region.
If the price fails to exit that box for
a while, it indicates a consolidation.
A Renko trader might either skip trading that
range if it is too narrow or might attempt to
fade each side (selling at the top of the band or
buying at the bottom), hoping the range persists.
Then, if price ultimately breaks out of that box,
you can quickly pivot into a trending strategy.
One essential concept is
the notion of pivot bricks.
You can observe that after a run of
consecutive bricks, the chart forms
a single or double brick in the opposite
color, then resumes the original direction.
That small counter move can be a
“pullback” in price action terms.
Many traders look to buy near the pivot
brick if the overall direction is bullish,
with a stop just below the last low.
This approach effectively tries to
catch the resumption of the trend
before it fully re-accelerates.
Of course, you might see a deeper
correction of multiple bricks,
indicating a stronger shift in momentum.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 5 – INCORPORATING BASIC INDICATORS
While many traders prefer a purely price action
approach, others enjoy combining Renko with one
or two basic overlays, such as moving averages.
Because Renko is a “price-distilled” chart,
certain indicators might behave differently.
For example, a 20-period moving
average on a Renko chart is not
measuring the last 20 bars in time,
but rather the last 20 bricks formed.
That means if the market was quiet and
formed few bricks, the moving average
might not update frequently; if the market was
volatile, the average shifts more rapidly.
One of the simplest uses is to add a single moving
average, say a 50-brick one, to observe whether
the price is above or below that line.
If the bricks remain stacked above the
line for multiple bricks, it
suggests a bullish environment.
If they cross decisively below the moving average,
it hints that momentum is turning bearish.
Renko makes these crossovers
potentially more significant,
because each brick must move a set distance.
On a typical chart, price might briefly poke below
a moving average, only to revert in the same bar.
On Renko, crossing that line typically means the
price overcame a threshold of movement—some
may see that as a more conclusive sign.
Additionally, some traders apply an
oscillator, like RSI on the Renko chart.
The logic is that although time is less
relevant, you can still check if the market
has momentum or not. Then you watch for a
color flip or a break of a certain pivot.
This might refine your timing.
You could, for instance, short when bricks
turn red right as RSI is below its 50-level.
Still, be aware that these indicators
might not behave the same as on time-based
charts, since they measure the last bricks.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 6 – MULTI-TIMEFRAME AND CROSS-VERIFICATION
Although Renko is distinct from time-based
charts, many traders find synergy
in analyzing multiple perspectives.
For instance, you might open a 4-hour candlestick
chart (or daily chart for bigger swings), to
identify key support or resistance
or major trends, then zoom into a
Renko chart for precise entries.
The higher timeframe guides your
direction bias—maybe you see that the
daily chart is forming higher highs,
indicating an uptrend—so you only take
“bullish” bricks on the Renko chart.
This alignment helps you avoid
fighting the bigger picture.
Some traders do the entire analysis
in Renko. You could, for instance,
use a “large brick” Renko chart to see the
bigger directional context, then switch to a
smaller-brick chart to fine-tune your entry.
On the large-brick chart, you see fewer
but bolder swings, which might counsel
that the market is overall bullish.
Then, on the smaller-brick chart, you watch for
a minor dip of 2 or 3 bricks as your entry.
Cross-verifying signals
can reduce false positives.
For example, if your big-brick Renko chart
has not reversed color but your small-brick
chart indicates a short signal, you might
pass, suspecting it is a micro pullback
that will soon revert to the major uptrend.
The same logic applies if your daily candlestick
chart shows a strong bullish technical
pattern (like a breakout of a range),
but your Renko intraday chart is unclear.
You might wait until the Renko chart
lines up with the overall bullish
story, thus confirming alignment.
━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━
CHAPTER 7 – STRATEGIES
Now let’s talk strategies. Price action
is the first method to study here.
Renko pairs well with price action
because each brick cuts out minor wicks.
You see true direction with fewer fake signals.
On renko, watch how bricks form and flip color.
A series of green bricks can mean an uptrend.
A quick shift to red bricks can
mean a short term reversal.
Look for patterns in the bricks. Sometimes
you see triple tops or double bottoms.
They form a stair-step shape on renko.
These patterns can guide you
on possible breakouts.
A triple top might show the
price failing three times at a certain level.
If you see a new brick above that level,
it might confirm an upward break.
The same logic applies
to double or triple bottoms.
Another approach is to watch pin-like bricks. On
standard candle charts, you might see a pin bar.
On renko, that becomes a sudden shift in bricks.
If you see a single brick that forms a quick
pivot, it might point to a strong bounce.
Supply and demand is next. These
zones reflect areas where buyers
or sellers took over in the past.
On a renko chart, these zones can
appear as brick clusters.
If you see a strong set of
bricks that moved up from a level, that
zone might act as a new support later.
If you see a fast drop from a high band,
that region might pose resistance.
Draw these zones on your chart. Wait for price to
approach them again. Watch how bricks react there.
If bricks stall or flip at an old
zone, that can tell you the next path.
Sometimes you see a cluster of
bricks turning red at a supply
zone. That might show renewed selling.
Price often stalls near these zones. When
renko bricks print sideways,
that can mean a base forming.
If those sideways bricks occur near a known
supply or demand band, you watch for an eventual
breakout. Some traders like to see a strong
color flip at these bands to confirm direction.
Others wait for a retest.
Moving averages can fit renko well,
as can help confirm the trend.
If bricks stay above the average,
that can show an uptrend.
If bricks stay below, it can show a downtrend.
Price action plus a moving
average can work smoothly.
Watch for bricks to align
with the average’s slope.
If the average points up and bricks
stay green, you might hold a long bias.
If the average flattens and bricks keep
flipping color, you might stay out.
Another strategy is a breakout approach.
Wait for a period of sideways bricks.
Then watch for that new brick that closes beyond
the range. If you see a multi-brick consolidation,
a breakout brick can indicate a bigger wave.
For instance, if bricks move sideways around
a specific level, then a green
brick closes above that zone,
that signals potential bullish momentum.
Confirm with your moving average
or an extra filter if you like.
That filter could be a supply zone
overhead. If you see no major supply zone
close by, the breakout might run further.
Another approach is a pullback strategy. Price
rarely runs straight up or straight down.
Even in an uptrend, there are dips. On
renko, watch for a series of green bricks.
Then watch for one or two red bricks
forming. That might be a pullback.
If you see the next green brick near a key
area, that can be your cue to go long again.
You can base that on a demand zone. Or you might
use the moving average to find a bounce area.
When you see a green brick appear again, it
might confirm that the uptrend still holds.
Supply-demand flips also shape a strategy.
Mark your supply zone overhead.
Mark your demand zone below.
If bricks reach the supply zone and flip from
green to red, that might be a short signal.
If bricks drop to a demand zone and flip from
red to green, that might be a long signal.
Some traders set an entry
one brick beyond the flip.
Others wait for two bricks to
confirm. Each approach is valid,
but test it on past charts first.
Candlestick patterns can be adapted to renko.
You do not see wicks in the same
way, but you see shifts in color.
Pay attention to quick flips. That might
mimic a bullish or bearish a pin bar.
If you see one color brick quickly
replaced by the other color brick,
with a wick, that can be a signal.
If that occurs near a supply or demand zone, it
gains weight and it may show a bigger reversal.
The length of any wick is key.
A long upper wick might reflect strong
selling pressure from a zone of resistance.
A long lower wick can hint that
buyers stepped in at a support layer.
The longer the wick, the bigger the rejection.
If you see a big wick, that can mean that price
tried to move strongly but got forced back.
That might mark a zone of heavy supply or demand.
If you see a tiny wick, that might be
a small hesitation, not a major shift.
No wicks can reflect a clean, forceful
run. Meaning strong momentum.
Many traders keep a note of
lines of support and resistance.
In a normal candlestick chart, you draw
horizontal lines at swing highs or lows.
With renko, you do the same,
but it can look steadier.
If you see repeated attempts to break a
horizontal level around the same brick level,
that forms a line. Wait for a decisive move
beyond that line to consider a trade.
Pair that with the shape of renko bricks.
Are bricks flipping color at that exact area?
That detail might confirm a
breakout or a false break.
A false break might show a single brick
that tries to push beyond the line,
but the next brick forms back in the old range.
Another strategy involves pivot points. I
personally never trade without pivot levels.
I monitor the daily or weekly pivot lines.
Then I look to see if the
bricks respect those lines.
If bricks hover near an “R1” pivot, you
might wait for a color flip for a short.
If bricks push above main pivot,
I might hold a bullish view.
Stop-loss placement can be simpler with renko. You
can place a stop a few bricks behind your entry.
If you go long on a green brick that forms
above resistance, you might tuck your stop
behind the last red brick.
Because renko bricks filter
small spikes, your stop might be tighter.
This is a technical approach, not psychological.
You can also trail your stop by a certain
number of bricks as price moves in your favor.
Some traders like to wait
for a color change to exit.
Other strategies might involve divergences.
If you use an oscillator, watch for a
discrepancy between price and your indicator.
If bricks make new highs but the indicator
does not, that can show momentum loss.
You might see a color flip soon. This is
more advanced, but it’s definitely worth it
Now, at first, practice on historical charts.
Mark each zone where price turned.
Mark each breakout. Watch how
many bricks form before a big run.
See if moving average crosses help.
Tweak your brick size if you
get too many false flips.
Check if your approach works best with
a trending pair or a more volatile one.
And always know that signals must have context.
That context is the bigger trend, the
supply-demand layout, and recent highs or lows.
Area-based strategies also fit. Mark
an area where price consolidated.
Then wait for either a breakout
or a bounce from that range.
If bricks break the top side, you might go
long. If bricks form below, you might short.
This is standard price action,
but renko can make it more direct.
Just remember you do not watch
time-based developments in the same way.
You watch price-based developments. That might
mean fewer signals, but they can be clearer.
Another variant is a reversal strategy that
seeks a color shift after a strong run.
If you see several bricks of the same
color, and then you get a shift in color,
that might point to a change.
This is riskier, because you are
going against the prior momentum.
But if it lines up with a big
supply or demand zone, it can work.
A channel approach can also work. Draw
an upward channel around renko bricks
that form higher highs and higher lows.
If price breaks below the channel
boundary with a red brick, that
might signal an end to that uptrend.
If you prefer to ride the trend,
watch the channel lines.
The moment bricks break outside, exit.
Or you could look for a brand-new
trade in the other direction.
Price patterns also matter. Head-and-shoulders,
or double tops or bottoms are easier
to spot on a renko chart,
Such pattern can signal a turn.
Look for a neckline. If a new brick closes beyond
the neckline, that can confirm the pattern.
Price patterns on renko reduce choppiness.
Now, if you're curious about mastering more
trading techniques, go ahead and
watch one of these videos next!