Let me tell you a secret: the success rate
of harmonic patterns is actually higher compared
to the other classic price patterns, like
triangles, wedges or flags.
And not many traders use them, despite the
fact they provide very precise conditions
for entering, and offer a high reward to risk
ratio when traded properly.
Today we’ll highlight one of the best harmonic
patterns – the Gartley formation.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel,
and stick around for the full video.
What is the Gartley pattern?
The Gartley pattern resembles an M/W shape
on the chart, depending on whether it is a
bullish or a bearish Gartley and consists
of five points on the chart.
These points are marked with X, A, B, C, and
D.
Gartley is a retracement and continuation
pattern at the same time, depending on its
location in a trend, that is formed when a
trend temporarily changes direction before
continuing in its original direction.
And it provides a low-risk opportunity for
traders to enter the market where the pattern
finishes and the trend comes back.
How to identify the Gartley pattern?
The Gartley pattern depends on several movements
in price.
Every swing has to confirm certain Fibonacci
levels.
To make it very simple, let’s look at each
component of the Gartley structure.
X to A swing
The movement begins with X to A and there
are no specifics for this leg.
This first leg gets formed when the price
sharply rises or declines from point X to
point A.
This is the longest leg of the pattern.
A to B swing
This is where Fibonacci becomes relevant to
the pattern.
The A-B leg will not retrace pass point X
– if it does, the pattern is considered
invalid.
The AB swing should be approximately 61.8%
of the XA leg.
B to C swing
This movement should be a retracement of 38.2%
or 88.6% of the movement of A to B. If the
B to C move retraces above point A, the Gartley
pattern is invalid.
C to D swing
This should be an extension of the B to C
leg.
If BC is 38.2% of AB, then CD should respond
to the 127.2% extension of BC.
If BC is 88.6% of AB, then CD leg should be
the 161.8% extension of BC swing.
A to D swing
After the completion of C-D, you measure the
overall movement of A to D. It should be a
78.6 percent retracement of the change in
price of X to A.
I know it might seem complicated at first,
but if you use Tradingview, you can use this
tool and you can start drawing the pattern.
You just need 4 price swings.
Just place the tools at the extreme of the
swings and start backtesting.
Ideal Gartley
The ideal Gartley will be defined by specific
Fibonacci retracements.
One of the most important numbers in the pattern
is the completion of point D at the 0.786
of XA.
Although the price action might exceed this
number slightly, it should not exceed point
X.
Another important point in the pattern is
the 0.618 retracement of the XA leg.
The AB leg should reverse very close to this
retracement.
The .618 retracement at point B is critical
because it will establish another Fibonacci
projection - usually a 1.27 of BC - in the
Potential Reversal Zone at point D.
The best part about Gartley patterns is that
they indicate both the timing and magnitude
of price movements.
Bullish Gartley Pattern
The Bullish Gartley starts with a bullish
XA move.
AB is then bearish.
BC is bullish, and CD is bearish again.
And you expect a reversal of the CD move.
This means that a bullish Gartley implies
a price increase from Point D.
The full target of the pattern is the 161.8%
Fibonacci extension of the AD move, which
resembles the AB=CD harmonic pattern upon
completion.
And, we have three intermediary targets before
that.
Target 1: B Swing
Target 2: C Swing
Target 3: A Swing
Bearish Gartley Pattern
The bearish Gartley has a bearish XA move,
a bullish AB move, a bearish BC move, and
a bullish CD move.
A bearish Gartley implies a price decrease
from Point D.
The expected price target of the bearish pattern
is the 161.8% extension of the AD move, with
the intermediary targets at swings B, C and
A.
How To Trade Gartley Harmonic Pattern
To enter a Gartley trade you should first
take note of the pattern and then confirm
if it is valid or not.
First, you outline the four price swings on
the chart and you make sure they respond to
their respective Fibonacci levels.
You mark every price action swing with the
important letters X, A, B, C, and D.
By doing this, you will be able to estimate
the overall size of the pattern and get a
clear idea about the parameters.
If you have a bullish Gartley for example,
you open a long trade if CD leg founds support
at 127.2 percent or 161.8 percent Fibonacci
level of the BC move.
You should always use a stop loss order regardless
of your preferred entry signal, to protect
yourself from any rapid or unexpected price
move.
The stop loss order of a bullish Gartley trade
should be found below the X point of the chart
pattern.
For a bearish Gartley, your stop loss order
should be found above the pattern’s X point.
As for take profits, you enter a position
after the bounce at point D and then scale
out at different levels.
Target 1: B Swing
Target 2: C Swing
Target 3: A Swing
Target 4: 161.8% of AD
These four levels on the chart are the four
minimum targets of the bullish Gartley.
That doesn’t mean that the bullish trend
will end when the price completes point E.
You are always free to use additional price
action rules or a trailing stop to exit your
trade.
If the price momentum continues to show signs
of strength, you can keep a small portion
of the trade open.
Use price action clues such as trend lines,
support and resistant techniques, candle patterns
and volume to find the right entry and exit
point.
And generally, if the price action shows no
signs of interrupting the new trend, just
stay in the trade for as long as you can.
Gartley after a Strong Price Move
This pattern is even more significant, if
it is preceded by a major price move.
Often, after a major price move, the Gartley
will begin with a strong counter move, which
becomes the X to A leg.
The price will appear to be consolidating,
attempting to stabilize before making another
strong move.
If a Gartley forms after such price action,
from my backtesting, this pattern will prove
to be a substantial opportunity.
In addition, the stop loss required in the
trade will be relatively small relative to
the potential reversal.
The primary reason for this powerful opportunity
is that a successful reversal will resume
the trend that was established by the initial
XA price move.
The Bullish Gartley after a strong sell-off
is a difficult opportunity to perceive.
When the price forms this pattern, it might
seem as if the market is making lower highs,
especially since point C is below point A
after the initial bounce.
However, the pattern is indicating a potential
buy at the Potential Reversal Zone.
The beauty of this set-up is that it requires
a very small amount of risk to see if the
trade will work out.
Since this is an unusually good set-up, the
potential profit is very large in comparison
to the amount needed to be risked.
The stop loss should be placed, of course,
just below X point.
This is a great example of a Gartley after
a severe decline.
The Potential Reversal Zone was very clear.
It had three harmonic numbers within a very
narrow range.
AB is 61.8% of XA, BC is 88.6% of AB, CD is
the 161.8% extension of BC.
At the same time, AD is 78.6% of XA.
Since this is a bullish Gartley setup, the
expected price move is to the upside.
For this reason, you would prepare to buy
when CD finishes at the 161.8% of BC and the
price action bounces upwards.
The stop loss would have been placed just
under X point.
You can see that this situation required only
a small stop to risk in exchange for a bigger
gain.
The first target of this long trade is located
at the level of point B.
The second target is at point C and it also
gets accomplished.
The price action also reaches the level of
point A, which is the next target on the chart.
And our last target, located at the 161.8%
Fibonacci extension of the AD price move.
Bearish Gartley after a Strong Rally
A Bearish Gartley after a strong rally is
a very powerful reversal signal, as well.
Essentially, a market that can’t rally to
new highs after a considerable move usually
indicates serious weakness.
In this example, the pattern forms after a
strong rally.
In this set-up, point X is usually an important
high for the price.
The figure starts with a bearish XA move.
AB is then bullish and BC is bearish.
CD then reverses the bearish BC move.
The pattern should complete in an area where
several harmonic projections converge.
AB takes 61.8% of XA.
BC is the 88.6% level of AB.
CD reaches the 161.8% extension of BC.
When the CD move is finished and the price
creates a bearish bounce from the 161.8% extension
of BC, we confirm that the bearish Gartley
is valid.
So a good sell zone is here, placing a stop
loss order above the swing at point X.
The first target at point B gets completed
rapidly.
The next targets located at point C and A,
also reached.
And the final target, located at the 161.8%
extension of the AD move.
The Gartley is a great pattern that occurs
frequently on all time frames, in all types
of markets and is 100% price action based.
The thing that works about Harmonic Patterns
in general is that they use the confluence
method, meaning that they expect reactions
from clusters of certain levels defined by
Fibonacci retracements.
They work because Fibonacci retracements are
used by many traders and their visibility
makes reactions more likely, thus increasing
the predictive power of the patterns.
If you are interested in seeing more harmonic
patterns and price action videos, leave us
a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.