Hello and welcome.
Today we'll look at Wyckoff method, we’ll
analyze the events in accumulation and distribution
phases and we'll cover the main guidelines
for finding the best trades, with excellent
risk to reward ratios.
So if you could… like, subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full video.
Ranges that are formed at the end of a previous
trend bring a balance in supply and demand
of the market.
In such ranges, neither buying nor selling
activity will be large enough to create significant
movement towards upside or downside.
Accumulation is nothing but a sideways market
activity that happens after an extended downtrend.
This is the phase where smart money try to
acquire positions without moving the prices
too much to the upside.
Distribution is a range bound market activity
that happens after an extended Uptrend.
This is the phase where smart money try to
sell off their positions without moving the
prices too much to the downside.
You may want to watch this video first if
you want to know the basics of Wyckoff trading.
Now, Richard Wyckoff offered detailed guidelines
for spotting Accumulation and Distribution
phases based on certain patterns that take
place within them.
I’ll try to keep it very simple and explain
each phase.
First, let’s analysis Wyckoff events during
accumulation.
PS—preliminary support, this is where substantial
buying begins to provide pronounced support
after a prolonged down-move.
Volume increases and price spread widens,
signaling that the down-move may be approaching
its end.
SC—selling climax is the point at which
widening spread and selling pressure usually
climaxes and heavy or panic selling by the
public is being absorbed by smart money at
or near a bottom.
Often price will close well off the low in
a selling climax, reflecting the buying from
smart money.
AR—automatic rally occurs because intense
selling pressure has greatly diminished.
A wave of buying easily pushes prices up.
The high of this rally will help define the
upper boundary of an accumulation trading
range.
ST—secondary test, in which price revisits
the area of the selling climax to test the
supply/demand balance at these levels.
If a bottom is to be confirmed, volume and
price spread should be significantly diminished
as the market approaches support in the area
of the selling climax.
It is common to have multiple secondary tests
after a selling climax.
SOS—sign of strength, which is a price advance
on increasing spread and relatively higher
volume.
Often a sign of strength takes place after
a spring.
A Wyckoff spring occurs when price falls below
its trading range, and makes a new “panic
low” — and then “springs” back into
its previous range.
LPS—last point of support, the low point
of a reaction or pullback after a sign of
strength.
The last point of support is the final drive
toward the bottom of the Accumulation area
before the uptrend begins.
A last point of support makes a higher low
and then turns upward.
BU—”back-up”.
A back-up is a common structural element preceding
a more substantial price mark-up, and can
take on a variety of forms, including a simple
pullback or a new trading range at a higher
level.
Now let’s analyze Wyckoff phases during
accumulation.
Phase A
Up to this point, supply has been dominant.
The decrease of supply is evidenced in preliminary
support (ps) and a selling climax (sc).
These events are often very obvious on charts,
with widening spread and heavy volume.
Once these intense selling pressures have
been relieved, an automatic rally (ar) typically
occurs.
A successful secondary test (st) in the area
of the selling climax will show less selling
than previously and a narrowing of spread
and decreased volume, generally stopping at
or above the same price level as the selling
climax.
If the secondary test goes lower than that
of the selling climax, you can anticipate
either new lows or prolonged consolidation.
The lows of the selling climax and the secondary
test and the high of the automatic rally set
the boundaries of the trading range.
Sometimes the trend may end less dramatically,
without climactic price and volume action.
In general, however, it is preferable to see
the preliminary support, selling climax, automatic
rally and secondary test, as these provide
not only a more distinct landscape but a clear
indication that smart money have definitively
initiated accumulation.
Phase B
In phase B, smart money are accumulating at
relatively low-price in anticipation of the
next markup.
There are usually multiple secondary tests
during phase B, as well as upthrust actions
at the upper end of the trading range.
In phase b, the price swings tend to be wide,
with high volume.
As professionals absorb the supply, however,
the volume on downswings within the trading
range tends to diminish.
Phase C
In phase C, price goes through a decisive
test of the remaining supply, allowing the
“smart money” to ascertain whether the
price is ready to be marked up.
As I said earlier, a spring is a price move
below the support level of the trading range
(established in phases a and b) that quickly
reverses and moves back into the trading range.
It’s an example of a bear trap because the
drop below support appears to signal resumption
of the downtrend.
In reality, though, this marks the beginning
of a new uptrend, trapping the late sellers.
In Wyckoff's method, a successful test of
supply represented by a spring (or a shakeout)
provides a high-probability trading opportunity.
The appearance of a sign of strength shortly
after a spring or shakeout validates the analysis.
Please note that the testing of supply can
occur higher up in the trading range without
a spring or shakeout.
Phase D
If we are correct in our analysis, what should
follow is the consistent dominance of demand
over supply.
This is evidenced by a pattern of advances
(sign of strength) on widening price spreads
and increasing volume, as well as a last point
of support on smaller spreads and diminished
volumes.
During phase D, the price will move at least
to the top of the trading range.
Last point of support in this phase are generally
excellent places to initiate or add to long
positions.
Phase E:
In phase E, the price leaves the trading range,
demand is in full control and the markup is
obvious to everyone.
New trading ranges can occur, this concept
is also known as “re-accumulation” by
smart money.
These trading ranges are sometimes called
“stepping stones” on the way to even higher
price targets.
Now let’s showcase Wyckoff events for distribution
PSY—preliminary supply, where smart money
begin to unload shares after a pronounced
up-move.
Volume expands and price spread widens, signaling
that a change in trend may be approaching.
BC—buying climax, during which you’ll
see increases in volume and price spread.
The force of buying reaches a climax, with
heavy or urgent buying by the public being
filled by smart money at prices near a top.
A buying climax often coincides with a great
earnings report or other good news, since
smart money require huge demand from the public
to sell their shares without lowering the
price.
AR—automatic reaction.
With intense buying substantially diminished
after the buying climax and heavy supply continuing,
an automatic reaction takes place.
The low of this selloff helps define the lower
boundary of the distribution trading range.
ST—secondary test, in which price revisits
the area of the buying climax to test the
demand/supply balance at these price levels.
For a top to be confirmed, supply must outweigh
demand; volume and spread should thus decrease
as price approaches the resistance area of
the buying climax.
A secondary test may take the form of an upthrust
(ut), in which price moves above the resistance
represented by the buying climax and possibly
other secondary tests before quickly reversing
to close below resistance.
After an upthrust, price often tests the lower
boundary of the trading range.
SOW—sign of weakness, observable as a down-move
to (or slightly past) the lower boundary of
the trading range, usually occurring on increased
spread and volume.
The automatic reaction and the initial sign
of weakness indicate a change of character
in the price action: supply is now dominant.
LPSY—last point of supply.
After testing support on a sign of weakness,
a rally on narrow spread shows that the market
is having considerable difficulty advancing.
This inability to rally may be due to weak
demand, substantial supply or both.
Last point of supply represent exhaustion
of demand and the last waves of smart money
distribution before the markdown begins.
UTAD—upthrust after distribution occurs
in the latter stages of the trading range
and provides a definitive test of new demand
after a breakout above trading range resistance.
An upthrust after distribution is not a required
structural element.
And here are Wyckoff phases during distribution
Phase A:
Phase A in a distribution trading range marks
the stopping of the prior uptrend.
Up to this point, demand has been dominant
and the first significant evidence of supply
entering the market is provided by preliminary
supply (psy) and the buying climax (bc).
These events are usually followed by an automatic
reaction (ar) and a secondary test (st) of
the buying climax, often with diminished volume.
However, the uptrend may also terminate without
climactic action, instead demonstrating exhaustion
of demand with decreasing spread and volume.
Phase B:
During this time, smart money review their
portfolios and initiate short positions in
anticipation of the next markdown.
This process leaves clues that the supply/demand
balance has tilted toward, supply instead
of demand.
For instance, sign of weakness are usually
followed by significantly increased spread
and volume to the downside.
Phase C:
This is the most interesting phase of distribution.
That is the time when many retail traders
go long, during one of the most popular traps.
In other words, phase C is the phase of misleading
retail traders.
Aggressive traders open shorts after upthrust,
as they have a very good risk/reward ratio.
But big players are not ready to allow retailers
to make money so easily.
That is the reason why very often you can
see a few upthrusts one after the other.
Basically… stop hunting in action.
Conservative traders wait to open shorts until
phase D, at last point of supply.
Phase D:
Phase D shows us the last signs of demand.
Price goes to or through trading range support.
The evidence that supply is clearly dominant
increases either with a clear break of support
or with a decline below the mid-point of the
trading range after an upthrust or upthrust
after distribution.
The best trading strategy in phase D is to
go short at last point of supply.
Phase E:
In phase E of Wyckoff distribution price leaves
the trading range and supply is in control.
Once trading range support is broken on a
major sign of weakness, this breakdown is
often tested with a rally that fails at or
near support.
This also represents a high-probability opportunity
to initiate short positions.
After a significant down-move, climactic action
may signal the beginning of a re-distribution
trading range or of new phase of accumulation.
If you’re learned something new and want
more Wyckoff videos, please hit the like button,
since it really helps us out, and subscribe,
to stay up to date with our latest releases.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.