This is one of the most important trading
videos you’ll ever watch: a smart money
trading course, with lots of strategies and
tactics to align yourself with the big players
in the market.
This is game changing!
Like, subscribe, and let’s get started!
1.
The Law of Supply and Demand
Any chart is a sequence of supply and demand
zones.
If you’re a beginner, I bet that trading
using classic support and resistance levels.
And there’s nothing wrong with that.
But I advise you to forget about them for
a second, and focus on supply and demand.
If you want to become a smart money trader,
you first need to learn the law of supply
and demand.
According to Wyckoff theory, supply and demand
determines the price direction.
• If demand is greater than supply, the
price will rise.
• If supply is greater than demand, the
price will go down.
• If supply and demand are in balance, there’s
no significant price change.
This is one of the most basic principles of
financial markets.
Now, in any market, there are 2 types of participants:
aggressive and passive.
Aggressive traders are the ones that use “at
market” orders.
They have urgency to enter and attack the
best price possible.
This type of aggressive orders represent the
real engine of the market since they are the
ones that initiate the transactions.
Passive traders are the ones that use limit
orders.
This is important, because the interaction
between aggressive buyers, aggressive sellers,
passive buyers and passive sellers is what
moves the price.
The main point is: an aggressive participation
of traders will produce a change in price.
Passive orders have the ability to stop a
move, but not the ability to make the price
move.
For the price to move upwards, buyers have
to buy all the supply orders that are available
at that price level and also continue to buy
aggressively to force the price up, to find
new sellers to trade with.
Passive buy orders cause the downward movement
to slow down, but by themselves cannot drive
the price up.
For the price to move downward, sellers have
to acquire all the demand orders that are
available at that price level and continue
to push downward, forcing the price to go
in search of buyers at lower levels.
Passive sell orders cause the upward movement
to slow down, but do not have the ability
to drive the price down on their own.
The price needs aggressiveness to move, but
it’s important to take into account also
that the lack of interest from the opposite
side.
An absence of supply can facilitate the price
rise, just as an absence of demand can facilitate
its fall.
In a rising market, as long as the buying
initiative is able to consume all the liquidity
(supply) found at higher levels, the price
will continue to rise.
On the other hand, in bear markets, as long
as the selling initiative is able to consume
all the liquidity (demand) found at lower
levels, the price will continue to fall.
At the moment of a market turn, we will normally
always have a three-step process:
1.
Exhaustion
2.
Absorption
3.
Initiative
During an uptrend, in the exhaustion phase,
there’s a lack of interest of the buyers
to continue buying.
During absorption phase, you’ll see more
and more sell orders placed by the smart money.
During absorption phase there are many passive
sellers.
The initiative phase is characterized by aggressive
selling.
More and more aggressive sellers are entering
the market.
During a downtrend, in the exhaustion phase,
there’s a lack of interest from the sellers
to continue selling.
During absorption phase, you’ll see more
and more buy orders placed by the smart money.
During absorption phase there are many passive
buyers.
The initiative phase is characterized by aggressive
buying.
More and more aggressive buyers are entering
the market.
And these interactions between aggressive
and passive buyers and sellers creates supply
and demand zones on a chart.
2.
Supply and demand trading
So, if you are a trader who wants to improve
your trading performance and trade along with
the big players, the first step is to implement
supply and demand concepts into your trading
strategy.
We already established that the market is
driven by the actions of smart money.
By identifying the areas where smart money
has placed their orders, you can trade along
with them and benefit from their influence.
A supply zone is where smart money has sold
at high prices, creating a bearish pressure
that pushes the price down.
A demand zone is where smart money has bought
at low prices, creating a bullish pressure
that pushes the price up.
These zones act as potential turning points
in the market, as smart money often leaves
pending orders at these levels to fill their
remaining positions.
So, in theory, if prices revisit these supply
and demand zones, it is highly probable that
they will be rejected.
To determine the optimal supply and demand
zones, first you need to search for sharp
price increases or decreases, which indicate
the involvement of smart money in the market.
These movements are referred to as market
imbalances, significant price shifts in one
direction.
To identify demand zones, look for fast impulse
moves, keeping a close watch on big green
candles.
These candles should have long bodies and
minimal wicks.
Once an impulse move is identified, you need
to locate the base of the zone.
To do so, place a line at the high price of
the most recent red candle preceding the impulse
move and another line at the most recent swing
low around the move.
To find supply zones, look for fast declines
and red candles with extended bodies and minimal
wicks.
Then find the most recent up candle before
the sharp down move and place a line at its
low price, along with another line at the
most recent swing high formed at around the
move.
In theory, the price is likely to reverse
once it returns to these supply and demand
zones.
But to effectively trade these zones, it is
important to understand the two key rules
to identify the right zones on the chart.
The first rule is to trade only fresh and
untouched zones because supply and demand
zones are one-time use.
Once price hits a zone and reverses, the zone
loses its power, and the probability of it
causing another reversal in the future is
lower.
The second rule is that recent zones are more
important than older ones.
Supply and demand areas that have been created
recently are far more effective than those
that were created a long time ago.
There are four distinct types of supply and
demand zones based on how the price approached
and left the zone.
These four types can be categorized into two
groups: continuation structures and reversal
structures.
First continuation pattern is the Rally-base-Rally,
which forms a demand zone during an uptrend.
The market structure begins with a rally,
followed by consolidation, and ends with another
rally, which creates the demand zone.
The second continuation pattern is the Drop-base-Drop
structure, which forms a supply zone during
a downtrend.
The market structure begins with a price decrease,
followed by consolidation, and ends with another
price decrease, which creates a supply zone.
In both cases, if the market returns to these
zones, the price is expected to move in the
direction that created the zone.
The Drop-base-Rally is the first reversal
structure, which forms a demand zone in the
market.
This zone is located where the market changes
from moving down to moving up.
The second reversal structure is the Rally-base-Drop
pattern.
This forms a supply zone when the market reverses
from moving higher to moving lower.
Again, if the market returns to these zones,
the price is expected to move in the direction
that created the zone.
The main advantage of supply and demand trading
is that it helps you to understand the market
structure and market dynamics much better.
This is the first component in your smart
money plan.
3.
The Law of Effort and Result
The Law of Effort vs. Result is another fundamental
principle of Wyckoff Theory and one of the
most important concept to follow the smart
money on any market.
This concept states that the effort made by
aggressive and passive buyers and sellers
will be reflected in the price movement of
any market.
The principle is based on the idea that the
market is a battle between buyers and sellers,
and the direction of the market is determined
by the side with the greatest effort, which
is represented by volume.
High volume indicates strong market participation,
while low volume indicates weak market participation.
Volume is very important because it provides
insight into market sentiment and future price
movements.
And it’s not difficult to understand once
you learn the basic principles of supply and
demand.
This simply requires you to relate the volume
with price action.
4.
Volume Spread Analysis trading
If you want to identify the signs of market
manipulation and follow the smart money's
footsteps, you need to learn Volume Spread
Analysis.
This is a game changer, and can give you an
edge over other traders who only look at price
action or indicators.
VSA can reveal when smart money is accumulating
or distributing an asset, when they are testing
supply or demand, and when they are ready
to start a new trend or reverse an existing
one.
Volume Spread Analysis (VSA) is based on the
premise that volume is the fuel that drives
price movements.
Volume is the amount of trading activity in
a given period, while spread (or range) represents
the difference between the open and close
prices of a candlestick.
By analyzing the relationship between volume
and spread, VSA can reveal the supply and
demand dynamics in the market.
It’s a lot to talk about, but the key concept
of VSA is that when volume and spread are
in harmony, it means that there is a balance
between buyers and sellers, and the market
is likely to continue in its current direction.
However, when volume and spread are in disharmony,
it means that there is an imbalance between
buyers and sellers, and the market is likely
to reverse or consolidate.
So, when price and volume are moving in the
same direction, it is a sign that the price
move is strong and is likely to continue.
For example, if a market is in an uptrend
and there is a significant increase in volume,
it is a sign that the uptrend is likely to
continue.
Divergences between price and volume occur
when there is a disagreement between the price
action and the volume of that market.
This can indicate that the price move is not
supported by market participation and may
not be sustainable.
For example, if a market is in an uptrend,
but the volume is decreasing, it is a sign
that the uptrend may not continue.
So, VSA is the second component of our smart
money trading plan.
5.
The Law of Cause and Effect
Another important smart money concept states
that the differences between supply and demand
are not random.
Instead, they come after periods of preparation,
as a result of specific events.
This is the law of cause and effect.
For the market to develop an effect (trend),
first there must be a cause (namely, accumulation/distribution).
Basically, this law states that every price
move has a cause.
Changes cannot happen out of nowhere and a
cause must be established first.
This starts during periods of sideways movement
or when the market is ranging.
This can be seen in charts when we have small
ranges or low volatility periods.
The longer this process continues, the larger
the expected resulting move.
So after a period of consolidation, there
is an expansion or explosive move in price.
In Wyckoff's terms, a period of accumulation
(cause) eventually leads to an uptrend (effect).
In contrast, a period of distribution (cause)
eventually results in a downtrend (effect).
6.
The Composite Man
When I started to study Wyckoff, my first
aha moment was when I was reading about the
Composite man.
Wyckoff created the idea of the Composite
Man as an imaginary identity of the market.
This single entity is responsible for controlling
the market.
And it always acts in his own best interest
to ensure he can buy low and sell high.
Think of composite man as an evil entity,
controlling markets by pushing buttons.
His single objective is to move the markets
to your disadvantage, seeking to maximize
his profit at “your” expense.
And he plans and executes his deceptions well
in advance.
He’s basically there to fool you to buying
positions that he has already accumulated.
He will tempt you to buy and sell at the worst
possible time.
And it makes a lot of sense.
Have you ever had the feeling that someone
is watching your positions?
That you entered the market, and immediately
price went against you?
Or the market is quiet, with low activity,
and as soon as you enter, the price starts
jumping up and down?
It’s like someone is driving prices, playing
with your emotions.
In essence, the Composite Man represents the
biggest players (so-called smart money).
It always acts in its interest to ensure that
it can buy at a discount and sell at a premium.
The Composite Man’s behavior is the opposite
of retail traders, and in order to adapt to
changing market conditions, we, retail traders,
must learn from his behavior.
If you don’t understand the game as he plays
it, you’ll take the wrong side of the trade
and you’ll sit in front if your screen,
desperate that the market moves once again,
against your position.
In order to understand the behavior of the
Composite man, you need to understand the
concept of liquidity.
7.
Liquidity clear-outs
In the world of smart money, it's important
to question the liquidity of the market you're
trading.
Whether you're trading the EUR/USD or Bitcoin
or Amazon, liquidity plays a crucial role
in a market's functionality.
In fact, an ample participation from buyers
and sellers is necessary for a market to be
considered rich in liquidity.
This is why market makers and smart money
often engage in liquidity hunting or liquidity
clear-outs, which involves extracting liquidity
from the market by flushing out weak players.
A Liquidity clear-out is when the price will
move just above or below an area where stop
loss orders of retail traders are placed,
executing those orders and reversing.
The goal of this strategy is to take advantage
of the liquidity that is provided by the stop-loss
orders of other traders.
Liquidity hunting works by identifying areas
of high concentration of stop-loss orders
in the market.
These areas are usually near support and resistance
levels, where many traders place their stops
to protect their positions.
Smart money, or the Composite man, will then
push the price towards these levels, triggering
the stop-loss orders and creating a spike
in volume and volatility.
This spike can also cause other traders to
panic and join the move, creating a double
trap.
Once the liquidity hunters have filled their
orders at favorable prices, they will quickly
reverse their positions and drive the price
back to its original range.
This can leave many traders with losses or
missed opportunities, while the Composite
Man profits from the price swing.
This is one of the main strategies used by
smart money to make money.
Liquidity is the third component in our smart
money trading plan.
8.
How to Think Like Smart Money
If you are a retail trader who wants to succeed
in the market, you need to learn how to think
like a smart money trader.
Imagine you don’t have a 5.000 dollars account.
You have a 1 billion dollar account.
You have the power to influence price movements
and develop trends on the market.
You have access to more information, more
resources, and more capital than 99% of retail
traders, and you need to use various tactics
to deceive and manipulate other traders to
your advantage.
How would you do it?
You wouldn’t trade like most retail traders.
You’re in the business of making money,
so you need many tactics to create false signals,
traps, and illusions in the market.
Here’s the reality.
Smart money are not necessarily smarter than
retail traders.
They are simply more experienced, disciplined,
and strategic.
They have a clear understanding of how the
market works, how other traders behave, and
how they can exploit their emotions and biases.
They do not trade based on predictions, opinions,
or hopes.
They trade based on probabilities, facts,
and evidence.
Smart money does not care about being right
or wrong.
They care about making money.
They are flexible and adaptable to changing
market conditions.
They do not chase after trades or revenge
trade.
They wait patiently for high-probability opportunities
and execute them with precision.
Smart money does not follow the crowd.
They lead the crowd.
They do not rely on lagging indicators, news,
or tips from others.
They do not trade what they see or hear.
They trade what they know and understand.
They do not react to the market.
They anticipate the market.
9.
The Tactics Used By Smart Money
Smart money knows that the market is a game
of psychology and deception.
They know that most retail traders are driven
by fear and greed, and they use these emotions
against them.
They use various tactics to create false signals,
traps, and illusions in the market that lure
retail traders into making bad trades or missing
out on good ones.
You already know their tactics very well,
you were the victim of those tactics on many
occasions:
- Stop hunting is the most obvious strategy:
This is when smart money pushes the price
to a level where they know many retail traders
have placed their stop losses or take profits.
This triggers a cascade of orders that either
liquidates their positions or fills their
orders at unfavorable prices.
This allows smart money to either exit their
positions with a profit or enter new positions
with a better price.
- Fakeouts are another tactic: This is when
smart money creates a false breakout of a
support or resistance level that attracts
many retail traders to enter in the direction
of the breakout.
However, after a few candles, the price reverses
sharply in the opposite direction, trapping
those traders in losing trades.
- Whipsaws are another smart money tactic:
This is when smart money creates a lot of
volatility and noise in the market that confuses
many retail traders and makes them second-guess
their trades.
The price moves up and down rapidly without
any clear direction or trend, causing many
traders to exit their trades prematurely or
switch sides frequently.
The reality is that many retail traders will
use the same price levels to place their entries
or stop losses.
And these are the perfect zones for smart
money to trigger one of their traps.
You might ask: why is this difference between
us, retail traders, and smart money?
Because they don’t trade like us, using
technical analysis, indicators or chart patterns.
Institutional players cannot trade the same
as the retail trader, because in low liquidity
price areas, they will push price far away
with large orders.
So they must use high liquidity zones to put
their own large orders in the market without
having too much impact on the price.
10.
Smart money traps - Fake breakout at the high/low
of the day
Now let’s go even deeper and let’s discuss
about the most common smart money traps.
If you are a day trader, you have probably
experienced the frustration of being stopped
out of a trade by a sudden spike in price
at the high or low of the day.
This practice is one of the most common ways
that smart money manipulates the market to
trap retail traders.
These are price movement that break a significant
level of support or resistance, in this case
the high or low of the day, but fail to sustain
the momentum and quickly reverse back into
the previous range.
Fake breakouts come with a higher volatility.
You see them often, on any market.
Here’s a fake breakout at the high of the
day, when price breaks above the highest point
reached during the trading session, but then
falls back below it.
And here’s a fake breakout at the low of
the day, when price breaks below the lowest
point reached during the trading session,
but then rises back above it.
Smart money uses these fake breakouts for
two main reasons: to shake out weak hands
and to accumulate or distribute positions.
Shaking out weak hands means forcing retail
traders to exit their trades prematurely by
creating fear or greed.
Smart money may push the price above the high
of the day to trigger stop losses and buy
orders from retail traders who are following
the breakout.
This creates a surge in demand that drives
the price higher.
However, once smart money has filled their
orders, they will dump their positions, causing
the price to fall back below the high of the
day and trapping retail traders who bought
at the top.
This also creates a supply and volume imbalance
that drives the price lower.
You can identify this type of fake breakouts
by carefully analyzing the volume and some
common price action patterns.
Fake breakouts often form specific price action
patterns that signal a reversal or continuation
of the trend.
For example, a double top at the high of the
day, after a fake breakout, or double bottom
pattern at the low of the day, again, after
a fake breakout, is a clear sign of market
manipulation.
If you find a reversal candlestick pattern,
that even better.
Fake breakouts often form specific candlestick
patterns that indicate bullish or bearish
sentiment in the market.
For example, a pin bar or a candle with large
wick is a clear sign of rejection after a
failed breakout.
Asian session trap
The Asian trading session is one of the main
zones targeted by the smart money.
The Tokyo range trap is a common phenomenon
if you’re trading Forex, crypto and indices,
and occurs during the Asian session, which
is typically characterized by low volatility
and tight trading ranges.
The Tokyo range trap refers to the situation
where smart money use the range of the session
to trap retail traders into false breakouts
and reversals, and then exploit their positions
during the London and New York sessions, which
are more volatile and liquid.
One of the most common tactics is to create
a false breakout of the Tokyo range, which
is the high and low of the price action during
the Tokyo session.
Price moves beyond the range, and then quickly
reverses and moves back into the range.
This creates a false signal for the average
retail trader, who may enter or exit trades
based on the breakout, only to find himself
trapped in losing positions when the price
moves against him.
Another tactic used by smart money traders
is to create a false reversal of the Tokyo
range, which is the opposite of a false breakout.
How to avoid falling into the Tokyo range
trap and even make some money?
One of the most effective ways is to use volume
to measure the strength of the breakout.
A high volume outside the Tokio range indicates
that there is strong market participation
and conviction behind a price movement, while
a low volume indicates that there is weak
market participation and low conviction behind
a price movement.
Therefore, a high volume breakout or reversal
is more likely to be genuine than a low volume
one.
Additionally, you can learn from past examples
of how the Tokyo range trap has affected market
trends.
If you analyze these consecutive Tokyo sessions
we see an interesting pattern:
Range traders who have taken short positions
at the top of the Asian range had their stop
losses hunted, outside of the range.
Each time, the market reversed aggressively
in the opposite direction.
The upward movement outside of the range also
seduced traders to take long positions, hoping
for a breakout trade.
That’s the second batch of traders, who
were trapped.
Long breakout traders.
Wedges triangles trap
Wedges and triangles are two of the most common
chart patterns that traders use to identify
potential reversals or continuations in the
market.
However, not all wedges and triangles are
genuine.
Sometimes, they are deliberately created by
smart money, to trap retailer traders.
Wedges and triangles are usually formed by
two converging trend lines that connect the
highs and lows of a price action.
They indicate a period of consolidation, where
the market is indecisive and the trading range
narrows.
Now, smart money knows that many traders rely
on wedges and triangles to make their trading
decisions.
Therefore, they can use these patterns to
create false signals and lure unsuspecting
traders into their traps.
You’ll often see that price breaks out of
a wedge or a triangle in one direction, but
then quickly reverses and moves in the opposite
direction.
This creates confusion and panic among traders
who followed the initial breakout signal and
entered positions in that direction.
The idea is to trap traders on the wrong side
of the market.
For example, smart money can create an ascending
triangle pattern in an uptrend and induce
a fake breakout to the upside.
This will attract buyers who think that the
uptrend will continue.
However, smart money will then sell their
positions at higher prices and drive the price
down below the lower trend line of the triangle,
triggering stop losses and creating more selling
pressure.
This will result in a sharp decline in price
and a minor reversal of the uptrend.
Stop loss hunting is also common.
This occurs when smart money pushes the price
to a level where many traders have placed
their stop losses, triggering them and causing
a sudden spike or drop in price.
Smart money can use stop runs to shake out
weak traders from their positions and create
liquidity for their own trades.
For example, they can create a symmetrical
triangle pattern in a sideways market and
induce stop runs on both sides of the triangle.
This will cause traders who entered positions
based on either side of the breakout to exit
their trades at a loss.
Smart money will then take advantage of this
liquidity and enter positions in their desired
direction.
From my experience, it’s very hard to know
for sure whether a wedge or a triangle pattern
is genuine or fake.
In this example, you can observe that on the
lower boundary of the wedge, the lows become
slightly higher each time it comes down to
the line.
This has the effect of ensuring that none
of the trades that have taken short positions
in these regions can turn a profit.
Similarly, on the upper boundary of the wedge,
the same thing is happening with each of the
highs becoming progressively lower and trapping
the long traders and pulling them down.
There is no way of predicting which direction
the price will ultimately breakout.
I personally avoid trading during this type
of consolidation.
But if you want to be active in the market,
volume is the only indicator that will help
you to anticipate the future direction.
Generally, volume should decrease as a wedge
or a triangle pattern forms, indicating that
traders are waiting for a breakout signal.
Market open manipulation
Market open manipulation is another common
trap, which refers to the deliberate actions
of smart money to create false impressions
of supply and demand in the market.
These actions are designed to influence the
price movements and the psychology of retail
traders, who often trade based on technical
analysis, indicators or news.
It’s a reality that every trader has to
face and deal with.
The market open manipulation happens for two
main reasons: smart money want to take profit
from their existing positions or to accumulate
or distribute more positions at favorable
prices.
For example, if smart money wants to sell
a large position, they may drive up the price
at the market open.
This will attract retail traders who buy into
the breakout, thinking that the market is
going to rally.
However, once enough retail traders are trapped
in their long positions, smart money will
dump their positions into the market, causing
the price to reverse.
This will trigger stop-loss orders and panic
selling from retail traders.
There are many types of market open manipulation
that smart money can use to trick retail traders.
By now, you already know them:
- Fake breakouts: This is when smart money
pushes the price above or below a significant
support or resistance level, only to reverse
it shortly after.
This creates a false signal that the market
is trending in one direction, when in fact
it is going in the opposite direction.
- Stop-loss hunting: This is when smart money
targets the areas where retail traders place
their stop-loss orders, such as below support
levels or above resistance levels.
- False signals: This is when smart money
uses indicators, news events, or other factors
to generate misleading signals that contradict
the actual market direction.
For example, smart money may release positive
news about a stock before the market open,
causing retail traders to buy into the hype.
Or they deliberately move the price above
a common moving average, to determine moving
average traders to enter.
And, once the market opens, smart money will
sell their positions at a high price and then
drive the price down.
During the market open manipulation, you’ll
witness increased volatility.
You’ll see fast price swings and fluctuations
in a short period of time.
This increases the risk for retail traders
who may get caught on the wrong side of the
market.
Market open manipulation can reduce the liquidity
in the market by creating artificial supply
and demand imbalances.
This can make it harder for retail traders
to enter or exit their positions at favorable
prices.
For a beginner trader, it’s very hard to
make money in these conditions.
Market open trap can distort the true direction
and strength of the market trends by creating
false breakouts or reversals.
This will confuse retail traders who rely
on trend-following strategies or indicators.
Accumulation / distribution trap
I hope you realize that trading is a game
of psychology and strategy, where smart money
traders try to outsmart and outplay retail
traders who often lack the knowledge, experience
and discipline to succeed in the market.
One of the ways that smart money gain an edge
over retail traders is by using accumulation
and distribution strategies to manipulate
and trap them.
Accumulation is the phase where smart money
traders buy or accumulate an asset at low
prices, creating a strong demand.
Distribution is the phase where smart money
traders sell or distribute their positions
at high prices, creating a strong supply.
The goal of these accumulation and distribution
strategies is to create false signals and
expectations in the market that lure retail
traders into buying or selling at the wrong
time.
For example, during an accumulation phase,
smart money traders may create a downtrend
or a consolidation pattern, making it appear
that the market is weak or bearish.
This may induce retail traders to sell their
positions or short the market, expecting further
price declines.
However, once smart money traders have accumulated
enough positions at low prices, they may suddenly
reverse the trend and push the price up, triggering
stop losses of retail traders with short positions.
This creates a bullish breakout that attracts
more buyers into the market, allowing smart
money traders to distribute their positions
at high prices.
During a distribution phase, smart money may
create an uptrend or a consolidation pattern,
making it to appear that the market is strong
and bullish.
This may induce retail traders to go long,
expecting further price increases.
And, once smart money have distributed enough
positions at high prices, they may suddenly
reverse the trend and push the price down,
triggering stop losses of retail traders who
went long.
This creates a bearish breakdown that attracts
more sellers into the market, allowing smart
money traders to accumulate more positions
at low prices.
Smart money traders often use volume to confirm
or conceal their accumulation and distribution
strategies.
For example, during an accumulation phase,
smart money traders may use low volume to
hide their buying activity and create a false
sense of weakness in the market.
But, if you analyze price action during this
phase, you’ll see higher lows at the bottom
of the accumulation, a bullish signal.
Then smart money traders will use support
and resistance to test and break the confidence
and conviction of retail traders by creating
false breakouts that trap them on the wrong
side of the market.
During an accumulation phase, smart money
traders will usually use the support level
to create false breakdowns that make retail
traders think that the price will fall further
below support.
11.
How To Align With Smart Money
Trading will always be a game between the
smart money against the dumb money.
Retail traders might see some patterns as
continuation ones, but the smart money are
seeing them as reversal patterns.
You’ve seen the different traps used by
big players.
In order to align yourself with their true
intentions, always remember that smart money
are always searching for pockets of liquidity
in order to fill their desired positions in
the market.
They are always looking to shake out weak
hands, particularly around support and resistance
levels that are being widely watched.
It’s time to reconsider how you trade and
to start building a strategy that allows you
to join the smart money, after a liquidity
clear-out, or after an obvious market trap.
Again, the big players need LOTS of liquidity
in order to fill their massive orders.
How do they get this liquidity?
By creating well known retail chart patterns
and traps in order to involve the retail traders
into the market.
So, remember this, never enter a position
if you haven’t spotted a recent liquidity
clear-out.
For retail traders like you and me, the aim
should be to spot such potential liquidity
zones and join the game of market maker and
to avoid being a liquidity target.
The simplest structure to pay attention to
are zones with equal highs or lows.
Always assume smart money will want to trap
traders around these areas.
A liquidity clear out should always present
itself with a rapid, strong reversal move
after a critical area is taken out—basically
a rapid rotation of price back into the previous
trading range.
And always monitor the lowest low or highest
high of a structure.
If the structure is not even on highs or lows
positioning (for example, when highs or lows
are connected through a trend line instead
of flat line), then the main area to watch
is the lowest low or highest high of structure,
because this is where the majority of stop
losses will sit and where breakout traders
might initiate other positions.
12.
Strategy no.1: Demand zone entry after liquidity
clear-out
My favorite way to align my positions with
the ones of smart money is to trade demand
zones, after a liquidity clear-out.
You need to follow these steps:
1) First, identify a liquidity run that breaks
below a previous swing low or support level
where many retail traders have placed their
stop-loss orders.
2) Then, identify a potential demand zone
that was previously formed near the liquidity
run
3) Wait for the price to retest the demand
zone and confirm its validity, by finding
signs of rejection or bounce.
Here you can check the volume, to confirm
the rejection
4) Enter a long position at or near the demand
zone with a stop-loss below the zone
5) Exit the position at or near a previous
swing high or at the next important supply
area, or where smart money may initiate another
liquidity run.
Here’s EUR/USD.
Market is in a general uptrend, so the plan
is to trade a long position, at a demand area,
only after we spot a liquidity clear-out.
1) We see this liquidity run that breaks below
this area where many retail traders have placed
their stop-loss orders.
2) We found a fresh and recent demand zone,
right here
3) Once the price touched our demand zone
we confirmed its validity after we saw this
candle with a lower wick.
A rejection candle.
4) A long position after the demand rejection,
after the liquidity clear-out, was the correct
trade in this case
5) Stop-loss below the liquidity run, and
you target the next important supply area
Strategy no.2: Supply zone entry after liquidity
clear-out
Another strategy to align your positions with
the ones of smart money is to trade supply
zones, after a liquidity clear-out, or after
you find other market trap.
1) First, identify a liquidity run or a market
trap that breaks above a previous swing high
or resistance level where many retail traders
have placed their stop-loss orders.
2) Then, identify a potential supply zone
that was previously formed around the liquidity
run
3) Wait for the price to retest the supply
zone and confirm its validity by finding signs
of rejection
4) Enter a short position at or near the supply
zone with a stop-loss above the zone or above
the liquidity clear-out
5) Exit the position at or near a previous
swing low or at the next important demand
area, or where smart money may initiate another
liquidity run.
Here’s GBP/USD.
Market is in a general downtrend, so the plan
is to trade a short position, at a supply
area, only after we find a liquidity clear-out.
1) We see this liquidity run that breaks above
this area, where many retail traders have
placed their stop-loss orders.
2) We found a fresh and recent supply zone,
right here.
We find the most recent green candle before
the drop and mark our area of interest
3) I see another trap here.
A triangle, which was broken to the upside,
baiting traders to enter into long positions.
But the trend is down, we are near a supply
area and we also have a liquidity clear-out
and many long traders trapped.
4) A short position after the supply rejection,
after the liquidity clear-out, was the better
trade
5) Stop-loss above the liquidity run, and
you target the next important demand area
Strategy no.3: Demand zone entry after down
thrust VSA pattern
Another way to align with smart money is to
trade demand zones, after you find a down
thrust VSA pattern.
You need to follow these steps:
1) First, you need to find a down thrust formation,
which appears as a bullish pin bar or a Doji
bar having an ultra-high volume or above average
volume.
The Spread of the down thrust bar is low meanwhile
the volume is relatively high.
So, there is more demand than supply, potentially
causing price to rise in near future.
2) Then, identify a potential demand zone
around the same area
3) If you find a liquidity clear-out, that’s
even better
4) Enter a long position at or near the demand
zone with a stop-loss below the zone
5) Exit the position at or near a previous
swing high or at the next important supply
area, or where smart money may initiate another
liquidity run.
Here’s Tesla.
Market is in an uptrend, so the plan is to
trade a long position, at a demand area, after
we spot a down thrust.
1) First, we see this liquidity run that breaks
below this area, and at the same time, we
have a down thrust VSA candle.
The Spread of the candle is low and the volume
is relatively high.
So, there is more demand than supply, a sign
that price may rise in near future.
2) We also have a fresh and recent demand
zone, right here
3) A long position after the demand rejection
is a high probability trade
4) Stop-loss below the down thrust candle,
and you target the next supply area
Strategy no.4: Supply zone entry after up
thrust VSA pattern
Another smart way to trade is to find entries
at supply zones, after you find an up thrust
VSA pattern.
1) First, you need to find the up thrust,
which appears as a bearish pin bar or doji
bar having an ultra-high volume or above average
volume.
The Spread of the up thrust candle is low
while the volume is relatively high.
In this case there is a disagreement between
spread and volume which signifies that there
is more supply than demand, potentially causing
price to fall in near future
2) Then, identify a potential supply zone
around the same area
3) If you find a liquidity clear-out, that’s
even better
4) Enter a short position at or near the supply
zone with a stop-loss above the zone
5) Exit the position at or near a previous
swing low or at the next important demand
area, or where smart money may initiate another
liquidity run.
Here’s Amazon.
Market is in a downtrend, so the plan is to
trade a short position, at a supply area,
after we find an up thrust pattern, which
is right here.
A bearish pin bar having above average volume.
Low spread while the volume is relatively
high.
A disagreement between spread and volume which
implies that there is more supply than demand,
a sign that price could fall in near future
2) Then we found a fresh and recent supply
zone.
We find the most recent green candle before
the drop and mark our area of interest
4) A short position after the supply rejection
was the obvious trade
5) Stop-loss above the supply area, and you
target the next important demand area
Strategy no.5 – Over and under break of
structure
The over and under break of structure is another
way to align yourself with the big players.
The break of structure is the first sign that
smart money have initiated a price shift.
For a bearish over and under pattern, after
a previous uptrend.
• Price creates a higher high
• then creates a lower high
• Price breaks the previous high and creates
a new higher high
• Then price breaks the previous low as
well and forms a lower low
For a bullish over and under pattern, after
a previous downtrend.
• Price creates a lower low
• Price creates a lower high
• Price breaks the previous low and creates
a new lower low
• Then price breaks the previous high as
well and forms a higher high
Now, this break of structure doesn’t always
result in a reversal.
That’s why, in order to align your positions
with the smart money, you need to use once
again, supply and demand zones.
So the plan is to find the break of structure
pattern, to wait for a retracement, and to
find a supply or demand zone for an entry,
to execute the trade with a higher accuracy.
Here, we see a significant decrease in price
on EUR/USD.
The price makes a swing low, followed by a
lower high.
Then makes a lower low, and it shoots up and
breaks the previous high, making a higher
high.
We have our break of structure and our over
and under pattern.
Now we need to find a demand zone for an entry.
First, you need to take a look at the left-hand
side of previous low, where the strong rally
has started.
You need to find the last bearish candle before
the strong rally.
I see a rally base rally formation, which
is a continuation pattern, forming a demand
zone.
When price returns to this area, you can open
a buy position, with stops below this demand
zone.
If you find a liquidity clear-out, again,
even better.
Here’s another break of structure pattern,
a bearish one.
The previous trend is an uptrend.
The price is forming a new swing high, declines,
then forms a swing low.
Price then rallies again to exceed the previous
high (making a higher high).
Then it decreased to form a new lower low.
This is our first sign that we might have
an over and under pattern.
Remember, you don’t enter just because you
find a possible break of structure.
You need to wait for price to rise again,
to a fresh and untested supply area.
You look at the left side of the previous
high where the previous strong down move started.
I see a drop base drop formation, which is
a continuation pattern, forming a supply zone.
When price returns to this area, you can open
a sell position, with stops above this supply
zone.
Strategy no.6 – Psychological numbers VSA
clear-out
Psychological numbers are quite important
for smart money traders.
These are price levels that have a significant
impact on the market sentiment and behavior.
They are often round numbers or multiples
of 50, 100, etc.
These numbers tend to act as support and resistance
levels, as well as trigger points for stop-losses
and take-profits.
These round numbers reflect the collective
psychology of the market participants, especially
the large institutional traders who have the
power to move the market.
One simple way to identify psychological numbers
is to look at the price charts and observe
how the price reacts when it approaches or
breaks these levels.
You will often see increased volatility, increased
volume, and many liquidity clear-outs around
these levels.
Supply and demand areas in combination with
round numbers is a powerful way to align yourself
with the smart money.
A supply zone, in combination with a psychological
level, is a good area to initiate a sell position.
A demand zone, which includes psychological
level, again, offers a low risk - high reward
buy situation.
Liquidity clear-outs in combination with round
numbers is one of the simplest way to trade.
If you know the main VSA patterns you’ll
have even better chances to trade with the
smart money.
Here’s Amazon, with the main psychological
levels added.
Have a look at this liquidity run, just below
the price of 90$.
And look at the candle which broke below the
level.
It’s a down thrust VSA pattern.
A bullish pin bar having an ultra-high volume.
In fact it’s the highest volume in recent
period.
The spread of the down thrust is low while
the volume is relatively high.
So, there is more demand than supply, a sign
that price to rise in near future.
And it happened at a very important psychological
number of 90$.
And we had a liquidity clear-out.
This buy right here is a no brainer.
Here’s Apple, with the main psychological
levels added.
I see an obvious liquidity run, taking stops
above 150$ and trapping long traders above
this level.
And look at the candle which broke below the
level.
It’s an up thrust VSA pattern.
A pin bar having above average volume.
The spread of the up thrust is low while the
volume is relatively high.
So, there is more supply than demand, a sign
that price could fall in near future.
And it happened at a clear supply area.
It’s right here.
So we had the liquidity clear-out.
The 150$ psychological number.
A supply area.
And the up thrust VSA pattern.
Perfect sell trade.
These trades are rare.
You’ll be lucky if you find one trade per
week, with a supply or demand area, a VSA
pattern, a liquidity run and psychological
number confluence.
But when you find this type of trade, don’t
hesitate, and take the trade, every single
time.
If this smart money trading course made sense,
please show your support by giving a like,
it goes a long way.
And if you haven’t watched our previous
day trading course, you definitely must watch
it later!
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!