Price action is the simplest and easiest form
of reading and analyzing a market.
But the problem is that many traders are complicating
their process, and analyze things on the chart
that are irrelevant.
Let me show you an easy method to read price
action, without needing to memorize dozens
of candlesticks or stare at the charts for
hours to find patterns.
You know the drill: like, subscribe, and stick
around for the full video.
TREND BARS
The first thing you should look for when you
are analyzing a chart, is the spread of recent
candles.
The spread is the difference between a candle’s
open and its close (this is the real body
of the candle).
The spread reveals the sentiment for that
candle.
A wide spread between the open and the close
indicates strong market sentiment, either
bullish or bearish, depending on whether the
closing price finished above the opening price
or below it.
And if the body of the candle takes up at
least 50% of the entire bar range, then you
are seeing a trend Bar.
Trend bars represent the meat of the market
fluctuations.
The concept of Trend Bars is very simple.
Price action simply creates a solid candle
with small wicks at the top or the bottom,
and is suggesting a strong and a likely continued
sentiment in the direction of the candle.
A trend candle represents strong market sentiment
and a narrow spread one shows a weak market
sentiment.
If we analyze this chart, between these two
points, there were no instances of consecutive
Trend Bars that closed in the same direction.
We had several Trend Bars, but they were isolated
instances.
When we had consecutive Trend Bars, they actually
closed in opposing directions.
Here we see consecutive bullish Trend Bars.
It shows evident bullish strength.
Very important: when the trend is strong,
you’ll see many trend bars in the direction
of the trend.
And, if there are no Trend Bars for the past
ten bars, for example, then the market is
likely consolidating.
LONG SHADOWS
The upper and lower wicks of candlesticks
reflect the buying and selling pressure.
Consider wicks as ‘rejection’ areas where
the market simply rejected the prices of the
wick.
When you see a wick that is large, that wick
is clearly telling you that the market was
not accepting the previous prices.
Time frame is important here and we’ll talk
about this later.
If you are trading on the 5min charts, then
the market has rejected that price level with
that wick, but for only the past 5 minutes,
which is not that significant.
However, when you start to look at 4hr or
daily charts, that wick is more significant.
The length of any wick, either to the top
or bottom of the candle is ALWAYS the first
point of focus because it instantly shows,
strength, weakness, or indecision, and most
important where buyers or sellers are entering
the market.
In fact, the wick itself is not important,
the price level at which the wick occurred
is what matters.
Taking a look at this chart, notice how every
time the market reversed, it did so with a
large wick and almost at the same price level.
This is telling you the market simply did
not accept prices at these levels, with sellers
aggressively entering the market quickly,
causing the price to drop faster.
CONSECUTIVE BARS CLOSING IN THE SAME DIRECTION
So, when you analyze a chart, you start by
paying more attention to trend bars and bars
with long shadows.
Now, in a market, there are trends at various
levels.
Consecutive bars closing in the same direction
is one of the easiest ways to identify minor
trends.
The number of successive bars matters too.
The more, the better.
When you have consecutive trend bars in the
same direction, you have lots of momentum.
In many cases, consecutive price bars will
help you to identify sustained price movements.
OVERLAP WITH THE PREVIOUS BAR
The degree of overlap with the previous bar
tells you the current market phase and the
power of the price bar.
In a strong trend, there is very little overlap
of the bodies of consecutive bars.
For example, in a minor uptrend, many candles
have lows that are at or just below the closes
of the prior candles.
Some candles don’t even test the close of
the prior bar, and traders trying to enter
with a limit order at the close of the prior
bar won’t get their orders filled, so they
have to buy higher.
The point is, if you find minimal overlap
between a candle and the preceding one, it
implies urgency.
And start paying more attention to this.
Again, in this bearish down move, many bars
have highs that are at or just above the closes
of the prior bar.
This shows strength and it’s an important
sign because the market is unable to go higher
and it keeps pushing lower.
So if no wick or a very small wick is created,
then this signals strong market sentiment
in the direction of the closing price.
It indicates urgency in the market.
If the bar you are looking at overlaps entirely
with the previous bar, the market doesn’t
have the greatest momentum.
This is especially true with inside bars.
Inside bar are smaller and within the range
of the prior bar.
100% overlap bars and consecutive candles
that are overlapping are a clear sign of market
congestion.
Wicks below bullish bars and above bearish
bars
In a strong uptrend, you will see wicks below
the bullish bars.
This represents a good signal that the buyers
are in control of the market and that are
trying to push the prices upwards.
You will also see wicks above the bearish
bars in a strong downtrend.
This shows that the sellers are in control
and that are successfully pushing the prices
downwards.
REACTION AFTER A TEST OF SUPPORT/RESISTANCE
Pay more attention to candlesticks that test
any support/resistance areas.
You may find that the candle has difficulty
breaking through the level.
Or you may find that the candle completely
ignores the level and breaks it with ease.
In either case, they help you to formulate
a trading approach.
If we look at the recent price action, I see
a test of this support level, which resulted
in a bullish Pin Bar.
As I said before, a long shadow implies bullish
pressure.
On the other hand, the market completely ignored
this resistance level and broke above it decisively.
No retest of previous breakouts
So let’s assume that price broke a significant
resistance level.
And of course, all trading manuals say that
in order to trade a breakout, you must wait
for price to re-test the breakout level.
But, very important, in a strong market, you
will not get a retest.
The buyers are unwilling to let the price
drop lower.
There is little profit taking after the breakout,
so price won’t come to retest the breakout
level.
So when you see an important level, and price
breaks it, and has strong upward momentum,
without re-testing the level, there’s again
a sense of urgency, a higher volatility and
high momentum.
TOP-DOWN ANALYSIS
When you’re reading price action, analyzing
only the 15 min chart, for example, won’t
bring you consistency in the longer term.
You need more information.
When a particular timeframe DON’T make sense,
then move to the next higher time frame, at
least, for the big picture or even on a lower
timeframe for the microstructure of move.
When you’re trading price action, you need
a top-down analysis, which is a more efficient
and effective way to trade.
A simple top-down approach means marking out
the support and resistance first on higher
time frames.
Then you read price action of the higher time
frames, and see what the price is telling
you and where it may be heading.
Then, with that market structure in mind,
zoom into the lower-level details.
Context of the price move
Now, reading price action is not about finding
pin bars, engulfing patterns, or seeing if
there are more green candles than red ones.
It is about observing price bars as they form
and understanding what the market has done
and is doing.
A candle of the same type will have a completely
different meaning depending on where it appears
in a price trend.
• Is it at a start of trend or in the middle
of the trend or end of it.
• Is it at support or resistance or in the
middle of a consolidation phase.
Candlesticks should be analyzed in the context
of the price move.
You should never try and read the candle in
isolation.
Analyzing multiple bars as a group, on several
time frames offers a lot more analytical value.
Here we have 2 similar pin bars.
But this one is the more important.
It appeared in the context of an uptrend,
with multiple trend bars at a support level.
While this one appeared after many candles
are overlapping, so in a congestion area.
The point is: start reading the current candle
in relation to the previous bars.
• Is the current candlestick larger or smaller
than previous ones?
• Which recent candles are showing momentum
increases or decreases
• Is the size of the body meaningful or
not?
• Are you seeing buying or selling pressure
Volume validates price
Price goes hand in hand with volume.
Is it possible to make money trading using
price action alone?
Sure.
But price in combination with volume is 10
times better.
First, you see what the CANDLESTICK is telling
you, then you check the volume, and see if
it’s validating or not with the recent price
action.
Volume validates price.
It’s the fuel that drives the market, and
the more fuel there is, the greater the market
momentum.
Volume confirms the strength of a candlestick
or suggests its weakness.
If the market is rising with a trend bar,
and we have volume which is increasing, then
this suggests that we have a strong price
move supported by an increasing number of
buyers.
This is BUYING volume, and you expect the
price move to continue in this case.
If you have a trend bar, but you see decreasing
volume, then this is WEAK price move.
If strong buyers were still in the market,
then this would be represented by RISING volume,
and in this case we have FALLING volume, so
this is a warning sign that the buyers are
NO LONGER INTERESTED.
The trend may be running out of steam.
This is the first sign of a POSSIBLE change
in trend.
Combining Volume and Price
Price alone can only tell you what a market’s
present technical position really is, and
where the trend is probably headed.
Volume help to validate the trend with more
accuracy and also detects turning points,
when to open or close trades.
And together, they form a complete picture.
I’ve talked about the Volume spread analysis
in this video, and if you haven’t seen it
yet, this must be your next video to watch.
VSA seeks to establish the cause of price
movements by considering the imbalance between
buying and selling.
If you think about it, volume expresses interest
and enthusiasm in one simple bar.
All the buying and selling decisions of investors,
retail traders and smart money are all contained
in one volume bar.
All the millions of trading decisions, whether
to buy or to sell are all captured in this
one bar.
Volume exposes the truth of a candlestick.
It reveals the conviction in the recent price
move.
If the market is moving higher, but with falling
or low volume, then this is simply telling
you that this is not a genuine move.
Equally, if the market is decreasing with
falling volume, then once again this is not
a genuine move.
The more volume associated with a price move,
then the more that price move is validated.
When there is low volume, few sellers in this
example, then this price may simply not be
validated.
But when we have many sellers, this will reflect
in high volume, and then our price is validated.
It really is that simple.
I hope that you can start to see how volume
and price are the only two aspects of a chart
that you need to understand.
Learn how these work together, and you will
join the elite group of traders who have the
ability to literally “read the market”
and are able to anticipate where price is
likely to be heading, before it happens.
If you want to see more videos like this one,
leave us a like and subscribe.
And check out our academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time!