If you want to be profitable trading market
pullbacks, the best way is to catch the first
pullback.
The first pullbacks are the trend entries
that can be found at the very start of a new
trend.
In today’s video we’ll explore the idea
of trading the first pullback in a new trend
and I will share my strategy to pinpoint the
exact moment to enter the market.
In an ideal situation, the most profitable
way to trade the market is to catch the run
from the very top and cash out at the bottom
of the market.
The opposite is also true if you catch it
from the bottom and exit right at the top
of the market.
However, the nature of trading is such that
we never really know where the top or bottom
is.
Above and beyond that, catching the top or
the bottom of the market is probably one of
the harder tasks and many traders have lost
substantial amount of money while attempting
to do so.
Instead of entering the market at the top
or bottom, the first pullback allows traders
to enter near the top or bottom (as shown
in this example), this is similar to entering
at the top or bottom, and you can still enjoy
the majority of the benefits.
Hence, entering the market at the first pullback
is the next best entry.
Essentially, the first pullback in the new
trend direction is also the final test of
the extreme in the old trend direction.
Understanding the final test of the extreme
is fairly important when identifying the first
pullback.
Just to be clear, the first pullback is not
a reversal set up.
Instead, it is a trend-following setup that
enters the market at a very early stage of
the new trend – it is the first trend entry
immediately after price has reversed.
While many traders would be afraid to enter
the market using this technique, smart traders
understand that this is a low risk and high
reward set up.
Now, let’s explore the concept of “first
pullback in a new direction”.
As we know, when the trend ends, it does not
imply that the new trend would start immediately.
So it is important to know what price action
sings to look for when searching for the first
pullback.
Before we search for the first pullback, we
need to analyze price action right before
it happens.
Using this example, the market is currently
in an uptrend (which is the old trend direction).
The first indication of a potential new pullback
(in a new direction) is when you see the first
lower high.
This is because the lower high is a sign of
weakness that shows that the buyers are not
completely in control.
This is also a potential final test of the
swing high.
Buyers are testing to see if they can move
any higher.
Meanwhile, the sellers are keeping a close
eye, and once they know that buyers are exhausted,
big sellers would take control of the market,
and they would push price lower.
However, the confirmation of the final test
requires a lower low or, in this case, a break
below Point C.
When you have a lower high (Point C in this
example) and when price breaks below Point
C, the first pullback in new direction is
completed.
In other words, the easiest way to find pullbacks
is to spot ABCD patterns.
BC wave is the actual pullback but a pullback
must include CD wave where point D moves beyond
point B, or the pullback is invalid.
The same applies here, price must move below
Point B for confirmation of the first pullback
in the new trend direction.
Once you have a full cycle, the chances are
higher that the market is now in a downtrend,
and the chances are now slimmer for price
to move upwards since the downward market
has already started.
Now, understanding the first pullback means
nothing if you do not take any positions.
You either catch the new pullback or you missed
it.
Truth to be told, there is nothing much you
can do about it once you miss the pullback.
Trading is all about preparation and the more
you are prepared for it, the more you can
grab a high probability trade.
So in your analysis you must be able to identify
some important signs for catching the first
pullback.
1.
First sign is that pullback fails in old direction
A break below Point A represents a confirmation
that a pullback in the old direction has failed.
This is also the first lower low that we were
looking for.
While we don’t know what happens next, we
can only wait for more price confirmation
to show us if the buyers or sellers are taking
the lead.
Nonetheless, the only thing that we are certain
is the old trend has lost its drive and that
is an important clue to note.
2.
Second sign is a trend bar showing confirmation
of failed pullback in the old direction
While a failed pullback is important, we need
the probabilities to stack in our favour.
Thus, in terms of price action, you want to
see a clear break below Point A and one of
the best ways to identify seller’s conviction
is by finding one or more long bodied bearish
trend bars breaking through point A.
This is a strong confirmation that the pullback
has failed and the probability of getting
a fake failed pullback has greatly reduced.
Trend bars are great to show strength in the
market, and you should look for them especially
at the start of a new trend.
They are very useful clues for trading success
especially near price extremes.
If the trend bar is longer than the average
size bar, that is also a good indication of
momentum and this is usually the start of
a market rally (or decline).
If you find that the trend bars have very
small tails that is evidence that the market
is one-sided, and the momentum is increased
further.
3.
Third sign is related to time frame correlation
When chasing the first pullback, you should
try your best to understand time frame correlation.
For example: - A price extreme at the hourly
chart is more relevant when trading a 15 minute
chart.
A price extreme at the daily chart is more
relevant when trading the hourly or the 4
hour chart.
The time frame below shows you the pattern
or the pullback that you are looking for.
Looking at this example, you can see from
the daily chart that price was very far away
from the moving average line.
This point is considered the extreme since
it was at the point where it was furthest
away from the moving average.
However, there was no clue showing the lack
of buyers until the first lower high on the
4 hour chart.
Using the daily chart to identify the market
extreme, you can then move to the 4 hour chart
to pinpoint when price pullback fails in the
initial trend direction.
The first clue that the buyers have run out
of strength is the price action double top
– a final test of the extreme.
Then, it was followed by a lower low.
The confirmation of the first pullback in
the new trend direction was when price broke
below this bar.
If you stayed on the daily timeframe, you
might not have spotted the pullback and would
have missed a good pullback entry.
4.
Fourth sign is a the creation of a reversal
pattern
Since a first pullback is an early entry in
a new trend, it should be no surprise that
you can find many first pullbacks immediately
after a reversal pattern.
So, let’s explore some conventional reversal
patterns.
Just to be clear, the idea is not to trade
the reversal patterns and it is important
to wait for price to have reversed before
looking for any first pullback entry.
First pattern: double top/bottom and neckline
pullback
A double top pattern is a good and simple
indication that the price has tested the extreme
one last time and resulted in a final test,
in the old trend direction.
The double top is only a potential start of
a new pullback and the clues that you should
be looking for are the new lower low (point
B) and a new lower high (Point C).
The retest of the neckline is an extra but
powerful clue as it is where the old support
becomes resistance.
In other words, the double top is only the
first clue, but not a confirmation that a
first pullback is ready.
Another pattern is the range market breakout
A range market can happen around the market
extreme or in the middle of a trending market.
A range market is only formed if there are
2 touches on either side of the market.
As you can see from this example, Point B
is the first lower low, and it is also the
first break outside the range.
However, Point B can also be a false break,
and you can only find out if it is by watching
Point C and Point D closely.
Point C is the most important one for our
analysis, being the first lower high and also
a retest of the resistance (previous support)
level.
Like all other pullbacks, the first pullback
is only complete once we have Point D, which
is the break below B to form a second lower
low and also a complete ABCD pattern.
The Head & Shoulders (H&S) pattern is another
classic reversal pattern and, like a double
top, it is also a good sign of price exhaustion.
H&S pattern would consist of three tops where
the left shoulder is the first top, the head
is the second (and highest) top and the right
shoulder is the third top.
The two lows in between the three tops would
determine the shape of the neckline – as
it can be a horizontal or a slope neckline.
In a horizontal neckline, the entire H&S pattern
relies on the fact that Point D must be below
Point B, which is also below the neckline.
The neckline carries quite a bit of probability
weight.
If price fails to break below the neckline,
this could turn out to be a double (or even
triple) bottom bullish continuation pattern.
Our first pullback would basically be the
right shoulder in the Head & Shoulders setup.
The first pullback in a NEW directional trend
is one of most rewarding setups.
They don’t always work 100% of the time.
Sometimes they offer small profits, and other
times the price will maintain its initial
direction, despite all reversal signs we identified.
But if you learn to correctly identify the
first pullback, the profits can more than
make up for any other failed attempts.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.