What if I told you that on every
chart, there is an invisible line?
Above that line, everything
is 'Premium'… it's expensive.
Below it, is 'Discount'…it's cheap.
Losing traders have no idea this line exists.
Today, I'll make that line visible for you. Plus,
I'll give you the two signals that tell
you exactly when to pull the trigger.
The Structure Shift
Here's something that will
completely change how you see the market...
Most traders spot a breakout and their
brain instantly screams "BUY!"
They see price breaking through a
level and think they've found the perfect entry.
And that's exactly when they get destroyed.
See, the mistake isn't chasing breakouts. The
mistake is thinking the breakout IS the trade.
Let me show you what's really
happening when that move occurs.
When price breaks a major swing
high or low with real conviction,
it's not giving you an entry signal.
It's giving you something way more valuable.
It's showing you the market's new blueprint.
Think of it like this - that break isn't
telling you to trade right now. It's
telling you WHERE to trade next.
Pay attention to this next part - it's
the difference between profit and loss.
Watch what happens after any major structure
shift. Price doesn't just keep running
forever. It pulls back. It retraces.
It comes back to test specific levels.
And when you know which levels
matter, you can position yourself
exactly where the smart money is waiting.
So here's the real edge - a real structure
shift breaks a MAJOR swing point. Not some
random high. Not a tiny peak. A major swing
that actually matters. The kind that changes the
entire market narrative. This is the first step
in my trading strategy. Find a genuine market
shift, one that breaks a major swing point.
Once you spot that shift, the game changes
completely. You're not guessing anymore.
You have a roadmap. And in the next chapter,
I'll show you exactly how to read that map.
________________________________________
The Premium Discount
Now, before I show you these invisible lines, let
me tell you what happens when you ignore them.
Most traders think support and resistance
are the only levels that matter.
But smart money sees the
market completely differently.
They see every swing as having three critical
zones - premium, fair value, and discount.
Retail traders buy when price looks
strong. They sell when it looks weak.
Banks do the exact opposite. They buy
discount and sell premium. Every single time.
This next technique is worth more than most
trading courses. Here's how the pros map this
out. Pay attention. Pull up the Gann Box tool
on TradingView. Draw it from the swing low
that started the breakout, to the swing high.
The quarters appear instantly. 25, 50 and 75%.
These aren't random numbers.
These are the exact levels
institutions use to define value.
This entire range becomes your universe. The
top 25% is premium territory - everything here is
expensive. The bottom 25% is discount - everything
here is cheap. And right in the middle at 50%,
that's fair value. That's the battleground.
But most traders can't see these
zones. They're invisible. Until now.
Watch this - this is where it gets crazy.
Look at any chart with this filter. You'll
see something incredible. Price respects these
levels over and over. It bounces at 25% discount.
It reverses at 75% premium.
It fights at 50% fair value.
The reason this works is pure psychology. When
price is in premium, sellers have the advantage.
They're distributing at expensive prices.
When price is in discount, buyers have the
edge. They're accumulating at cheap levels.
And this creates our entire trading edge.
While retail buys premium thinking it's
"strong," we're selling into their buying.
While they panic-sell discount thinking
it's "weak," we're buying their fear.
This invisible framework is running on
every chart, every timeframe, every market.
Once you see it, you can't unsee it.
And when you combine it with what I'm about
to show you next, it becomes almost unfair.
________________________________________
The Confluence Zone
Now here's where this strategy
becomes unstoppable. We're going to add one more
layer that turns good setups into great ones.
Look at this chart. We have our
premium and discount lines mapped out.
But how do you know, where price will stop? You
want to buy at the 25% level, but you can also get
a decent trade at the fair price, at the 50% line.
It’s simple, we’ll add support
and resistance level to the mix.
Check this out. Here's a support zone.
Observe how price dropped to this level, then
exploded higher. And look where it sits. This is
near our 25% discount line. That’s confluence.
This is where two powerful concepts overlap.
The power of overlap is incredible. When
our premium or discount lines intersect
with a key level, the probability of success
goes through the roof. It's like the market
is giving you a double confirmation.
This is crucial - most traders get this
completely wrong: they see support and resistance
everywhere. But they don't understand location.
A support in premium territory is weak.
But a support in discount territory…
that's where institutions want to buy.
So here's how to spot these confluence
areas. First, map your premium discount
lines after every structure shift.
Then, mark your key level
for that particular move.
Then you look for the overlap. When
these two systems agree, pay attention.
The rejection signals are beautiful when you find
these spots. Price comes down to test confluence,
and boom. Instant reaction. Strong reversal
candles. Volume spikes. The market will show
you institutional activity.
You want to see rejection.
You want to see strength.
This single filter will eliminate
at least 80% of the fakeouts that would have
previously cost you money. But let me show
you exactly how to put this all together.
________________________________________
The Complete System Integration
Here's where it gets interesting.
You now have the foundation, the zones,
and the confluence points. Here's how
they work together as a complete system...
Step one - wait for a structure shift. This
is non-negotiable. The shift tells you the bias
and creates your premium/discount framework.
Step two - map your levels immediately.
Swing low to swing high for bullish
shifts. Swing high to swing low for bearish
shifts. Get those quarters on your chart.
Step three - identify your support or
resistance zones. Which ones sit in
premium? Which ones sit in discount?
Step four - wait for price to enter
your overlap zone. Support zones
in discount for buys. Resistance
zones in premium for sells. No exceptions.
Then you look for rejection patterns. Pin
bars. Engulfing candles. Momentum shifts. These
confirm institutional activity at your level.
This isn't about perfection. It's about
probability. When all these factors align,
you have the highest possible
edge. You're trading with
institutional logic, not retail emotion.
________________________________________
Buying Discount
Real quick, let me walk you
through an actual trade. I’m on the hourly chart.
Dow Jones Index had been in clear downtrend
for days. But then we got this beautiful
structure shift. Price broke above this
major swing high with conviction. Look at that
impulsive move. That's institutional buying.
Now watch what I do next. I immediately map my
Gann box from the lowest point that led to this
break, all the way up to the new high. I have 2
buying places in my mind. One at the 25% discount
line. And another one at the 50% fair value.
But I'm not trading yet. I'm waiting for price
to return to discount territory. And look
what happens next. Price starts to retrace
lower. It's coming back to test our levels.
Here's where confluence comes in. Right here,
there’s a clear role reversal zone. A previous
resistance, now potentially acting as support.
And check this out. It sits at our 25%
discount line. This is the sweet spot.
Now I wait for price to test my confluence
zone. And boom. Look at that reaction. A
strong bullish engulfing candle right at the
confluence of my support and discount line.
This is my entry signal. I'm buying at
discount with institutional confluence.
My stop loss goes just below the discount
line. My first target is fair value at
50%. My second target is premium at 75%.
Here's the beautiful part about this system.
Price moved from our discount entry
at 25%, through fair value at 50%,
all the way toward premium targets. That's
a textbook move from discount to premium.
This is what happens when you align
your trades with institutional thinking.
The beautiful part is how clean everything
was. Clear structure shift. Clean
confluence. Strong rejection. Obvious targets.
This isn't just a theory. This is a new weapon
in your arsenal that you can deploy right now.
________________________________________
Selling Premium
Now let me show
you a premium trade on the Gold market.
Here's the situation on the 30-min chart.
Gold made this massive structure shift to the
downside. Price broke below this major swing
low with serious institutional selling
pressure. That's smart money in action.
Most traders saw this break and wanted to
short immediately. But that's exactly the
trap. Instead, let’s map our zones.
Here's my Gann box from the highest
point that led to the break, down to
the new low. Now I wait for price to
rally back up to premium territory.
During the previous move, price had
created this resistance zone. And it sits right
at the 75% premium line. Perfect confluence.
Price rallies up to test our confluence zone. And
here’s the immediate rejection. A long wick right
at resistance. Not quite at the 75% level.
But I’m still selling at premium with
institutional confluence backing me up. My
stop loss goes above the premium line. My
targets are the discount zones.
Watch what happened next.
Price dropped from premium through
fair value back toward discount levels.
The lesson here is powerful. Selling
premium and buying discount is the closest
thing to a trading cheat code you'll find.
________________________________________
Advanced Mastery Techniques
You've got the foundation.
Now let me show you some advanced techniques.
First, know that 75% and 25% are your ideal zones,
but they're not your only zones.
Sometimes the best trades happen
at fair value or even at the extremes.
Here's what I mean. You're waiting for
price to hit your 25% discount zone,
but it only retraces to 40%. Do you
pass on the trade? Not necessarily. If you see
strong institutional activity at fair value,
that can still be a high-probability setup.
And here's something most traders miss.
The extremes can be goldmines. When
price reaches your 100% or 0% levels,
it often creates the strongest reversal setups.
Think of it as premium or discount on steroids.
Second technique is the liquidity
sweep setup. This is where the
strategy becomes absolutely devastating.
Watch this example. Price is coming down toward
our discount zone, but first it does something
beautiful. It breaks below this lower timeframe
support level, grabs all the stop losses,
then reverses back up from our discount zone.
This liquidity sweep is like rocket fuel for
your trades. Banks just grabbed all the weak
hands' money and now they're ready to
push price in the opposite direction.
When you combine premium and discount
zones with liquidity sweeps, you're
trading with institutional precision.
________________________________________
MASTERY RECAP
Let's lock this in.
You now have:
• The ability
to spot genuine market structure shifts
• A complete premium discount framework
• And advanced confluence zone mapping skills
The next time you see a structure shift,
you'll know exactly what to do.
You map your zones. You wait for confluence.
And you buy discount… and sell premium.
Start using this immediately…