At some time during a bearish move, prices
will start to resist further down-moves.
And when these moves are followed by an ultra
high volume bar, this is a very good signal
to enter into a trade.
When you see an ultra high volume bar, something
is going to happen in the market.
A high volume suggests a high participation,
a lot of interest in trading that particular
area, around that particular price.
The question you must ask yourself is why
there are traders interested in participating
in that zone, what are their intentions?
To answer these questions you have to analyze
the volume along with the price action.
It's about seeing what the price does with
that volume.
Today I will share a very powerful way to
day trade, a scalping strategy more exactly,
using ultra high volume bars, on the 1-min
time frame.
So, like, subscribe, and stick around for
the full video.
The power ultra high volume bar
Stopping volume is a well-known concept in
volume spread analysis (VSA).
It refers to a dramatic increase in volume
that stops the market from falling further.
This is your ultra high volume bar, which
appears after a downward move.
There are many ways to integrate volume with
price action.
But I find that the best technique involves
spotting extreme volumes.
These signals are not frequent, but they are
reliable, showing that professional money
has stepped in and has taken an opportunity
to accept the selling – usually from weak
participants.
Volume Spread For VSA Indicator
One of the main benefits of volume is that
it’s a leading indicator, giving you early
signals when the price movement is going to
continue or reverse.
One of the main principles involving volume
is related to Wyckoff’s law of effort versus
result.
This provides an early warning of a possible
change in momentum.
Divergences between volume and price often
signal a change in price direction.
For example, when there are several high-volume
but narrow-range price bars after a substantial
rally, with the price failing to make a new
high, this suggests that we might have a change
in trend.
This indicator tells us whether the volume
is ultra high,high, low or average.
It’s called Volume spread for VSA.
It’s very easy to read volume using it.
Red means ultra high volume, Yellow – high
volume, Green – average volume and blue
– low volume.
You just need to focus on the red lines, because
these are the ultra high volume bars on the
chart.
The trading plan
Now, the scalping strategy involves fading
the ultra high volume.
Here’s the trading plan.
• The market is decreasing
• Then, it experiences a significant surge
in volume.
This is when an ultra-high volume bar appears.
• After you spot the ultra high volume,
you find the candlestick associated with the
surge in volume.
• Then you simply draw a channel, from the
candlestick’s high and low price
• In theory, the ultra high volume should
stop the price decrease.
• So, the plan is to fade the downward move,
and buy if and when the price goes on the
other side of the channel.
• Stop loss goes below the ultra high volume
candle and the minimum target is a risk to
reward ratio of 2.
But the profit potential is much higher, as
this might be the beginning of a new trend.
Ultra high volume + price action
When an ultra high volume bar appears, after
a down move, what sort of price action should
you expect?
In the best-case scenario, it spots the end
of a short term bear trend.
In this case, the signal will potentially
lead you into the start of a bull trend.
And at the same time, a lot of trend traders
will be trapped on the down side.
At times, instead of preceding a bullish reversal,
it pushes the market into a trading range.
And, of course, there’s also the possibility
that the market will continue to decrease
despite the signal, implying powerful bearish
momentum.
That’s why, to filter bad trades, it’s
better to draw the channel on the ultra high
volume candlestick, and trade when there’s
some sort of activity to the upside.
Narrow Spread Candles + Ultra high volume
A narrow spread candle should have low volume.
However, the ones that are of high or ultra
high volume are special.
This should instantly alert you.
If you have a down candle with a narrow spread
and ultra high volume, then the market is
showing some signs of strength.
As we know, high volume should result in a
wide spread candle, not a narrow spread.
Effort vs result.
Wyckoff.
The sellers are starting to struggle at this
price level.
Equally, if we see ultra high volume on an
up candle then the reverse applies.
Here, the buyers are starting to see signs
of bearish sentiment enter the market.
The candle is narrow, with sellers coming
in, and supporting the market at this level.
Again, this is the first sign of a potential
reversal from bullish to bearish.
Future price action will confirm or invalidate
this premise.
A downward breakout, below the ultra high
volume candlestick is your confirmation to
enter short.
We trade Visa on the 1-min time frame.
I see a range after the market opened and
another down leg.
As price was traded at the previous support,
we see not one, but 2, ultra high volume bars.
And there are narrow spread bars.
By spread, I mean the difference between the
high price and the low price of the candle.
We have our channel, which is right at the
support, the ultra high volume after a down
leg, and 2 narrow range bars.
If price breaks the upper side of the channel,
the plan is to go long.
Stop loss goes below support.
We target the next major swing in price structure.
That’s a risk to reward ratio of around
2.2.
Remember we are scalping, so we want to get
in, with a narrow stop loss, and get out quickly.
When you trade the 1-min time frame, you will
find many ultra high volume bars, but you
won’t trade each signal you see.
Focus on volume bars which stand out.
Here we see a potential signal.
We have an up leg, an ultra high volume bar
and a narrow candle.
A break below the channel, with a very small
stop loss, targeting the previous swing low
offers a decent risk to reward ratio, of around
2.
We have another signal, this time a potential
long trade.
I see a potential double bottom, and an ultra
high volume bar, on a narrow spread up bar.
This isn’t a text book example, because
this is a green candle, and not a red one,
but we are still in a down leg, so if price
is breaking above the high of the candle,
I’ll still risk a long trade.
Which indeed happens.
Stop loss below the most recent swing low.
Take profit at the next major swing.
That’s a risk to reward ratio of around
2.5.
We’ll use the same 1-min time frame, on
euro-yen.
We have a minor uptrend and this is our ultra
high volume bar, which appeared on an average
spread green candle.
The plan is to go short below the channel,
if price breaks it.
And here’s our breakout.
Stop loss above the channel, and take profit
a few points above this support level.
A risk to reward ratio of around 2.
We move to pound dollar.
We see an ultra high volume bar at the London
open.
The candlestick is a high spread one.
So this is a high effort, high result situation.
Not the stopping volume we want to trade.
This looks more like a continuation than a
reversal.
But if price breaks below the channel, we’ll
still risk a trade.
Price indeed went higher, and consolidated
above the channel.
So this was a no trade in the end.
We have another potential signal here.
I see a triple top, a major resistance and
a break of structure right here, which signals
that sellers might be interested in pushing
the market down.
If you saw my previous video regarding the
break of structure, you know this is a perfect
opportunity to short the market.
The signal came after the breakout of this
candle.
Stop loss, as usual, above the channel and
above this previous high.
As a side note, it gives me more confidence
when I see that the signal appeared at a major
intraday resistance.
Take profit at the next swing low in the price
structure.
Again, a risk to reward of around 2.
Again, you are scalping.
And if you’re trading on the 1-min time
frame, there will be lot of noise.
And many ultra high volumes, which might confuse
you.
If you’re using Tradingview, the 3-minute
time frame is a decent alternative to filter
signals.
In this example, we see an intraday downtrend,
and an ultra high volume bar.
The signal appeared at a support level, so
this is an opportunity to scalp a few points,
on the long side.
Price breaks the upper level of the channel
and this is our signal to enter.
Stop loss below this swing low, or below the
low of the day.
And we target this swing high.
Unlucky, we lost this one.
The main limitation of this strategy involves
the market noise.
To reduce it and to reduce false signals,
I advise you to trade ultra high volume candles
during active market hours.
For example, if you’re trading Forex, most
pairs are traded the most between the time
the London trading session begins and when
the US sessions ends.
Volume patterns you see form during low activity
periods,during Tokio session for example,
have a lower probability of working out successfully.
If you trade stocks, you’ll usually see
several ultra high volume candles, right at
the New York open.
I would advise you to avoid trading during
the first 30 minutes, after the open, if you’re
not experienced, and try to find volume spikes
when volatility turns down.
And I’ll say it once again: location of
the signal is very important.
Look for volume spikes around support and
resistance levels, supply/demand areas, Fibonacci
levels or near VWAP or common moving averages.
These are the high probability signals which
will bring you profits.
As always, if you learned something new, drop
a like to show your support.
And check out our Academy program, if you
want to further level up your trading.
Until next time.