most traders are familiar with
traditional moving average studies such
as the simple moving average or the
exponential moving average
and there's nothing wrong with these
indicators but if you want more accuracy
and less lag you can take a look at the
double or triple exponential moving
average
the double and triple emas are an
improvement over the traditional
exponential moving average because they
allocate more weight to recent data
points the reduced lag results in a more
responsive moving average which helps
short-term traders to spot price
reversals faster
the double ema was developed in order to
reduce the lack of traditional moving
average indicators and to provide more
timely entries
the double ema is more responsive to
recent price data since moving averages
tend to be lagging indicators they can
generate somewhat delayed trading
signals
the double ema tries to address this
disadvantage present with all moving
average studies
here's a price chart with several moving
average studies the red line represents
the 50 period simple moving average line
the blue line represents the 50 period
exponential moving average and the
yellow line represents the double ema
line
notice how the double ema hugs the price
action better than both the simple
moving average and the exponential
moving average we can observe that the
double ema is closest to the price
points and with the least deviations
since the double ema line mimics the
prices most closely it is therefore most
sensitive to the market volatility
the double exponential moving average
has a somewhat complicated formula
behind it
essentially the double ema indicator is
a combination of single and double
exponential moving averages that results
in another exponential moving average
the dima indicator is named so because
it uses an ema of another ema and not
because it uses two exponential moving
averages you don't need to memorize this
formula to implement a double ema you
just need to know that it will provide
earlier entry opportunities since it is
more sensitive and more responsive to
recent price action
here are two double emas on the sim
daily chart the red line is the 50 days
dima which is significantly detached
from the price compared to the 10 day
dimma which is the yellow line the lower
the number of days of the moving average
the higher the effect of the last data
point will be
and the lesser the number of days used
to calculate the moving average the
higher the volatility of that moving
average will be
so dima of a lower number of days will
be more volatile and will incorporate
the price changes more accurately
what's the difference between the double
exponential moving average and that
triple exponential moving average
essentially the triple ema utilizes a
triple smooth exponential moving average
along with a single and a double
smoother dmas
there's no need to know the exact
formula of the triple ema you just need
to understand that this indicator will
be even more sensitive to recent price
action than the double ema
here's a price chart that shows both the
dima and team indicators
the double ema line is shown in yellow
and the triple ema line is shown in red
it's obvious that the triple ema reacts
to price changes quicker than the double
ema line for this reason triple
exponential moving average is very well
suited for short-term trading due to its
more sensitive
nature how to trade using dima and team
indicators
first method trend analysis
without knowing what the current market
environment is it will be difficult to
consistently beat the market that's why
you need a method for identifying
whether the market is trending or not
although you can often glance at a price
chart to get an idea of what the general
trend of the market is you could apply a
more objective measure for defining the
current trend using double or triple
emas
the direction of the double or the
triple ema is the direction in which the
prices are expected to move in the
future
rising moving averages signifies a
probable rising price
whereas falling moving averages
signifies a probable price fall
when the price is trading above the
double or the triple ema and the line is
sloping upward then we can say that the
trend is up
when the price is trading below the
double or the triple ema line and the
line is sloping downward then we can say
that the trend is down
and finally when the price is trading
sideways and the moving average appears
relatively flat then we can say that
there is no trend in place or that there
is no clear direction currently in the
market
[Music]
number two dynamic support and
resistance analysis
there are two main types of support and
resistance levels in the market fixed
and dynamic
fixed support and resistance represents
levels that are static or based on a
particular price level
the second class dynamic support and
resistance levels can change with each
new bar that prints on the price chart
the double and triple ema indicators can
be quite useful in finding levels of
support within uptrend or levels of
resistance within a downtrend
when price moves away from these
indicators to the upside and then pulls
back towards the ema line it often
creates an area of support
when prices move away from the ema
indicator to the downside and then pulls
back towards the line that interaction
can create an area of resistance
very important this movement depends on
the proper look back period for the
moving average
if you plan to use the double or the
triple ema indicator for finding dynamic
support and resistance areas the moving
averages should have already provided
support and resistance in the past
if the indicator didn't provide support
or resistance in the past it probably
won't be doing this in the future
[Music]
number three entry trigger
the simplest method would be to wait for
a price crossover from below to the
upside of the double or the triple ema
line to signal a long entry
and you could wait for a price crossover
to the downside of the edema or the
timon line to signal a short entry
one of the most commonly used signals
produced by moving averages is when a
shorter term ema crosses above or below
a longer term moving average
the shorter term moving average crossing
above the longer term moving average is
considered a bully signal
whereas a cross below is considered a
very signal
the choice of length of the two moving
averages is important when monitoring
crossovers
a short to medium term crossover may
employ a 10-day and a 50-day moving
average while a longer-term system may
employ a 50-day and a 200-day moving
average
since moving averages are lagging
indicators keep in mind that a crossover
signal may come very late in the new
trend and this lightness is increased as
the length of the moving averages
increases
moving average crossovers are best used
when a strong continuing trend is
present and when confirmed with other
elements
moving average crossovers can also be
used as a system of free moving averages
in this case a bully signal is triggered
when a medium-term moving average is
above a long-term moving average and the
short-term moving average crosses above
the medium-term moving average
a berry signal is triggered when the
longer-term moving average is above the
medium-term moving average and the
short-term moving average crosses below
the medium-term moving average
[Music]
so
because moving averages in general lack
the price you can use other tools to
filter your signals one good filter is
volume the idea of this strategy is to
take signals that include high trading
volumes
as you probably know the market is
trending when volumes are high
during low volumes prices are likely to
range or not trend this means that low
volumes are the major causes for the
sideways price action for this reason
double or triple exponential moving
average signals which appear during
lower trading volumes tend to fail
using this approach it's better to enter
the market only when prices crosses
through the dima or team indicators when
trading volumes are high
in this example we added the 50 period
triple ema and at the bottom of the
chart we added our volume indicator the
chart starts with a range consisting of
light volume notice that for the crosses
beneath and above the triple exponential
moving average we ignored the signals
because of the light volume
as volume begins to increase the price
forms a bigger bullish candle and at the
same time the price begins to move above
the triple exponential moving average
and the price continues higher on high
volume
besides volume i mostly pay attention to
the slope of the moving averages
mainly the direction of the double or
the triple ema is angled indicates the
short-term price direction
when the line is sloping up that means
that the price is moving up
when it's angled down the price is
moving down
there is still a small amount of lag in
any heater so when prices changes
quickly the indicator may not change its
angle immediately
[Music]
double and triple exponential moving
averages tend to work well in trending
markets but provide little insight when
the market is choppy or range bound
during such times the price will
frequently cross back and forth across
the lines
also the reduced lag of the double and
triple ema can be good in some scenarios
like when the actual price reversal
occurs because gets you out of the trade
quicker yet reduced lag can also result
in over trading
double and triple exponential moving
averages provide more signals than a
traditional moving average for example
if you don't choose the correct length
for the moving average the indicator can
tell you to close your position when the
market makes only a minor move against
you you close your position only to
watch the price continuing in its
original direction
sometimes lag is good and sometimes it
isn't it depends on what you want from
the indicator that's why choosing the
correct length is very important
it's up to you to find the balance and
determine exactly how much lag works for
you
as always if you learned something new
and found value give us a like to show
support subscribe to our channel and
click the bell icon to stay notified
every time we upload a new video
until next time