If you want to start trading or get back to
what actually works, master this strategy.
It's built for beginners, but every profitable
trader uses these exact principles. Here's the
foundation everyone needs. The Language
of Price: Internalizing Market Structure
I used to be one of those traders with a
Christmas tree chart – 10 different indicators,
all blinking and beeping like a damn
casino. I thought I was a genius...
But here's the brutal truth: all those
indicators are just fancy ways to lose
money faster. The only thing that matters
is learning to read the market's language.
This is called market structure and it's
built on one simple thing: swing points.
These are the obvious highs and
lows price makes as it moves.
A swing high is a candle that's higher
than the candles on both sides of it.
A swing low is lower than the nearby candles.
Now, in an uptrend, the market makes a
series of higher highs and higher lows.
In a downtrend, it makes
lower lows and lower highs.
These are the building blocks of everything.
And these swing points aren't random. They're
the market's way of telling you who's in
control and when that control is shifting.
Let me show you the two most
important concepts you need to know.
First is the Break of Structure. This
is when price breaks a previous swing
high in an uptrend. It's the market's way of
saying "the trend is still alive and kicking."
Second is the Change of Character. This is when
price breaks the last major swing low in an
uptrend. It's the market's first warning
sign that the trend might be in trouble.
Watch this. We're in a clear uptrend,
making higher swing highs and higher
swing lows. Each time price makes a new
high, that's a Break of Structure —a
confirmation that buyers are still in control.
But look what happens here. Price makes a sharp
move down and breaks below the last swing low.
That's a Change of Character. The market just told
you that the trend structure is cracked.
This doesn't mean the trend is over,
but it means you need to be careful. The
character of the market just changed from
strong bullish momentum to potential weakness.
Here's the key insight: You want to trade with
the structure, not against it.
In a trending market with clean
Break of Structure patterns, you look for
entries in the direction of the trend.
But when you start seeing Change of Character
patterns, you either take profits or step aside.
This is how you read the market's
intentions while everyone else is
guessing. Most traders spend months figuring
this out. You just learned it in 2 minutes.
Context is King: Are You in a Trend or a Range?
Okay, so you can read basic structure. Now,
let me show you the most important decision you
must make before even thinking about a trade.
You have to identify the overall market state.
Before you even think about entering a trade,
you must answer one simple question:
Are you in a trend or a range?
This is the most important first decision
you'll make. Because different strategies
apply to trending markets versus ranging markets.
So how do you tell the difference? Here's the
dead-simple method that works every time.
Add a single moving average to your chart,
the 50 EMA. When price is above this
line, you have an uptrend bias. When
price is below, you have a downtrend bias.
But what about ranges? Watch this. The 50 EMA will
be flat, and price will be chopping around it.
Here's what most traders get wrong. They try
to force trades in every market condition.
But the professional waits for the right
context. If you're in a strong
uptrend, you look for dips to buy.
If you're in a range, you look
for bounces off the boundaries.
This single concept will save you more
money than any fancy indicator ever will.
Chart Setup for Clarity, Not Confusion
Look at this chaos. Most beginner traders
have charts that look like this. Ten indicators,
five different timeframes open at once,
and they wonder why they can't make a decision.
Most traders get wrong about chart setup. They
think more information equals better decisions.
But in trading, you need clarity, not confusion.
Your chart has one job: to
help you execute trades,
not to analyze the entire market. So we're going
to strip everything down to the essentials.
First, pick one market. I don't
care if it's euro dollar, Tesla,
or Bitcoin. Pick one and stick with it for your
next 100 days. You need to learn how that one
market moves before you start jumping around.
Next, you need exactly two timeframes. Not five,
not ten. Two. The 1-hour chart for
structure and the 5-minute chart for entry.
The 1-hour tells you the big picture. The
5-minute tells you when to pull the trigger.
Now, for indicators, you get one,
for now... The 50 EMA. That's it.
This line will show you trend direction.
The goal is to see price action clearly.
Price is the only thing that pays
you. Everything else is just noise.
The Only Two Levels That
Matter: Support & Resistance
Here's a question that will make you rich or keep
you broke: where do trades actually happen? Well,
they happen at specific price levels.
At support and resistance. These are
the only levels where the market actually
gives a damn. Everything else is noise.
And here's where 90% of traders
completely lose their minds.
They start drawing lines everywhere. A line
here, one there, trendlines going in every
direction like a spider web designed by a madman.
Remember this like your trading life depends
on it: the market only cares about two types
of levels: real support and real resistance.
First, forget everything you know
about drawing lines. These levels
aren't thin lines—they're zones. Areas
where price has repeatedly shown interest.
Look at this level. Price has touched it 2 times.
Each time, it bounced off this area. That's a
support zone. It's not a single price point—it's
a range of prices where buyers keep showing up.
But here's the part no one explains. Not
all support and resistance zones are created
equal. You need to understand the difference
between "fresh" zones and "tested" zones.
A fresh zone is one that hasn't been
revisited since it was created. These zones
often provide the strongest reactions.
A tested zone is one that's been hit
multiple times. Each time it gets
tested, it gets a little weaker.
Most traders keep trading the same tested
levels over and over, wondering why they're
not working anymore. You need to hunt for the
fresh zones that haven't been discovered yet.
And there's one more concept that changes
everything. Role reversal. When a strong support
level finally breaks, it doesn't just disappear.
It becomes a powerful new resistance level.
Watch this happen. We had a major support
zone. Price kept bouncing off it. Then,
it breaks through with force. Now watch what
happens when price comes back to test that
same level from below. Rejection! The old
support is now acting as new resistance.
Just by understanding these simple concepts,
you've already put yourself
ahead of 90% of traders.
Spotting the Traps - Liquidity and Inducement
Now I'm going to teach you something that most
traders learn too late. The market is designed to
take your money. It's not personal—it's business.
And the way it takes your money is
through liquidity hunting and inducement.
Let me ask you something. Where do you think
most traders put their stop-losses? Above obvious
highs and below obvious lows, right? That's
exactly what big market players is counting on.
These areas where stop-losses cluster are called
liquidity. And smart money hunt this liquidity.
Here's how it works. You see a resistance area.
It looks like a perfect short opportunity.
Where do you put your stop-loss? Above the
highs, of course. So does everyone else.
But smart money sees this differently. They
see all those stop-losses sitting above the
highs as an opportunity. They push price up to
trigger all those stops, collect the liquidity,
and then dump the market hard.
This is called inducement.
The market creates a seemingly
perfect setup to lure you in,
then traps you before making the real move.
Most beginners see this happen and think they
just got unlucky. But you're different, you’re
going to see it as a predictable pattern.
Here's the question that will save you thousands
of dollars: Where is the obvious trade? And where
would the stops for that trade be? Because
that's where the market will likely go next.
Let me show you this in action. We have a
perfect-looking support level. Most traders
see this and think "great, I'll buy the bounce and
put my stop below the low." But smart money sees
all those stops below the low as a target.
Watch what happens. Price comes down to
the support level, breaks through it
just enough to trigger all the stops,
and then immediately reverses back up. They
hunted the liquidity and then made the real move.
This is why most traders get stopped out right
before the move goes in their favor. They're
not unlucky—they're predictable. And in trading,
predictable equals profitable... for someone else.
High-Probability Zones: The Power of Confluence
Now we start building. The foundation is laid.
Let me show you how to find an A+ trading
location. This is a concept called confluence,
where multiple factors align to signal a powerful
opportunity. Most traders are one-dimensional.
They see a support level and they buy. That’s
it. They trade one reason and hope it works.
The smart approach is to wait for
multiple, independent reasons to
align at the same place and time.
Here's your first confluence model,
and it's going to be the backbone
of your entire trading approach.
You need your higher timeframe trend
plus a key support or resistance zone.
Let me show you exactly what this looks like.
On the 1-hour chart, we're in a clear uptrend.
Price is above the 50-EMA, making higher highs
and higher lows. That's your directional bias.
Now, price is pulling back to a
major support zone. But this isn't
just any support zone—it's one that used to be
resistance. Remember the role reversal concept.
So you have a higher timeframe uptrend meeting
a key structural level. This is confluence,
and it's where you start paying attention.
But here's the key—this confluence doesn't
mean you trade yet. That's amateur hour.
Professionals use confluence to narrow
down where they want to trade,
then they wait for confirmation.
This is the difference between hoping
and knowing. You're not hoping the level
holds—you're waiting for the market
to show you that it's going to hold.
That's one of the three key pillars of this
entire system. And we're just getting started.
The VWAP Magnet - Your Entry Anchor
Now let me show you a weapon that
institutional traders use as a daily benchmark.
It's called the Volume Weighted Average Price,
or VWAP and it's the true mean
price for the day, weighted by
volume—like the market's center of gravity.
Here's why this matters. When institutional
traders want to buy or sell large positions,
they use VWAP as their benchmark. They try to
buy below VWAP and sell above VWAP. This
makes VWAP act like a magnet for price.
So let me show you how to use this. Add VWAP
to your 5-minute chart. You'll see it as a
dynamic line that moves with price, but it's
much more responsive than a moving average.
Watch how price behaves around it. In a
trending market, price will pull back to
this line. It touches the VWAP, bounces off it,
and continues in the direction of the trend.
This is your entry anchor. Remember that
confluence zone we found? When price
pulls back to that zone, you're not just
looking for any entry. You're looking for
a specific test of the VWAP within that zone.
This is how you turn a good setup into a great
setup. You have your higher timeframe trend, your
key structural level, and now your institutional
benchmark all lining up in one place.
So the absolute A+ setup is when the
1-Hour trend is up, price has pulled back into a
1-Hour support zone, and on the 5-minute chart,
that pullback is now touching the VWAP line.
This VWAP test is the anchor for our entire
trade idea. It's the precise point
of interest within our broader zone.
But remember, this VWAP test is the
anchor, but it's not the entry signal.
The signal is a specific candle pattern
that confirms buyers are actually stepping
in right here, and I'll show you exactly
what that looks like in just a moment.
The Entry Myth: Setup vs. Signal
First, let's talk about a critical
distinction that trips up almost every
beginner. You see the price come down
to your perfect level—the 1-Hour support
zone, the 5-minute VWAP test. Everything
is aligned. The problem is, the amateur
trader gets excited and buys immediately.
They're buying at a location, hoping it holds.
But imagine if you waited for one final piece
of evidence, a confirmation that buyers
are actually present and fighting back.
The result is you would filter out
so many failed trades where the
price just slices right through the level.
This is the difference between a "setup" and
a "signal." The setup is the context. It's the
high-probability condition we've just defined:
a pullback to the VWAP that happens inside a key
higher-timeframe support zone, all while the main
trend is up. The setup tells you where to look.
The "signal" is the specific event on your
5-minute chart that tells you when to act. It's
the proof. It’s the footprint of buyers stepping
in and dominating sellers at that exact spot.
The professional waits for this perfect alignment.
The amateur buys the location and hopes.
You now understand the difference
between a location and a reason. Most
traders never learn this distinction.
The Outside Candle - Your Go-To Signal
Now I'm going to give you the most
reliable entry signal in your entire
arsenal. It's called the outside candle,
and it's the market's way of screaming
that the momentum has shifted.
A bullish outside candle is a large green
candle that completely swallows the body
of the previous red candle. It's the market’s
way of saying that buyers are now in control.
A bearish outside candle is a large
red candle that engulfs the body of
the previous green candle. It means
sellers just took over with force.
But here's the critical part. This
candle pattern is only valid when it
shows at your VWAP test. An outside candle
in the middle of nowhere is meaningless.
Let me show you this in action. We have
our perfect setup: uptrend on the 1-hour,
pullback to a key support zone, and
price testing VWAP. Now we wait.
Watch what happens here. This candle
completely engulfs the previous candle's body.
That's your signal. The market just told
you that buyers stepped in with force at
the VWAP level. This isn't hope—this is evidence.
And the size of the outside candle tells you how
strong the momentum shift is. A large candle with
high volume is like the market screaming. A small
candle is like the market whispering.
You want the market to be screaming
when you enter a trade. You want that
outside candle to be large, decisive.
This is your go-to entry signal. It's simple, it's
reliable, and it works in all market conditions.
Fibonacci Precision - Layering Your Targets
Now I'm going to show you how to add a third
layer of confluence to your system. We're going
to use Fibonacci retracements and extensions
to find precision entry and exit points.
The Fibonacci retracement tool helps you
identify where pullbacks are likely to end. The
most important levels are the 61.8% retracement,
also known as the "golden pocket."
When your VWAP test also lines up
with the 61.8% Fibonacci level, you have
triple confluence. Trend direction, VWAP,
and Fibonacci all pointing to the same level.
And here's where it gets really powerful. You
can use Fibonacci extensions to set logical profit
targets. The 1 61 and 2 61 extension levels are
where institutional traders often take profits.
Let me show you this system in action. We have
our uptrend, price pulls back to VWAP, and that
line happens to be right at the 61.8% Fibonacci
retracement. That's your perfect entry zone.
Now, instead of guessing where to take profits,
you use the Fibonacci extension tool. You draw
it from the start of the pullback swing, to the
end of it, and then back to the entry point.
This gives you a clear plan for where you
might take profits, instead of just guessing.
By combining Structure, VWAP, and Fibonacci,
you now have a three-layered confirmation
system for your entries and exits.
The A+ Setup Scorecard
You now have all the pieces, but I'm going to show
you how to put them together into a systematic
approach that eliminates all the guesswork.
I call this the A+ Setup Scorecard—your
quality control system that separates
opportunity from mediocrity.
Here's how it works.
Every potential trade gets scored on five
criteria. You don't take the trade unless
it scores at least four out of five points.
Point one: Is the 1-hour chart trending?
If price is clearly above or below the 50 EMA
with clean market structure, you get one point.
Point two: Is price testing a key
support or resistance zone? If your
pullback is happening at key level that has
proven its importance, you get one point.
Point three: On the 5-minute chart, is price
testing the VWAP inside that zone? If yes,
you get one point. No VWAP test, no entry.
Point four: Is there Fibonacci confluence?
If your VWAP test also lines up with the
61.8% retracement level, you get one point.
Point five: Do you have a clear outside
candle signal? If the market is showing
you strong rejection at your level
with conviction, you get one point.
This scorecard eliminates emotional trading.
You're not trading because you're bored or
because you feel like you should be in the
market. You're trading because the setup
meets your criteria like a checklist for success.
A five-point trade is perfection. A four-point
trade is excellent. A three-point trade is
average. Anything below three points is a pass.
Most traders take three-point trades and wonder
why they're not making money. You're going
to wait for four and five-point trades.
This is your filter for quality control.
Your One-Page Playbook
Let's lock this in. You
now have all the components. The final step is
to distill this entire strategy onto a single
page. This is your playbook. Your business plan.
Take a screenshot of a perfect five-point trade
setup. Print it out and put it next to your
monitor. This is your template for what to
look for every single day.
Below that screenshot,
write out your five-point scorecard
If you have four or five boxes checked, you take
the trade. If you have three or fewer, you wait.
This is your entire business plan for the next
100 days. Your only job is to
hunt for this single picture.