Today we’re gonna talk about day trading
using order blocks and how I use them in combination
with price action.
So, order blocks.
These are areas with significant volume orders,
typically placed by large trading institutions.
The key concept behind trading with order
blocks involves finding specific points in
the market where price has experienced a substantial
upward or downward movement.
A bullish order block is marked at a price
level where the market has displayed a strong
advance, indicating the presence of buying
pressure.
A bearish order block is identified when the
market has undergone a sharp decline, indicating
selling pressure.
The fundamental principle of order block trading
revolves around the notion that when the market
executes a swift and substantial move, the
smart money are unable to enter their entire
trade at once.
So, they strategically leave pending orders
to buy or sell within the order block zone,
anticipating that the market will retrace
back to that zone, allowing them to fill the
remaining portion of their trading position.
A Bullish Order Block refers to the last downward
candle or series of downward candles that
occur before an upward impulse in price.
It serves as a support level that pushes the
price higher.
These order blocks signify the presence of
buy orders from institutional traders and
banks, essentially representing an accumulation
of orders at that specific price level.
A Bearish Order Block is the last up candle
or series of up candles before a downward
impulse in price.
And it will act as a resistance.
These order blocks indicate the presence of
sell orders from institutional traders and
banks, representing a distribution of orders
at that particular price level.
When the price eventually breaks out of an
order block, it often retraces back into its
range.
This retracement offers you a chance to enter
trades within the order block range, taking
advantage of the potential market orders that
are expected to be executed.
A significant part of traders struggle when
it comes to effectively trading these zones,
and one of the key factors at play is liquidity.
Liquidity is the ability to buy or sell something
without causing a large price change.
When a large player enters the market with
a market order, it immediately removes liquidity
from the market because he is demanding an
immediate execution of his trade.
His market order is then matched with someone
who has a pending order to sell.
If the market order is bigger in size than
the opposing pending order, what will happen
is part of the market order will be filled,
but the rest will remain unfilled.
So the market must move higher in order to
seek out additional pending orders, to fill
what remains of his market order.
Essentially, this implies that pending orders
contribute liquidity to the market since they
are the orders against which market orders
are matched.
These pending orders act as a buffer, providing
opportunities for market orders to be executed
without causing significant price disruptions.
As a retail trader, your trade sizes are typically
not large enough to significantly impact market
prices, so you rarely need to worry about
the placement and execution of our trades.
But for large institutions however, getting
in and out of trades can be a big problem.
Given the substantial size of the trades they
enter, professional traders face the challenge
of minimizing their impact on the market price.
Therefore, one of their primary goals is to
find areas in the market where there is ample
liquidity.
And these pockets of liquidity are often located
at levels where retail traders have placed
their stop losses.
The reason why stop hunts are seen frequently
in any market is down to professional traders.
They are strategically placing large trades
with the intention of pushing the price into
the stop loss zones.
When it comes to order block trading, one
common rule is to consider how long the market
has been away from a particular zone.
It's believed that the longer the market stays
away from an order block, the higher the chance
of a successful trade when it eventually returns.
However, this belief is actually incorrect.
Think about it this way: if a bank places
an order to buy or sell when the market returns
to an order block, do you think they would
wait around for a long time for this to happen?
No, they want to act quickly to seize the
opportunity.
Let's compare older order blocks with more
recent zones.
It’s clear that trading in recently created
zones tends to be more profitable than trading
in zones that were created a long time ago.
In simpler terms, it's better to focus on
recently created order blocks because they
have a higher chance of resulting in successful
trades.
Just imagine if you had traded these recent
order blocks I marked on the chart.
Each zone would have given you a decent trade.
But if you had traded the older zones, the
success rate is much lower.
So here's the key takeaway: when the market
quickly returns to an order block, there's
a higher chance of getting a successful trade.
On the other hand, older blocks don't usually
work out well, so it's better to focus on
zones that have been created recently.
Another order block rule says: "The stronger
the move away from an order block, the higher
the chance of a strong move when it eventually
returns."
Basically, if you mark an order block on your
charts and there was a big move away from
it, the likelihood of having a successful
trade in that zone depends on how significant
the move was.
But here's the thing: the strength of the
move out of the zone doesn't really determine
the success of the trade.
Many times, you may have placed a trade at
an order block with a strong move away, only
to see the market go straight through it when
it returns.
This has happened to me too, and I used to
base my entries on this idea.
The truth is, the strength of the move away
doesn't necessarily indicate how strong the
order block is.
Even though common teachings would consider
this a strong area, as you can see, the market
can easily break through without stopping.
So, it's important to understand that the
strength of the move away from an order block
doesn't guarantee a successful trade, and
you shouldn't solely rely on it when making
trading decisions.
So how do you determine which order blocks
are stronger than others?
The best order blocks must include a liquidity
run, and a break in market structure or change
in character.
In this example, whoever brought when the
market was down here had a lot of money at
their disposal.
As a trending movement increases in length,
more and more people begin trading in the
same direction.
Look at the last down swing before the bullish
order block is created.
At the time of this drop a lot of traders
are beginning to go short expecting lower
prices.
In order for the market to be able to move
up from here, someone needs to come into the
market and buy from all the traders who are
going short.
This would take a huge amount of money.
Look at this obvious liquidity run, taking
stops below this level and triggering new
sell positions.
This is the first condition.
The market eventually stops falling lower
and begins advancing higher, breaking above
the previous lower high, making a higher high.
This is a change or character.
The second condition.
This bullish order block has a very high probability
of giving you a successful trade, not because
it has a strong move away, but because we
know whoever brought down here creating the
zone has invested a lot of money into the
market.
So we first had a liquidity run, a change
of character, with the order block forming
between these 2 phases.
When price returned to this area, that was
your chance to enter, with the smart money
positions on your side.
Take a look here.
First we have a significant uptrend which
is very obvious, then we have a strong, near
vertical move down.
This move down tells you that smart money
entered the market and absorbed all the buy
orders from the traders going long into the
uptrend.
Look at the obvious liquidity run, taking
stops above this level and trapping buyers
on the wrong side.
And as I said, the order blocks which have
the highest probability of working out successfully
are the ones that trigger a break of structure
of a change of character.
In this case, we have a change of character.
Which is right here.
The price broke below this previous higher
low, forming a new lower low.
A bearish order block created after the market
has been going up for a long duration of time,
and which includes a liquidity clear-out and
change of character, has a much better chance
of working out profitably.
In this example, we can see a bullish order
block formed after the market has been falling.
We have lower lows and lower highs, and a
break of structure here.
A large percentage of retail traders entered
into short trades at this point which meant
there was a lot of profit to be made by the
banks if they came into the market and caused
a reversal.
When banks enter into their long trades, they
consume all the sell orders coming into the
market and the price begins to increase, eventually
breaking the swing high found at the top of
the last move lower.
The previous break of structure was in fact
a liquidity run.
And this is the change of character.
Both of our conditions were met.
Soon after the break of the high we see another
drop taking place.
This drop causes a lot of retail traders to
start shorting again, believing the move higher
was simply just a pullback to the downtrend.
When the market comes into contact with the
order block which was created by the first
round of buying, smart money will buy again
to get more trades placed in the direction
of the reversal.
If the banks didn’t buy and the market fell
below the order block then they would be put
at a loss on their positions and would have
to liquidate their buy trades.
In this example, we spot a bearish order block.
The market had a significant move up, followed
by a liquidity run that hits stops above this
particular area, triggering new buy positions.
After the liquidity run, the market starts
declining, breaking below the previous higher
low.
This is the change of character.
The bearish order block forms between these
two phases.
This area has a high probability of being
successful.
When the price eventually revisits the order
block, it provides a chance to enter a short
position, in line with the smart money positions.
Another example.
The market shows a bearish order block after
a significant uptrend.
As the banks enter their short trades, they
absorb all the buy orders in the market, causing
the price to decline and eventually break
the previous swing low.
The previous break of structure was a liquidity
run.
Lower lows and lower highs are then observed,
and this is the change of character.
This indicates that big players entered into
short trades, providing a potential trade
if the price returns to the order block.
And as expected, a sharp drop takes place,
when the market revisits the order block created
by the first round of selling, as smart money
will sell again to reinforce the reversal.
Let's analyze another trade.
We had a previous downtrend where the price
consistently made lower lows and lower highs.
Now, pay attention to the first rally out
of the zone.
During this rally, we saw bullish large range
candles that pushed the market significantly
against the previous downward movement.
Here's the key: Those bullish candles indicate
that there was very little selling pressure.
It's unlikely that banks were placing sell
trades as the market rallied higher.
The rally also managed to break the most recent
swing high.
When you trade order blocks, the best advice
I can give you is to make sure that the zone
you're trading breaks a recent swing high
or low.
This break represents either a change of character
or a break in the market structure, aligning
with the current trend.
The reason why this change of character gives
the zone a better chance of working out, is
partly down to the retail traders who enter
into long trades on the candle which breaks
the swing high.
When the market breaches a high/low traders
using technical analysis will know a possible
trend change is taking place as the majority
of traders primarily use higher highs and
lower lows to determine current trend direction.
Another factor to keep in mind is the impact
of traders who find themselves stuck in losing
trades when the market fails to make a new
swing low.
Let me explain: When the market is close to
breaking below a swing low, breakout traders
place orders in advance at that low, anticipating
a breakout to happen.
Once the market moves below the low and triggers
their pending orders, they enter their trades.
However, when the price fails to continue
moving in the direction of the breakout and
starts moving in the opposite direction, these
breakout traders find themselves trapped in
trades that are no longer profitable.
At this point, often around the order block
area, these traders decide to close their
losing trades.
Now, here's the interesting part: When these
breakout traders start closing their losing
trades, a significant number of buy orders
come into the market.
This influx of buy orders actually contributes
to the upward momentum of the market.
Now, most of the traders who trade order blocks
try to predict where a movement will end instead
of trading in the direction of the movement
itself.
What these traders typically tend to do is
mark all the order blocks which the market
hasn’t encountered yet and wait for the
price to enter these zones before going either
long or short.
Usually these zones were created a long time
ago which means they don’t have a high chance
of causing a reversal anyway.
We talked about that.
Meanwhile, as these traders wait for the market
to hit these old zones, there are plenty of
new zones forming in the direction of the
current movement that they are ignoring.
Instead of being so fixated on predicting
where the entire market will reverse, you
would have more success if you focus on trading
order blocks that form in the direction of
the most recent high or low.
A new high or low in the trend, meaning a
break of structure, or a BOS, is a signal
that the current momentum is to the upside
or downside, by trading against this momentum
you are unnecessarily putting yourself at
risk of losing money because you’re trying
to trade against the trend.
Let's take a look at an example to illustrate
this point.
Imagine a trader who had already marked a
bearish order block on their charts before
the price made a new high.
However, when a bullish move occurred and
a new high was reached, instead of recognizing
it as a signal that the price wants to continue
moving higher, the trader decides to place
a short trade because he believes the order
block will cause a market reversal.
And, after reaching the marked area, the price
only experiences a small drop before breaking
higher again, forming another new high and
creating a bullish order block in the process.
When the market returns to this area, it triggers
another upward movement.
By always trading in the direction of the
most recent high or low, you give yourself
the best opportunity to have winning trades.
It's important to recognize the current momentum
and follow the direction indicated by the
most recent high or low, rather than trying
to predict reversals based solely on order
blocks.
Here another example of an order block after
a break of structure.
Remember what I previously said: the quicker
the price returns to the order block the more
likely you are to end up with a profitable
trade.
When the price moves up or down, forming a
trading zone, it's possible that banks and
large traders may have remaining trades that
they were not able to execute during that
initial movement.
In such cases, these market participants may
choose to take some profits off their trades
and manipulate the market to return to the
region where their remaining trades were intended
to be placed.
This allows them to enter the rest of their
positions into the market.
In this example, when the price shoots up
creating the order block and forming the BOS,
the banks still have a few more buy trades
left which they need to be placed.
To bring the price back into the trading zone,
banks may take some profits from their existing
buy trades.
By doing so, the buy orders that were supporting
the price are consumed, resulting in a downward
movement.
As the price falls into the region where the
banks initially placed their buy trades, they
leverage the new sell orders that have entered
the market due to the drop.
These sell orders are generated by traders
on lower timeframes who are selling in response
to the price decline.
The banks utilize these sell orders to facilitate
the execution of the remaining buy trades
they intended to enter into the market.
Let's consider another instance of an order
block following a break of structure.
In this particular example, we see the price
moving down, creating the order block and
forming the break of Structure (BOS).
If the banks still have some sell trades remaining
that were not executed when the price initially
formed the order block, they will book some
profits from their existing sell trades and
manipulate the market to move back into the
area where their trades were intended.
So to entice the price to rise into the order
block zone, the banks may take partial profits
from their sell trades.
Once the price reaches the region where the
banks initially placed their first sell trades,
they utilize the newly emerged buy orders
from traders on lower timeframes, who entered
buy positions due to the upward movement.
These buy orders assist the banks in executing
the remaining of their sell trades.
You can see how the banks strategically navigate
the market to maximize their trade entries
while maintaining control over price movements.
When I started trading order blocks, I used
to enter trades by placing pending orders
at the zones, which is a common approach in
many trading methods.
However, I discovered that using pending orders
at the order blocks often resulted in losses.
The market would often disregard the zone
and continue moving strongly in the opposite
direction, causing my trades to fail almost
immediately.
Many times when I first began trading these
zones, I found many order blocks which met
all the criteria, but when it came to trading
these zones with pending orders most of the
time the market would just blow past the zone
and I would almost instantly lose my trades.
One way is to navigate on lower time frames,
and try to find another OB or a break of structure
or a change of character.
And this is a valid way to enter.
Using candlestick patterns to enter trades
is another method.
I like to use pin bars and engulfing candles
as my trigger for entering trades at order
blocks.
The strongest price action setup you can use
in conjunction with order blocks is the engulfing
candle.
Engulfing candles, when found around order
blocks show you that bank traders have an
interest in making the market move away from
a zone.
The candle itself is the result of bank traders
entering into the market.
The way we would have traded this is by first
locating the order block on our charts, then,
when the market returns to the zone we will
switch to a lower time frame to see if an
engulfing candle appears, which we can use
as an entry trigger into our trades.
When switching to lower time frames to look
for trades I suggest you go no lower than
the 5 minute chart.
It's important to avoid going too low in time
frames, such as the 1-minute chart, as it
can generate many false signals.
Here we are looking at an order block on the
5 minute chart, we can see an engulfing candle
appears shortly after price entered the zone.
This is your trigger for entering the trade,
when you see this candle form.
While it's possible to enter trades using
the same time frame on which the order block
is identified, it is often beneficial to switch
to a lower time frame.
By doing so, you can reduce your risk and
potentially increase your reward.
If you chose to enter the market based on
the engulfing candle observed on this time
frame, for example, the distance between your
entry point and the stop-loss level would
be 20 pips.
However, if you switched to a lower chart,
and entered the trade based on the engulfing
candle seen there, your risk would be reduced
to only 10 pips.
By doing so, you have effectively decreased
the risk on the trade by 50%.
Over a series of 10 to 20 trades, this reduction
in risk can accumulate to a significant amount
of money saved or earned.
Furthermore, by entering the trade on lower
chart using the engulfing candle, you not
only decreased your risk but also you increased
the potential gain.
This is because your entry occurred right
at the beginning of the downward movement.
If you had traded based on the engulfing candle
seen on the higher time frame, you would have
entered the trade after the market had already
moved down slightly.
As a result, the potential profit you could
make from the trade would have decreased.
The two candles which make up an engulfing
pattern are directly linked to whether the
zone is likely to work out or not.
I want you to look at this engulfing pattern.
There’s two candles which make up this engulfing
structure.
The first is a small bullish candle and the
second is this bearish engulfing candle.
Whenever you see a small candlestick engulfed
by a large candlestick in an order block,
it’s a good indication that the market is
going to move out of the order block.
The first bullish candle makes retail traders
think the market is going up, so they begin
to buy.
And when the engulfing candle shows up and
pushes the market down really quickly, it
has the effect of putting the buyers under
intense pressure to close their positions.
This is the important bit, the aspect of how
time affects the actions of the traders.
If the bearish engulfing candle was small
and only just managed to engulf the small
bullish candle, the buyers would feel less
compelled to close their trades, the loss
they are in is small, therefore they would
be more willing to continue holding their
trades.
When the engulfing candle is big, the traders
are faced with a loss much greater.
This is the reason these types of engulfing
structures tend to work so well.
As the loss for traders who have bought increases,
they become more inclined to close their positions.
This action of closing their losing trades
can create a swift movement away from the
order block.
The other price action signal you’re able
to use when looking for entries into order
blocks is the pin bar.
Pin bars, as you should already know, show
a rejection is taking place in the market,
usually from a support and resistance level
or recent swing highs and lows.
Here’s an order block.
When price returns to the zone you will then
need to switch to a lower time frame to look
for a pin bar that you can use as an entry
trigger into your trade.
As you can see when the market enters the
zone it produces a bearish pin bar.
The way you would have traded this would be
to first wait for the pin bar to close, then
you place a trade sell trade using a market
order.
with the stop-loss placed above the high of
the pin.
In this example, we have a pin bar formation
on the 4-hour chart.
While you could potentially trade this setup
directly from the 4-hour chart, it is more
advantageous to decrease risk and increase
potential profit by scanning lower time frames
for additional pin bars.
Looking at the 30-minute chart, we can see
another pin bar within the same order block
zone.
It's interesting how this pin bar is actually
nested within the larger pin bar seen on the
4-hour chart.
To trade this setup, we would follow the same
approach as before.
We would enter a buy trade once the pin bar
has closed, placing our stop-loss order below
the low of the pin bar.