As a scalping trader, you should always test
different ways of trading to try and find
something that will give you a better edge
in your trades.
You shouldn’t be afraid to explore new approaches
that aren’t popular in the trading game
and trading with range bars is an approach
that is often neglected or ignored completely
by most of traders
Range bars belong to a type of chart that
is independent of time.
Unlike the more conventional chart types such
as the candlestick and bar charts, with range
bars, only the horizontal price level is plotted.
Time is redundant.
Range bars were designed by a Brazilian trader,
Vicente Nicolellis, back in the 90s.
Due to the volatility of the markets at the
time, he believed that price was the most
important aspect when analyzing an asset.
As the local markets at the time were very
volatile, Nicolellis became interested in
developing a way to use the volatility to
his advantage.
He believed price movement was paramount to
understanding and using volatility.
He developed range bars to take only price
into consideration, thereby eliminating time
from the equation.
As the name suggests, range bars are specifically
used to identify ranging price action and
trending price action.
Now, most of the existing trading platforms
have not yet incorporated the range bars as
one of the default chart types.
But there are a lot of workarounds including
on the mt4 trading platform.
You can find this type of chart on Tradingview
platform.
So how do range bars calculate price?
Range bars take only price into consideration;
therefore, each bar represents a specified
movement of price.
You are most likely familiar with viewing
charts based on time; for instance, a 30-minute
chart where one bar shows the price activity
for each 30-minute time period.
Time-based charts, such as the 30-minute chart
in this example, will always print the same
number of bars during each trading session,
regardless of volatility, volume or any other
factor.
Range bars, on the other hand, can have any
number of bars printing during a trading session:
during times of higher volatility, more bars
will print; conversely, during periods of
lower volatility, fewer bars will print.
The number of range bars created during a
trading session will also depend on the instrument
being analyzed and the specified price movement
of the range bar.
Range bars follow three simple rules
Each range bar must have a high/low range
that equals the specified range.
Each range bar must open outside the high/low
range of the previous bar.
Each range bar must close at either its high
or its low.
In this example we have a 10 pip EURUSD range
bar.
The high and low of each bar in this chart
is 10 pips.
A new range bar opens only when price closes
above or below the previous range bar’s
high or low.
Basically, a range bar is a bar that has the
same price increment and each bar closes either
at the high or the low, regardless of where
it opened.
So, if you want a range of 10 cents for a
stock, set your range to 10.
Every time the stock moves 10 cents up or
down in total for that bar, it will complete
the current bar and start a new one.
Time has no effect.
This can give you an edge in markets that
are moving sideways or are very flat.
How to set range bar size
Specifying the degree of price movement for
creating a range bar is not a one-size-fits-all
process.
Different trading instruments move in a variety
of ways.
For example, a higher priced stock such as
tesla might have a daily range of 20-30 dollars
or even more; a lower priced stock, such as
general electric might move only a percentage
of that in a typical day, maybe 30 or 40 cents.
It is common for higher priced trading instruments
to experience greater average daily price
ranges.
Let’s compare both tesla and general electric
with 10-cent range bars.
One-half of the trading session for tesla
can barely be compressed to fit on one screen
since it has a much greater daily range than
general electric, and therefore many more
10 cent range bars are created.
Tesla and general electric provide an example
for two stocks that trade at very different
prices, resulting in distinct average daily
price ranges.
It should be noted that while it is generally
true that high-priced trading instruments
can have a greater average daily price range
than those that are lower priced, instruments
that trade at roughly the same price can have
very different levels of volatility, as well.
While we could apply the same range bar settings
across the board, it is more helpful to determine
an appropriate range setting for each trading
instrument.
One method for establishing suitable settings
is to consider the trading instrument's average
daily range.
This can be accomplished through observation
or by utilizing indicators such as average
true range (ATR) on a daily chart interval.
Once the average daily range has been determined,
a percentage of that range could be used to
establish the desired price range for a range
bar chart
Another consideration is the trader's style.
Short-term traders or scalpers may be more
interested in looking at smaller price movements,
and, therefore, may be inclined to have a
smaller range bar setting.
Longer-term traders and investors may require
range bar settings that are based on larger
price moves.
For example, a scalper trader may watch a
10-cent (.01) range bar.
This would allow the trader to watch for significant
price moves that occur during one trading
session.
Conversely, an investor might want a one dollar
(1.0) range bar for the same asset.
This would help reveal price movements that
would be significant to the longer-term style
of trading and investing.
Now, do not confuse range bars with renko
charts.
At a first glance, it is easy to find some
similarity between a renko bar and a range
bar.
In fact, there is something common between
these two chart types.
They are both independent of time and focus
on price alone.
However, that’s where the difference ends.
In range bars, every bar is of the same length
(including reversals).
In renko bars, every bar is of the same length
(including reversals, but price must travel
two times the renko bar in the opposite direction).
Trading with range bars
Range bars can help traders view price in
a "consolidated" form.
Much of the noise that occurs when prices
bounce back and forth between a narrow range
can be reduced to a single bar or two.
This is because a new bar will not print until
the specified price range has been fulfilled.
This helps traders distinguish what is actually
happening to price.
Because range bar charts eliminates much of
the noise, they are very useful charts on
which to draw trend lines.
Areas of support and resistance can be emphasized
through the application of horizontal trend
lines; trending periods can be highlighted
through the use of up-trend lines and down-trend
lines.
Range bar charts are perfect for scalping
strategies and that is because you can read
volatility better.
Volatility refers to the degree of price movement
in a trading instrument.
As markets trade in a narrow range, fewer
range bars print, reflecting decreased volatility.
As price begins to break out of a trading
range with an increase in volatility, you
must spend time observing a particular trading
instrument with a specific range bar setting
applied.
Through this careful watching, you can notice
the subtle changes in the timing of the bars
and the frequency in which they print.
The faster the bars print, the greater the
price volatility; the slower the bars print,
the lower the price volatility.
Periods of increased volatility often signify
trading opportunities as a new short trend
may be starting.
If you scalp the forex market for example,
and you seek to make 10 pips on a trade, wouldn’t
it be more useful to pull up a 10 pip range
chart?
Yes it would be.
Sounds logical.
A 10-pips range bar would not take the time
factor into account, instead, it would reflect
the price movement completely, which is exactly
what we need.
Once the currency trade moves outside the
10 pip range, another candlestick will form,
no matter how many minutes or seconds this
may take.
The ability to exclude the market noise, is
the cornerstone of success in trading in the
financial markets.
Range bars will help you to see the true picture
of what really happens with the price of the
traded financial instrument.
Independent of what indicators you use, range
bars will become a perfect supplement to the
trading methods you use, since they react
to the market changes much faster.
This video was basically an introduction to
range bars, but in the future, we’ll go
deeper and build some trading strategies,
based on range bars.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.