Heiken Ashi charts are very powerful when
combined with price action analysis.
The idea is simple: you look for the emergence
of new trends, or for the reversal of already
existing ones.
In today’s video I will share a trading
strategy I’ve been back testing lately with
promising results, strategy with is mainly
price-action based, using Heiken Ashi charts,
one exponential moving average and the rising
wedge pattern.
Heiken-Ashi candles essentially capture the
pace of price.
What I like about Heikin Ashi charts is that
candles don’t change colour until the trend
changes, and as a result, these charts generally
have longer runs of green or red candlesticks.
There is a tendency with Heikin-Ashi for the
candles to stay red during a downtrend and
green during an uptrend, whereas normal candlesticks
alternate color even if the price is moving
dominantly in one direction.
Another major advantage is that Heikin Ashi
charts provide much simpler interpretations
as there are not as many patterns as there
are with candlestick charts and the averaging
of the open and close prices means that trends
are easier to identify.
In essence, Heiken Ashi make trends easier
to spot and helps traders to remain longer
in trade.
Each of the Heikin Ashi bars start from the
middle of the bar before it, and not from
the level where the previous candle has closed.
This is a major factor between the standard
and HA candlestick patterns.
And this is important to know because in this
way, you filter noise, foreshadow reversals
and identify more easily classic chart patterns.
There are five primary signals that identify
trends and trade opportunities:
• green candles signify an uptrend
• green candles with no lower “shadows”
indicate a strong uptrend
• candles with a small body surrounded by
upper and lower shadows indicate a trend change
• red candles indicate a downtrend
• red candles with no higher shadows identify
a strong downtrend
The second component of the strategy is the
rising wedge.
The Rising Wedge is a bearish pattern that
begins wide at the bottom and contracts as
prices move higher and the trading range narrows.
While the rising wedge is mainly a reversal
pattern, this formation can also fit into
the continuation category.
As a continuation pattern, the rising wedge
will still slope up, but the slope will be
against the prevailing downtrend.
As a reversal pattern, the rising wedge will
slope up and with the prevailing up trend.
Regardless of the type (reversal or continuation),
rising wedges are bearish.
The rising wedge can be one of the most difficult
patterns to accurately recognize and trade.
While it is a consolidation formation, the
loss of upside momentum on each successive
high gives the pattern its bearish bias.
However, the series of higher highs and higher
lows keeps the trend mainly bullish.
What we need to identify is the final break
of support.
Also, the rising wedge chart pattern forms
when price consolidates between two converging
support and resistance lines.
In this case, the support and resistance lines
both have to point in an upwards direction
and the support line has to be steeper than
resistance line.
The third component of our strategy is an
exponential moving average, mainly to confirm
the wedge breakout that we intend to trade.
We will use an exponential moving average
because it exhibits a lower lag than a simple
moving average, which makes it better for
identifying how the price behavior may be
changing.
The choice of moving average length is largely
dependent on the time frame you’re analyzing
and your trading style.
A 50 EMA or 100 EMA are good potential averages
you could use.
With the addition of the exponential moving
average, you basically analyze price crossovers.
When you identify a wedge breakout, you want
to see price moving below the EMA, to confirm
the momentum shift to the downside.
The full strategy involves finding a rising
wedge pattern on a Heiken ashi chart, and
trade after the price breaks the pattern,
below the exponential moving average.
Here are the 10 main aspects of this strategy:
1.
Heikin-Ashi: Heikin-Ashi filters out market
noise and reduces small corrections making
the signals more transparent.
The smoothing effect makes it easier to find
our rising wedge pattern.
2.
Prior Trend: In order to qualify as a reversal
pattern, there must be a prior trend to reverse.
Sometimes the current trend is contained within
the rising wedge; other times the pattern
will form after an extended advance.
3.
Upper Resistance Line: It takes at least two
reaction highs to form the upper resistance
line, ideally three.
Each reaction high should be higher than the
previous high.
4.
Lower Support Line: At least two reaction
lows are required to form the lower support
line.
Each reaction low should be higher than the
previous low.
5.
Contraction: The upper resistance line and
lower support line converge as the pattern
forms.
The advances from the reaction lows (lower
support line) become shorter and shorter,
which makes the rallies unconvincing.
This creates an upper resistance line that
fails to keep pace with the slope of the lower
support line.
6.
Support Break: Bearish confirmation of the
pattern does not come until the support line
is broken in a convincing fashion.
As I said earlier, the breakout is the signal
we will use as our entry signal.
Once support is broken, there can sometimes
be a reaction rally to test the newfound resistance
level.
7.
Volume: Ideally, volume will decline as prices
rise and the wedge evolves.
An expansion of volume on the support line
breakout can be taken as bearish confirmation
signal.
8.
EMA breakout: After the market breaks down
through the lower support line, it should
also break below the EMA, and ideally should
remain below it.
9.
Profit Target: Usually, you should aim to
have a risk-reward ratio of 2 or more.
Rising wedges are said to have a price target
that’s equal to the widest distance of the
wedge.
You measure the distance of the wedge and
you project the distance on the breakout point.
10.
Stop Loss: Generally, you should place the
stop loss to give the market some room to
move.
False breakouts are quite common, and by giving
the market some extra room to play with, we
may avoid some of these!
The high of the wedge is a good start for
an initial stop loss, which could be moved
as the market makes lower lows.
Here an example of a rising wedge we found
on this Heikin Ashi chart.
- we have the prior uptrend
- the upper resistance line and lower support
line converged as the wedge pattern formed.
The slope of the lower support line is steeper
than that of the upper resistance line.
Less slope in the upper resistance line indicates
that momentum is weakening as the price makes
new highs.
- the price tested the support line before
finally breaking with a sharp decline.
The previous reaction low was broken after
this Heikin ashi candlestick
- volume decreased before the support line
was broken.
And there was an expansion of volume after
the breakout, which is a good sign that the
market has shifted to the downside
- entry below the breakout point with a price
target that’s equal to the widest distance
of the wedge
- and stop loss above the high of
the wedge.
Another effective confirmation is a bearish
divergence on a momentum indicator.
The rising wedge pattern in an uptrend signals
exhaustion of momentum.
You can confirm this exhaustion in another
way, when a technical indicator will disagree
or “fight” with the actual price action.
A divergence appears when a technical indicator
(like RSI,MACD, Stochastic) begins to establish
a trend that disagrees with the actual price
movement.
The disagreement or divergence between bullish
price action (higher highs) and the trend
of the oscillator (lower highs) is another
clue that the market could go down.
If in
the
previous examples, we traded the setup as
a bearish reversal pattern, we can also trade
it as a bearish continuation pattern.
In this case, the price came from a downtrend
before consolidating and forming higher highs
and even higher lows.
As a continuation pattern, the rising wedge
will still slope up, but the slope will be
against the prevailing downtrend.
During the formation of a rising wedge during
a downtrend, there are the same clues that
can be used to determine whether the pattern
is worth trading:
- the upper resistance line formed with minimum
2 successive higher peaks.
- the lower support line formed with minimum
3 successive higher lows
- price contraction with the slope of the
lower support line steeper than that of the
upper resistance line
- the volume declining as price was rising.
And an increase of volume after the support
line breakout
- and additionally, you could look for a divergence
on a momentum oscillator
There are many false patterns or patterns
in disguise that may come off as a rising
wedge.
That’s why we are using Heikin Ashi charts,
instead of traditional candlesticks, to eliminate
noise on the chart and keep the dominant trend
in display.
In addition, the other way to differentiate
a true rising wedge from a false one is by
finding price/volume divergences.
When the breakdown does happen, you have the
green light to go short.
Here are several example of valid trades.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and click
the bell icon to stay notified every time
when we upload a new video.
Until next time.