99% of traders use time-based charts for their
technical analysis.
But in recent years, another chart is becoming
more and more popular among day traders and
scalpers, as it provides a different perspective
on trading than traditional time frames.
In today’s video we’ll discuss about tick
charts, and I will explain how you should
use them to find better entries in your trading
strategies.
Tick charts are very simple to use and very
effective when measuring market momentum and
trend strength.
This type of charts is especially useful for
short-term traders, being often used in scalping
and day trading strategies.
So, what Are tick charts.
Well, the bars on the tick charts are plotted
based on a particular number of transactions.
For example, if we have a 200 tick chart,
each bar measures 200 trades per bar.
After 200 trades are completed, a new bar
plots.
Now very important, a single transaction could
include 1 contract, or 50 contracts, for example.
The number of trades is what determines the
creation of a new tick on the chart, not the
number of contracts.
This is a very common confusion with tick
charts.
So, tick charts are not measuring the true
number of contracts traded.
It’s actually the number of transactions
made between traders, of varying contract
sizes.
With tick charts, the time element is removed.
If you are trading on traditional charts,
you have limited options.
With tick charts, you can backtest and choose
your own settings.
Some prefer charts with 50, 100 or 200, 1000
or 2000 ticks.
Others prefer to use Fibonacci numbers when
setting their number of ticks, like 21, 34,
55, 89, 144 etc.
Another approach would be to select the tick
number on your charts by comparing it to a
time-based chart.
For example, if you prefer day trading on
the 5-minute charts, you can choose a tick
chart looking similar to that chart, like
200 ticks for example.
If you prefer to scalp, charts with 50 or
100 ticks will probably suit you.
For day trading, 500 or 1000 ticks are the
most common used.
Of course, there is no best number of ticks
to trade with.
You just have to test different settings and
select the one that suits you.
Tick charts come with many advantages.
1.
Less Market Noise
As tick charts are transaction based and new
bars are formed only when there have been
enough trades, the market noise is reduced.
The noise is often represented by useless
candles, with no real value to the chart.
Plus, the wicks of the candlestick often induce
traders into error.
The higher the noise, the more difficult it
becomes to make intelligent decisions.
You practically lose sight of what’s important
on the chart and focus on unimportant elements.
The main advantage of a tick chart is that
compresses low-activity trading periods.
On the time-based charts, you may see 30-40
useless candles, while the tick chart may
offer you only 10-15 relevant ones.
Look at the difference.
We have these 2 trading range on the 5-minute
chart.
And see the difference on a 200-ticks chart.
The activity on the tick charts is more condensed.
This may potentially enable you to get a clearer
picture of overall price action.
2.
Better Analysis of Volatility
With tick charts, you will see a new bar forming
only when there have been enough trades completed
between buyers and sellers.
In times of high activity, tick charts plot
more bars.
This could signal an increased volatility.
Usually, when the market opens, the volatility
increases and tick bars occur quickly.
During the lunch hour, when the number of
trades decreases, the volatility decreases.
This is often reflected in the activity on
the tick charts.
During low activity periods, tick charts only
display a few bars.
This is a better measurement of volatility
because on the time-based charts you’ll
continue to see the less important candles.
Look at this example.
The first day was a low volatility day, with
few bars plotted on the tick chart.
The second and third days had a higher volatility,
with large price movements and a higher number
of bars.
This represents an important information for
a trader.
During the first day, a trader might skip
a signal occurring towards the end of the
trading session, knowing that the market volatility
for that day was low.
3.
Clearer Swings
Without the accumulation of small candles
like the ones on the time-based charts, tick
charts make it easier for the trader to spot
swings.
Also, while during high volatility periods
time-based charts may show only a long candle,
tick charts show several smaller candles.
In this way, tick charts provide traders with
more information about the recent market swings.
When the volatility increases, a tick chart
shows more price waves and traders are able
to identify proper support and resistance
levels.
Here we have a 1-minute chart, showing the
market reaction after a non-farm payroll announcement,
a powerful move in just a few minutes.
On a 50-tick chart, the large movement printed
several bars, more exactly a 3-wave downtrend.
A trader analyzing the tick chart had the
possibility to join the downward movement
after a small pullback.
The 1-min chart contained only 4 red candles,
all having wicks, to fool retail traders.
4.
Better Visualization of Breakouts
With tick charts, traders are able to spot
breakouts faster than using a time-based chart.
By using tick charts, traders can open a position
faster and, in most cases, at a better price
level.
Look at this example.
Let’s say you try to scalp a new swing high
on the 1-min chart, waiting to trade an upside
breakout.
The breakout finally occurs, but you wait
for the price to retrace to the former resistance
level and trade the retest.
But the pullback never came.
The market continued to go higher.
Despite the fact that you anticipated the
breakout and lost a lot of time waiting for
the setup, you missed a great trade.
And, here’s the same setup, on a tick chart.
We have the breakout and the chance to enter
long once the price retraced to the former
resistance level, which became support.
The tick chart allowed you to see the retest.
The red candle which followed the breakout
candle was visible on the tick chart, but
on the time-based chart wasn’t.
This little aspect made the difference between
a successful trade and a wasted opportunity.
5.
More Accurate Signals from Technical Indicators
When using tick charts, traders receive more
accurate signals from the technical indicators
they use, because the market noise is reduced,
so the signals generated by indicators have
more relevance.
Take a look at this 200-ticks chart, with
the Stochastic Oscillator added.
Look at the divergence signal visible on the
indicator when using tick charts.
Now, the same evolution, on a 5-minute chart.
As you can see, no divergence is shown.
Also, the choppiness of indicators is more
visible on time based charts.
If you compare the signals offered by time
based chart with the ones generated by the
tick chart you’ll see a slight difference.
6.
Better Measurement of Volume
A volume indicator plotted on a tick chart
will offer you a better understanding of the
strength or weakness of a price move.
The combination of tick charts and volume
could help traders to join strong moves and
avoid moves that show weakness.
The great thing about combining the use of
volume with tick charts is that each tick
bar is equal.
This allows you to see which price movements
are supported by high volume, and which aren’t.
It essentially tells you which trends are
supported by smart money, and which ones are
just retail money, making it likely to turn
over.
7.
Smaller and More Accurate Stop-Loss Orders
Tick charts can help you in placing better
stop-loss orders and take-profit levels on
the chart.
This is especially useful during periods of
high volatility and rapid price movements.
For example, when a market moves rapidly,
the tick chart may plot multiple price swings
which can be used for placing stops and profit
levels.
By using a time-based chart, you can place
orders taking into account only one-two bars.
Basicaly, when using time-based charts you
use slightly higher stop-loss orders, based
on the swings on the respective chart.
With tick charts, not only that you will be
able to see more waves and more entry points
to set your orders, but you will also use
smaller stop-loss orders.
Look at this chart.
If you want to scalp this up move, a stop-loss
of 30 pips is required to enter a trade.
That’s a big stop to be used on the 1-minutes
chart.
Now look at the same situation on the 50-ticks
Here you are able to buy the market at a much
better price.
Also you can place the stop-loss order below
the recent swing, at 20 pips distance, compared
to the 30 pips stop-loss order placed on the
M1 chart.
When you scalp, this 10-pip difference is
huge, and gives you a safety net to manage
your orders.
Keep in mind that tick charts come with several
limitations.
Tick charts can give you an advantage in day
trading, but they come at a cost as not many
platforms are offering free tick data.
Quality tick data can be really expensive
and not always is 100% accurate.
Also, if you have the chance to compare tick
charts from different data feeds, you may
notice that they differ.
Some data feeds contain errors and not all
ticks are included.
And this may affect your results.
Sometimes drastically.
Although it has many advantages over a candlestick
chart, a tick chart should be used as a complementary
tool.
Sure, you can use only tick charts in your
trading activity, but I recommend you to be
conservative and try to combine them with
the classic time-based charts.
This way, you have the full picture of the
market.
A common technique used by traders is to spot
trends and support and resistance levels on
the time-based charts and pinpoint the entries
on the tick charts.
This way you reduce the market noise, determine
the volatility and take the signals on the
tick charts while confirming the movement
with the help of time-based charts.
As always, if you learned something new and
found value, leave us a like to show your
support, subscribe to our channel and hit
the bell icon to stay notified when we upload
new videos.
Until next time.