Many traders are either unaware of the importance
of divergences or are unable to accurately
apply the divergence concept.
A divergence occurs when price and the indicators
provide conflicting signals by moving in opposite
directions.
If you spot such a situation, it could be
worthwhile taking a closer look at what is
really going on.
In today’s video we’ll talk about divergence
trading, and I will share 10 important rules
you must follow to profit consistently from
market divergences.
1.
Use the right indicators to spot divergences
Most of the technical indicators used to observe
divergences are momentum oscillators.
But some indicators are better to find regular
divergences, while other are suited for hidden
divergences.
From my experience, oscillators that are used
to determine whether a market is overbought
or oversold are more effective for spotting
hidden divergences.
Stochastic indicator and RSI are perfect to
find hidden divergences, which happens when
the technical indicator shows a new extreme,
but the corresponding price action does not.
For example, in this bullish hidden divergence,
the Stochastic makes a lower low while the
price make a higher low.
In essence, while the price is higher than
it was before, the indicator is lower, suggesting
the market is much more oversold.
In a hidden bearish divergence scenario, the
Stochastic makes a higher high while the price
makes a lower high.
Hidden divergences are also called continuation
divergences because are used to trade the
continuation of a trend.
For regular bullish and bearish indicators,
I found that MACD histogram and Money flow
index are very effective to find such patterns.
Bullish divergences are used to trade the
change in direction from a downwards move
to an upwards move.
They occur when price creates a lower low
and at the same time, the technical indicator,
MACD in this example, is making a higher low.
In essence, MACD is not following the price
down, suggesting the move lower is weakening
and losing momentum, resulting in a possible
move higher.
Bearish divergences are used to trade the
change in direction from an upwards move to
a downwards move.
They occur when price creates a higher high
and at the same time, the indicator is making
a lower high.
In this case, MACD is not following the price
up, suggesting the move higher is weakening
and losing momentum, resulting in a possible
move lower.
2.
Adjust the settings of indicators to identify
divergences more easily
For any given divergence indicator, there
will usually be different settings for different
markets and different settings for different
time frames.
Let’s say you prefer trading hidden divergences
with RSI.
Here, the first 2 RSI settings were able to
spot the hidden divergence, while the smoother
RSI, with the longer period, was unable to
find it.
So remember this: higher lookback periods
on indicators will not suit hidden divergences.
The same for regular divergences.
Larger settings will produce a higher lag.
Of course, there will be periods when market
volatility and momentum cycles will change
and the indicator settings you have been using
will be much less useful.
So you may need to slightly shorten or increase
the lookback period to find the optimal divergences.
3.
Only take divergences in the direction of
the main trend
With regular divergences, the oscillators
indicate momentum shift and thus, point toward
a reversal of the trend.
This implies that a regular divergence warns
the end of a trend is expected.
Hidden divergences signal momentum coming
into the main trend, suggesting a possible
continuation in the main direction of the
trend.
Now, the reason why so many traders fail when
taking divergence signals is because they
take counter-trend signals.
They spot a regular divergence and immediately
think the market will reverse.
A smarter way to trade divergences, is to
identify the main trend and find divergences
that go along with the trend.
In the case of an uptrend, you ignore bearish
regular divergences (those appearing on the
top of the oscillator) and search for bullish
regular divergences.
In addition, you also concentrate on bullish
hidden divergences.
In the case of a downtrend, you ignore bullish
regular divergences and search for bearish
regular divergences and bearish hidden divergences.
In this way, you have a higher probability
of a successful divergence trade.
4.
Always wait for price action confirmation
(trend line breakout)
While using divergences is a great tool to
have in your trading toolbox, there are times
when you might enter too early because you
did not wait for more confirmation.
And a divergence signal always needs a confirmation.
If you keep entering divergences too early,
you’ll keep getting stopped out and you’ll
slowly rack up losses.
The best confirmation is a trend line break
out.
When a divergence forms and the price starts
changing direction and breaks a trend line,
there is a higher probability the price is
going to reverse.
This example shows a bullish MACD divergence
with a confirmed trend line breakout.
So for better results, just wait for a trend
line breakout, or a support or resistance
breakout.
When you see price action breaking a major
level, it could signal a shift in power from
buyers to sellers (or vice versa) and that
a price reversal might occurring.
5.
Take divergence signals from support/resistance
levels
To avoid trade entries that don’t go anywhere,
I highly suggest you add other criteria and
confirmation tools to your arsenal.
Besides the trend line breakout, the location
of the divergence is very important.
Adding the filter of location can usually
enhance the quality of your divergence signals
and trades.
Instead of taking trades just based on a divergence
signal, you’d wait for the price to move
into a previous support/resistance zone and
only then look for divergences and trend shifts,
to time your entries.
In this example, you see an uptrend with two
divergences.
However, the first one completely failed and
the second one resulted in a massive winner.
What was the difference?
When we analyze the big picture, we see that
the first divergences happened in the middle
of nowhere and the second divergence formed
at a very important resistance level.
As a trader, you first identify your support/resistance
zones and then let price come to you.
Such an approach will impact your performance
in a big way.
6.
Confirm divergence signals using volume
Volume is one piece of information that is
often neglected by many market players, especially
the beginners.
However, learning to read volume brings many
advantages and could be of tremendous help
when it comes to analyzing divergences.
To correctly read the volume data, it must
be seen in the light of what the price is
doing.
So the implication of a trading volume depends
on the price movement.
If the price is rising in an uptrend, a divergence
is visible, but the volume is reducing, it
may show that there’s little interest in
the asset, and the price may reverse.
Similarly, when the price is rapidly declining
and forms a divergence but the volume is low,
it could mean that the institutional traders
are not interested in the price direction.
So the price might soon reverse to the upside.
A high volume after the divergence usually
indicates more interest in the asset and the
presence of institutional traders.
A divergence confirmed by a rising volume
represents one of the safest trades.
7.
Find confluence with common moving averages
No matter how appealing a divergence signal
is, don’t take the trade without confirming
the signal with some other type of analysis.
You can do this by using confluence.
Confluence forms in a spot where you have
more than one indication of where price will
go.
For example, confluence occurs where price
reaches a commonly used moving average.
If in that point, you see a divergence forming,
you confirm your direction with the moving
average, and you will have a stronger signal
and a higher probability of price going your
way.
Here is another example, when price touched
the simple moving average.
We have a hidden bearish divergence on the
RSI and the RSI reached overbought area.
8.
Use higher time frames to trade divergences
Divergence signals tend to be more accurate
on the longer time frames because you get
less false signals.
This means fewer trades but if you structure
your trade well, then your profit potential
can be huge.
Divergences on shorter time frames will occur
more frequently but are less reliable.
That is why I advise you to look for divergences
on 1-hour charts or longer.
Of course, there are many divergences on lower
time frames.
But, on those time frames, there’s just
too much noise and the probability of a divergence
to fail is higher.
9.
Use Ultimate Oscillator to trade multiple
timeframe divergences
The ultimate oscillator combines short-term,
intermediate-term, and long-term price action
into one oscillator and offers divergence
signals that might warn of future price reversals.
It basically measures momentum for three distinct
timeframes.
The second timeframe is double compared to
the first, and the third timeframe is double
compared to the second.
Even though the shortest timeframe carries
the most weight, the longest timeframe is
not ignored, which reduces the number of false
divergences.
The ultimate oscillator generates fewer divergence
signals than the other oscillators due to
its multi-timeframe construction, so the market
noise is greatly reduced.
Of course, while the multiple timeframe trading
method for the indicator may help eliminate
some poor trades, it also eliminates many
good ones.
Therefore, it is sometimes necessary to change
its settings to reduce sensitivity and increase
the number of signals.
10.
Don’t force divergence trades
When trading divergences, you must be careful
and precise with your entry point.
If you spot a divergence but the price has
already reversed and moved in one direction
for some time, the divergence should be considered
played out.
You missed the boat this time and it’s better
to stay aside and don’t force a late trade.
All you can do now is wait for another swing
to form and start over your divergence search.
Why?
Because if you enter late, you alter your
risk:reward ratio for the trade.
When trading divergences, the entry point
and risk/reward management are both important
aspects that any trader should become familiar
with.
If you miss a divergence entry, after the
price rejected a moving average for example,
and you decide to enter after the price already
moved a lot, you will have to increase your
stop loss, and if the trade doesn’t have
much profit potential, you will have a hard
time managing your trade.
Remember: there are always going to be other
divergence opportunities.
The key is to be patient.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like to show your support, make
sure you subscribe and click the bell icon
to stay notified when we release new videos.
Until next time.