The doji candle is one of the most famous
patterns followed closely by price action
traders.
A doji candle pattern appears when the open
price and close price for a determined period
are the same, or very close to being the same.
The lengths of the shadows can be different.
The perfect doji has the same open price and
close price, however, something must be considered.
If the difference between the open and close
prices is within a few ticks, this could also
be interpreted as a doji.
When you’re not sure if a candle should
be considered a doji or not, just follow the
recent price action.
If the previous candles had open and close
prices within a few ticks, then probably you
should not consider the current candlestick
as a doji.
If the pattern forms alone, that’s a valid
doji.
In this chart, we see several candlesticks
that could be interpreted as a doji pattern.
But, looking at the bigger picture and at
the price action as a whole, we should not
consider the candles as doji, as they offer
no relevance to the current trend.
As you can see, this interpretation is quite
subjective and there are no strict rules but
to look at recent price action.
A series of very small real bodies as in this
example would not be read as doji candles.
Another technique is based on recent support
and resistance levels.
If the market is at an important market support
or resistance and there are other technical
signals, the appearance of an uncertain doji
candle could be interpreted as a doji.
Looking at this example, we are at an important
level of support, tested several times in
the past.
The highlighted candle could be interpreted
as a doji pattern, as it formed near an important
level.
Now, how to read doji candlestick.
First, doji meaning market indecision.
One of the most important values of a candlestick
chart is the ability to read market sentiment.
A doji candle is the perfect example for reading
market sentiment.
This pattern is an outcome of indecision in
the market.
A doji candlestick suggests a lack of control
in the market either by the bulls or the bears.
The lack of direction is clear: bulls moved
prices higher, bears moved prices lower, but
in the end, the market price closed exactly
or very close to where it opened.
Now, if the doji candle highlights market
indecision, it is safe to say that it does
not offer insight into whether bulls or bears
are in control.
You have to guess the market’s next direction.
So, the first thing you should take note is
to use doji candle in combination with other
technical indicators or price action, never
on its own.
Doji candle meaning possible reversal.
Doji candle offers traders an early warning
that there may be a change in market momentum
or a possible change in direction if current
conditions don’t change.
Please remember that the “possibility”
of a change of direction does not represent
a guaranteed change of direction.
The truth is that we don’t know if a trend
is exhausted.
We don’t know the exact moment when the
trend is going to end.
A doji will not guarantee that a certain setup
will occur or that the market will reverse.
Traders incorporate doji in their analysis
in an effort to try to predict future price
movements.
They try to get the probabilities in their
favor as much as they possibly can.
So, a doji candle by itself is not significant
enough to predict a reversal in prices, it
represents only a warning of an impending
trend change.
Steve Nilson, the person that introduced candlesticks
to western traders, affirmed that doji candles
tend to be better at indicating a change in
trend when they occur at market highs instead
of at market lows.
This could be explained by the fact that for
an uptrend to continue, new buying power must
be present on the market, while a downtrend
could continue at full strength without becoming
weaker.
Doji pattern near support and resistance
Doji candles formed at relevant market highs
or lows can sometimes turn into support or
resistance areas.
When forms in the middle of a trend or trading
range, a doji candle has little significance.
Doji candles are commonly met during periods
of consolidation and can help traders to spot
potential price breakouts.
When it forms near round numbers or around
previous levels of support and resistance,
pivot points or Fibonacci retracements, doji
candles offer traders decent entry points.
There are five different types of doji candles:
The first type is the common doji.
A common doji is the candlestick pattern we
talked before.
A doji candle pattern appears when the open
price and close price for a determined period
are the same, or very close to being the same.
Next we have the gravestone doji.
A gravestone doji forms when the doji is at,
or very near, the low of the period.
As the upper shadow is quite long, this means
that the gravestone doji is a bearish pattern.
The bearish outlook of the pattern is evident:
the price opened and traded higher all the
period, but closed where it opened, which
also coincides with the low price for the
period.
Gravestone doji can also be interpreted as
a failed rally.
Traded by itself, this pattern is not profitable.
Just look at the picture above, the price
indeed declined after the appearance of a
gravestone doji, but not before taking some
stop-losses on its way.
That’s why it’s better to trade this pattern
near strong support and resistance levels
and in combination with other indicators.
Then we have the dragonfly doji.
The dragonfly doji forms when the open price
and close price are at the high of the period.
As this pattern has a long lower shadow this
means that dragonfly doji is a bullish pattern.
The bullish outlook of the pattern could be
explained as follows: the price opened and
traded lower all the period, but closed where
it opened, which also coincides with the high
price for the period.
This means that despite the selling pressure,
the bulls entered the market strong and pushed
the price back up.
As in the case of gravestone doji, this pattern
is not profitable when traded by itself.
If we look at the picture above, the dragonfly
doji pattern formed near an important level
of support, which indeed drove the price higher.
That’s why it’s important to trade this
pattern near strong support and resistance
levels and in combination with other tools.
Next type is the long-legged doji.
The long-legged doji has long upper and lower
shadows in the middle of the period’s trading
range, reflecting the indecision of buyers
and sellers.
Throughout the period, the market moved higher
and then sharply lower, or vice versa.
It then closed at or very near the opening
price.
This signals market indecision, as neither
the bulls nor the bears won the battle.
From my experience long-legged doji candles
will offer many false signals and should only
be traded on higher time frames and in combination
with other technical tools.
The last type is the rare doji.
The rare doji occurs the open, high, low,
and close of the price are all the same.
This pattern forms when a market is very illiquid
or the data source did not have any prices
other than the close.
The rare doji pattern should be interpreted
as a complete and total uncertainty in the
market direction.
Now, this is how I trade the doji.
Like I said before, I always take trades only
around support and resistance areas.
You can use recent market swings or fib retracements,
but I prefer to use pivot points.
This chart shows the exact sequence we need:
a doji formed around a pivot point level.
The next one to three candles after a doji
forms must close above the high of that doji
candle.
That is the key; the close is the confirmation
that a bullish transition took place.
So in this pattern, we are looking for a specific
conditional change to take place in the market,
namely, a higher closing high above a doji’s
high, but must occur near a pivot point level.
That’s the most important part of this setup
which will help to eliminate and filter out
false signals.
Initially, use stop below the low of the doji.
Once the market begins to produce a profit
and moves in the desired direction, then you
can change it or continually trail the stop.
If you don’t like to trade 100% price action,
you can also use a “filter” or backup
process to confirm the buy signal with other
indicator (stochastic, moving average, whatever
you prefer)
Here is another example, on a 15-minute chart
on the British pound US dollar.
Once we added our pivot points, we have our
first area of interest here.
As you can see, the market traded around the
pivot level and a doji pattern formed.
He have a close above the doji’s high.
Also note that the market closed above the
moving-average which is also bullish.
Once we have a close above the high of the
doji, we can start searching for long entries.
To summarize, when you identify a doji at
or near the pivot level, wait for confirmation
of the next candle to close above the doji’s
high.
Here are other examples of trades, using doji
patterns around pivot levels.
Looking at these examples, i hope you noticed
that I prefer to consider doji candles as
accumulation zones where bull or bears are
gaining momentum for a continuation of the
main trend.
I’m not chasing reversals like most of traders,
I’m looking for continuation patterns.
And I always combine this doji pattern with
other technical tools, to confirm the main
trend.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, don’t forget to subscribe,
hit the bell icon and leave us a like to show
your support.
Until next time.