here is what I've learned after 14 years
of trading the most emotionally and
complicated aspect of trading is knowing
how to set up take profit and stop-loss
orders period do traders can use the
same strategy and during at the same
price on a chart but record different
results why is that because of trade
management if you enter a trade without
any kind of exit strategy you will put
yourself in the situation to take
premature profits or worse to run losses
there are only two ways you can get off
of a trade by taking a loss or by making
a profit and money management is one of
the most important aspects of trading
often neglected by a lot of traders and
investors today I'll show you my two
best exit technical indicators that will
help you to lock more profits and will
reduce the probability of taking a loss
before we continue if you are new to my
channel make sure you subscribe turn on
notifications and leave a like to show
your support so when talking about exit
strategies we use terms like take profit
and stop-loss orders hopefully during
your training day you'll encounter more
take profit orders than stop losses
that's why in order for you to limit the
risk on a trade you need an exit plan
the complicated part when it comes to
trading or investing is to exit a
position when have a respectable profit
rather than waiting for the market to
come back against you and exiting out of
fear the difficulty here is that you
will not want to exit the trade when it
is in profit and moving in your favour
as it feels like the trade will continue
in that direction the irony is that not
exiting the moment Atreides
significantly in your favor usually
means that you will make an emotional
exit because at some point the trade
will come back crashing against your
current position now how do you know how
to exit a trade when in profit here are
the best indicators you could use to
exit the market the first indicator the
chandalier exit chandalier exit is a
volatility based indicator
created to enable a trader to stay in a
trade until there is a definite trend
reversal by using the Chandler exit
indicator you will be able to avoid
early exits and maximize returns
indicator is created using the average
true range values over a given time
period other than the average true range
the highest high and the lowest low
price of an asset over a specific time
period is used in the calculation the
default settings for this indicator is
22 because there are 20 to 20 days in a
month
the Chandler exit is based on the
principle that there exists a high
probability of a trend reversal whenever
the price of a stock moves against the
prevailing trend by a distance equal to
three times the average volatility so
let's say you took a long position on a
stock by setting the chandalier exit
three average to range values below the
period high the indicator provides a
buffer that is three times the
volatility a decline strong enough to
break this level warns you about your
long position so when the price closes
below the chandalier exit you should
re-evaluate your long position the
opposite applies to short positions so
you are short on a stock and the
Chandler exit is set three Average True
Range values above the period low
providing a volatility based buffer and
events strong enough to exceed is level
is a sign that you might want to take
your profits but even though is mostly
used for stop losses the CH and earlier
exit can also be used as a trend tool
sometimes you will see a strong uptrend
but not know where to jump the trade
legendary exit can be used to define the
trend and set as a trailing stop loss in
this example we see the stock breaking
out and starting an extended uptrend the
Chandler exit defined this up movement
quite well
as it followed price action going higher
also keep in mind that some stocks are
more volatile than others and require a
bigger buffer which means that the
multiplier should be increased this
example shows the stock in a clear
downtrend for most of the year when
normal chandalier exit would have
triggered some stops just before the
down trend continued noticed how the
stock moved above the dashed line
several times during this downtrend
so when trading more volatile stocks you
should increase the average to range
multiplier in this example the Green
chandalier line allows for more
volatility by using 5 as the multiplier
the second indicator useful for exiting
your trades is the dawn Jian channel
this indicator is similar to the
Bollinger Bands and analyzes the
evolution of the price by plotting the
highest high and the lowest low over a
specific time interval the most common
settings for tracking the price higher
highs and lower lows is the 20 period
don't change channels is a useful
indicator for measuring volatility in a
market the volatility measures the rate
at which stock moves a volatile stock is
one that records rapid fluctuations in
price while a non volatile stock
registers moderate price fluctuations
don't change channels contract when the
volatility is low and expand when
volatility increases during periods of
low volatility don't change channels are
narrow while during periods of high
volatility don't change channels expand
drastically
the don't change channels are the basis
of a popular training strategy called
turtle trading in essence the turtle
trading strategy is based on a breakout
of the upward
resistance line or lower support line as
the upper and lower don't change channel
lines actually represent previous
support and resistance lines a break of
those lines generates buy and sell
signals the exit signal is simply a
breakout of the channel to the opposite
side this allows to write the trend for
a long period before exiting the trade
so don't change channels is also a great
trend indicator when the price action
breaks true and closes above the upper
don't chain band the signals an upward
movement and a possible by signal when a
price action breaks true and closes
below the lower don't chain band the
signals a downward movement and a
possible sell signal this may seem a
little confusing if you are familiar
with the Bollinger Bands many traders
assume that a breakout above upper or
lower don't change channels signals an
overbought and oversold area and the
reversal could be on accords this
assumption is wrong trading with don't
change channels is similar to support
and resistance trading it's simple if
the market momentum is able to surpass
don't an upper channel then an uptrend
could be developing conversely if the
market momentum breaks below the dungeon
lower channel a new downtrend could be
developing just like in the case of
support and resistance lines once the
support level is broken becomes a
resistance level and once a resistant
line is broken becomes a support line
so how do you take your profits with
don't change channels the original
turtle trading strategy used the
stop-loss of two volatility units which
basically equals to two times the
average true range of the last 20
periods if you use the default settings
this gives enough room for the price to
move up and down in order not to be
stopped out too early during a strong
trend you can place your stop losses by
using the lower support line and place
your stop-loss just below the support
for a long position or just below the
resistance for a short position here's
an example of the don't change channel
breakout with a stop loss level above
the upper resistance line and the exit
level at the break of the upper channel
line notice how don't change channel
moves with the recent periods highs and
lows we were able to write the trend
until the break of the upper resistance
line which initiated a new Uptrend
afterwards another exit signal can be
generated using a touch of the midpoint
line of the channel if we look at the
daily chart of this stock we can see
that if you use a 50-day period for the
don't change channels using the rules
discussed before long trade if there's a
close above the channel with a closing
of the trade when touching the midpoint
line we see a couple of trades within
the past year it all depends on your
trading risk aversion if you use the
midpoint you will leave some profits on
the table more often when the trends are
strong you'll often witness that the mid
band will be touched by the price during
retracements and will act as support or
resistance and the trend will resume so
you have to choose if you want to exit
your trade at the lower band or at the
middleman if you got any value from this
video don't forget to subscribe hit the
bell icon and leave us a like to share
our support
until next time