although it's important to be able to
spot new trends it is equally important
to be able to identify what a trend ends
getting out at the right time isn't
difficult but it does require some close
observation of price action and looking
for clues that my predictor Universal or
a trend change when trading Forex or the
stock market it's easy to find trades
that match your technical criteria but
taking a timely exit requires great
skill one indicator that can help you to
identify what a trend might be ending is
the parabolic SAR so in this video we'll
talk about a parabolic SAR you'll learn
how to correctly trade with it and I'll
show you how to use it along with eg
more cloud in a trading strategy before
we continue if you are new to my channel
make sure you subscribe turn on the
notifications and give us a like to sure
support parabolic SAR is an indicator
displayed as a series of dots mainly
used to identify the market direction
and the beginning of reversals it allows
traders to evaluate the trend direction
to pinpoint entry and exit points and
also placing training stops the dots of
this indicator shift from being below
the candles during the uptrend to above
the candles when the trend reverses into
a downtrend when the price is trading
below the parabolic SAR this can be
explained as a signal to sell or remain
short on the other hand if the price is
trading above the parabolic SAR this can
be explained as a signal to buy or
remain long if you prefer price action
what you need to know is that during
strong trends the gap between the price
and the dots widens however if the
market is flat or choppy the dots and
price interact with one another quite
frequently
calculating the parabolic SAR indicator
is a rather complex and I don't want to
bore you with it what you need to know
is that the SAR comes with two values
which can be adjusted depending on your
preference step in a maximum step are
the values offered by the parabolic SAR
and they determine how sensitive the
indicator is to changes in price
movements the default settings of the
SAR are 0.02 for the step and 0.2 for
the maximum step once the price makes a
new high or low the acceleration factor
increases by 0.02 this explains the
reason why the gaps between the
parabolic SAR and the price increase
during strong trends by increasing the
values of the step and maximum step you
can increase the sensitivity of the
indicator but at the same time
sacrificing its precision because the
parabolic SAR will offer many false
signals by lowering the values of the
step and maximum step the parabolic SAR
will become less sensitive but will also
provide more accurate signals from my
experience it's important to find a
balance between these two values in
order to generate quality signals which
are not lagging the price speaking about
lag parabolic SAR is indeed a lagging
indicator because it follows the price
and you will need the help of other
trading tools to generate quality
signals now how do you trade with
parabolic SAR well this indicator
provides distant signals that the market
trend is about to change here's how it
works a dot appears below the price when
the trend is upward and a dot is placed
above the price when the trend is
downward the parabolic SAR trails the
price until the trend has finished and
begins to reverse as the trend comes to
an end the parabolic SAR moves closer to
the price and ends up touching the price
then forms a dot on the other side of
the price signaling a change in
direction
this is probably the easiest indicator
to interpret because it assumes that the
price is either going up or down with
that said this tool is best used in
markets that are trending and that have
long rallies and small Corrections
however you don't want to use this
indicator in a choppy market where the
price movement is sideways that's why
it's better to use it as an exit
indicator the parabolic SAR provides
decent exit points as it provides a stop
loss level that moves closer to the
price regardless of the market direction
the rule is that you should close by
positions when the price moves below the
SAR and close sell positions when the
price moves above the SAR so from my
experience it's better to use the
parabolic SAR to help you determine
whether you should close your trade or
not but if you insist of taking your
entries based on the parabolic SAR here
is how I would do it first I would use
it on higher time frames and here's why
trading the parabolic SAR on a lower
time frame will allow you to find a lot
of trades every day everything is faster
with a lot of noise if your analysis
isn't on point
the SAR might offer contradicting
signals in a spare of a few hours or
minutes on higher time frames your trade
will move slowly this will avoid you to
get too emotional and jump in a trade
that is not ready many traders get into
trouble trading the parabolic SAR on all
time frames because they start watching
this noise and they think they see a
signal which in fact is nothing more
than noise this can all be avoided by
sticking the SAR indicator to the 4-hour
or on the daily time frame were above
but you cannot trade with a parabolic
SAR alone I would even say it's almost
impossible to stay consistent trading
just on the basis of the parabolic SAR
that's why I would add the Ichimoku
cloud in the setup if you don't know
what each more quiz make sure you watch
this video on my channel it will teach
you the base
six of using it now the advantage of
using Ichimoku is the fact that it
offers a unique perspective of support
and resistance the most important role
of Ichimoku indicator is the coup
macleod and this is all we need for our
setup so we have the coup macleod as
dynamic area of support and resistance
and the parabolic SAR for entries and
exits we also pay attention to price
action for obvious patterns static
support and resistance levels and
breakouts here is the setup for long
opportunities we want a price to be
above the coup MacLeod and a dot must be
formed below the price for short
opportunities the price must be below
the coup macleod and the dot must be
above the price very important you never
take trades inside the cloud so here is
the euro JPY 104 hours chart tracking
the price action in the past three or
four months here is our first short
opportunity as the prices below the
cloud and a dot appeared above the price
we then had another short here which was
most likely a losing trade depending on
the stop loss level and then we had a
great short here
and another sell position here observe
how the parabolic SAR was well separated
from the price indicating a strong trend
we had another short here which brought
a small profit or a break-even trade and
a losing trade here as the price entered
the cloud
so during this period we recorded five
or six profitable trades and losing ones
so don't expect ten winning trades out
of ten let's continue with our analysis
the price didn't manage to break through
the cloud and resumed its downtrend and
here was a great short trade which
brought nice profits followed by another
winning trade here then we had another
short signal which was a losing trade or
a breakeven one depending on the risk
management adopted here we have our
first buy order in three months the
downward trend was too strong and the
price retraced back below the cloud we
had another short opportunity here and
currently we are also in a short setup
let's take an example on the stock
market here's Tesla on a 4-hour chart
following the evolution of the price
since January 2019
the first short here the second one here
which was a losing trade another short
opportunity here which was a great trade
another decent trade here here was
another tricky trade the market opened
with a large gap down and I personally
wouldn't be comfortable pulling the
trigger at that point but if you
followed the system and took the trade
after the gap this was a losing trade
but no worries because we had other
opportunities to short the market here
and here the last trade in particular is
the perfect trade with a price slowly
going down with small Corrections and
now we are now possible by mode because
the price is above the cloud we just
have to wait for a dot to be formed
below the price keep in mind that the
signals occurred in the past six months
because we trade the higher time frames
so you just have to be patient and wait
for the right moment and don't be
discouraged if you get one or two losing
trades in a row of course try to trade
when you see a clear trend and avoid
markets that are arranging or with low
volatility now if you got value from
this video and learn something new make
sure you subscribe turn on notifications
so you don't miss future uploads and
give us a like to show your support
until next time