You can be the most knowledgeable person at
the trading desk, but if you don’t know
how to handle yourself when you press the
buy and sell button, you are going to be an
average trader, at best.
Unfortunately, few people know how to actually
handle their emotions when trading.
In today’s video we’ll talk about the
most common mistakes you are probably making
on a daily basis, and I’ll showcase the
actual steps I took to become more disciplined
and more patient.
So, like, subscribe and stick around for the
full video.
Blow several demo accounts, deliberately!
Here’s an exercise which will massively
improve your discipline.
Open a demo account and blow it, intentionally.
Make all of your trading mistakes on that
demo account, because you first need to make
them, in order to learn not to repeat them.
You basically get your trading mistakes out
of your system.
So open on your demo account, and go nuts.
Make all the mistakes you know: chasing a
position, overtrading, trading having large
positions.
Lose a trade and then open a second one, to
recover the losses.
Trade without stop losses.
Blow your demo account, then open another
one and repeat the same mistakes.
Observe your mistakes, but also be aware of
your feelings.
Try to visualize that mistake on a live account
and be grateful this is only a demo account.
This exercise helped me to become more disciplined.
It’s weird, but it works.
Learning how to trade correctly and eliminate
mistakes is about doing something that’s
hard, until it becomes easy.
Making mistakes and failing, means you are
working through the hard parts.
But the key point of this exercise is to remember
your emotions, your state of mind, when you
make a certain mistake.
If you’re doing it correctly, it will prevent
you from repeating the same mistake, on a
live account.
This sounds like a cliché, but you actually
learn a TON from bad trades, specifically
from reviewing them.
I suggest you take a screenshot of the chart
on a bad trade.
Go back and look at it several days or weeks
later.
You’ll look at it and say, ‘What the hell
was I thinking?
What did I enter there?”
In the end, screen time, practice, and education
will make you capable of finding good trades;
but learning to avoid the bad trades will
make you profitable.
Risk averse to profit taking but risk seeking
when losing
Here’s one of my own past struggles: I had
an inclination to wait on a losing trade with
the hope of getting out at break-even, but
I used to take my profits very quickly, because
I got very anxious when I was in profit.
It was very frustrating.
Do you see the paradox?
I was being too risk averse when it came to
profit taking, I wasn’t able to contain
my emotions when in profit, but I was risk
seeking when it comes to loss taking.
I have invested an excessive amount of time
and energy watching losing positions than
watching winning trades.
You know the famous saying that 90% of traders
are losers.
But here’s the reality: most losing traders
are not really consistent losers, they are
instead blowing up their account on one bad
trade.
They do not slowly lose the funds in their
account; trade by trade.
In fact, they are making profits, or preserve
their capital, at first.
What ends their trading accounts is one bad
trade, one stubborn trade, where they do not
accept a small loss.
You might be amazed, but most traders are
blowing up their accounts on just a few bad
trades.
And this CAN be avoided 100%.
Many poor trades taken out of frustration
It’s easy to be overwhelmed if you load
yourself up.
Too many markets to keep track of, too many
strategies to back test.
You need to narrow it down.
I remember when I first started trading Forex,
I used to have a template with over 20 currencies.
And I woke up every morning, and manually
placed the support and resistance levels on
each pair, before the London open.
And I tried to monitor them, simultaneously.
You know the outcome: many missed trades,
which resulted in many poor trades taken out
of frustration.
You have a lot of things to cover: market
selection and preparation, pattern recognition,
risk to reward, indicators, volume, position
size, entry level, price action, trade management.
It’s easy to become overwhelmed.
So when day trading, focus on fewer things
at one time.
Trying to squeeze every dollar out of the
trading day
Even though the price will go up or down,
you don’t need to trade every moment.
There is enough money to be made trading only
a few times each day.
You don’t need to sit in front of the screen
all day.
I spend an hour, maximum two every day researching
and trading, or maybe even less.
But you must decide what works for you.
You only need a few good trades a week to
be profitable.
I know that there is a tendency to try to
squeeze every dollar out of the trading day,
but when you have reached your profit target
or stop seeing setups, stop trading.
When you realize this, you won’t have the
need to frantically get into a trade, any
trade, to not miss out on the profit.
This reduces risk, losses and trading commissions.
Don’t turn a day trade into a swing trade
After several similar mistakes, I now have
a simple rule when I’m day trading: I must
close my positions at the end of the day,
even at a loss.
You should never turn a day trade into a swing
trade and hold it overnight.
You know the feeling: you open a trade hoping
for a quick profit, and instead of closing
it, you find yourself justifying staying in
a bad trade, the second day.
This is one of the deadliest sins a day trader
can make.
You need to change your mindset.
Think about it: you can always get back in,
but it’s hard to recover from a big loss.
You may think, “I don’t want to take a
$100 loss.”
Well, you definitely don’t want to take
a $300 loss.
And if you ended up taking a $500 loss, it
would be really hard to recover from that.
Again: never turn a day trade into a swing
trade.
Take the loss and come back when the timing
is better.
Don’t average down on a losing trade
In my first years, I used to average down
on losing trades.
Imagine you buy 10 shares of a company at
$100 in the anticipation of selling them at
around $110.
Instead, the stock breaks the support level
and drops to $80.
You have lost the trade and you should have
been stopped out.
But, instead of accepting the loss and moving
on, you buy another 10 shares at $80, and
you now have 20 shares with an average cost
of $90.
It is unlikely the price will hit your initial
target of $110, but now you’re hoping the
price will rally back to $90.
At $90, you can sell all of your 20 shares
at break-even and save the previous losing
trade.
Even better, if their price goes to $95, you
can even record some profits.
It’s very tempting to average down on a
losing trade with the hope of getting out
at breakeven, but you shouldn’t do it.
Averaging down a losing trade is a recipe
for wiping out your account.
90% of the time maybe you will profit when
you average down.
But the 10% of the time you are wrong, you
will blow up your account.
I’ve done it and I still remember the frustration
and the anger.
Every day you hope that price will turn around
and will save your account.
It is a waste of your mental energy and I
don’t want to feel those emotions ever again.
FOMO: The deadliest of all trading sins
Fear of Missing Out is perhaps the deadliest
of all trading sins that you can make.
It is wishful thinking, and it can be a very
costly trading mistake to jump into a trade
before a pattern has either formed or been
confirmed.
It can also be a very costly trading mistake
to chase a pattern that is visible but is
not offering a good risk to reward opportunity.
Although FOMO is very dangerous, it is actually
also very easy to avoid.
You just need to ask yourself one simple question
before entering any trade: “What is my risk
to reward in this trade?”
If you cannot identify a good risk to reward,
then it is a fear of missing out trade, and
you should not take it.
If you cannot determine a stop loss or profit
target, then it is a trade based on FOMO,
and you should not take it.
When we talk about FOMO, we also talk about
greed.
If you see that the market is moving toward
the weekly high with heavy volume, breaks
the level, you might take a position, even
though this wasn’t your initial plan.
And there is nothing wrong with that.
It is not greed or FOMO because you saw a
clear signal of opportunity to take a position.
But, if you take a position just because you
saw a Youtube video saying that Bitcoin is
going to the moon, or a Reddit post that said
that it’s time to buy a random stock, and
there’s significant money to me made, then
you are trading based on FOMO.
You have to be able to make the difference
between a FOMO trade and a trade which maybe
wasn’t in your plan, but it’s backed by
your technicals.
Your previous losses affect your current trades
Fear can be triggered, for example, by your
concerns over your profitability and your
account.
You are afraid to take a trade because you
are too focused on the fact that your $5,000
account is now at $4,000 and you have had
five bad trading days in a row.
That is not the mindset to have.
Your previous losses have nothing to do with
the trade you are about to enter.
If you are concerned that the price action
is not clean, or that the volume in the trade
is not enough, or that you don’t have a
confirmation, that is okay, because those
concerns are not based on fear.
But, if your concern over another loss is
based on a bad trading day the week before,
that is a disruptive fear.
You have to realize that your current trade
idea has absolutely nothing to do with how
you have traded in previous days.
If, instead of responding to the market, you
are reacting to your own concerns regarding
profitability, you are acting in fear, and
this will take you out of the current reality
of the market.
Instead, you will be acting based upon your
own uncertainties and insecurities.
Whenever you fear pulling the trigger, try
to find out why are you afraid.
Is it because of the price action?
Or is it because of your own insecurities?
Feeling uncomfortable is your new “comfort
zone”
Dealing with losses and failures, on a daily
basis, can be difficult.
Because no setup is perfect and every setup
is unique.
Even winning days are full of small mistakes
and things that could be improved.
In many other areas of life, perfection is
a worthy goal, but not so with trading.
I’m a perfectionist, and this is still one
of my main struggles in trading.
As a perfectionist, you’re used to think
“inside the box” rather than outside of
it.
As a trader, feeling uncomfortable is your
new “comfort zone.”
You must see what others don’t, you test
new ideas, new strategies, you seize new opportunities,
and you take risks.
This requires courage and the ability to keep
going despite daily losses.
It is very important to understand the risk
and probabilities involved in trading.
Think of trading as a business that operates
based on probabilities.
The market is a random environment.
Anything can happen at any moment.
Having that understanding is the key to peaceful
trading.
A trader’s career is based on probability
and statistics.
If you learn to trade proper risk to reward
trades, you trade defensive and always use
a stop loss, in the long term you will make
more money than you will lose.