the pinbar is without a doubt one of the
most powerful and reliable price action
trading signals that can be traded
across many different markets and
timeframes the beauty of using a pin bar
is that a firm offer
and they appear on all time frames
showing a simple approach to technical
analysis the main advantage of using a
pin bar trading strategy is its
simplicity nowadays traders use
sophisticated trading strategies to come
up with less productive trades you don't
have to do that when you are trading a
pin bar you just need to read price
action today we will talk about one of
my favorite candlestick formations the
pin bar and I'll show you how to
correctly identify them in order to
increase your winning ratio if you're
new here make sure you subscribe and
click the bell icon to enable
notifications and also leave a select to
show support a pin bar is a press action
pattern which signals that the reversal
may be about to take place in the market
the great thing about being bars and the
reason I prefer them is the fact they're
really easy to spot on your charts there
can be no confusion as whether the
candle you are looking at is a pin bar
or a different type of candlestick let's
take a look at what pin bars are
supposed to look like when they are
formed on your charts this is a simple
example of a bearish pin bar notice how
the body is found at the bottom of the
candlestick and the long wick is found
at the top all very spin bars you'll see
form in the market will follow this
basic structure they all have their body
at the bottom candlestick and they're
weak at the top sometimes the body of
the candle will not be found right at
the bottom like you see in this chart
but it will always be found in the
bottom half of the candlestick
here we have a bullish pin bar as you
can see bullish pin bars look very
similar to bearish ones the only real
difference between the two is the body
of the bullish pin bar is found at the
top of the candle instead of the bottom
and most of the wick is found at the
bottom instead of the top similar to the
previous example the body of this
bullish pin bar doesn't manage to close
right at the top of the candle but like
I said before this doesn't make a
difference it's still a bullish pin bar
and should be treated the same as all
other bullish pin bar you see form in
the market now here comes the missing
piece of puzzle and the reason why many
traders fail to tray them correctly how
to make sure it's a pin bar simply
knowing that the body of the candlestick
needs to close towards the bottom or the
top of the candle in order to be a
bullish or bearish pinbar is a bit of
incomplete advice especially for new
traders who have little experience
identifying pin bars of the market I
consider a valid pin bar a candle that
meets three conditions the open and
closed with in previous bar the wick is
minimum three times the length of the
body and the weak must stick out from
all other candles and must be very
obvious here's the common mistake among
traders they don't know how to correctly
identify pin bars the less well-defined
pin bars and smaller pin bars are
generally the traits you don't want to
be trading the rules for a pin bar are
straightforward the price opens and
closes within a previous candle the wick
should be three times the length of the
body and the wick itself must stick out
from all candles here are a few examples
of valid pin bars
[Music]
another important thing is the fact that
pinbar is a reversal signal and not a
continuation the major reason why many
traders lose money over and over again
trading pin bars is because they try to
trade the pin bar as a continuation
signal to trade a pin bar as a reversal
it means we have to pick the price to
reverse and form between points if we
want to trade a bearish pinbar
and anticipate the price to move lower
we first need to see price moving higher
so we can pick priced reverse we can
play a bearish pinbar reversal signal if
the price has not first moved higher
notice in this example our price first
moves higher and after this the price
forms a bearish pinbar here's an example
of what not to do in this chart the pin
bar is traded as a continuation rather
than a reversal as all pin bars should
be this pin bar is a bearish pin bar but
the pin has not been traded after the
price made a move higher this pin bar
has been traded to see if the price can
continue to move lower if you decide to
trade this pin bar you will be selling a
low and hoping to buy back even lower
which is the wrong approach the number
one rule in trading and investing is buy
low and sell high trading pin bars as a
continuation means you buy high and hope
to sell even higher or sell low and buy
even lower
it might work in some cases but the high
probability trade is to treat pin bars
as reversal signals
Trading BIM bars from incorrect areas on
the chart is another big problem which
is getting traders into trouble
you cannot enter a trade just because
you see a valid BIM bar the pin bar has
a higher chance of reversal if it occurs
at a strong area of support or
resistance pay attention at this chart
you will notice that it has two pin bars
the major problem of trading this pin
bars is the fact that there is no wrong
you are trading straight back into the
recent high which represents the
near-term resistance as you can see on
this chart this resistance held and
pushed price lower trading pin bar
signals with support and resistance
confirmation this perhaps one of the
most effective ways to trade when
combined with a strong support or
resistance level pin bars can be one of
the most accurate straining signals
available the best pin bar setups occur
near confluent levels of previous price
action as the market moves in one
direction and then regresses back to
retest the previous support or
resistance level we can see in this
chart two successive pin bar testing of
previous report and resistance level and
then resuming downward momentum the more
confluence you can combine with a pin
bar signal the higher its accuracy
becomes in this example we are looking
at a bearish pinbar sell signal that
formed in the context of a Down trending
market and formed at the confluent area
in the market the confluence between the
dynamic moving average resistance zone
the horizontal resistance and the
downtrend gave a lot of weight to the
pin bar signal when we get well-defined
pin bars like this that has formed at
the confident area or a level the market
like this
it's a very high probability setup and
here's another important tip the very
best pin bars stick out they are not
hidden in your charts a big
misconception with new traders is the
fact they want to find the smallest bin
bars they can because it will offer them
the smallest stop and the biggest risk
reward this is completely wrong
the bigger the rejection and the bigger
the pin bar the more powerful the signal
the best pin bars are large and obvious
candles that as soon as you flick over
to your charts you will notice them
these are the pin bars that stick out
and are practically screaming at you to
trade all good pin bars need to have
their wicks sticking out from all
candles and if they don't then they
don't fit the basic criteria I've talked
about this chart is a great example of a
pin bar that sticks out from all other
candles first notice how it opens and
closes within the previous candle and
then notice how the price has moved
higher before forming the pin bar this
pin bar is being played as a reversal
and it has space to move down the really
great thing about pin bars is the
variety of different ways in how you can
trade them in this video we've talked
about the basics of pin bars but in the
next ones
we'll go even deeper and I'll show you
how to trade with them how to find the
best areas to trade them how to set up
stop losses and how to establish take
profit targets as always if you learned
something new make sure you subscribe
click the notification icon and give us
a like to show support at the next time
you