It is so simple to jump into trading using
the RSI indicator without testing different
settings, or educating yourself on the proper
interpretation of this indicator, because
of a desire to grab money quickly!
As a result, the RSI has become one of the
most widely misused indicators.
Once understood and correctly applied, the
RSI has the ability to indicate whether prices
are trending, when a market is overbought
or oversold, and the best price to enter or
exit a trade.
The relative strength index (RSI) it’s a
momentum oscillator that measures the speed
and change of price movement.
The RSI oscillates between 0 and 100 and it’s
often used to measure overbought and oversold
conditions in the market, divergence or it
can be used to identify the general trend.
Basically, the RSI is analyzing the total
number of down periods versus the total number
of up periods and plots the average on the
RSI curve.
There are many different techniques for using
it, but it can be altered depending on your
specific needs.
An overlooked method of using RSI is the use
of trend lines directly on the oscillator
itself in much the same way that they are
used on price charts.
Trend lines are one of the most common and
helpful tools in a trader's kit.
They are used to show the price upwards, downwards,
and sometime sideways, movement.
Confirmed trend lines are drawn by connecting
a cycle low, or high, with at least two other
of the highest or lowest points on a chart,
to create a line of best fit.
Connecting rising swing lows of the RSI in
an uptrend or lower swing highs in a downtrend,
traders can find trading opportunities with
strong risk to reward setups.
Because RSI measures the surge in closing
prices, when RSI changes direction and either
breaks above or below a trend line, a significant
move in price can result.
So, we’ll use the RSI indicator to show
us if the prevailing trend has ended and a
new trend is underway.
We’re not going to measure the overbought/oversold
conditions or as a crossover system, we’re
going to take it one step further and look
for a break in momentum of the prevailing
trend.
What I mean by this is that we’re going
to look at the changes in prices relative
to the changes in the peak and the valley
that the RSI indicator will generate.
Trend lines placed on this oscillator provide
an additional level of precision as well as
additional trade setups.
Because the signals are leading rather than
lagging, stops can be placed relatively close
to the entry point.
This allows for a good risk to reward trading
opportunity.
The RSI-trend line approach works best on
higher timeframes but it can be used on any
time frame, for day trading for example.
The rules of this technique are straightforward,
we only need to connect the most recent RSI
peaks or valleys with a trend line and we
search for a breakout of the trend line, which
will warn us that the market has lost its
steam and the prevailing trend has lost its
momentum.
There is one more condition that needs to
be satisfied in order to enter a trade, we
need for the price to still be trading below
its trend line, so we’ll need the RSI trend
line to be broken, and the price to be trading
below its trend line.
This is the most important principle in order
for the RSI-trend line strategy to work because
it tells us there is also a divergence between
momentum and price.
Momentum always goes ahead of price and that’s
the reason why this strategy can yield a great
return.
The breaking of an RSI trend line usually
precedes the break of a trend line on the
price chart, providing an advance warning
of a reversal.
Therefore, recognizing the break of the RSI
trend line can be an important and profitable
indicator that the price direction is about
to change.
This is a leading signal.
a leading signal appears before the new trend
or reversal occurs.
RSI, in its nature, is a lagging indicator.
Lagging indicators only give signals after
the price change is clearly forming a trend.
The downside is that you’d be a little late
in entering a position.
Often the biggest gains of a trend occur in
the first few bars, so by using a lagging
indicator you could potentially miss out on
much of the profit.
That’s, when trading the RSI trend line
breakout, you’ll get leading signals.
Now you’re probably saying to yourself,
“Oh, I’m going to get rich with leading
indicators!”
Since you would be able to profit from a new
trend right at the start.
You’re right.
You would “catch” the entire trend every
single time if the leading indicator was correct
every single time.
But it won’t be.
When you use leading indicators, you will
experience a lot of fakeouts.
That’s why it’s important to look closely
at the price action.
If you would take a trade every time you spot
a RSI trend line breakout, you would soon
find out that the outcome is not as expected.
The RSI trend line has leading qualities,
but after all it’s still an indicator.
You need to analyze the price.
You need to draw key support and resistance
levels, to identify the trend and take RSI
trend lines in the direction of the main trend.
Here is a common mistake.
Many traders that implement the RSI trend
line breakout approach, use it as a reversal
signal.
They see an upward trend, they spot a RSI
trend line breakout and go short.
This could work, yes, but it’s not the most
consistent way of using it.
I use it in a more conservative way.
When I spot the same uptrend, i search for
RSI trend line signals that offer buy opportunities.
I have zero interest in RSI signals indicating
short trades.
I go with the main trend.
In GBPUSD chart, we noticed some RSI trend
line breaks.
The use of the trend line provided additional
visual confirmation that a trade opportunity
is near.
The use of trend line breaks gave buy signals
a few candles before the actual move.
In this another chart, we can have a representation
of how a short setup would look like.
We have the price making lower lows and lower
high, so we are definitely in a downtrend.
We added the main support and resistance levels.
Then we identified the RSI trend line breakouts.
In terms of stop loss level, a common practice
is to use the candle on which the RSI broke
its trend line, so in the case of our short
setup our SL would be above that candle.
In real time trading, this isn’t best practice.
That’s why I rely on recent market swings.
I aim to place my stop loss above an important
swing.
If you prefer a better visualization of the
trend, add a long term moving average, and
take trades in its main direction.
Here are other examples of RSI trend line
trades.
Regarding the settings, or better said, the
period of RSI.
RSI like many other oscillators is defaulted
to a 14 period setting.
This means the indicator looks back 14 bars
on whatever graph you may be viewing, to create
its reading.
Even though 14 is the default period, that
may not make it the best setting for your
trading.
Normally short-term traders use a smaller
period, such as a nine period RSI, to replicate
shorter term movements in the market.
Longer-term traders may opt for a higher period,
such as a 21 period RSI or even 50.
Depending on your trading style, you can lower
your RSI to increase sensitivity or you could
raise it to decrease sensitivity.
Keep in mind that on lower timeframes, with
lower RSI settings, you will get a lot of
false signals, because the indicator will
have increased sensitivity.
So, maybe it’s better to increase the value
of the RSI if you want to back test this technique
on smaller timeframes.
If you want a smoother analysis, with less
noise, go on higher timeframes.
Here you could use a lower period on the RSI,
which will offer more trend line opportunities,
but you could also adopt a less sensitive
approach, by using a higher period RSI, like
the 21 for example.
The key is to back test and find the best
approach that works with your trading style.
The RSI is a powerful tool that can offer
a great assistance on when to buy and when
to sell.
Sometimes it can also predict the trend other
indicators are too slow to acknowledge.
An important tip is that you shouldn’t chase
the trades, let them come to you.
RSI is an indicator and just follow the price.
You should be patient and wait for a clear
break of its trend line.
Maybe sometimes, you should wait to see how
the first candle acts after the breakout and
after that take your trade.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, leave us a like to show your
support.
Also don’t forget to subscribe and click
the bell icon to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.