hey guys so I'm sure that many of you
are familiar with the standard pivot
points but let me ask you how many of
you take your trading decisions based on
the daily pivot range the daily pivot
range is one of the most powerful pivot
indicators and is very important because
it can tell you a lot about the
potential movement of the upcoming day
and can offer a certain bias about the
current day's price action what if I
told you that knowing this location of
this price range will allow you to know
the pulse of the market and will also
provide you with a significant trading
edge so in this video we'll discuss
about this new concept regarding the
pivot points the daily pivot range
you'll discover how to interpret this
range and you'll also learn how to trade
based on this important area before you
continue if you are new to this channel
and you find value or learn something
new please consider subscribing and
leave us a like to show your support so
the daily profit range concept was
introduced by mark fisher in his book
the logical trader the pivot range aims
to identify areas in which the buyers
are likely to support the market or
sellers should dominate the resistance
the pivot range is easily calculated
using the high low and close of a
trading period first we add the high low
and close of the previous trading day
and divide this number by 3 let's say
that a stock had a high of 111 and
closed at 98 those three numbers added
together and divided by 3 would be 96
this is the daily pivot number now you
add the high and the low and divide the
amount by 2 in this example adding the
high of 100 and the low of 90 then
dividing by 2 would give you 95 then we
calculate the difference between the
daily pivot number that we previously
calculated 96 and the number we
calculated before 95 the result 1 point
is the daily pivot differential the
daily pivot range is equal to the pivot
we're plus and minus the people
differential in this case the pivot
range would be 96 plus 1 and 96 minus 1
now that we've calculated the daily
pivot range what does it tell us first
the underlying tone or the sentiment of
the market is revealed when we look at
the close of the previous trading day
compared with the day's pivot range if
the previous closed was above today's
daily pivot range that would be
considered bullish for today's trade if
it closed below the daily pivot range it
would be considered bearish for example
if the market closed yesterday at 69
point 4 and the pivot range was lower at
68.4 to 69 it would set a bullish tone
conversely if the market had closed
yesterday at 69 point 7 and the pivot
range was at sixty nine point eight to
70 it would indicate a bearish tone the
daily pivot range will help you to see
where something has to happen if the
market is below the pivot range and
makes a move upward it will meet
resistance at that level if the market
does manage to break through the pivot
range it will have enough force behind
it to make a significant upward move
conversely if the market is above the
people range and makes a downward move
it would find support at that level if
the market does breach that support it
should have enough force behind it to
make a significant downward move the
next step is to factor the daily pivot
range into your trading strategy for the
current day depending upon where the
market settled the previous day the
daily pivot range would either be
support below the closed or resistance
above the closed if the market settled
within the daily pivot range it will be
neutral now based upon what the market
does today
the current
the pivot range we did our validate or
dismiss the previous day price section
for example let's say that on a day the
market rallied intraday and settled
strongly above the daily pivot range
that obviously sets a bullish tone for
the next day for the bullish sentiment
to be validated the market would have to
find support at the daily pivot range
and not trade below it like in this case
but what if the opposite happened and
the market broke with a daily pivot
range and traded lower then the previous
day bullish indication would be invalid
if you have identified the daily pivot
range as support and saw the market
going easily through it this would be a
good time to short the market why
because the market broke through the
daily pivot range so easily and is
likely to go much lower let's take a
look at some specific strategies using
only the pivot range as you can see on
this chart the ExxonMobil stock has a
daily pivot range of 80 1.2 to 81.4 and
closed at eighty two point nine setting
a bullish tone for the next day the next
day the stock opens at eighty three
point one the pivot range at eighty two
point four to eighty two point seven
represent support the stock trades lower
approaching eighty two point six but
does not go below and find support at
that point the price bounces and traded
immediately higher to eighty two point
nine what does that tell you in this
instance the market has snapped back
near the pivot range area and it
reversed quickly in this instance you
would go long after the market bounces
off the pivot range why because the
pivot range identified support the
market traded to that support level but
it couldn't go further as it rejected
that area the likelihood was for an
upward move
as in every trade the question you must
always ask yourself is where do I get
out if I'm wrong in this example with a
long position taken above the pivot
range your stop would be on the other
side of the Peapod range now let's
change the scenario in this chart you
can see that the ExxonMobil stock has a
daily pivot range of eighty one point
six to eighty one point seven five and
it closed at 82 it opens the next day at
eighty two point seven and it's traded
lower in this example as the market
approached the pivot range the selling
intensity increased and the stock traded
lower and the market sliced easily
through the pivot range and traded down
to eighty one point one at this point
you are watching to see if the stock
does indeed trade below the pivot range
it found the resistance at the pivot
range area at which you would initiate a
short position once again where is your
stop
at the top of the pivot range above
eighty one point nine so as the market
broke through the daily pivot range and
traded lower then the previous day
bullish indication would be invalid
that's why it's always good to wait for
the price to confirm or invalidate our
bias for the day let's take another
example what works when the market is
above the pivot range is also appliable
when it's below the pivot range for
example in this chart this stock had a
pivot range of eighty to two 82.6 and
closed the previous day at eighty one
point six the market opened higher
installed around the pivot range and
then slowly consolidated around that
area at this point the market reverses
and came back to retest the range at
eighty two level what would you do of
course this is an opportunity to short
the market why the market touched the
edge of the pivot range but it couldn't
and
trait the resistance zone the likelihood
was for a downward move your risk to the
upside would be the other side of the
pivot range here's another scenario you
can see the pivot range is at eighty to
two eighty-two point four with a closed
at eighty one point seven five this time
the market opens at eighty one point six
and trade steadily higher to eighty two
point two we're right in the middle of
the pivot range what would you do then
you would wait this is a neutral area
and until the market gets through one
side or the other you don't take any
trades so you don't take any positions
while the market is inside the pivot
range under another scenario this stock
has a pivot range at sixty eight point
two to sixty eight point four and the
outlook for today was bearish as the
price closed lower than the previous day
but this time the market traded steadily
higher from the opening and as you can
see was able to slice through this
resistance zone easily what would you do
now the answer is obvious with the pivot
range acting as resistance broken to the
upside your strategy would be to go
along your stuff is of course the bottom
of the pivot range below sixty eight
point two by now I hope you realize the
power of this technique using the daily
pivot range is one of the most powerful
ways to establish the potential movement
of the upcoming day which can offer at
the same time a certain bias about the
intraday price action so if you learn
something new and found value please
consider subscribing to our channel
share and like this video as it will
help us a lot in the future until next
time