The MACD is very popular among traders, yet
there's more to using and understanding it
than meets the eye.
The MACD uses moving-average lines to illustrate
changes in price patterns.
MACD is a great indicator to confirm the setups,
locate and follow the trends, no matter what
trading system you trade.
Among all the signals or patterns that MACD
makes, a MACD divergence is my favorite and
the most reliable leading signals I could
get.
A divergence in general occurs when the price
action is seeing lower lows while in a downtrend,
but the indicator is not reflecting that move.
Similarly, when the markets are trending higher,
you notice divergence when the price action
is seen scaling higher highs but somehow the
indicator remains firm of the changes, and
forms lower highs.
So, when the price of an asset, such as a
stock or currency pair, is moving in one direction
and the MACD's indicator line is moving in
the other, that's divergence.
This type of signal is supposed to warn of
a price- direction reversal, but the signal
can be misleading and inaccurate.
Another type of divergence is when a security's
price reaches a new high (or a new low) level,
but the MACD indicator doesn't.
Essentially what it conveys is the shift in
the market momentum.
After all, the markets are driven by momentum
and the momentum is the force that oscillates
between highs and lows and thereby bringing
the changes in the price action.
Traditionally, this would indicate that the
price's direction is losing momentum and is
priming for a reversal.
But, by its own, this can also prove to be
an unreliable trading signal.
While you don't need to understand the math
that underlies the calculation of the MACD,
by understanding more about how the MACD indicator
works, you'll be better positioned to avoid
getting fooled by its false signals or lack
of signals, such as when the price turns but
the MACD doesn't provide any warning.
So, let’s discuss about the main issues
with MACD divergences.
1.
First, MACD divergence after a sharp move
Monitoring the MACD indicator in relation
to price action reveals a few problems which
could affect traders who rely on the MACD
divergence tool.
A divergence pattern between the two MACD
lines will almost always occur right after
a sharp price move, whether higher or lower.
Determining whether a price move is sharp,
slow, large or small requires looking at the
velocity and magnitude of the price movements
around it.
Price momentum can't continue forever so as
soon as the price begins to level off, the
MACD trend lines will diverge (for example,
go up, even if the price is still dropping).
After a strong price rally, the MACD divergence
is no longer useful.
By dropping, while the price continues to
move higher or move sideways, the MACD is
showing momentum has slowed but it doesn't
indicate a reversal.
In this example, the EUR/USD is falling, yet
the MACD is rising.
Had a trader assumed that the rising MACD
was a positive sign, they may have exited
their short trade, missing out on additional
profit.
Or they may have taken a long trade, even
though the price action showed a significant
downtrend and no signs of a reversal (no higher
swing highs or higher swing lows to indicate
an end to the downtrend).
That doesn't mean divergence can't or won't
signal the occasional reversal, but it must
be taken with a grain of salt after a big
move.
Since divergence occurs after almost every
big move, and most big moves aren't immediately
reversed right after, if you assume that divergence,
in this case, means a reversal is coming,
you could get yourself into a lot of losing
trades.
2.
Problems with divergence between MACD highs
(or lows)
Traders also compare prior highs on the MACD
with current highs or prior lows with current
lows.
For example, if the price moves above a prior
high, traders will watch for the MACD to also
move above its prior high.
If it doesn't, that's a divergence or a traditional
warning signal of a reversal.
This signal is also related to the problem
discussed before.
A lower MACD high-price level shows the price
didn't have the same velocity it had last
time it moved higher (it may have moved less,
or it may have moved slower), but that doesn't
necessarily indicate a reversal.
As discussed above, a sharp price move will
cause a large move in the MACD, larger than
what is caused by slower price moves.
An asset's price can move higher or lower,
slowly, for very long periods of time.
If this occurs after a steeper move (more
distance covered in less time), then the MACD
will show divergence for much of the time
the price is slowly marching higher (relative
to the prior sharp move).
If a trader assumes a lower MACD high means
the price will reverse, a valuable opportunity
may be missed to stay long and collect more
profit from the slower increase higher.
Or worse, the trader may take a short position
into a strong uptrend, with little evidence
to support the trade except for an indicator
which isn't useful in this situation.
This example shows a downtrend.
The downtrend is caused by sharp downward
moves, followed by slower downward moves.
This results in divergence when the next price
wave isn't as sharp, but in no way indicates
a reversal on the MACD.
MACD divergence was present this whole time,
yet the price dropped all day.
If monitoring divergence, an entire day of
profits on the downside would have been missed.
Another problem with watching for this type
of divergence is that it often isn't present
when an actual price reversal occurs.
Therefore, we have an indicator which provides
many false signals (divergence occurs, but
price doesn't reverse), but also fails to
provide signals on many actual price reversals
So, having these 2 MACD problems in mind,
how you improve the accuracy rate of spotting
divergences correctly using this indicator?
I use 3 steps:
First one.
It’s safe to say we must focus on the price
action first, instead of divergence.
For a downtrend to reverse, the price must
make a higher swing high and/or a higher swing
low.
To reverse an uptrend, the price must make
a lower swing high and/or a lower swing low.
Until these occur, a price reversal isn't
present.
Whether divergence is present or not isn't
important.
Traders make money off price movements, not
MACD movements.
The second step.
I look for double divergence patterns, meaning
i want to see a divergence on both the histogram
and on the signal and MACD line.
Third step.
With the creation of a double divergence on
the charts, i prefer to draw a trend line
on the charts and enter after a breakout.
This way, my stop loss is optimized below
or above the breakout and the entry points
are clearly identified.
Keep in mind that a trend might continue over
an extended period even after a double divergence.
So it goes without saying that your stops
should be in place at all times to act as
safety net against any potential misreading
or miscalculation of risks.
Another interesting factor, to notice in case
of a double divergence, is volumes will decrease
when the second divergence is underway.
Thus, it is a point where the momentum and
the volume seem to arrive at common grounds
to represent a specific price action phenomenon.
Here’s visa on a 15-min time frame.
We have a first divergence on the histogram
here.
The second divergence on the MACD line here.
The market was making higher highs and higher
lows, so in order to trade the double MACD
divergence, we needed the price to record
a lower low.
Which it did, and at the same time, we had
the 3rd step completed, as the trend line
marking the uptrend was broken to the downside.
With all 3 conditions met, a short after the
breakout was a high probability trade.
So we combined price action, with the MACD,
to find a decent short trade.
The same pattern but on a downtrend.
The histogram divergence.
The MACD line divergence.
A higher swing high.
And the downslope trend line breakout.
Perfect entry.
Here are other examples of double MACD divergence
trades.
It goes without saying that the price action
needs to be followed after you’re in a trade.
It does not mean that you have to be up and
awake in front of the screen all day monitoring
ever pip move but at the same time, you must
remember never to lose sight of the primary
levels and how they need to be capitalized
in conjunction with the new trend in the market,
which hopefully started after the MACD divergence.
And remember not to have irrational expectation
from the market.
Set up realistic profit and loss targets and
work towards realizing the profit.
I like to use this double divergence strategy
in my day trading activity, but it can also
be used with as a swing trading tool.
If you learned something new and found value,
leave us a like to show your support and don’t
forget to subscribe and hit the bell icon
to stay in touch with new uploads.
Until next time.