eople points are used by forex traders
to locate potential support and
resistance areas they are levels where
price interaction may cause a reaction
in addition pivot points help traders
confirm the bias and sentiment in the
market over a given time interval a
pivot point is calculated as an average
of significant prices high low and close
from the performance of a market in the
prior trading period if the market in
the following period trades above the
pivot point it is usually evaluated as a
bullish sentiment
whereas training below the pivot point
is seen as bearish pivot points are
considered leading indicators as they
have predictive qualities many forex
traders prefer to use pivot points over
many other types of horizontal levels as
they are more objective and easy to
understand
pivot points are a tool that can help
traders recognize points of interest
where traders are likely to see
increased order flow traders tend to
play stop-loss orders and take profit
targets around these levels so there's a
higher chance of activity that can cause
price rejections or breakouts from these
levels many forex traders are aware of
what people points are and may even
incorporate the support and resistance
levels into their trading strategy but
there are many different variations of
pivot points the ones you are most
likely familiar is the standard pivot
points one of my favorite type is the
fibonacci pivot point
Fibonacci studies such as retracements
expansions and projections are quite
popular in the financial markets
the primary Fibonacci levels that
traders watch most closely are the 38.2
and the 61 point 8 with trace month
levels but did you know that you can
incorporate these different levels into
a people two-point calculation as well
in fact it is very similar to the
standard pivot points with the
additional inclusion of the thirty-eight
point to sixty one point eight and one
hundred ratios fibonacci pivot points
method uses the same formula to
determine the central pivot point level
as the floor traders pivot method the
support and resistance levels are
calculated by using Fibonacci
retracements and extensions levels of
the previous session trading range
Fibonacci pivot points can be used in
two ways to spot the main trend of the
traded instrument or use them to enter
and exit the market to identify the
direction if the price level of the
pivot point is broken in an ascending
move the market is bullish and if it
breaks below it it is bearish generally
if price is hold above the fibonacci
pivot point it can be seen that the
market will be up trending and if the
price holds below the pivot point the
market is down trending so the simplest
way to use Fibonacci pivot points are as
regular support and resistance levels
here are some important tips regarding
fibonacci pivot points you should be
aware of first the more times the price
touches a pivot level then reverses the
stronger the level is if the market
found rejection at that particular level
it means it holds a great significance
for market participants here are some
examples of fibonacci pivot point
rejections
[Music]
the second dip support one-and two-and
resistance 1 and 2 of the Bonacci pivots
may cause reversals but they may also be
used to confirm the trend for example if
the price is falling and moves below s1
it helps confirm the downtrend and
indicate a possible continuation to s2
if the price is increasing and moves
above r1
it helps confirm the uptrend and
indicate a possible continuation to r2
here are some examples of continuation
moves after the breakout of s1 + r1
levels now let's see how to trade using
Fibonacci pivot points this trading
strategy is very simple but it's one of
the most powerful ways that you can take
away from trading with Fibonacci pivots
the training rules are straightforward
if we are in an upward trend with the
market making higher highs and higher
lows he will look to buy at support at
either s1 or at the main pivot point
with our target set at either
r1 or r2 if we are in a downtrend with
the market making lower lows and lower
highs you will look to sell at
resistance and either r1 or at the main
pivot point with your target set at
either s1 or s2
also don't focus on s2 s3 or r2 and r3
levels in a strong upward or downward
training market since these levels are
not often tested during a strong bullish
or bearish advance so remember that this
is a trend following strategy not a
pivot reversal strategy looking at this
chart you can see the importance of 180
people points in their accuracy in this
example we determined the main upward
trend by analyzing recent market swings
you could also add a moving average for
a better visualization of the trend I
prefer to use longer period moving
averages to confirm the trend like the
200 or the 100 moving the average during
this rally
we have consecutive days of higher
pivots the central pivot point is the
most important part for me the location
of the main pivot point on the chart
represents a critical information to be
aware because there is a high
probability that it will be reached
that's why I prefer to compare the value
of the main pivot point with a value of
the previous day and if the current
pivot point is higher than the previous
one I consider taking only long entries
if the current pivot point is lower than
the previous one I consider taking only
short entries so coming back to our
example you can observe that the main
pivots are well separated and are acting
as a perfect area of support s2 and s3
are never touched during these days so
we'll look to buy around the central
pivot point and s1 levels using price
action or any other technique you prefer
you can also use indicators to spot your
entry the choice is up to you
here are other examples of trending
markets and opportunities to buy or sell
using Fibonacci pivot points you can
also merge the Fibonacci pivot levels
with regular Fibonacci retracements to
discover trade entries the best
combination from my experience is the
daily central pivot point or the s1 or
r1 levels with the 38.2 and the 50 if
you wanna to retrace mint levels
practically you will draw deep levels
and you want the retracements to
correlate with pivot points like in this
example observe how the retracement
level practically coincided with the
Fibonacci divot point which is a
powerful signal there are a number of
variations and potential entries for
this specific strategy from candlestick
patterns trendline breakouts or even
entries based on indicators so we look
for a confluence of people naturally
trace match levels with the daily
central pivot point or s1 + r1 level if
price retraces to the identified
confluence either enter at the market or
wait for a candle signal or any other
trigger at the conference zone obviously
it is more risky to enter before getting
the confirmation signal but such
approach gives a higher risk reward
ratio here are other examples of entries
based on retracement levels and pivot
points
while training with the Fibonacci pivot
points you have to follow some important
rules you have to use money management
and risk management techniques also you
should take into consideration the
features of the certain markets where
you conduct your analysis because the
price react in a way on the forex market
and in a completely different way on the
stock market for example ideally
Fibonacci pivot points have to be used
with other methods of analysis and
forecasting of the behavior of your
instruments from my experience it's
better to use Fibonacci pivot points on
the charts for one hour and higher the
higher the timeframe the stronger the
signal will be if you enjoyed this type
of content give it a thumbs up to show
your support also make sure to subscribe
and hit the bell icon to get notified
each time we upload until next time