Trading with patterns is an essential component
of technical analysis.
This means that you need to shift your focus
on price action and what the pattern shows.
All markets, regardless of type, have one
thing in common.
That is, they all consolidate in ranges.
A lot.
Therefore, one of the most common chart patterns
are triangles.
The triangle pattern is a specific figure
formed on the price chart, typically identified
when the tops and the bottoms of the price
action are moving toward each other like the
sides of a triangle.
When the upper and the lower level of a triangle
interact, traders expect an eventual breakout
from that area.
As such, many breakout traders use triangle
formations for identifying breakout entry
points.
There are different kinds of triangles that
can be seen on a chart.
In this video we’ll take a closer look at
the ascending triangle pattern and the corresponding
trade setups.
Once you are equipped with this knowledge,
you should be able to add a triangle trading
strategy to your trade setup arsenal.
The ascending triangle formation is a continuation
pattern and as the name suggests it has the
shape of a triangle.
The ascending triangle is also known as the
bullish triangle because it leads to a bullish
breakout.
This is how the ascending triangle looks like:
The first element of this price pattern is
an upward slope followed by a flat top.
This shows that the market has tried multiple
times to break the resistance top but it couldn’t.
Hence, we have developed a resistance line.
The second element of the ascending triangle
is a rising trend line moving upwards.
This is what makes the pattern bullish.
Now, all continuation patterns need to have
a context of a trend.
In the case of the bullish ascending triangle,
we need to have a previous uptrend to support
the breakout.
Now that you learned how the ascending formation
looks like i want to share with you several
important things that I’ve learned from
trading the bullish triangle.
First, on a price chart, the triangle pattern
will rarely have a perfect shape.
Often times you’ll see an ascending wedge
pattern which will break the resistance line
but have no real momentum behind the breakout.
Other times, the pattern will develop spiky
bars that will lead to false breakouts.
There is no perfect pattern.
What's the first thing you see in this chart?
That's right, the pattern is not perfect.
I remember how I would read a book on a specific
chart pattern and then when i would go in
the market, I could never find an exact match.
For example, in this chart, notice how the
highs are not aligned perfectly.
But, notice how the stock breaks through the
uptrend line, only to go higher.
So don’t search only for perfect triangles.
Also, you really need to think in terms of
what it’s going on behind the scene.
You don’t just have to look at the price,
but also try to read what the market participants
are doing.
When the price is moving up, it starts to
develop the classical higher lows.
For whatever the reasons, the buyers may become
a little bit more aggressive with each new
successive higher low.
Or, we can say that the sellers aren’t too
aggressive when the market turns down inside
the ascending triangle chart pattern.
Whichever alternative you prefer, that is
what it’s causing the triangle price formation
to develop.
When we reach the climax point of the triangle
where the price has nowhere to go, that’s
the moment when you should anticipate a breakout.
The location of the pattern is also important!
If the triangle pattern is inside of a big
trading range, then the solid resistance level
might not be that significant.
If you pay attention at this chart, you’ll
notice the triangle pattern, but the problem
is that it develops inside a big trading range,
so even if there is a small breakout, the
upward movement is restricted by this other
resistance.
However, if the ascending triangle price formation
develops in the middle of a bullish trend
that would add more weight to the pattern.
When the ascending triangle develops within
a trend then we’re going to be interested
in buying the breakout, like in this example.
Regardless of their location, during a trend,
ascending triangles are bullish patterns that
indicate accumulation.
The higher lows in the pattern are a clue
that buyers are not letting their position
go at lower prices as the pattern makes higher
lows.
Another important tip is that you need to
have a clear resistance level, with a series
of highs occurring at or near the same price.
You don't want to have one or two peaks, because
it might be a swing high or double top.
There needs to be a number of clear attempts
by the bulls that go nowhere with the price.
Once the triangle breakout happens you need
to see a pick-up in volume that will result
in a nice long trade.
The next thing you want to see in a breakout
is for volume to accelerate on the move higher.
This does not mean the volume on the breakout
has to be the highest over the last 24 hours
or something.
It just means you need to see some acceleration
to the upside.
The key point is you want to see buyers participate
in the move to increase the likelihood of
follow-through.
How do you trade an ascending triangle pattern?
The classic method is to buy the breakout
once you have had 3 or more touches with volume.
Now, you have a few choices of where to enter.
The first option is to buy on the highest
high after three or more tops.
The potential issue with this approach is
that the price could fail and is still either
developing the ascending triangle or you are
caught in a bull trap.
The main problem with triangles, and chart
patterns in general, is the potential for
false breakouts.
The price may move out of the pattern only
to move back into it, or the price may even
proceed to break out the other side.
A pattern may need to be redrawn several times
as the price edges past the trend lines but
fails to generate any momentum in the breakout
direction.
What I prefer is to look at pivot points.
I like to wait for a key pivot point resistance
level to be breached and then place a buy
order slightly above this level.
The potential issue with this approach is
you are exposed to more risk as you are buying
at higher levels with greater downside exposure.
But, this will eliminate a lot of false breakouts,
which will occur a lot.
That’s why I like to add a safety net by
using pivot points.
So, if you pay attention at this example,
we have the upper trend line, with higher
lows, the clear resistance level, and the
breakout.
But, in real time, as we don’t know if the
breakout is real or not, we wait for the price
to consolidate above this pivot level, as
a confirmation of the breakout of the pattern.
Once the price consolidated above, we can
safely search for long entries.
Here are other examples of ascending triangles
breakouts, with pivot points confirmation.
Another approach is to buy inside of the triangle.
Once you see the pattern setting up, you can
wait for a touch of the uptrend line and then
place a long entry.
The benefits with this approach are that you
can place a tighter stop since you are closer
to the demand line (support), this also gives
you a potential profit before the actual breakout.
The downside to this approach is you could
wait a longer time for the move through the
top of the triangle, in a possible consolidation
phase.
This is a more advanced technique, and the
most important thing is that you need to have
a clear uptrend.
When you spot an ascending triangle on the
chart, you should be prepared to catch a bullish
price move equal to at least the size of the
triangle.
A profit target can be estimated based on
the height of the triangle added from the
breakout price.
The white lines correspond to the size of
the triangle and its potential target, which
is typically a 1:1 measured move.
So, the profit target for the setup is the
distance of the triangle added to the top.
Regarding stops, there are multiple areas
where you can place your stop orders.
First, you can place the stop order beneath
the uptrend line.
You can also use the low of the breakout candle.
If the price is able to break out, you can
place your stop below the low of the candlestick.
This way if the price reverses, you are not
waiting until the uptrend line is breached.
This way you can keep more of your gains.
Also, keep in mind, while ascending triangles
provide a profit target, that target is just
an estimate.
The price may far exceed that target, or fail
to reach it.
This is why, using proper risk-reward ratios
is mandatory.
Otherwise, the risk is that the triangle pattern
will transform into something else and will
invalidate the reason you have entered in
that particular trade in the first place.
If you got any value from this and learned
something new, don’t forget to subscribe,
hit the bell icon and leave us a like to show
your support.