the average true range is one of the
best indicators a day trader can use as
it basically tells you how much the
price of a market moves up and down the
ATR indicator is always moving it goes
up when price movements get bigger and
down when they get smaller every time a
new time candle forms the ATR gets a new
reading on a one minute chart the ATR is
figured out every single minute on a
daily chart the ATR is calculated once a
day so the ATR differs from time frame
to time frame all this readings are
connected to make a line and this lets
you see how the price swings have
changed over time the ATR has one main
job to tell you how much the price of a
market is really moving around when the
range is Big it means there's a lot of
volatility when the range is small it
aest price action is Cal the ATR is
basically a special kind of moving
average of the the true range most of
the time Traders use the 14 period ATR
but you can use shorter or longer ATR
values depending on the time frame
you're looking at a longer ATR will be
slower and give fewer trading signals a
shorter ATR will give more trading
signals and make you trade more often
here's how to read the average true
range indicator first the ATR is a tool
for filtering trades based on how how
much the price is moving if you like
markets with big swings the ATR can help
you avoid markets that are too calm if
you prefer quiet markets the ATR can
help you stay away from times that are
too wild for you but it's important to
remember that the ATR doesn't tell you
which way the price is going by looking
at the default ATR indicator you can't
tell what the main trend is the ATR only
measures how big the range is it's not
the best for making trading signals on
its own I have a solution for this I'll
explain it in a few
moments now the market moves in Cycles
it expands and contracts and moves from
periods of rest to periods of activity
and the ATR is your key to understanding
these Cycles when the ATR is low when
it's at its lowest values it's a sign
that the market is in a phase of
consolidation this is the Market's rest
phase volatil is low and there's not a
lot of action happening this phase of
consolidation is often seen in chart
patterns like rectangles triangles or
Flags the price is essentially coiling
up getting ready to move in One
Direction or the other this is your
signal to be on high alert so when you
see the ATR at its lowest values you
start to prepare you look for Clues as
to which direction the market might
break you look at things like the
overall trend key supply and demand
areas volume or Candlestick formations
you use these to get a sense of the
Market's
intentions if the prevailing trend is up
and the price is consolidating above a
key demand area with a low ATR you might
anticipate a bullish breakout the market
is catching its bread before the next
leg up on the other hand if the
prevailing trend is down and the price
is consolidating below a key resistance
level with a low ATR we might anticipate
a bearish breakdown this is the power of
using the ATR to identify phases of
consolidation it gives you a heads up
that a big move might be coming and it
allows you to prepare
accordingly the longer the ATR remains
at low values the more powerful the
following move is likely to be so if you
see an extended period of low ATR values
a prolonged phase of consolidation be
ready for a potentially large move this
is where the phase of expansion comes in
once the market breaks out of its
consolidation phase it enters a phase of
expansion this is when the ATR starts to
rise indicating increasing volatility
and larger price moves if you've
anticipated the direction correctly you
can now look to enter trades in the
direction of the breakout aiming to
capture a chunk of this expansionary
move as I said the average true range
doesn't tell you which way the market is
going if the ATR is going up on the
chart it doesn't mean the trend is up so
instead of using the default ATR you
could use other indicators that
incorporate ATR into their calculations
the first one is the chandelier exit at
its core the chandelier exit is a
volatility based indicator that will
help you determine where to place your
stop loss orders it does this by using
the ATR and a multiplier this is a
dynamic indicator meaning it adjusts its
levels based on the recent price action
and volatility as the price moves up the
chandelier exit moves up with it always
maintaining a set distance based on the
ATR if the price starts to fall and hits
the chandelier level it's a signal that
the trend may be reversing and it's time
to exit exit the
trade the chandelier exit plots a single
line on your chart either above or below
the price action depending on whether
you're looking at a long or short trade
when the price hits or crosses this line
it's a signal to exit your trade the key
is in the settings you get to decide two
inputs the length of the ATR period
usually 14 or 22 and the ATR multiplier
usually between two and four a higher
multiplier will place your chandelier
further away from the price giving your
trade more room to breathe but also
potentially leading to larger losses if
the trade goes against you a lower
multiplier will keep your stop- loss
tighter protecting your Capital but also
potentially leading to more frequent
stops for day trading you could start
with an ATR period and a multiplier of
two then you back test it's all about
finding that sweet spot that aligns with
your strategy and risk tolerance the
beauty of this indicator is its
Simplicity it can be used with any
trading strategy here's a basic setup
for a long trade you identify a market
that's in a clear uptrend and looks
poised to continue you wait for a
pullback or consolidation and then look
for a bullish entry signal like a
breakout or a bullish Candlestick
pattern once you're in the trade you
place your stop loss at the current
chandelier exit level as the price moves
up the chandelier exit will move up with
it effectively trailing your stop loss
to lock in profits if the price hits the
chandelier level you exit the trade it's
a simple but effective way to let your
winners run while also protecting your
downside and of course like any
indicator the chandelier exit isn't
perfect F signals will happen especially
in choppy or sideways markets that's why
it's important to use it in conjunction
with other forms of analysis like price
action and key
levels the ATR bands indicator is
another volatility based tool which
creates bands around the price action
using the average true range this
indicator contains two bands that sit a
certain distance away from the price
action this distance is determined by
the ATR and a multiplier think of it
like a river with two Banks the price
action is the water and the ATR bands
are the river banks containing and
guiding the flow the width of the ATR
bands is dynamic it changes based on the
price volatility when the price is more
volatile the ATR will be higher and the
bands will be wider when the price is
less volatile the ATR will be lower and
the bands will be narrower
So based on how much the price has been
moving the indicator offers you a
reasonable range for where the price
might go next it's all about watching
the price action in relation to the band
when the price is trading close to the
upper band it suggests that the market
is in a strong uptrend if it touches the
upper band this could be a signal to
consider taking profits or to be
cautious about new long positions on the
flip side when the price is trading
close to the lower band it suggests that
the market is in a strong downtrend when
price touches the lower band this could
be a signal to consider exiting short
positions or to be on the lookout for a
potential bounce and of course the ATR
bands have their limitations they're a
lagging indicator meaning they're based
on past price action so take the time to
understand how the indicator works and
experiment with different settings like
the ATR period and the
multiplier super trend is another ATR
based indicator that helps you determine
the direction of the trend and potential
buy or sell signals when reading super
Trend indicator it's all about watching
for changes in color and position
relative to the price when the super
trend line is green and below the price
it's pointing North signaling a buy or
an uptrend when it's red and above the
price it's pointing South signaling a
cell or a downtrend I like it because it
gives you a clear visual representation
of the trend by using a combination of
the ATR and a multiplier that multiplier
is a way to adjust the sensitivity of
the indicator as long as the price
remains above a green super Trend or
below a red super Trend the trend is
considered intact this can help you you
ride trends for longer potentially
increasing your profits if you make a
habit of Consulting the ATR before every
trade you'll be a step ahead of the game
so take the time to understand how the
indicator Works how to read its signals
and try to incorporate it into your
trading plan and if you need some
strategies that work perfectly with the
ATR you definitely must check out these
videos