The relative strength index.
Every time i read an article or see a video
about it, there’s the same misconception
every single time: it’s an overbought/oversold
indicator, you buy when the RSI is oversold
and sell when it’s overbought.
No, this doesn’t work, not by itself.
You will not make money using the RSI in this
way.
There’s a lot more about the RSI besides
the overbought and oversold levels and in
the following minutes I’ll show you everything
you must know about the RSI, how to correctly
trade with it and how to avoid bad signals
so you don’t get stuck in overbought or
oversold territory for weeks or months.
Before we continue, if you are new to the
channel, make sure you subscribe, hit the
bell notifications and leave a like to show
your support.
Now, the relative strength index is one of
the most popular technical indicators and
is adjusted by the amount by which the market
increased or fell.
The RSI values range from 0 to 100.
A high RSI occurs when the market has been
increasing rapidly.
A low RSI occurs when the market has been
selling off sharply.
On lower time frames, the relative strength
index is very volatile, frequently reaching
extreme highs and lows, and generating contradicting
signals.
In flat markets, the RSI will generate signals
while prices trade in a range, with no clear
direction.
So, used in a wrong way, RSI is useless for
many traders.
Let’s see what are the main techniques involving
the RSI and how to correctly use it to maximize
you trading results.
First, you could use RSI as an overbought/oversold
indicator.
The RSI is indeed useful for gaining an overview
of the overbought/oversold conditions of the
market but it should not be used as a trading
signal without a confirmation.
Don’t let the 70/30 RSI levels fool you
into entering countertrend positions.
Simply because a market reaches overbought
or oversold levels, doesn’t mean that prices
will immediately reverse in the opposite direction.
During periods of strong upward trends or
downward trends, markets can remain in the
overbought or oversold areas for days, weeks
or even months.
Just look at this example.
A short here would have been a very bad trading
decision, because the price continued to increase
aggressively.
Here’s an important tip to increase your
chances for trading overbought and oversold
levels.
Combine support and resistance levels with
the RSI and look for area of confluence between
the RSI and strong areas of support and resistance.
An overbought RSI at 75 level means nothing,
but at RSI at 75 and the price at an important
level of resistance has a higher probability
for a successful short.
Here is a simple example.
We have the Apple stock on the 30 min chart.
The RSI hit 70 level and the price was trading
at a resistance level, which also coincided
with an area of breakout from previous price
action.
So we had 3 major forces around that area.
This is a no-brainer short, at an area of
confluence.
We have almost an identical trade on this
tesla chart.
The price broke the support to the downside,
and came back to the breakout level, with
the RSI reaching overbought areas.
As soon as the price hit that area, was unable
to go higher and continued its downward direction.
Here is a buy example.
Remember that the markets are not perfect
and not all the time the price will stop right
at the support level.
Here we had some stop loss hunting or a false
breakout and the price reversed.
If we look a little back in the chart, we
have another buy opportunity, when the RSI
was oversold and the price met support.
Another great use of the relative strength
index is to look for divergences between the
RSI and the price of the security/stock.
For example, when prices rallies to a new
high but the RSI cannot increase to a new
high, then we have a divergence.
However, a divergence between the RSI and
price is not an exceptional signal.
Just because an RSI divergence appears on
the charts, that doesn’t mean that you should
automatically enter a reverse position.
Here the price was in an aggressive downtrend
and the RSI formed a divergence.
Many traders bought here and got stopped out
very soon, because the price continued to
decrease sharply.
So don’t trade divergences blindly, look
for confirmation from price action.
A valid way to trade RSI divergences is to
wait for a trend line breakout.
In this example, we have a bearish RSI divergence,
with the price forming a double top, but the
RSI making lower highs.
A smart entry would be to wait for the price
to break the lower trend line of the upward
channel.
The price indeed rallied downward after the
price broke the trend line.
And here is a bullish RSI divergence.
We have a double bottom this time, and a RSI
making higher lows.
Once the price broke the upward trend line,
the market opened with a gap up and pushed
the price upward.
Another strategy you could use is to take
signals on RSI around the 50 level.
When RSI indicator crosses above 50, a buy
signal is generated
When RSI indicator crosses below 50, a sell
This leads some people to think when the RSI
crosses the 50 level to the upside that the
trend up, and when the RSI drops below the
50 level, the trend is down.
But here is what you need to know: during
trending conditions, the RSI indicator will
offer very good signals.
If you look at this Apple chart, you can clearly
see some excellent signals but what about
when the markets are not trending?
You would get chopped out.
So try to use this technique when the markets
are trending.
In order to smooth the signals offered by
the RSI indicator, you could add a moving
average on the indicator.
By adding a moving average on the RSI, you
could search for crossovers, for better quality
signals.
Now, when you want to trade a crossover between
the RSI and a moving average, you should be
aware of an important thing.
A crossover will catch good movements when
markets are trending.
When markets are trading in a range, this
approach is will lead to a lot of losing trades.
A longer-term moving average added on RSI
will work better than short-term moving average
and will produce fewer false signals.
So, instead of adding a 10 moving average
on the RSI for example, try adding a 50 moving
average or a 100 moving average and see what
the market tells you.
The RSI indicator can also be useful for drawing
trend lines.
The technique of drawing trend lines is subjective,
is not a precise science.
This method is simple: you draw straight lines
on the RSI indicator connecting support points
for an uptrend or resistance points for a
downtrend.
A valid trend line should connect two or more
support points that define the trend.
Now, here’s what you should consider.
If you will start drawing trend lines on lower
time frames, it will not work.
There is too much noise and you will record
lots of false signals.
So never use this technique on a time frame
lower than H1 (one hour).
Since the RSI is one of the most popular indicators,
traders always tweak their RSI settings, depending
on their favorite timeframe or trading style.
RSI indicator is excellent at generating buy
and sell signals.
Most of them use the standard settings, RSI
set on a 14 period.
RSI of 5, 7 and 50 period are also popular
among traders.
A shorter RSI period – below 10 - will be
very volatile and will generate a lot of false
signals
A longer RSI period – above 20 - smooths
out the plotted line and will generate fewer,
but more accurate signals.
Now that we saw how to trade with the RSI,
let’s consider the pros and the cons of
using this indicator.
The RSI is good during a trending market condition,
combined with moving averages.
Also, is excellent at identifying divergences
on the chart and overbought and oversold areas.
At the same time, the RSI is a lagging indicator
and does not contain all of the data necessary
for proper analysis of price action, so it
should be used in combination with other tools.
If you liked this video, make sure you hit
that like button, subscribe and turn on the
notification bell, so you’ll be notified
every time we upload.
Until next time.