You are programmed to always chase
price, always one step behind the market.
That’s because the big players hunt liquidity,
creating the moves others try to follow!
Today I'll teach you how to spot and
trade liquidity, just like the pros!
What is liquidity?
When you first started
trading, you probably learned about support and
resistance, chart patterns, and other basic stuff.
Many brokers even offer free education on these
topics. But why? It's not just to be nice!
They want lots of traders
using the same strategies.
Because this creates predictable
liquidity, that can be exploited.
Think about it. If most traders are using
the same methods, it's easy for big banks and
institutions to predict what they'll do.
They can use this knowledge to move the
market in ways that benefit them.
It's like setting up dominos. Once
they're all lined up, it just takes
a little push to create a big effect.
This is liquidity! In its simplest form,
liquidity refers to the orders or money
present in the market.
Market prices move based
on the flow of buy and sell orders.
More buying pressure pushes prices up,
while more selling pressure pushes prices down.
For substantial price movements to occur,
the market needs to interact with areas of high
order concentration, also known as liquidity.
So liquidity means all the buy and
sell orders waiting to be filled.
Now, here's the interesting part - if there
isn't enough liquidity, the big players,
the smart money, will create it.
For big traders, like banks or
hedge funds, liquidity is critical.
They deal with large amounts of money.
In less liquid markets, their big
trades can push prices around a lot.
This makes it hard for them to
buy or sell without losing money.
Now, if you understand where liquidity sits, you
can identify magnet areas, those price levels that
attract price movement.
What are liquidity pools
Your main task is to find liquidity pools.
Liquidity pools are like busy trading spots
in the market.
They're areas
where lots of buy and sell orders gather.
And they form at key price levels. These could
be previous highs or lows, round numbers or other
important points. We’ll talk about these later.
Now, traders often place their orders at these
levels, creating a cluster of potential trades.
There are different types of liquidity pools:
Major liquidity pools, which form at the
highs and lows of longer timeframes.
These are big, important levels that
many traders watch. You might see them on
weekly, monthly, or even yearly charts.
Medium liquidity pools, that show up on shorter
timeframes, like 1-hour charts. These are still
significant, but not as big as the major pools.
Minor liquidity pools appear on very short
timeframes, like 1-minute or 5-minute
charts. These are smaller and might
only matter for very short-term traders.
Liquidity pools work by attracting price.
When price approaches a liquidity
pool, a few things can happen.
It might reverse, as lots of
orders get filled at that level.
Or it might pause there before continuing.
Sometimes, it might even break through quickly,
if there's enough momentum.
And big players are constantly
trying to "hunt" these liquidity pools.
They often push price to these levels, to trigger
a bunch of orders, causing a sharp move.
How to identify liquidity zones
So liquidity zones are key areas on a chart where
smart money players often target, to protect
their positions and to trap retail traders.
These zones act like magnets for price, drawing
it in, and often causing significant moves.
So let's talk about each type of liquidity zone,
and how smart money uses them to their advantage.
First area is around structural highs and lows.
These are major turning points in price action.
The the peaks and valleys you see on a chart,
that stand out from the rest.
Smart money loves these spots
because they know traders often place
their stop losses just beyond them.
Let's say we have a strong uptrend, with
a series of higher highs and higher lows.
Traders often jump on this trend, placing
their stops just below the most recent low.
And smart money knows this. They often
push the price down, breaking that low
and triggering all those stop losses.
This flood of sell orders drives the
price down further, often before smart
money steps in to buy, at a discount.
The same happens in downtrends. Retail
shorts place their stops above recent highs.
Smart money spike the price up, hit those
stops, then drive the price back down.
To spot these zones, look for clear
swing highs and lows on your charts.
The more obvious they are, the more
likely they are to attract attention.
Trend lines are another favorite tool of traders.
The diagonal lines that connect a series of
lows in an uptrend, or highs in a downtrend.
They're simple to draw and easy to understand,
which is why so many traders rely on them.
Big players often target these trend lines,
especially long-standing ones.
They know that many traders will have
stop losses placed just beyond these lines.
By breaking a significant trend line,
they can trigger a cascade of orders.
For instance, in a long-standing uptrend,
many traders will be long with their
stops just below the trend line.
Smart money might push the
price down to break this line.
As stops are hit, more sell orders flood in.
Smart money can then step in, and buy at lower
prices before resuming the uptrend.
Equal highs and lows, also known as
double tops and double bottoms,
are also exploited by smart money.
These patterns form when price reaches the same
level twice, creating a potential reversal point.
Traders often see these patterns and
place their trades accordingly.
For a double top, they might go short,
with a stop just above the equal highs.
For a double bottom, they might go long,
with a stop just below the equal lows.
Smart money knows this and often pushes the
price just beyond these levels to trigger
stop losses, before reversing.
This creates a liquidity pool
that they can use to their advantage.
Trading sessions, particularly the Asian,
London, and New York sessions, often
create their own ranges. These ranges
can become significant liquidity zones,
especially at their highs and lows.
Big players often target the sessions’ highs
and lows, because they know many traders use
them for entries and stop placements.
For example, many traders use the Asian
session range as a guide for the London session.
They might place buy orders above the Asian high,
and sell orders below the Asian low.
Smart money might push the price just
beyond these levels to trigger these orders,
creating liquidity that they can trade against.
They might spike the price above the Asian high,
triggering buy orders, only to sell into this
liquidity, and push the price back down.
The previous day's high and low are other
significant levels that many traders watch.
They often serve as support and resistance
levels for the current day's trading.
Again, the big boys know this, and frequently
target these levels.
For instance, many traders place
buy orders just above the previous day's high,
expecting the upward momentum to continue.
Smart money will push the price up to trigger
these orders, creating a pool of liquidity.
They can then sell into this liquidity,
potentially reversing the price direction.
The previous week's high and low also
attract a lot of attention. You might
not even know where those levels are.
These levels often act as key support
and resistance on higher timeframes.
And smart money often exploit these levels,
knowing that many swing traders
and position traders use them
for stop placement and entry orders.
For example, in a downtrend, many traders
might place sell orders below the previous
week's low, expecting the trend to continue.
Smart money often push the price
down to trigger these orders,
creating a liquidity pool they can buy into.
Supply and demand zones are other liquidity
zones. These are areas where price has
shown significant rejection in the past.
And these zones are prime targets
for smart money manipulation.
Smart money know many traders
place their orders around them.
For example, many traders might place buy orders
at a strong demand zone. Smart money might
push the price into this zone, triggering
these buy orders and creating liquidity.
They can then potentially sell into this
liquidity, driving the price even lower.
That’s why you see so many demand
zones that should work, in theory,
but in reality, they fail.
The same happens with supply
zones. Traders often place sell orders
at these levels, expecting price to drop.
Smart money might spike the price into the
supply zone, triggering these sell orders,
then buy into this liquidity to
potentially drive the price higher.
Fair Value Gaps (FVGs) are also
targeted. These are areas on the
chart where price has moved rapidly.
These gaps often act as magnets for
price, drawing it back to "fill" the gap.
Smart money often uses these gaps as targets.
For example, if there's a bullish Fair
Value Gaps, below the current price,
many traders might place buy orders in this area,
expecting price to come back and fill the gap.
Smart money might push the price down
through this level, triggering these
buy orders and creating liquidity.
The same happens with bearish Fair
Value Gaps, above the current price.
Traders often place sell orders in these
areas. Smart money might spike the price up
through the gap, triggering these sell orders.
That’s why maybe 90% of fair value gaps
fail. But that’s a topic for another video!
Round numbers, ending in zero or double zeros, are
psychologically significant levels that attract a
lot of attention from traders.
These levels are prime
targets for smart money manipulation.
Smart money knows that many retail traders
place their orders around these round numbers.
Many traders might place buy orders just above
a round number, or sell orders just below it.
The big boys often push the price to these
levels to trigger these orders, creating
liquidity that they can trade against.
For instance, if there's a round
number at the 50 dollar level,
many traders might place buy orders slightly above
it, expecting the price to rise above this level.
The big boys might push the price up, to trigger
these buy orders, creating a pool of liquidity.
They can then potentially sell into this
liquidity, driving the price back down.
Understanding all these liquidity zones,
and how smart money targets them is key.
It helps you avoid common traps.
As you practice, you'll start to see patterns.
You might notice that price often reverses
after taking out a previous high or low.
Or you might see that certain levels
keep causing price to pause or reverse.
And please, don't just draw
liquidity zones all over your chart.
Focus on the most important ones. Too many
zones can make your analysis confusing.
Also, pay attention to how price reacts
when it reaches a liquidity zone.
Does it reverse sharply? Does it pause and
then continue? Or does it blow right through?
This can give you clues about the strength
of the move, and what might happen next.
You might notice that certain types of zones
work better in certain market conditions,
or for certain currency pairs or stocks.
This is where keeping a detailed trading journal
with your findings, can be incredibly valuable,
allowing you to refine your strategy over time.
Liquidity inducement
Now let’s talk about liquidity inducement.
Inducement is about creating situations that make
other traders want to trade, at certain levels.
This creates available liquidity for bigger
players to use, when they want to enter
or exit their positions.
To understand this better,
let's look at how the market is structured.
When we look at charts, we see highs and lows.
Above these highs, we assume there's
buy-side liquidity, and below the lows,
we assume there's sell-side liquidity.
Buy-side liquidity is all the liquidity
that buyers will use, created mainly by stop loss
orders of sellers, and buy stop orders of buyers.
In a bullish market, price often uses buy-side
liquidity to fuel the next upward move.
To have a big bullish move, the market needs
sell orders to generate more liquidity.
Also, the buy orders from stop losses of sellers
generate more buy orders, which is why you often
see a surge in buying when price breaks out.
Sell-side liquidity is the opposite.
It's the liquidity that sellers will use,
created mainly by stop loss orders of
buyers and sell stop orders of sellers.
Imagine you see a double bottom on your
chart. This is when price hits the same
low point twice, forming a support level.
Many traders might want to buy at this support
level. Now, think about where these traders
would put their stop losses.
They'd likely put them just
below the lows. This creates a pool of
sell-side liquidity below the lows.
This is important because big
players need this liquidity.
They can't just jump into the market with huge
orders - that would cause wild price swings,
and could work against them.
Instead, they use liquidity
inducement to their advantage.
These big players create patterns or situations
in the market, that encourage other traders
to place their orders in predictable spots.
This builds up pools of liquidity,
that the big players can then use
to enter or exit their positions.
Now, before we continue, let us know
in the comments what topics you’d like us to
cover! And please drop us a like to help us
with Youtube algorithm.
Liquidity sweeps
Now let's talk about how big players
use this liquidity. They often create
what's called a "liquidity sweep".
It's when big players in the market,
try to take advantage of areas where
there's a lot of buy or sell orders waiting.
These areas are like pools of money
just sitting there, ready to be used.
For instance, if there's a strong support level
with many stop losses just below it, price might
sweep down to hit those stops before reversing.
This action "sweeps" the liquidity, letting
larger players fill their orders.
Knowing about liquidity sweeps can
help you in two main ways.
First, you can look for where
sweeps have already happened, as this might
show where big players have been active.
Second, you can use this knowledge
to guess future moves, by spotting
where available liquidity might be.
One way to trade these liquidity sweeps,
is by identifying "the inducement"
before a potential zone of interest.
This is where price action might
encourage traders to enter positions,
creating more liquidity for a potential move.
For example, if you're looking at a possible
buy zone, you might see price dip below
a previous low before the main move up.
This dip could make sellers enter
short positions or exit longs,
creating liquidity that larger players
can use to enter their long positions.
liquidity and market structure
Liquidity goes hand in hand with market structure.
Market structure refers to the overall pattern
of price movement. It's about identifying trends,
key levels, and the flow of the market.
Liquidity is about where buying and selling
activity clusters. These two concepts
work together to shape market behavior
Here's how they interact.
First, areas of high liquidity
often become key points in the market structure.
For example, a level with lots of buy orders
might become a strong support level.
If price keeps bouncing off this level,
it becomes part of the market structure.
Key structural levels tend to attract
liquidity. Traders often place their
orders around important structural points,
like trend lines or previous highs and lows.
This creates a feedback loop where structure
and liquidity reinforce each other.
Breaks in structure can drain liquidity.
When price breaks through a key structural level,
it often leads to a surge in trading activity.
This can temporarily drain liquidity from other
areas as traders rush to adjust their positions
Liquidity flows with structure: in a
strong trend, liquidity tends to cluster
in the direction of the trend.
For example, in an uptrend,
you might see more liquidity above the current
price as traders anticipate further rises.
Structure helps predict liquidity.
By reading the market structure,
you can often predict where liquidity might be.
For instance, after a series of higher lows in
an uptrend, you can expect liquidity
to gather below each of these lows.
Liquidity confirms structure. Sometimes, the
way price interacts with liquidity can confirm,
or deny the current market structure.
If price easily breaks through what
should be a liquidity-rich level, it might
signal a change in the overall structure.
Both liquidity and market structure guide price
movement. Price often moves towards liquidity,
but within the constraints of
the larger market structure.
And institutional activity links them.
Big players in the market often use
their understanding of both liquidity
and structure, to plan their trades.
Both liquidity and market structure change
over time: just as market structure evolves,
so does the distribution of liquidity.
What was a key liquidity level last week
might not be as important now. So keeping track
of both helps you stay in tune with the market.
The interplay between liquidity and structure
can help you spot truly important levels in the
market. Areas where structural levels align with
high liquidity are often the most significant.
In trading, we often talk about
"market structure shifts". The
big changes in the overall trend of the market.
Inducement often plays a role in these shifts.
For example, before a major trend change,
you might see price action that looks
like it's continuing the old trend.
This can trick traders into entering
positions in the direction of the old trend,
creating liquidity for the smart money to use
when reversing the market.
Also, liquidity inducement
is part of a larger market cycle.
The market typically goes through phases of
accumulation, markup, distribution, and markdown.
Liquidity inducement often occurs during the
accumulation and distribution phases, as smart
money prepares for the next significant move.
During accumulation, for instance, you might see
price action that looks choppy and directionless.
This can discourage retail traders and shake
out weak hands, while smart money quietly builds
positions. The apparent lack of direction
is itself a form of liquidity inducement,
creating opportunities for larger
players to buy at favorable prices.
This is why it's crucial to look beyond
just price action and consider volume,
momentum, and other factors that might
indicate the true market dynamics.
Liquidity inducement strategy
Liquidity inducement isn't something bad.
If you can spot it happening, you
might find good trading signals.
For entries, look for areas
where there's a lot of liquidity.
When the market is going up, look for
buy entries just below recent lows.
That's where big players often buy,
scooping up all the sell orders.
When the market is going down, look
to sell just above recent highs.
That's where big players often
sell into all the buy orders.
For exits, think about where other traders might
have their stop losses, or take profit orders.
These create pools of liquidity.
As price approaches these areas,
be ready to exit your trade.
The price might reverse once
it hits these liquidity pools.
Every time the market makes a
new range, mark the high and low.
If you're trading in this range,
you might enter at one end (where there's
internal liquidity) and exit at the other
end (where there's external liquidity).
Also, you want to trade where there's low
resistance. This means there should be little
stopping for the price to move in your favor.
Start on a bigger timeframe, like the
daily chart. Mark major liquidity levels.
Move down to a smaller timeframe,
like the 1-hour chart. Look for price
approaching your marked liquidity levels.
As price gets close to a liquidity level,
switch to an even smaller timeframe,
like the 15-minute chart.
Watch for signs of a stop hunt – a quick spike
through the level, followed by a reversal.
If you see this, get ready to enter a
trade, in the direction of the reversal.
Also, don't jump on every breakout. Wait
for the price to show it's really going
to keep moving in that direction.
Always consult multiple time frames:
check larger time frames to see if a move fits
the bigger picture or if it might be inducement.
If you see the price quickly reject a level after
breaking it, be ready for a possible reversal.
And don't put your stops right at obvious
levels. That's where inducement often targets.
Tools/indicators to analyze liquidity
There are several tools and indicators
that can help you spot and
analyze liquidity in the markets.
First one, volume: This is one of the
simplest and most effective tools.
High volume often shows high liquidity.
So look for volume spikes, which
can indicate liquidity events.
Second, Market Depth Charts. These show pending
buy and sell orders at different price levels.
They can help you see where
liquidity pools might be forming.
Third, Time and Sales (or Tape Reading):
This shows real-time trades. Large trades
or clusters of trades at certain
prices can indicate liquidity.
Fourth, Order Flow Indicators: These
advanced tools try to show the balance
of buying and selling pressure.
And fifth, Volume Profile: This shows
where most trading has happened at different price
levels, helping identify high-liquidity zones.
It's best to use a mix of tools, and combine
them with market structure and price action.
Also, these tools don't directly show "liquidity."
They show things that often relate to liquidity.
You still need to interpret
what they're telling you.
Liquidity and order flow analysis
Liquidity and order flow
analysis are closely linked.
Order flow analysis is all about understanding
the buying and selling pressure in the market.
This pressure often shows up as liquidity.
Order flow analysis looks at the actual orders
coming into the market.
It tries to spot where
big players are buying or selling.
Basically, order flow analysis can help
you find where liquidity is building up, when
liquidity is being used up, and potential price
levels where big players might be active.
In order flow analysis, you need to get
familiar with several concepts.
First one, volume clusters:
order flow analysis often looks for
clusters of orders at certain prices.
These clusters are actually liquidity pools.
Next concept is “absorption”: When a price
level "absorbs" a lot of orders without moving
much, it's often a sign of high liquidity.
Here’s a familiar concept, imbalances: Order
flow tools might show imbalances between buy
and sell orders. These imbalances
can create or drain liquidity.
It’s a lot to talk about, that’s
a topic for another video.
How to use liquidity analysis to
compete with institutional traders
Retail traders like you and me, can level the
playing field by using liquidity analysis to
compete with institutional traders.
Here's how:
Know the closest liquidity pools. Mark
the areas where lots of buy or sell
orders cluster. When price hits these spots,
it often bounces or breaks through fast. You
need to be ready for both scenarios.
Watch for traps and liquidity sweeps.
Big players set traps to trick small
traders. They often push price to key
levels. Don't fall for these fake-outs.
Use multiple timeframes. Check both higher
and lower timeframes. This gives you a
fuller picture of liquidity across different
market views. It helps you spot potential
reversals or continuations more accurately.
Track order flow. Pay attention to how orders
are coming in. Look for big buy or sell walls
in the order book. These can signal where
institutions are placing their orders.
Identify liquidity gaps. These are areas
on the chart with little trading activity.
Price often moves quickly through these
zones. Knowing where they are can help
you set better entry and exit points.
Study market structure. Look for key
swing highs and lows. These often
mark areas of high liquidity.
Focus on session overlaps. When major
trading sessions overlap, liquidity tends
to increase. This can lead to bigger price
moves. Use these times to your advantage.
Don't chase breakouts. Many traders jump
on breakouts, only to get burned. Instead,
look for pullbacks to liquidity zones, after a
breakout. This is often where smart money enters.
Use volume profile. This tool shows you
where the most trading has happened at
different price levels. High volume nodes
often act as strong liquidity areas.
Now, if you want to learn
other smart money tactics,
you need to watch one of these videos next.