So in this video, I wanted to share some cool
strategies I learned involving the Anchored
VWAP.
This indicator measures the volume-weighted
average price (VWAP) but starts the calculation
at any time you choose.
Usually with the default VWAP, it takes the
whole day's trading to figure out the average.
But sometimes you just care about what happened
after a certain point.
Like maybe there was big news at lunchtime
that seemed to shift how prices were trading.
With regular VWAP you can't see how prices
acted just since then.
But with Anchored VWAP, you pick the exact
bar on the chart where you want to start the
calculation.
Then it will draw the VWAP line from that
moment onwards.
This lets you see clearly if buyers or sellers
have been in control since that important
event.
You get the benefits of VWAP but customized
to the period that matters most to you.
It's neat because trading is all about recognizing
when things change.
Anchored VWAP helps uncover shifts that regular
VWAP might miss since it always uses the whole
daily session.
You have more flexibility to analyze shorter
windows and focus on what really moved the
market at that key moment you chose.
The price level represented by the Anchored
VWAP serves as a benchmark.
When big funds and banks make lots of trades,
they can't just dump it all at once or it
would really move the price away from where
they want.
So instead they spread it out slowly over
time.
And how do they know if they're getting a
good deal while doing that?
Well, the VWAP line tells them!
It shows the average price up to that point.
On up days, the big boys buy more when price
dips below the VWAP line.
That way they're scooping it up for a bit
cheaper than average.
And on down days, the opposite - they sell
when the price goes above the line to bank
the profits from higher than average prices.
Either way, it helps those big fishes trade
without rocking the boat too much.
So the anchored line gives us an idea of the
"fair value" range that all the big action
is centered around.
And the anchored version is way better because
I can start it whenever I want, even if it
was days or weeks ago!
And then it will keep updating all the way
to present, so I have a VWAP line I can watch
evolve over the whole time period I care about.
Regular VWAP won't do that since it's tied
to just one day.
The anchored one gives you full control to
put the starting point wherever is most useful
for reading the chart.
And that makes it way more helpful if I'm
looking at longer time frames than just today.
And it’s also way better than moving averages.
Starting the VWAP anywhere opens up way more
chances to spot opportunities and trends compared
to a moving average.
So how to trade using Anchored VWAP.
Major turning points or events are perfect
spots to add it.
Those were the times when tons of buyers and
sellers were battling it out - so it's a perfect
average to measure from.
In this example, this huge crash would be
perfect to anchor from.
It's obvious something massive happened there
to cause such move.
That dip is definitely a moment the smart
money was piling in, so anchoring there gives
the real picture of what it's done since.
Clicking right on that candle gives us a clear
line to see what happened after all those
people finished trading.
And now it's clear the buyers have been winning
since then.
Most of the action has been above VWAP line,
so bulls have clearly had the power in pushing
it up from that low average price.
It's like we get to watch exactly who's been
in control stage-by-stage after such an important
turning point.
Scouting for pullbacks to the VWAP line is
one of the easiest ways to hunt momentum moves.
When a market is in a strong up trend, it's
natural for it to have little breathers where
it consolidates or dips a bit before blasting
off again.
And the anchored line gives you a perfect
spot to anticipate that mini dip, knowing
it's still respecting the overall trend.
As long as the highs keep getting higher and
price is staying consistently over the VWAP,
you know the buyers are still in control.
All you gotta do is watch for price to touch
back down to the VWAP after stretching out
above it.
That's your low-risk entry to hop on for the
next leg up!
The anchored line basically shows support
developed since that key moment you anchored
it to.
As long as buyers are still strong enough
to keep bounces from falling below, you know
the trend is still in gear.
Looking for euphoric extremes is another way
to use the anchored VWAP.
We've all seen those sky high price runs that
seem unsustainable.
When the price gets waaay over the line, buying
seems risky.
In this example, price hitting the third VWAP
band is a clear signal it's running too hot.
In this case, you must avoid jumping in because
the odds of a pullback are very high.
And for contrarian swing traders and risk
takers, it sets up a sweet chance at a mean
reversion trade!
If you believe in technical analysis and that
everything fluctuates around an average, well
once price moves that far above the VWAP,
the math says it's "due" to a big pullback.
Betting on it coming back to more reasonable
levels starts to make sense the more stretched
out it gets.
Obviously it takes some guts to fade that
kind of momentum.
But scoping for extreme spreads between price
and the anchored line is a good way to trade
some high probability reversal setups.
Patience is key though - no way I'd jump in
to sell right at the top of that euphoria!
But having the anchored lines as guides, you
can spot when something is overbought and
due for a breather.
The Anchored VWAP line can also be used to
confirm trends and identify hidden areas of
supply or demand on the chart.
The big thing is we can set it anywhere that
marks an important switch.
Before that point the trading might not tell
us much since sentiment was different.
But once we select our "anchor" bar, that
VWAP line will show us the true average price
based on the price action that happened after
whatever event we chose.
From there it gets real simple - if the market
stays mostly over the line like we see here,
we know buyers are in control of setting the
market value.
And if it respects the line as support on
dips, that's an even stronger sign buyers
are willing to hop in at "fair" prices.
Conversely, prolonged breaks below could mean
sellers have power now.
Remember: the key is choosing the right starting
point to reflect an actual shift in how traders
are thinking.
When anchored to the right moment, the line
then becomes your guide for seeing hidden
levels where buying or selling finds support
or turns the price around.
This indicator is versatile.
I use it mainly for swing trading, but if
you’re day trading or scalping, its power
remains the same.
When you plot the standard VWAP, this line,
you could see why you wouldn't get the full
picture - it drags in all that early choppiness
before the real action kicked in.
But when dropping that anchored line at the
morning low, everything suddenly became way
clearer!
That dip was obviously a turning point where
buyers stepped up.
So zeroing in on just the data since then,
the VWAP line perfectly mirrors how the price
has reacted going into the rest of the session.
If my plan was buying a dip at the average
price line, I'd be way better off following
the anchored one.
I can totally see several buy zones with it.
The normal VWAP just doesn't have that precision.
I hope you see how well the anchored line
fits the price action vs the default line.
So, what are the best places to anchor the
line.
Like I said, choosing that starting anchor
point is crucial.
It's gotta line up with a real shift in how
most traders are viewing things, not just
some random spot in the middle of the chart.
Everyone seeing the same key moment is what'll
make that line a meaningful support or resistance.
Think about it, if many are paying attention
to the same place on the chart, there's bound
to be a crowd reaction when price gets back
to that level.
Much more so than an arbitrarily dropped line
or a common moving average.
So make sure the anchor it's at obvious turning
point that others will recognize too.
The line has to start where the whole market's
psychology changed.
I like to monitor volume to find the anchor
point.
That metric reveals so much about what the
big players are really doing under the surface.
A high volume candle shows there's legit interest
building, whether it's bulls or bears in control.
Combining volume spikes with a price pump
is the decent confirmation a new trend might
be kicking off.
Anchoring the VWAP there capitalizes on that
shift.
The line immediately highlighted several clean
dips you could have hopped in for a quick
scalp upwards.
Chasing volume surges is a sweet day trading
approach.
Let the big money lead the way to find legit
breakouts, then play the anchored VWAP bounces
for short rides back up as it regains steam.
Way better than random guesses about support
- this lets the market tell you exactly where
it's at.
Using the anchored VWAP at major swings to
find reversal and bounce plays is another
strategy.
More specifically, I prefer to look for the
first pullback to the line.
That has the greatest potential for a VWAP
bounce.
Just looking for highs and lows is one thing,
but layering in the average price context
blows it wide open.
Plotting them at clear swing highs and lows
really brings hidden levels to light.
Just look here: those anchor lines unveil
hidden demand and supply zones that rookie
traders definitely miss.
Especially on that first pullback after plotting
the anchor - textbook short term setup right
back to demand.
And then seeing it work the same way shorting
off at supply.
These hidden support/resistance zones are
gold for swing trades.
Scaling it down to intraday swings uncovers
even more entries.
Another pro move is plotting anchored VWAP
at earnings or dividend reports, for stock
trading, or after major releases, like Non-Farm
Payrolls for Forex trading.
Those are perfect inflection points where
the whole outlook could flip, so zeroing in
on the before and after gives you a tailored
view of the sentiment shift.
Those are obviously pivotal moments that can
swing a market either way depending on how
the numbers look.
Here on Nvidia, we anchored the VWAP on the
most 2 recent dividend reports.
Even though price traded above and below the
first line, you could totally see it respecting
that level.
The second anchor kicks off a clear bull phase
as buyers took over above the line.
Seeing the reaction so clearly with this tool
is game changing.
It makes swing trading a lot easier.
So start watching those report dates closer.
Another awesome way to use anchored VWAP is
around the daily or weekly ranges.
Placing the anchor at previous highs and lows
from the last weeks will give you several
relevant levels, that aren't always plain
to see.
With these anchors plotted, any retest suddenly
becomes loaded with potential.
Much more so than just watching naked highs
and lows on the chart.
It’s a really smart way to identify premium
opportunities when price is testing those
"value areas".
Having those levels mapped out will help you
recognize congestion areas and will give you
an early heads up on potential reversals or
price continuations.
Whether you end up taking a trade off them
or not, the added context they provide is
invaluable.
I've noticed myself picking up on market structure
and analyzing reactions in a whole new light
since incorporating this approach.
The Anchored VWAP is truly the perfect blend
of all the key factors that drive markets
- price, volume and time.
And the flexibility to drop it anywhere you
see fit opens up so many new ways to analyze
a chart.