Losing scalpers trade with lagging indicators
like RSI and moving averages. Professional
scalpers read order flow and market microstructure
with tools that you've probably never even heard
of. Here are eight scalping techniques
that separate losers from professionals.
Mark the previous day's high and low, then
watch how price interacts at those levels.
This area often works like a magnet, drawing
attention from both buyers and sellers. You
want to monitor if price breaks through or bounces
off, or rejects them. Scalpers keep their eyes on
these breakouts looking for a quick burst. A
successful break can lead to short-term buys.
If the break stalls or fails, they may close out
fast, expecting a slide back into the day's range.
That same logic applies to the previous
day's low. If price pushes below that
point but struggles to go lower, it might
climb back, sparking quick trades. Volume
flow at these points shows who
carries more weight on the chart:
the group ready to push higher or the group
ready to defend and revert price lower.
For instance, day traders might see it with
a wider view if volume fails to rise and
the price breaks. They see that as a weakness
that could hint at a chance to fade the move,
expecting a drift back into the
range. In a bullish setting,
though, a clear break above the past
high might signal bigger gains. Again,
wait for retest of these highs or lows to
confirm support or resistance. A strong
surge suggests bigger participants stepping in.
A weak spike suggests the break might not hold.
Another interesting strategy is to
mark highs and lows from multiple
days to see confluence. If many
past highs cluster in one region,
that marks a bigger level on the chart. Order
flow analysis also builds on these zones.
In a bullish flow, price may seek buy stops
above a prior high. When price drives higher,
that might feed more buying interest. In a
bearish flow, it might head for sell stops below
a previous low. If momentum keeps running, price
extends further. If it fails, it can whip back.
Footprint charts split each candlestick
into two columns of executed orders.
One column shows the volume on the bid side
and the other shows the volume on the ask
side. This view helps you see who might be more
active at each price level. In a strong rally,
the footprint can reveal if buyers are
pushing price upward in a steady way.
In a strong drop, it can reveal if sellers
keep hitting the market with large orders.
This method is direct and numeric. A footprint
chart doesn't rely on a guess about patterns.
It relies on actual trades. Each block of
traded contracts or shares is visible at
each step. Imbalances come into play here.
An imbalance occurs when one side greatly
exceeds the other at a given price level. On a
footprint chart, that might appear as a large
difference between the bid-side volume and the
ask-side volume. This gap can hint at which side
is more aggressive. It can also reveal if
big participants are stepping in with size.
In a fast-moving uptrend, repeated buy imbalances
can reinforce the bullish pressure. If you see
repeated sell imbalances, you might guess that
big participants are forcing price lower. At
key turning points, footprints might show
signs of absorption. Absorption means one
side is absorbing the other side's orders.
That can appear on the footprint. If you see
big numbers on both sides but no real progress
upward in an uptrend, a footprint might reveal
hidden pockets of supply. If the bars show
large selling imbalances at certain levels,
that might stop the move. The idea is to watch
the actual fight between buyers and sellers.
The footprint is a lens into the order flow.
At times, the footprint view can show that even in
a strong uptrend, large sell orders keep popping
up at certain levels. Price might stall there. If
the volume on the buy side absorbs those sellers,
price might break higher anyway. But if large
sellers hold that line, price might turn. The
footprint chart helps highlight these battles.
A normal chart might show a candle with a wick,
but the footprint might show that this wick
printed huge trades on the left side. That can
sometimes mean a sudden wave of sellers. For day
trading or scalping, footprint charts are a must.
Some charts show hidden pivot clusters.
These clusters happen when three or four
pivot highs or lows stack near one price.
I personally like to watch to see if price
builds a block of these points. Price might
respect these zones. It might hit that band
and pause. It might bounce off it or break
through. These clusters can matter to many
groups of traders. And I try to keep my chart
structure simple. If there are three or four
pivot points in the same neighborhood, that can
form a hidden cluster. If I group them together,
I see a stronger band. This can help
me spot places where price might react.
I treat these clusters like wide support or
resistance zones. They are not exact single
lines. They are areas on the chart. Sometimes
these clusters coincide with pivot points. Many
day traders and scalpers use daily pivot formulas.
If a cluster lines up with a pivot calculation,
that might strengthen the zone further.
It might bring more eyes onto that spot.
That can create a self-fulfilling
effect, at least for a short time.
I also look for clusters that might be hidden
inside candle wicks. The market spikes up or
down and leaves a wick. That wick might mark a
pivot high or low. If I see multiple wicks that
poke into the same area, I might highlight
that as a cluster. The candle body closes
might not show the same price, but the wicks
might. That can still matter to me. If price
returns there, it can trigger a new burst
of activity or it might hold as a barrier.
I also consider how wide the band is. If
the pivots are spread over a big range,
it might be less precise. If the pivots are
very close together, the cluster might be
tighter. Tight clusters can create sharp reversals
because many orders might be loaded at nearly the
same price. Wide clusters can lead to choppier
action because price might drift within that zone.
Some see clusters of pivot highs as zones
full of potential sell orders. Clusters of
pivot lows may hold buy orders. That might
be because each pivot left a memory in the
market. Some participants may have open orders
there from before, or they see that zone as a
logical place to set stops or limit entries.
This is why these clusters can become magnets.
TPO stands for Time Price Opportunity and is
a great tool for scalping and day trading.
A TPO chart displays time at price in a
letter-based format. These charts break
down each time frame into letters. Each letter
aligns with a price level in that time frame.
One advantage of TPO charts is how they
strip away messy candle wicks. Instead,
you see a clean layout of
time spent at each price.
A bar chart might show big upper
shadows or wide intraday ranges,
but it can be unclear how much time was spent at
certain levels. TPO charts reveal that detail.
If you see 10 letters at one level, that means 10
distinct time blocks spent some portion of trading
at that price. That is a direct way to sense
how the market balanced or tested each zone.
If a big cluster forms around the
middle of the day, some interpret
that as a balanced session. When you
see the cluster push up near the top,
you might sense that participants
welcomed higher pricing. If you spot
a cluster near the bottom, that can mean
persistent acceptance at lower levels.
A short stack of letters at a certain price
might show that the market tested that level
but quickly moved away. That might reflect swift
rejection. If the price tried to stay there,
you would see more letters added.
If you see only one or two letters,
that can mean the market spent
just one or two time blocks there.
Some traders place special importance
on single TPO prints at extremes. That
single print might highlight a strong
rejection. Market profile watchers may
call that a sign that the market poked into
that territory, found no willingness to trade,
and reversed. Rejection becomes visible because
the chart never built a tall column there.
The middle area often becomes the point of
control, referencing the price level with the most
TPOs. In many sessions, the distribution might not
be symmetrical. It could skew higher or it might
skew lower. That tilt can show that either buyers
or sellers took control for much of the session.
In an active bullish scenario, you might see
a heavy cluster of letters near the top. That
can hint the market accepted higher prices,
finishing near the highs with a strong cluster.
In a bearish environment, you might
see a thick cluster near the lows.
That can mean repeated trading
activity in that lower region.
People also track the value area in a TPO chart.
The value area often covers the price range where
70% of the day's TPO activity took place.
That area is presumably the day's fair zone.
Day traders watch the open in relation to the
prior day's value area. If the market opens
above it and keeps building letters at higher
levels, it can reflect bullish acceptance. If
it drops back into the previous day's value area,
that might show a failure to sustain new ground.
Combine a trend line with a volume spike
test to see how price reacts on each retest.
Draw a steady line through points on your
chart. Then watch how volume changes each
time price touches that zone. Here
we have a rising line under price.
Suppose price taps that line more than
once. Track the effort behind each tap.
If volume expands at the contact point but price
does not break lower, buyers might be holding the
line. That reveal can guide you to think buyers
are present despite the test. If price closes
firm above the line, that hints that buyers
outweigh sellers, so the uptrend may continue.
On the other hand, imagine volume spikes at
the trend line as the price breaks. The line
can become a weaker barrier. A strong
close beyond it can mark a firm change.
Sometimes you see a wide bar pushing
through that line with large activity
and no bounce on the retest. That scenario
often signals a real shift. You might see a
giant volume bar as the final push and price
continues well below the line. That can warn
that sellers stepped in aggressively.
The line no longer stands in their way.
First, test your approach on past charts. Open
a chart and draw your rising or declining line.
Then, wait for price to drift there. When
it does, watch the volume level. If volume
exceeds the average by a visible margin, see how
the candle closes. Does it close well above the
trend line or below it? That single data point
can speak volumes about the market intent.
Watch for sideways drifting near the line. If
price stalls near that line and volume bars climb,
that might suggest big players are building
positions. Price might then explode above
or below. A strong breakout with a wide range
bar plus large activity can confirm the path.
A breakout with low volume will often fade.
Observing the spike helps you see if big
participation is present. That is the advantage
of combining a trend line with volume spike tests.
Examining each bar's range is a simple way to
see if price might break free or stay quiet. The
gap between the bar's high and low reflects
market energy. A bar's high reveals how far
buyers try to push. A bar's low shows how far
sellers try to push in that same period. That
difference in height, known as the range,
can show if the market is slow or alive.
A big range can hint that traders are pushing
and pulling with greater force. A small range
can point to caution or waiting. This practice is
called range analysis and it starts with reading
each bar in a straightforward way. It does not
require fancy tools. A day trader looks at the
bar on the chart, notes the distance from high to
low, and compares it to prior bars. If the new bar
towers over the one before it, that can be a sign
of more volatility. If the new bar is smaller,
that can be a sign of reduced action. This is
a direct and practical way to gain insight.
Range expansions can show that something
has changed. A large bar might mean that
many players jumped in during that period.
Traders holding positions could have strong
opinions on direction. That strong opinion can
create a surge. When price covers more ground,
it can catch some off guard. Some might
see the big bar and believe the market is
on the move. Others might step aside,
not wanting to fight that momentum.
Contraction is the opposite. When bars
get smaller, it might show that traders
are waiting. They might not see a clear
path. The highs are not too high. The lows
are not too low. That can create a cluster of
narrow bars, each one marking a slim distance
between high and low. Some traders anticipate
a breakout from such quiet stages. They keep
watching for that first big bar that bursts
in one direction. That bar can bring energy,
hooking new orders into the market. Others
remain cautious, unsure if the quiet phase
will continue. Sometimes the quiet phase drags
on, frustrating those who wait for a spark.
Seeing expansions or contractions in
the bar range helps judge market tempo.
It shows if the market is active or calm.
This direct reading helps keep the focus
on price. Of course, you must pair it with
volume data. You want to see if the wide bar
also had high volume. That suggests
strong commitment from big players.
Candle close location value shows how each
bar finishes relative to its high-low range.
If a candle closes near its high, buyers
kept pushing until the end of that time
frame. If a candle closes near the low,
it shows larger selling pressure toward
that bar's finish. A close around the
midpoint marks a balance between buyers
and sellers. Day traders watch these closes to
see who seems stronger over a series of bars.
If many bars close near their highs, it can
hint that buyers are consistently winning.
In an uptrend, a streak of bars that finish
high suggests strong interest at each step.
If a bar suddenly closes near its low after
that streak, it may point to a shift in mood.
This 5-minute chart shows consecutive closes near
the top. That can mean buyers are active on each
bar's final trades. If the next bar closes deep
in the range, watch if buyers step aside. If that
low close coincides with wider ranges or bigger
candles, it might reveal a sudden wave of selling.
Candle close location also helps you detect
subtle shifts. Suppose a market moves upward
but the candles start closing near their
midpoints, creating shadows on top. You
might guess that sellers are active even
if price is still climbing. Over time,
those repeated mid-range closes could foreshadow
a stall. On the flip side, a market in a downtrend
that begins closing near the high of each
bar might show stronger buying than before.
Traders sometimes calculate an average
candle close location over a set of bars.
If a candle closes near its high, its
value is one. If it closes near its low,
its value is zero. If it closes in the
middle, it has a value of 0.5. Then you
consider the average value over a set of bars.
If that average stays near 0.8, for example,
bullish pressure is steady. If it oscillates
around 0.5, the market looks indecisive. A
swift drop toward 0.1 can point to a big change in
tone. Candle close location is straightforward and
thrives on raw price action. That direct view can
help you sense if momentum is building or fading.
Identify a measured move to see how price might
extend in a trend. Picture a market that rises a
certain distance, then pulls back, and then
drives higher again. That distance from the
first surge often helps you estimate how far
the next wave might go. You take the size of
the first move and project it above the pullback.
This is a measured move, a quick way to guess a
possible target. If the market meets that
target and stalls, that might confirm the
measured move idea. If the market blasts past
the target, that might reveal extra strength.
Imagine a clean uptrend. Price rallies 100 pips
from a swing low. Then it retraces about 50 pips,
forming a short pause. Now price moves up again.
Some traders measure that first wave and plot that
same distance from the swing low of the pullback.
That new level becomes a reference. They watch
if price hits it or not. This approach feels
basic, but it can help you map out expectations.
You look for symmetrical movement in a trending
environment. If a market makes a series of waves
that mirror each other in size, that might confirm
the trend has a steady rhythm. If you see multiple
measured moves that keep playing out, you get a
sense that the trend is healthy and consistent.
Of course, markets don't always honor the
symmetrical moves precisely. You might see
it come close, then fade, or you might see it
power right through. Measured moves aim to give
you a ballpark estimate, not an absolute
rule. But this concept can also help you
with risk assessment and with your targets.
This is a simple chart geometry approach. You
measure a prior leg and replicate it. You
see if the market respects that geometry.
So use symmetrical moves to project possible
targets and then interpret if the market
exceeds or falls short of that measure.
If it overshoots, it might be a sign of
strong momentum. If it undershoots, it might
warn that momentum is weaker than before.
And if you're ready to fit this
into a full A to Z trading system,
that's what our academy is for.
Link is in the description.