Regular candlestick patterns fail 80%
of the time without volume confirmation!
My price action trading completely changed,
once I discovered the power of volume candles.
These candles expose institutional order flow and
show you exactly where smart
money is placing their orders.
Let’s talk about it!
Chapter 1: The Power of Volume Candles
Trading becomes clear when you strip away all
indicators and focus on what truly moves markets:
pure price action and volume.
You see, price action alone
misses crucial market information.
You might see a price move up or down,
but without volume, you can't tell
if that move carries real weight.
Volume fills this gap. It acts as the only
true leading indicator, revealing market
direction before big moves happen.
While price tells you what happened,
volume shows you if that move was real or fake.
The iconic traders of the past, Charles Dow,
Jesse Livermore, and Richard Wyckoff,
used this simple yet powerful approach.
They didn't need fancy indicators
or complex systems. They understood
that the combination of price and volume
revealed everything about market behavior.
Clean charts let you spot things
that indicators often hide.
When you remove all the clutter, you
start seeing the market's natural rhythm.
And volume adds depth to this view. It shows the
strength or weakness behind every price move.
Volume works as the truth-teller in
markets. When you see a price move,
volume instantly tells you if
that move deserves your attention.
High volume means many traders participated,
giving the move more credibility.
Low volume suggests weak conviction
and possible fake moves.
99% of traders tend to overcomplicate their
process. But the market hasn't changed in over 100
years - volume and price still drive all moves.
And volume candles paint a much clear picture
of market strength, and buyer-seller activity.
This type of chart allows for a visual assessment
of the volume of trades for each candle.
These are still candlesticks, but the
width of each candle depends on the volume of
trades, during the formation of this candle.
The greater the trading volume
during the formation of the candle,
the larger the width of the candle.
Chapter 2: Anatomy of a Volume Candle
A volume candle holds seven critical parts
that tell the full story of price movement.
Let’s break down each element and
show you how they work together.
Every volume candle has an open price, which
marks where trading started in that time period.
For green candles, you find this at the bottom
of the body. For red candles, it sits at the top.
This starting point sets the stage for
the battle between buyers and sellers.
The high price shows the maximum point
buyers pushed during that period.
You see this at the top of the upper wick. This
tells you how far buyers managed to drive prices
up, even if they couldn't hold those levels.
The low price, marked by the bottom of
the lower wick, reveals the lowest
point where sellers drove the price.
These extreme points show you the full
range of the price battle that happened.
The close price tells you who won that
period's battle - buyers or sellers.
On green candles, you find it at the
top of the body, showing buyers won.
On red candles, it's at the bottom,
meaning sellers took control.
The upper wick, that line sticking up from
the body, shows rejection of higher prices.
A long upper wick means buyers
tried pushing up, but failed.
No upper wick signals strong buying
pressure, that held through the close.
A long lower wick reveals sellers
tried pushing down, but failed.
When you see no lower wick, sellers
maintained control throughout the period.
The candle body, the thick
part between open and close,
shows who won the period and by how much. A wide
body means strong conviction in that direction.
A narrow body points to weak
conviction or indecision.
Now, what makes volume candles
special is their width variation.
Unlike regular candles that stay
the same width, volume candles grow
wider or narrower based on trading activity.
This adds a vital dimension to your analysis.
Wide candles mean heavy trading volume,
lots of buyers and sellers fought
over prices during that period.
Narrow candles show light volume,
fewer traders participated.
This width variation reveals
trading intensity at a glance.
The relationship between candle
parts tells deeper stories.
Take a wide candle with no wicks.
This shows strong agreement on price
direction with heavy participation.
But how about a wide candle
with long wicks! That reveals
intense fighting between buyers and sellers.
Watch how the candle width changes as price moves.
Increasing width during price
rises shows growing buyer strength.
But if the width starts shrinking while price
still rises, buyers might be losing steam.
The open and close positions relative
to the total range matter too.
A close near the high with wide volume suggests
strong buying pressure likely to continue.
A close far from the extremes with
high volume might signal indecision.
Some traders focus only on candle colors or
patterns. But volume width adds crucial context.
A tiny green candle with huge volume, might mean
more than a large red candle with thin volume.
Pay special attention to how volume
width changes around key price levels.
A surge in width near support or resistance
often signals important market decisions
happening. We’ll talk about this later.
The real power comes from reading
all these elements together.
Each part adds to the story,
but the volume width ties it all together by
showing the conviction behind every move.
The beauty of volume candles lies in
their ability to show both price action,
and trading intensity, in one clean visual.
This complete picture helps you make faster,
more accurate trading decisions.
Chapter 3: Understanding Price Movement Flow
Stop looking at single candles, and start
seeing the market as a flowing story,
where each candle connects to the next.
A green candle might signal buying, but its true
meaning changes based on where it appears, at the
start of a trend, in the middle, or near the end.
The market moves in phases,
not in isolated events.
The same type of candle carries different weight,
depending on its place in the overall flow.
A wide green candle at support means something
very different from the same candle at resistance.
Think of price movement like
reading a book. You wouldn't
try to understand a story by reading
random sentences, you read them in order.
The same applies to candles. Each candle flows
into the next, creating a complete narrative.
“Price trends” develop and validate
themselves through this continuous flow.
Take a series of rising candles
- as they form one after another,
they confirm or deny the strength of the move.
The story becomes clearer with each new candle.
Three consecutive up-candles with
growing volume, show rising strength.
This tells a story of building momentum.
The flow reveals more than patterns.
While a single candle might show buying pressure,
the flow shows if that pressure sustains or fades.
This continuous view helps spot
genuine moves from fake ones.
You see, smart money leaves
footprints in this flow.
They don't act in single candles,
but across a series of moves.
Reading the flow helps track
their actions and intentions.
Each candle connects to the
next, creating a rhythm.
Breaking this rhythm often signals
important changes in market direction.
Volume doesn't just validate single
candles - it validates entire moves.
Rising prices should see rising
volume in a healthy trend.
When analyzing flow, consider the whole context.
A candle that looks bullish alone might actually
signal weakness, when viewed
as part of the larger movement.
This approach helps spot reversals early.
Chapter 4: Volume Candles as the Truth-Teller
Volume candles act as market truth-tellers,
exposing the real story behind every price move.
The first rule to spot genuine moves is simple
- the volume must match the price action.
A strong price rise needs strong
volume to prove it's real.
Take a wide up candle with small wicks.
The high volume shows many traders joined in,
proving the move has real support.
This matches the basic rule of effort
versus result, big price moves need
big effort shown through volume.
The opposite situation warns you of fake moves.
Picture a price rising with thin volume. This
mismatch rings alarm bells.
If a move lacks the volume
to support it, smart traders stay away.
Low volume means few traders believe in the move.
A narrow body candle with low
volume tells a different story.
If price barely moves and volume stays low,
that actually validates the quiet period.
Volume reveals if moves come
from buying or selling pressure.
Look at a series of rising candles,
with growing volume, but no wicks.
This can only mean buying volume -
sellers aren't fighting back at all.
Such clean moves with rising volume
signal genuine buyer strength.
Wide spread candles need matching volume.
If a big price move happens on weak volume,
that warns you of potential manipulation.
Real moves need real participation.
Let's break down a typical false move.
You see price shooting up with a
long upper wick, but tiny volume.
This screams warning - despite the
high price, few traders joined in.
The small volume exposes this as
likely manipulation.
True strength shows in
the details. When price rises steadily with each
candle wider than the last, volume also increase.
This rising volume confirms more traders join
with each push higher, validating the whole move.
Look for volume that matches candle
size. Big candles need big volume.
Small candles match with small volume.
When these don't match, something's wrong.
This simple check helps avoid false moves.
Also, don't trust wicks without checking
their volume. A long wick might look like
strong rejection of price, but low volume
means that rejection lacks conviction.
Strong rejections need strong volume to
prove many traders acted.
Volume patterns tell deeper
stories. Rising price with falling volume,
meaning thinner candles, warns of weakness.
Falling price with rising volume, meaning
wider candles, shows real selling pressure.
These volume shifts often signal important
trend changes, before price confirms them.
Always remember that smart
money leaves traces in volume.
They can't hide their large trades.
When you see wide volume candles,
with small price moves, big players might
be quietly accumulating or distributing.
These volume hints reveal their plans.
I repeat, price action can lie,
but volume tells truth.
Market makers can push price around temporarily,
but they can't fake real trading activity.
This makes volume candles one of the most
reliable tools for spotting genuine market moves.
And watch how volume reacts at key price levels.
Strong support or resistance needs
strong volume candles to break.
Thin volume candles at these levels often
means the break will fail, no matter how
good it looks on price alone.
At a key level, when in doubt,
volume candles hold the answer.
Price action might look perfect,
but without supporting volume, they often fail.
Chapter 5: Thin Candles vs Wide Candle Signals
So, narrow candles with low
volume show weak market interest.
Wide candles with high volume
reveal strong conviction.
Let’s start with narrow spread
candles. These form when price
moves very little during the trading period.
If this happens with low volume, if they are thin,
it actually makes perfect sense - small price
movement matches small trading activity.
Large spread candles tell a different story. When
price moves far in one direction, creating a wide
candle, it has strong volume to prove it's real.
A wide candle forms from lots of buying or
selling, and the high volume
validates that activity.
A small but wide body candle,
means unusually high volume.
This warns you something big might happen soon.
Think about it - lots of trading, but little
price movement, means big players
might be quietly building positions.
Watch closely when you see large
body candles, with thin volume.
This mismatch sends a clear warning,
the price move lacks real support.
Despite the big price change, few traders
joined in. Such moves often reverse quickly.
A series of narrow candles with falling
volume often signals a coming breakout.
The shrinking volume shows fewer
traders want to trade at current prices.
This pressure builds until price must
break out to find new trading levels.
Volume intensity affects how you read wicks too.
A long upper wick usually signals
rejection of higher prices.
But this only counts if the volume matches.
High volume with the wick proves
many traders rejected that price.
Low volume means the rejection might not stick.
Volume intensity helps spot trend changes early.
A series of large spread candles, with
falling volume, warns of weakening momentum.
Even though price still moves
strongly, the dropping volume
suggests the trend might soon end.
Location also matters when
reading volume intensity.
A narrow and thin candle at
support might just mean quiet consolidation.
The same candle forming at resistance could
signal failing momentum, before a reversal.
Also, track volume intensity changes over time.
Rising volume with wider candles
confirms increasing market interest.
Falling volume with narrowing
candles shows dropping interest.
These shifts often predict big moves.
Smart money leaves clues through
volume intensity patterns.
They often accumulate positions using
many narrow candles with steady volume.
Then they push price hard with a few
high-volume wide candles.
Spotting these patterns
helps you trade with the big players.
The relationship between candle spread
and volume intensity reveals market psychology.
Wide spread, high volume candles show strong
agreement about price direction.
Narrow spread, low volume candles
show uncertainty or disinterest.
These volume intensity principles will
definitely help you avoid false moves.
Chapter 6: Key Level Analysis
The volume candles at support and resistance
levels tell a story about future price movement.
Wide volume candles at support or
resistance signal strong interest.
A wide green candle with high volume bouncing off
support shows buyers stepping in with conviction.
A wide red candle with high volume, at
resistance, indicates sellers taking control.
Thin volume candles at key
levels need special attention.
When price reaches an important level but
produces narrow candles, it shows hesitation.
This often precedes a false break or reversal.
Picture price approaching a resistance level - if
the candles get thinner with lower
volume, the break attempt might fail.
The change in candle width as
price tests a level also matters.
Wide candles turning into thin
ones suggest momentum loss.
At resistance, if candles start wide
but shrink while testing the level,
it warns of weakening buying pressure.
Watch for clusters of thin candles at key levels.
These often form right before a strong move.
Think of it as pressure building, the narrow
range shows neither buyers nor sellers
want to commit until the break happens.
Multiple tests of a level
create patterns in candle width.
First tests might show wide
candles with high volume.
Later tests often show thinner
candles, but don't ignore these.
Sometimes the quiet approach
leads to the real break.
Support breaks need proper
volume candle confirmation.
A break with thin candles raises doubts.
Look for wide candles pushing through the level,
showing real selling pressure. The width of the
candles tells you if sellers mean business.
Market structure changes
show through candle patterns.
A series of wide candles breaking a
trend line, or a key structure level,
carries more weight than thin ones.
The width shows conviction in the
structural change.
Price congestion
zones create their own key levels.
Notice how candle width changes in these areas.
Wide candles pushing into congestion
often fail, while patient accumulation
with thinner candles might succeed.
The character of candles shifts at major levels.
A trend of steady wide candles might turn
into erratic thin ones at resistance.
This change warns of possible trend exhaustion.
False breakouts often start with thin candles.
Even if price moves beyond the level, narrow
candle width suggests lack of commitment.
So wait for wide candles
to confirm the real break.
Volume candle width helps spot distribution tops.
At resistance, rising price with shrinking candle
width warns of weakness. Big players
might be quietly selling into the move.
Support and resistance lose strength with each
test. But watch how candle width evolves during
retests. Widening candles show growing interest.
Some levels hold special weight - like
weekly highs or lows.
Expect wider candles at
these points, as more traders watch them.
Thin candles at major levels often precede
violent moves.
Market memory
also creates support from old resistance.
When price returns to these flipped levels,
compare current candle width to previous tests.
Similar patterns often produce similar results.
The stopping volume pattern shows as a
single wide candle. It appears at key levels,
often with a long wick. This candle
type signals strong rejection.
Price congestion creates
natural support and resistance.
Study how candle width changes when
price enters and exits these zones.
Wide candles leaving congestion
often start strong trends.
Momentum loss shows through candle width changes.
As price approaches resistance,
watch if candles get thinner.
This gradual weakening often precedes reversals.
Supply and demand balance
shows in candle patterns.
Wide candles mean strong imbalance,
thin candles suggest equilibrium.
Key levels often flip when this
balance shifts dramatically.
Time frames affect how you read candle width.
A wide candle on a daily chart carries
more weight than on a 5-minute chart.
So match your analysis to your trading timeframe.
The market structure creates its own
key points through swing highs and lows.
Watch how candle width behaves
at these natural levels.
They often work as well as
traditional support and resistance.
I hope you see how price action becomes
more reliable when candle width confirms it.
A resistance break with wide candles
and high volume shows conviction.
The same break with
thin candles might trap traders.
Chapter 7: Entry and Exit Triggers
Volume candles give clear signals
for entering and exiting trades.
I said it before, wide candles
show strong market commitment.
But when a wide green candle engulfs
several previous red candles, this
signals potential buying pressure.
The opposite happens when a wide
red candle swallows prior green ones.
Pin bars with extra width need special attention.
A pin bar is like a rejection stick
- when it's wider than surrounding
candles, the rejection carries more weight.
Look for these wide pin bars at key price levels,
especially if they come with high volume.
Entry timing improves by watching
the candle width progression.
If candles get progressively wider
during a move, it shows building momentum.
This often leads to stronger trends. The
width increase confirms price direction.
Exit signals often appear as reversal candles.
When a strong trend shows wide candles in one
direction, watch for an opposing wide candle
to signal potential reversal.
The wider the reversal candle,
the stronger the signal.
Of course, false signals need
filtering. Not every wide candle means action.
Look for confirmation from surrounding price
action and volume patterns. Single
candles rarely tell the whole story.
Time of day affects candle width
interpretation. Market opens or closes
often show wider candles. These times need
different analysis than mid-session trading.
The first hour of trading deserves special
study. Wide candles during this time often
set the day's tone. But be careful -
early moves sometimes reverse quickly.
Risk management also links to candle width.
Wider candles often mean more volatility,
suggesting wider stops.
Adjust position size
accordingly to maintain consistent risk levels.
Trend confirmation uses candle width patterns.
A sequence of widening candles in the
trend direction supports continuation.
Thinning candles might warn of weakness.
Price gaps between candles need attention.
Wide candles after gaps often signal continuation.
But watch for reversal patterns if
volume doesn't confirm the move.
Counter-trend signals need extra confirmation.
A wide reversal candle against
the main trend needs more support,
than one moving with the trend.
Pattern recognition improves with practice.
Start by marking wide candles on your charts.
Notice how they cluster at important
points and what follows them.
My go-to signals using volume candles
include engulfing candles and pin bars.
A bullish engulfing candle happens when
a green candle completely covers the
body of the previous red candle. This
shows buyers taking control with force.
The real power comes from volume analysis.
Here, you see a bearish trend with several small
red candles. Then suddenly, a large green candle
appears, with volume much higher than the average.
This green giant engulfs previous red candles.
That's not just a reversal signal, it's a
strong sign of smart money stepping in.
Volume candles tells if the
engulfing move is real or fake.
Small candles with low volume, followed by
a wide engulfing candle with high volume,
shows real buying pressure.
Smart money likes to move prices
when other traders least expect it.
A pin bar looks like a hammer - it
has a long wick and short body.
But volume makes some pin bars
more special than others.
A pin bar with much higher
volume carries more weight than regular ones.
It shows strong rejection of a price level.
Take this example: The price drops for
several candles, with thin red candles.
And right here, you see a big pin bar - wider
than the previous candles, with a long lower wick.
The volume on this pin bar is higher
than normal. This isn't just a pin bar,
it's smart money entering.
You see, professional traders
don't just look at candle body size.
They combine it with volume study.
A thin pin bar with low volume might be a trap.
But high volume confirms real market intent.
During consolidation, you might see
small candles with average volume.
Then breaks out with a wide engulfing
candle and big volume. This shows
institutional players making their move.
Volume shifts during the day matter too.
An engulfing pattern at market open needs
different volume than one at mid-day.
Morning sessions often have naturally higher
volume, so adjust your expectations.
Remember older price zones
when studying these patterns.
A pin bar at previous support, showing higher
width and volume, carries extra significance.
The market remembers these levels.
A wide red pin bar with high volume,
at resistance, often signals selling pressure.
The opposite happens at support - green
pin bars with volume can mark bottoms.
Several narrow candles followed by a wide
engulfing one shows building pressure. If volume
rises with each candle, the signal gets stronger.
Narrow candles with low volume followed by a
wide engulfing candle often trap retail traders.
So look for volume spikes with engulfing patterns.
A bullish engulfing candle erasing three prior red
candles shows control shifting.
This move could be significant.
These setups often lead to sustained trends.
Wide candles engulfing multiple prior bars show
decisive action.
And of course,
pattern recognition improves with practice.
Now, if you want to learn other price action
and volume strategies, go ahead
and watch one of these videos next.