Make no mistake, volume is the missing
puzzle piece that completes the picture
of chart patterns, the secret weapon in
your trading arsenal. So, starting
today, no more guessing or relying on
luck. Now, when applying volume spread
analysis, there are two important
factors to consider. First, you look for
validation between price and volume. And
second, you look for any disagreements
between them. Validation occurs when any
price movement is supported or confirmed
by the corresponding volume activity. On
the other hand, if there is a
disagreement between price and volume,
it signals a potential change in the
market. So, if the price is rising but
the volume is decreasing or not keeping
pace, it may indicate a weakening of the
trend and a possible reversal in the
near future.
Validation and divergence are the key
concepts in VSA. Traders using VSA are
not just looking at price action after
it already happened. They also analyze
volume in real time to anticipate future
chart patterns. By understanding whether
the volume supports or diverges from the
price movement, you will better
anticipate the market's potential for
continuation or reversal.
Now, there are numerous patterns that
traders use to analyze the market. But
we won't talk about triangles, wedges,
flags or other ineffective retail junk.
No, we will analyze the patterns that
have proven to be highly effective and
occur frequently. Some of the patterns
are retail, but some of them are related
to smart money concepts.
The first one is the trend continuation
pattern or if you study ICT, the break
of structure pattern. The BOS in a
bullish trend continuation pattern we
observe a series of upward movements and
corrective pullbacks. The highest points
in the price are higher than the
previous highest points and the lowest
points in the price are also higher than
the previous lowest points. This pattern
indicates a continuation of bullish
momentum as buyers push the price to new
higher levels showing a sustained upward
trend. When a market is moving up, it
needs buying pressure to sustain the
upward movement. This buying is
typically seen when the present bar
closes higher than the previous bar. And
it's important to pay attention to the
volume of the up bar. The volume should
be increasing but not excessively.
Excessive volume may indicate that there
is more supply in the market in the
background. If you notice that the
volume is low as the market moves up,
it's a false indication. The low volume
suggests that smart money who have
significant influence are not
participating in the upward movement
because they perceive the market as weak
and without the involvement of this
smart money, the market is unlikely to
rise significantly in the future. In a
bearish trend continuation pattern, we
see a series of downward movements and
corrective pullbacks. The highest points
in the price are lower than the previous
highest points and the lowest points in
the price are lower than the previous
lowest points. This pattern signifies a
continuation of bearish momentum as
sellers drive the price to new lower
levels indicating a sustained downward
trend. During this pattern, you may see
temporary upward movements on low
volume. This implies that professional
traders are not interested in higher
prices and are not actively
participating. A legitimate downward
movement requires evidence of selling
pressure which is reflected in increased
volume on down bars. When the present
candle closes lower than the previous
candle, however, if the volume increase
is excessive, it's a warning sign that
there may be demand in the background.
If you notice the volume drying up on
down bars, it indicates a reduction in
selling pressure. The market may
continue to fall, but be aware that it
could quickly reverse and rise
momentarily due to the lack of supply.
Decreasing volume on down bars suggests
that there is no significant
professional interest in further
downside movement.
The next pattern is the double top which
contains a liquidity run. In a double
top pattern, we start with an upward
trend. The price reaches two similar
highs creating a resistance level. The
swing low between the highs is known as
the neckline. This pattern suggests a
loss of momentum in the previous uptrend
indicating a weakening of buyer
interest. Basically, the two high points
represent unsuccessful attempts by
buyers to push the price higher. When
the price falls below this neckline, it
confirms the double top pattern. Now, I
have more confidence to trade this
pattern if it includes a liquidity run
on the second high point. It's quite
common to see the market clearing the
double top with the spike, triggering
stop- losses before moving in the
intended direction. During the formation
of the first high, volume can provide
valuable insights. If the volume is
high, it suggests strong buying
interest. At this point, you don't know
if a double top is forming. It's just a
simple break of structure pattern.
However, if the volume is low, it could
indicate a lack of conviction from
buyers. After the first high, there is
usually a pullback phase where the price
retraces slightly. During this phase, a
decrease in volume is common, indicating
a decrease in buying pressure. As the
price climbs towards the second high,
observe the volume again. If the volume
is lower than during the formation of
the first high, it could indicate
diminishing buying interest and
potential exhaustion of the uptrend. It
suggests that fewer traders are willing
to buy at higher prices. This volume
decline acts as a warning sign,
suggesting a weakening trend. The
liquidity run on low volume is another
sign that something is suspect. The most
critical phase of the double top
formation is when the price breaks below
the neckline. Here volume plays a vital
role in confirming the pattern. If the
price falls below the neckline on high
volume, it suggests a strong shift in
sentiment with sellers taking control.
High volume during the breakdown adds
credibility to the pattern and increases
the likelihood of a trend reversal.
In a double bottom pattern containing a
liquidity run, we start with a bearish
trend continuation pattern, a bearish
BOS. The price reaches two approximately
equal lows creating a support level.
Again, I like to see a liquidity run on
the second low taking stops and trapping
traders on the short side. The swing
high between the lows forms the
neckline. This pattern suggests a loss
of momentum in the previous downtrend,
indicating a weakening of sellers
interest and a potential trend reversal.
The two low points represent
unsuccessful attempts by sellers to push
the price lower. When the price rises
above this neckline, it confirms the
double bottom pattern. When the price
reaches the first low point, pay
attention to the volume. If the volume
is high, it suggests strong selling
interest. But if the volume is low, it
could indicate a lack of conviction from
sellers. After the first low, there is
usually a pullback phase where the price
retraces. During this phase, a decrease
in volume is common, indicating a
decrease in selling pressure. During the
formation of the second low point, look
at the volume. If the volume is lower
than during the formation of the first
low point, it could suggest diminishing
selling interest and potential
exhaustion of the downtrend. This volume
decline acts as a warning sign
indicating a possible trend reversal.
The liquidity run should ideally occur
on low volume. The most critical phase
of the double bottom pattern is when the
price breaks above the neckline. Here
volume provides the confirmation you
need. If the price rises above the
neckline on higher volume compared to
the previous low point, it suggest a
strong shift in sentiment with buyers
taking control.
Now let's briefly discuss how you can
incorporate these patterns into your
trading strategy. There are four main
variations to consider. First is the
neckline breakout entry in a double top
pattern. Once the price breaks below the
neckline and makes a new lower low, it
confirms a reversal and a change in
trend direction in a double bottom
pattern. Once the price breaks above the
neckline and makes a higher high, it
confirms the reversal and the possible
change in trend direction. The second
aspect is the pattern formation at the
key level. Identifying a key level of
supply or demand is crucial. If a double
bottom pattern forms at the demand area
or a double top pattern forms at the
supply area, it strengthens the pattern
significance.
My favorite entry is the pullback into a
recent supply or demand area. Instead of
entering a trade immediately after a
breakout, you may prefer to wait for a
pullback to a lower time frame supply or
demand area. This provides an
opportunity to enter the trade at a
better price and you don't blindly chase
the breakout.
Consider candlestick patterns at these
key levels. Combining candlestick
patterns with double top or double
bottom patterns can provide additional
confirmation. Look for candlestick
reactions at the moment of the neckline
breakout or at the pullback to a supply
or demand zone. pin bars and engulfing
bars in particular. For example, a
double top pattern forming with a long
weak candle at a resistance level can
confirm a trend change from an uptrend
to a downtrend. Or an engulfing candle
after the price tests the neckline after
the breakout is another good sign.
A trend change pattern, also known as a
change of character, occurs when the
price breaks a significant swing high or
low for the first time. This signals a
potential shift in the market's order
flow. For instance, if the market has
been in a downtrend with lower lows and
lower highs and the price breaks above a
previous major swing high, it indicates
a change of character. From a price
action standpoint, these patterns show a
loss of momentum from sellers. Instead
of continuing to make lower lows, the
price creates a reversal pattern. Buyers
are gaining control, suggesting a trend
change from a downtrend to an uptrend.
During the formation of the lowest low,
keep an eye on the volume. If the volume
is lower compared to the previous swing
low, it could suggest diminishing
selling interest and potential
exhaustion of the downtrend. This volume
decline is the first warning sign. The
most critical phase is when price breaks
above the previous major swing high. If
the price rises above this level on
higher volume compared to the previous
swing low, it confirms the shift in
sentiment with buyers taking control.
Conversely, in an uptrend with higher
highs and higher lows, when a price
breaks below a significant level, it
forms a new lower low, indicating a
potential trend reversal. From a price
action perspective, this pattern
indicates a loss of momentum from the
buyers. Instead of continuing to make
new higher highs, the price creates a
reversal pattern, suggesting a potential
shift in order flow. After a minor
pullback, if the price continues to
create lower lows and lower highs, it
indicates a new bearish trend. If the
volume during this high point is lower
than the volume during the previous
swing high, it indicates a decrease in
buying interest and the possible
exhaustion of the uptrend. This decline
in volume serves as an initial warning
sign. You don't know yet if a reversal
is on the cards. However, the most
crucial phase is when the price breaks
below this previous major swing low. If
the price breaks this level and does so
on higher volume compared to the volume
during the previous swing high, it
confirms the shift in the market
sentiment. Buyers have taken control,
further supporting the potential trend
reversal.
The head and shoulders pattern, although
a retail one, is a decent one to monitor
as it marks the transition point between
an uptrend and a downtrend with the left
side representing the end of the uptrend
and the right side representing the
beginning of the downtrend. The pattern
starts as a series of higher highs and
higher lows. That sequence is altered
when a low point is formed that has the
same approximate values as the previous
low. If it contains a liquidity run,
it's even better. The price rallies from
this low point, but instead of resuming
the sequence of higher highs, a lower
high occurs. Then the price slides back
to the previous low for a third time. If
a higher high occurs on expanding
volume, this is considered healthy and
normal in an uptrend. However, in an
ideal scenario, the head and shoulders
pattern sees volume diminish on each
successive high. The higher high that
forms the highest point of the head
should ideally occur on lower volume
than the previous high which formed the
left shoulder. Volume should diminish
further on the third high as the right
shoulder forms. This demonstrates a lack
of enthusiasm from the buyers who are
losing their will to continue buying at
higher prices. If and when the neckline
breaks, that break should occur on high
volume. Observe how volume decreased as
the pattern formed. The volume under the
head is low compared to the rally that
preceded it. In fact, volume is
extremely low on this bounce from the
neckline. Once the neckline was broken,
volume began to increase as the price
moved lower. In fact, it started to
increase prior to the breakout, which
confirms the selling pressure.
This also works if it's not a head and
shoulders. Maybe you have a triple top,
which includes a liquidity run. The
neckline is the focal point if you wish
to use this pattern to your advantage.
This is the area where many buyers
remain trapped with losing positions.
Since the price moved up from the
neckline on several occasions, we can
assume that many traders were buying at
that level. We know that those buyers
along with any buyers who entered at
higher levels and are still in the trade
will be holding losing positions if the
neckline should break. These losing
traders will be forced to sell which
should help push the price lower. Also,
aggressive traders will close long
positions and start to sell as the price
breaks through the neckline. This adds
momentum. Entering this phase, you must
see increasing volume.
The double liquidity run pattern, also
known as the master pattern, is another
common smart money formation. It's a
trap to attract both buyers and sellers
to take losing positions. First, price
breaks a swing high, but then it quickly
reverses, deceiving all buyers who took
the bait of the breakout. Amateurs will
enter what looks like an obvious
breakout. Then the professionals will
push the market back the other way. This
is the first liquidity run. The second
part of the pattern consists in another
trap. Price will decrease and will break
a swing low this time and trapping
sellers on the wrong side. This is the
second liquidity run designed to trap
the weak hands in the market. very hard
to make money as a retail trader if you
don't know what you're doing. If you
analyze this pattern, you'll observe it
contains three market phases:
contraction, expansion, and trend.
Firstly, we have the contraction phase.
This is when the market is setting up.
The contraction phase occurs on low
institutional trading volume resulting
in mostly sideways movement. It's not an
ideal phase for trading, but a part of
retail traders are taking the bait
hoping to catch a breakout. You'll often
see this phase during the Tokyo session.
Secondly, we have the expansion phase.
This seems like an exciting phase for
retail traders. Expansion is
characterized by a minor increase in
trading volume. The market becomes more
active, breaking previous highs and
lows. Smart money takes advantage of
this phase to accumulate positions at
discounted prices while inexperienced
traders often get caught in the whips
movements. It can be a challenging phase
because market breaks on both sides of
the range trapping most retail traders.
Finally, we have the trend phase. This
is the phase where the market makes a
significant and aggressive move in one
direction with increasing volume. During
this phase, institutional traders use
the market's liquidity to exit their
previously accumulated positions.
These three phases complete one market
cycle. Once they've played out, you can
expect the market to go through these
phases once again. One more example.
During the contraction phase, you'll see
periods of sideways movements. You'll
notice low institutional volume. As a
beginner, it's wise to avoid the
contraction phase.
Then we have the expansion phase, the
double manipulation with two liquidity
runs. First, a breakout below the range.
As soon as they see the market breaking
down, retail traders start selling
believing it will continue to decline.
Then later, when they see the market
breaking up, they start buying, assuming
it will rise further.
However, what they fail to understand is
that smart money operates differently.
They sell when the price is above
average and buy when it's below average.
If you look at the volume at the time of
the fake breakouts, you'll see that it's
low. Lastly, we have the trend phase
where we see the price move
significantly and you'll notice a volume
increase during this phase. You cannot
control when or how these phases occur.
But if you try to understand them, you
can improve your trading approach and
have a better grasp of the market
dynamics.
Now, let's go deeper with some advanced
smart money patterns. First is the
accumulation one. Accumulation is
nothing but a sideways market activity
that happens after an extended
downtrend. This is the phase where smart
money try to acquire positions without
moving the prices too much to the
upside. So let me explain why events
during accumulation. First we have the
preliminary support. This is when a lot
of buying starts happening after a long
period of prices going down. The volume
increases and the difference between the
highest and the lowest prices widens.
Then we have the selling climax. This is
the point where the selling pressure
reaches its peak and the difference
between the highest and the lowest
prices widens even more. Riddle traders
continue to sell but smart money start
buying at or near the bottom. Then we
have the automatic rally. After the
intense selling pressure decreases,
there is a wave of buying that easily
pushes the prices up. This rally helps
us define the upper boundary of the
trading range during the accumulation.
Next is the secondary test. The price
revisits the level of the selling climax
to see if there is a balance between
supply and demand at that level. For a
bottom to be confirmed, the volume
should be significantly lower as the
market approaches the support level
around the selling climax area. And it's
common to have multiple secondary tests
after a selling climax.
And then we have the sign of strength.
This happens when the price goes up with
increasing price difference and
relatively higher trading volume. A sign
of strength often occurs after a spring,
which is a fake breakout, a liquidity
run trapping retail traders on the short
side. A spring is when the price falls
below its usual range and then quickly
jumps back up into that range. And then
we have the last point of support. This
is the lowest point during a pullback
after a sign of strength. It marks the
final push toward the bottom of the
accumulation phase before the upward
trend begins. The last point of support
creates a higher low and then the price
starts going up again aggressively.
Now let's analyze the different phases
of an accumulation taking into account
the volume. First is the phase A. This
is where the sellers have been dominant
until now. We see a decrease in supply
during the preliminary support and the
selling climax. These events are usually
obvious on the charts with wider price
differences in high trading volume. In
phase B, smart money start buying at
relatively low prices in anticipation of
the next increase. The price swings are
wide with high trading volume. But as
smart traders absorb the available
supply, the volume during downward
swings within the trading range tends to
decrease.
In phase C, the price goes through a
decisive test of the remaining supply to
determine if it's ready for an increase.
It's like a trap for those who sold. A
successful test of supply with the
spring provides a good opportunity to
initiate a long position. In phase D,
demand starts dominating supply
consistently. we see a pattern of price
advances, signs of strength with wider
price differences and increasing trading
volume. There is also a last point of
support with smaller price differences
and lower trading volume. And finally,
we have phase E. This is when the price
leaves the trading range and demand
takes full control leading to an obvious
increase. New trading ranges can also
occur known as reaccumulation by smart
money. These ranges are like stepping
stones toward even higher price targets.
Let's also talk about woff events during
distribution.
First is the preliminary supply. This is
when smart money starts selling after
prices have been going up. the trading
volume increases and the difference
between the highest and the lowest
prices widens. This suggests that the
trend might be changing. Next, we have
the buying climax. During a buying
climax, there is a peak in buying
activity with higher price differences.
A buying climax often marks a top in the
market. Next is the automatic reaction.
After the buying climax, the intense
buying pressure decreases and the
sell-off occurs. This reaction helps
define the lower boundary of the
distribution trading range. Next is the
secondary test. The price revisits the
level of the buying climax to test the
balance between supply and demand. So,
the trading volume and price differences
should decrease as the price approaches
the resistance level of the buying
climax. Sometimes a secondary test takes
the form of an up thrust, a liquidity
run, where the price briefly moves above
the resistance level before quickly
reversing back below it. Next is the
sign of weakness. This is observed as a
downward move to or slightly below the
lower boundary of the trading range. It
usually happens with increased price
differences and increased volume. The
automatic reaction and the sign of
weakness indicate that supply is now
dominant in the market. And finally, we
have the last point of supply. After
testing support on a sign of weakness,
there may be a rally with narrow price
differences. The market struggles to
advance during this rally, indicating a
weak demand.
Now, let's look at the phases of
distribution. In phase A, the prior
uptrend stops and the supply starts
entering the market. We see preliminary
supply and the buying climax followed by
an automatic reaction and a secondary
test of the buying climax. In phase B,
smart money initiate short positions in
anticipation of the next decline. Signs
of weakness are often followed by
significant downward price movements and
increased trading volume.
Phase C is an interesting phase. This is
where up thrusts may occur. Price moves
above the trading range and then sharply
reverses back down. Many retail traders
fall into the trap of going long during
this phase. In phase D, signs of demand
decrease and the price may break the
trading range support or decline below
the midpoint of the range. It's a good
time to go short at the last point of
supply. It's also the last opportunity
for long position holders to close their
positions and go short. In phase E,
which is the final phase of
distribution, supply is in control and
price breaks below the trading range
support.
The high volume supply breakout pattern
is one of my personal edges. When smart
money push up through a potential area
of supply which is known as a resistance
level, they face a challenge. Many
traders who bought within that area are
still holding their positions and want
to sell to recover their investments.
These traders represent potential
supply, meaning they can act as a
resistance to the market's upward
movement. If market makers are expecting
higher prices and want a rally, they
need to avoid being forced to buy from
these traders at what may seem like high
prices. So, they use a strategy called
gapping, which means quickly and
significantly pushing the price up
through the supply zone. By the way, I
learned this from Tom Williams book,
Master the Markets, a must readad if you
want to learn more about this. This
momentum candle on high volume
discourages the trap traders from
selling. As the market approaches the
point where these sellers can sell
without a loss, the price suddenly
shoots up, often creating a gap on the
chart. This gives these traders a profit
and reduces their inclination to sell.
Gapping up through supply on high volume
is a tactic used by smart money to limit
the amount they need to buy to sustain
the rally. It helps them avoid buying at
high prices. When high volume follows
this wide spreads, it indicates that
professional traders were willing to
absorb the selling from the trap traders
who did decide to sell and this is known
as absorption volume.
This breakout triggers a new wave of
buying as traders who shorted the market
need to cover their positions and others
looking for breakouts also enter the
market. Traders who were not previously
participating may feel they are missing
out and start buying as well. All these
factors contribute to the professional
traders bullish positions. If you see
any testing or down bars on low volume
after the gapping event, it is
considered a strong buy signal. This
suggests that the market is likely to
continue its upward trend after the
initial breakout.
[Music]