What if I told you the big banks and hedge
funds can actually control the markets?
And that with a little observation, you could
easily spot their moves before anyone else.
Volume price analysis is the answer.
The volume price analysis is based on the
idea that big players like banks and hedge
funds manipulate the market behind the scenes.
Once you accept that, you can assume that
these big players know where the market is
going before anyone else.
If that's true, then all you need to do is
follow their moves.
You want to buy what they're buying and sell
what they're selling.
And when they're not actively participating,
you should stay out of the market too.
So these are the simple concepts behind this
trading method.
And we can see what the big players are doing
by paying attention to price and volume.
Basically, even though these big traders try
to hide their moves, there's one thing they
can't hide - the volume.
Since they handle such huge amounts of money,
it's obvious when they're getting into or
out of a market because the volume will increase.
On the other hand, if the price jumps but
the volume stays low, that usually means the
big traders are just manipulating the market
but not actually putting in any real money
themselves.
So you have to be careful of traps in those
cases.
Only by keeping an eye on both price and volume
together, you can read what those banks and
hedge funds are up to.
And once you know where they're putting their
money to work, you've got a good idea of where
the market is likely headed next.
This Volume Price Analysis (VPA) method was
developed by Richard Wyckoff back in the day.
He came up with three main laws that it's
based on.
First law is about effort and result.
Basically, it means the volume, or effort,
needs to match up with the price move, or
result.
So if volume is high, you should see a big
change in price.
If they don't line up, something ain't right.
You can use anomalies between volume and price
to figure out if the big players are buying
or selling.
We’ll talk about them later in the video.
Wyckoff's second law is about cause and effect.
Basically, about time.
If they take a long time to build up a new
move, you can expect the resulting price change
to be large too when it happens.
The final law is supply and demand - if supply
is greater than demand, price will drop.
But if demand is bigger than supply, then
price goes up.
These three laws explain how price is always
rotating between bull and bear markets over
different time periods.
And volume helps uncover what the big money
are doing.
This trading cycle follows the same pattern
no matter what time frame you look at, whether
it's a 1 minute chart or 1 month chart.
Of course, you have the odds in your favor
when you’re analyzing higher time frames.
I prefer to monitor the daily chart when I’m
analyzing volume.
It’s easier this way, 1 candle means 1 trading
day, and it has more meaning than 1-min time
frame.
Now, a full rotation between market phases
happens from the selling climax up to the
buying climax and back down again.
When I talk about a buying climax, that's
when these big players are starting selling
near the top of a rally.
The selling climax is when they're start buying
at the bottom of a drop.
At the buying climax, the market has been
moving up so long that little guys are terrified
of missing out.
Eventually they cave and jump in right as
the big players start their selling into a
weakening market.
Volatile price action and news are used to
dump their positions.
FOMO, or fear of missing out, is a powerful
emotion the big traders use to their full
advantage getting the little retail guys to
buy at highs.
Once their positions are cleared, they start
planning the next phase.
The selling climax happens when the big money
players need to refill their positions.
At this point, fear of losing money triggers
everyone else to bail their positions.
Quickly, the big players crash the price down
usually because of some news.
Then retail traders panic sell right into
the big guys' buy orders.
Once they've accumulated enough, the big guys
jump in to stop the market from falling further.
And then a next phase begins.
This also explains why markets drop faster
than they rise.
Smart money have all the time in the world
to let prices rise to make their big profits.
They actually plan everything out.
The worst thing would be getting overwhelmed
by too much buying or selling early, wrecking
their new plan.
That's why before starting a new campaign,
they run a quick test.
Once the big accumulation phase finishes at
the sellling climax, before they launch their
new campaign, they run a quick test.
This makes sure any leftover sellers have
been soaked up.
Doing so ensures the upcoming bull run can
unfold smoothly without any major sellers
pulling it down.
The test involves a small downward price push,
below support.
Volume staying low confirms it.
They call it a "supply test".
If it passes with low volume, their next buying
campaign has the green light.
Similarly, at the end of the big rally (buying
climax), a "demand test" happens before the
bearish campaign.
The big guys briefly send it higher, often
times above resistance – and no extra demand
means it will fail back with ease.
This confirms no major buyers are around.
So, the whole premise of understanding the
volume price analysis is accepting the big
players control and manipulate everything
behind the scenes.
The only thing we need to know is when they're
actively buying, selling or sitting out a
move.
In my approach, watching each daily candle,
monitoring price changes and volume, helps
me with that, by looking if those two factors
sync up or contradict each other.
If the price and volume are high, then the
big players are steering things and are in
the driver's seat.
But if they are in disagreement, things are
suspect.
One of the most important areas on the price
chart is when a market is in congestion, as
markets spend 70% to 80% of their time in
such regions, and only 20% of the time trending.
It's real simple - these are the areas where
new moves are cooked up by the big players
planning for the next part of their plan.
Could be huge areas like right before a big
sell-off or rally, or even maybe smaller moves
where a market has paused in the primary trend.
Understanding congestion phases along with
support and resistance or supply and demand
is a key element of volume price analysis.
And many traders don't get it or ignore it
trying to chase trends all the time.
The longer a market remains at a price level,
then the greater the concentration of volume,
and price will only continue to move on, once
the balance of bearish or bullish sentiment
shifts.
And whenever a breakout happens, volume tells
you if it's a real move or fake news.
So, support and resistance levels, supply
and demand and price action must be part of
this volume analysis.
This example shows a wide range candle over
one trading day.
Volume was way above normal.
So the trading activity backed up the price
movement that day.
For a move to be real, the effort to push
it higher should be seen in the volume.
That's Wyckoff's third law - it takes effort
to drive prices up or down, so a big daily
change means heavy trading volume backing
it up.
And that's exactly what we got here.
Therefore, the volume validates the price
action as genuine.
So the move wasn't secretly manipulated by
big players or market makers.
And for now, the trend is still bullish since
we don't see anything telling us otherwise
yet.
This chart shows a narrow body candle with
wicks on top and bottom.
Trading volume was way below average too.
Even though the price rose a bit, the move
was really small so the candle is narrow.
Volume backing it up is also low.
That's because of Wyckoff's law again - effort
and result need to match up.
If the price only increased a bit (the result),
then volume (the effort) shouldn't be heavy.
So once more, the volume confirms that what
we're seeing with price action is real.
A small daily price increase implies slim
trading activity.
Volume is still validating the price movement
as genuinely reflecting what's happening behind
the scenes.
Here we see a wide candle, so the volume should
match that big move.
Instead, volume is low even though price had
a wide range - and this is a divergence!
A large daily candle body usually means heavy
trading to push it there.
But a low volume bar doesn't add up.
If I was already in a long position and saw
this, I'd start questioning the move.
Could it be a trap forming?
You will see that this divergence pattern
often shows up at the start of equity sessions.
Basically the big money is feeling out sentiment
in the market by shooting price up to test
buyer interest.
But again, the move was fake.
It's designed to trick traders into weak longs
and hit their stop losses before price reverses
hard.
That's why VSA is so powerful - volume reveals
the truth behind prices.
It unmasks the intentions of big players setting
traps versus real momentum shifts.
Now we see a narrow candle range but massive
volume, which is another mixed signal.
By Wyckoff's law, a small price move should
need low volume, but that's not happening
here.
There's really only one way to read this - the
market is starting to look suspect.
Patterns like these often show up at turning
points, like tops of price increases or bottoms
of down moves.
For example, in an established bullish phase,
price rises a bit at the open but then the
big boys start cashing out their gains.
More buyers hop in, but price stops going
up since the smart money are selling into
them and pocketing profits at this level.
What's actually happening is this price can't
keep rising no matter how many buyers jump
in because the smart money are constantly
selling to take profits.
So when price and volume tell different stories
like this, it's signaling underlying weakness
in the overall trend.
Here we see a rising market with prices following
volume higher.
That's exactly the sync we want to see.
The first candle has a small range and volume
is low, matching the little price move.
No issues there.
The second candle is wider so its volume should
be greater.
And yes, volume increased along with price
action.
By the third candle's even bigger daily range,
its volume needs to be really strong.
Once again, trading activity backed up the
result.
Price action on the candles has been validated
by the volume.
Price increased higher over the period while
volume increased with it each step of the
way.
Everything is lining up between effort and
result - bullish price action reinforced by
heavy buying volume.
This is the ideal trend validation.
In this example, we see a confirmed uptrend
starting with a small candle on low volume
as expected.
The second candle's range increased a bit
but volume was higher compared to the tiny
price action.
That's a divergence - a small price move shouldn't
pump volume that much.
Candle no. three was wider but volume decreased
versus the big move before.
It should've been higher too with the bigger
daily price change.
Another warning.
Then candle four was a wide range one, yet
volume dropped again.
Multiple mixed signals stacking up now.
A wide price swing shouldn't have volume declining
more.
Falling volume conflicts with the ongoing
bullish run.
We have several divergence problems in this
supposed trend.
Things are no longer lining up like they should
between effort and result.
I hope you see how price alone can only tell
you what a market’s present technical position
really is, but not where the trend is probably
headed, at least not accurately.
Volume helps to validate the trend with more
accuracy and also detects turning points,
when to open or close trades.
And together, they form a complete picture.
Price must go hand in hand with volume.
Is it possible to make money trading using
price action alone?
Sure.
But price in combination with volume is 10
times better.
First, you see what the CANDLESTICK is telling
you, then you check the volume, and see if
it’s validating or not with the recent price
action.