Hello and welcome.
Today we’ll talk about volume spread analysis,
I’ll show you how to read the market, BEFORE
it moves and you’ll learn to anticipate
where the market is going next based on simple
logic and the power of volume and price.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel
and stick around for the full video.
When using VSA, you should be looking for
two things.
Whether the price has been validated by the
volume, or whether there is a divergence with
the price.
If the price is validated then this confirms
a continuation of the price behavior.
By contrast if there is a divergence, then
this is sending a signal of a potential change.
These are the only things we are constantly
searching for in VSA.
Validation or Divergence.
Before we begin, I want to recommend you a
book I’m currently reading.
It’s called “A Complete Guide To Volume
Price Analysis” by Anna Coulling.
I highly recommend this book.
Now let’s further discuss Validation and
Divergence.
In this example, we have a wide spread up
candle with small wicks on top and bottom,
and the associated volume is well above average.
So, the volume is validating the price action.
Let’s assume each candle represents one
trading day, which is also my preferred time
frame for VSA.
In this case we have a market which is bullish,
and has risen strongly in the trading session,
closing just below the high of the session.
If this is a valid move then we would expect
to see the effort required to push the market
higher, reflected in the volume.
Remember, this is also Wyckoff's third law
of effort vs. result.
It takes effort for the market to rise and
also takes effort for the market to fall,
so if there has been a large change in price
in the session, then we expect to see this
validated by a well above average volume bar.
Which we have.
Therefore, in this case the volume validates
the price.
And from this we can assume two things.
First, that the price move is confirmed, and
has not been manipulated by the smart money
or market makers, and second, for the time
being, the market is bullish, and until we
see a divergence signaled, then we can continue
to maintain any long position that we may
have in the market.
Here we have an example of a narrow spread
candle formed on low volume.
In this case the price has risen, but only
marginally higher, and the spread of the candle
is therefore very narrow.
The wicks to the top and bottom are once again
small.
The associated volume is well below average
and is once again validating the price action.
And the reason is again because of effort
and result.
In this case the market has only risen in
price by a small amount, and therefore we
would expect to see this reflected in the
volume, which should also be low.
After all, if effort and result validate one
another, the effort required to move the market
a few points higher (the result), should only
warrant a small amount of effort (the volume).
So once again, we have a true picture with
the volume validating the price.
Here we have our first divergence.
It is clear we have a wide spread up candle,
and if we follow Wyckoff's third rule, then
this result should be matched by an equal
amount of effort.
What we have instead is a big result, from
little effort.
This is a divergence.
For a wide spread up candle, we would expect
to see a high volume bar, but here we have
a low volume bar.
If we were in a long position in the market
and this appeared, we would immediately start
to question what is happening.
Why has this divergence appeared?
Is it an early warning of a possible trap?
This is a pattern which often occurs at the
start of trading sessions in equity markets.
What is happening here is that the smart money
are trying to 'feel out' the sentiment in
the market.
The market opens, then the price is pushed
higher to test interest in the market from
the buyers.
Once again this is a signal of a potential
trap.
The move higher is NOT a genuine move but
a fake move, designed to suck traders into
weak positions, and also take out stops, before
reversing sharply and moving in the opposite
direction.
This is why VSA is so powerful.
Volume and price together reveal the truth
behind market intentions.
In this example we can see a narrow spread
candle with high volume which, once again,
is another divergence.
As we saw earlier, a small increase in the
price (result), should only require a small
increase in volume (effort), but this is not
the case here.
The small price increase has been generated
by a huge amount of volume, so clearly something
is wrong.
There is only one conclusion we can draw.
The market is starting to look weak, and this
is a typical pattern that starts to develop
at the top of a bullish trend, or the bottom
of a bearish trend.
For example in an established bullish trend,
the market opens, starts to rise a little,
and the buyers are now starting to take their
profits.
As these positions are closed out, more eager
buyers come in, but the price never rises
as the longs continue to liquidate and take
their profits.
And the cycle repeats throughout the session.
What is actually happening is that the market
has reached a price at which further effort
does not result in higher prices, as each
wave of new buyers is met with longs selling
out at this level and taking their profits
'off the table'.
So there is no sustained move higher in price.
In other words, what this combination of price
and volume is revealing is weakness in the
market.
Now, VSA is only part of the story.
You need to use a variety of other techniques
to confirm the picture and provide additional
validation.
The most important of these are support and
resistance or supply or demand areas.
This is where the market is pausing, before
reversing.
Alternatively, it may simply be a pause point
in a longer term trend, which will then be
validated by our volume analysis.
A breakout from one of these regions of consolidation,
coupled with volume, is always a strong signal.
Trends are equally important.
Whenever you see a divergence which sets the
alarm bell ringing, the first step is to establish
were you are in any trend.
For example, are you at a possible bottom,
where perhaps the market has been selling
off for some time, but is now looking at a
major reversal?
Or perhaps you are in the middle of a trend,
and you are experiencing a minor pull back
or reversal in the longer term trend.
Deciding where you are in the trend, is where
you bring in some of your other analytical
tools which then help to complement VSA.
In judging where you are in the trend, and
potential reversal points, you will always
be looking at support and resistance, candle
patterns, individual candles, or trend lines.
All of this will help to identify where you
are in the price action on the chart.
In this example we have a bullish trend developing
in a rising market, and what is obvious is
that rising prices are followed by rising
volume.
This is exactly what we would expect to see.
The first candle forms, a narrow spread up
candle with low volume, which is fine.
The volume validates the price, no divergence
here.
The second candle then begins to form, the
spread of this is wider than the first, and
based on Wyckoff's rule, we expect to see
greater volume that on the first bar, which
is indeed the case.
So the uptrend is valid, the volume has validated
the price on both candles.
By the time the third candle starts to form,
and closes with a spread which is wider than
both the first and the second, we should expect
a high volume bar which reflects Wyckoff's
third law of effort vs result.
Once again, the price action on the candle
has been validated by the volume.
The three candles themselves are now validating
the price trend.
The price over the three bars has moved higher,
developed into a trend, and the volume is
rising and NOW validating the trend itself.
In this example, we have what appears to be
a bullish trend, with the first narrow spread
candle followed by relatively low volume.
This is fine as the volume is validating the
price and is in agreement.
The second candle then forms and we have a
slightly wider spread candle than the first,
but with high volume.
This appears to be a divergence.
With high volume we would expect to see a
wide spread candle.
Instead, we only have a candle which is marginally
wider in price spread than the previous candle,
so this is our first sign.
The third candle then forms, and closes as
a wide spread candle, but with volume that
is lower than on the previous candle.
Given the spread of the bar, it should be
higher, not lower.
Another warning signal.
The fourth candle then forms and closes as
a very wide price spread, but the volume is
even lower!
We now have several divergences here.
On second candle we have a modest spread in
price, but high volume.
The market should have risen much further
given the effort contained in the volume bar.
This is signaling potential weakness.
During the third candle the price spread is
wider than the previous candle, but the volume
is lower.
The buying pressure is draining away.
Also, we have a market that is rising, but
the volume has fallen on this candle.
Rising markets should be associated with rising
volume, NOT falling volume.
During the fourth candle, we see further confirmation
that the volume and price on this trend are
no longer in agreement.
We have a wide spread up candle and even lower
volume than on previous candles in the trend.
So, the falling volume is confirming that
we have a divergence on the trend, as we expect
to see rising volume with a rising trend,
whereas here we have falling volumes on a
rising trend.
What are the conclusions?
The problems start with candle two.
Here we have effort, but not an equivalent
result in terms of the associated price action.
This is therefore the first sign of possible
weakness.
The market is what is known as 'over bought'.
The sellers are moving into the market sensing
an opportunity to short the market.
This creates a resistance to higher prices,
which is then confirmed on the third and fourth
candles, where volume is falling away.
Smart money have seen this weakness, and are
starting to sell, preparing for a move lower,
but continue to mark prices higher, to give
the appearance of a market that is still bullish.
It is not.
This may only be a temporary pause, and not
a major change in trend, but nevertheless,
it is a warning of potential weakness in the
market.
The high volume is as a result of an increasing
number of buyers closing out their positions,
and taking their profits, whilst the remaining
buyers do not have sufficient momentum to
take the market higher.
Smart money are also selling at this level
adding to the volumes.
This is the reason why volumes fall on the
next two candles, as they continue to mark
the market higher, but are no longer involved
in the move themselves.
They are trapping traders into weak positions.
The initial weakness appeared on candle two,
which was then FURTHER confirmed by candles
three and four.
This is often the sequence of events that
unfolds.
Initially we see a divergence that appear
using the single candle analysis.
We then wait for other candles to appear,
and analyze them against the initial divergence.
In this case, the divergence was confirmed,
with prices continuing to rise on falling
volumes.
And now we have a market which is apparently
weak, and confirmed as such.
The next step is to move to the final level
in our analysis, which is to consider the
analysis in the bigger picture of the chart.
This will determine whether what we are seeing
is a minor pull back, or the pre-cursor to
a change in trend.
If this make sense, make sure you watch our
other VSA tutorial.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.