Market structure should be the foundation
of your analysis.
The first part of any trading plan is to establish
which side of the market is in the commanding
position, buyers or sellers, demand or supply.
Today we’ll talk about that, the market
structure and you’ll learn how to read charts
correctly.
So if you could like, subscribe to channel
and stick around for the full video.
What is market structure
When reading market structure, you have to
pay close attention to one thing on the chart:
price.
Price will tell you all you need to know.
When price is moving influenced by supply
and demand, this creates trends.
A bull trend is depicted by higher highs (HH)
and higher lows (HL).
The trend will continue in that direction
until a lower low is printed by the asset
price.
The trend begins to show signs of weakness
when it fails to print a higher high.
A bear trend is the price action of lower
lows (LL) and lower highs (LH).
The bear trend will continue to fall as long
as lower highs continue to print.
Once a higher high comes into the price, the
trend will end.
The sign that the trend may be reversing is
when price begins to print higher lows or
equal lows.
A sideways trend is a trend that has equal
highs and equal lows.
Price trends in a range during this point
of the market and is in consolidation.
Markets can move in a period of consolidation
for a long time.
This trend is broken if the price breaks out
from the top or bottom of the range.
This could be the beginning of one of the
first two trends.
These are the obvious concepts regarding market
structure.
Now let’s go deeper, and let me share the
subtleties of market structure.
Price prints new high/low that breaks the
previous high/low
The first principle is the most obvious one:
for a market to be in an active cycle, it’s
most recent structure must be one where price
prints a high that breaks the previous high
(this is the case of a bullish cycle).
A down-cycle will be established if the latest
swing low in price breaks below the most recent
low.
In this hourly chart, you can clearly see
the market in an up-cycle phase on higher
highs and higher lows.
Several Closes Beyond Last High/Low
To confirm that a bullish trend or up-cycle
is evolving in a healthy manner, not only
we need to see the high printed being higher
than its previous high, but we also should
expect at least several closes above that
high or support area, as further evidence
that the market is accepting and building
value.
Failure to print at least two or three closes
above that high may translate into a false
breakout, and while the move still holds its
merit to qualify as a new high in the cycle,
the quality of the leg is poor in nature.
Find confirmation from higher time frames
You must avoid the trap of being short-sighted
by only sticking to one chart analysis.
When conducting your market structure analysis,
it’s all about finding confirmation from
higher time frames down to your trading time
frame.
What this means is that if you are going to
find an entry trigger on the hourly time frame,
you should then understand what type of conditions
are dominant in the immediately higher time
frames.
The most popular in this case would be the
4h and daily charts.
50% retracement rule
A major mistake made by traders when analyzing
market structure is allowing too much guessing
play a role in their analysis.
When analyzing the charts, how do you determine
a relevant swing high/low?
Is it this one, or this one?
Which is more relevant?
That’s why you need to find a mechanical
approach that will allow you to qualify a
relevant swing high or swing low in the chart.
Here’s my general rule, if a swing low/high
doesn’t make it to at least the 50% retracement
of its previous swing, I disregard that price
movement as not relevant enough to represent
a valid leg.
I only want to focus on the creation of relevant
and valid legs that will lead to new cycles
and create in the process relevant levels
of supports and resistances.
We’ll talk about this later.
Transitions From Trends To Ranges
Market don’t always trend, and you’ll
come to the point in the market structure
where the dominant trend starts drying up,
maybe due to increased profit-taking, removals
of liquidity, intervention by market-makers
or economic data-driven moves.
While in an up-cycle, the interpretation of
the market structure is straightforward, you
must determine when you’ve transitioned
from a trend into a consolidation.
Here’s my method.
We’ll cover an uptrend transitioning into
consolidation.
Firstly, you must see a failed test of a valid
high.
Price is unable to break the recent high.
Secondly, a failed test of the most recent
swing low would confirm that we have entered
a consolidation phase, which would last until
the most recent valid high or low is broken,
with at several closes above/below the level.
In this context, don’t forget that the consolidation
is within the context of an up-cycle.
Until sellers manage to break and hold below
the latest valid swing low, the strength remains
to the upside.
Magnitude of the Cycle
Another major sign that will help us determine
the health of the cycle is the type of progress
made by the dominant side in control of the
cycle.
You need to ask the following question: Are
the new legs in the cycle increasing or decreasing
in magnitude?
Here, despite having entered a period of consolidation
in the hourly chart, if we measure the latest
swing high, if we measure its extension from
the last low to the newly established high,
we see that this is a bigger advance vs the
previous up leg.
This means that buyers are increasing their
commitment on each new cycle high (greater
demand imbalances), therefore, this is yet
another clue that the strength is to the upside.
Velocity of the Cycle
When it comes to the distance the price moves,
the magnitude is only half of the equation.
The other one has to do with the velocity
of the move or the speed.
Was the new leg created after a fast and impulsive
move?
Or did price make a new low or high with the
movement being sluggish, compressive and taking
too long to form?
A good rule of thumb is to count the approximate
number of candles it took to achieve a new
leg.
In this case, you can see that the second
leg was created with a lower number of candles.
At a faster speed.
So the cycle continues to prosper in a healthy
manner.
Projection Targets In A New Cycle
A reliable measure I have found to set targets
when trading cycles is to measure the 100%
Fibonacci projection from the most recent
valid swing low to its high.
In Tradingview, you use this tool, Trend-based
FIB Extension.
You need to join the lowest, the highest point
and the low of the retracement or the pullback
as the third point.
For example, looking at this chart, we are
in an up cycle.
The first point to draw the Fibonacci extension
would be at point A, the point B will be here
and the third point will be here, at the low
of the retracement.
This will give you the 100% Fibonacci projection,
and other probable resistance levels where
the price may face resistance in the near
future.
If the cycle continues in the expected direction,
you will start to appreciate the power and
usefulness of these targets to consider taking
profits or trailing stops, in the hope of
a larger profit for your trade.
In this example, notice how this target was
reached almost to the pip before buyers took
profit.
Cluster Of Levels Nearby
Another important exercise you must perform
is to draw the most immediate lines of support
and resistance — at least 2 up and 2 down
— based on a top-down analysis.
They should be obvious to spot.
Here you must take into account:
- the number of times the area has been tested
(ideally, minimum 2 times),
- the type of reaction away from this area
(the stronger the more relevant),
- time frame (the higher the timeframe, the
more significant the level is).
Here, I’ve drawn the two most immediate
levels of support and resistance in the daily
and H4.
What this means is that if you are going to
find trades on the H1 chart, you must be aware
that once the price reaches these areas in
the higher time frames, a potential reaction
in the structure in your trading time frame
(H1 in our example) may occur, so you must
be aware by anticipating this potential outcome.
Marking these levels in your chart allows
you to know when to expect a potential reversal.
If you’ve followed me this far, you now
understand that a new cycle would be confirmed
if we can break and have several closes outside
a range.
However, what if we break the current range
but we are faced with another recent low immediately
ahead?
If the distance is relatively narrow, a safer
approach is to wait until a breakout of the
most distant level in that cluster of support
areas, which would be several closes below
this second level, to confirm the down cycle.
Essentially, when this situation occurs, what
you probably want to do is to expand the size
of the range and wait for a resolution outside.
How to trade market structure
So, how can you go about trading these cycles?
• First , assuming you are trading off the
hourly chart, you want to make sure to trade
also in line with at least the immediately
higher timeframe cycle (H4), and ideally both
(daily and H4).
• You also want to double-check that the
hourly market structure is trending, several
closes beyond the last valid swing low/high
to confirm a new leg in the cycle.
• It’s important that you then check the
absence of nearby cluster levels from higher
time frames or economic data releases that
may disturb the structure.
• And pay attention to both the magnitude
and the speed on the creation of a new cycle.
If we are in a healthy cycle with lower lows
for example, decent magnitude moves and no
obstruction of higher timeframe levels, pay
attention to the 50% fib retracement of the
correction.
The 50% fib retracement a great location to
start looking for trades based on your ideal
entry technique.
Some traders may prefer to set limit orders
at this levels with a stop a few pips away
from the most recent high.
Others may prefer a confirmation trigger such
as the break of a trendline, a particular
pattern (flag, triangle etc) or a specific
price action formation such as engulfing bars,
pin bars.
Whichever way you approach your trades, the
area you are looking to trade from must hold
value on the basis of decent risk-reward prospects.
You can alter the entry approach as you wish.
I personally like to find entries at the 50%
fib retracement, but you can also wait for
entries at the area between 50 - 61.8%, also
known as the golden zone or at 78.6% fib retracements.
In fact, a great pattern for a potentially
large risk-reward is to be on the lookout
to trade a retracement at the 78.6% Fibonacci
within the context of a strong and healthy
cycle.
These trades tend to offer the best opportunities,
with a narrow stop and a larger profit potential.
Fibonacci extensions are a great way to establish
price targets or find projected areas of support
or resistance, when the price is moving into
an area where other methods of finding support
or resistance are not so evident.
If you are long on a trade for example, and
a new high occurs, you can use the Fibonacci
extension levels for an idea of where the
price may go.
You have the option to decide whether to cover
the position at that level.
I prefer the 100% Fib projection and the next
important one is at 1.618 level.
This is the simplest way of analyzing a market.
The big advantage in analyzing market structure
this way consists is keeping your charts clean,
uncluttered, away from unnecessary indicators.
And of course, some degree of subjectivity
will always be required.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.