Today I’m helping you with your trading mindset.
Your mindset is made up of all the established
beliefs and attitudes you default to,
internally, when it comes to trading.
And speaking from experience, a
change in mindset is one of the
hardest things to achieve. But when you
do it, trading will become a lot easier.
It’s gonna be interesting. So, like, subscribe,
and stick around for the full video.
Trading is more about people than prices
Trading
is as much about game theory than any underlying
economics. You don’t make money by predicting
performance, you make money by predicting how
people respond to changes in a particular market.
There’s a common saying: the market has memory.
Well, I would say the market participants,
the crowd, have memory.
Optimism and pessimism,
hope and fear—all these emotions can exist in one
trader at different times or in multiple traders
or groups at the same time.
The market psychology is
steering market trends and price action.
Reading market trends and market psychology can
be extremely hard for a beginner. But it can be
done if you analyze volume and the open interest.
You will be in a much better
position to assess the mood of the
market and adjust your position accordingly.
So remember, trading is a game with your own
rules, a game of psychology and discipline.
Numbers, analysis, data etc are secondary.
What drives your decision-making?
Each one of us has a unique risk
tolerance. Some are more aggressive,
some more conservative or analytical.
I’ve said many times, make sure you
use a strategy that fits your risk
profile and fits your daily schedule.
Many traders fail because of their
inability to understand themselves.
You need to ask yourself some questions:
• How do you handle stress?
• How do you deal with uncertainties?
• Can you cope with losses?
• Do you get euphoric after substantial gains?
• Can you detach from money?
• Are you patient?
• Are you flexible and
willing to change during a trade?
• Can you admit being wrong?
These questions are related to fear,
greed, and the adrenaline that
interfere almost on a daily basis.
Answer to them honestly, and try to
understand what drives your decision-making.
Your dominant personality traits will
sooner or later influence your trading
Let’s make a quick exercise. Write down your
strengths and weaknesses when it comes to trading.
Look at yourself from a distance and try
to be as objective and neutral as possible.
By putting your traits down on paper, you force
yourself to express your thoughts clearly.
In my case, as strengths I’ve
wrote down: analytical mindset,
self control, very organized and
logical, passionate for trading.
And as weaknesses: inability to be 100% detached
from money when I’m in a live trade, not the
most patient trader when I’m scalping, the need to
perfection sometimes affects my trading decisions.
It’s a simple exercise aiming at understanding
your personality traits, and your strength
and weaknesses. In the end, all your dominant
personality traits will sooner or later influence
your trading and thus your profits (or losses).
So do yourself a favor, and think about your
personality type. And build your trading
around your strengths, not your weaknesses.
No trade and no strategy is perfect
Expecting the perfect entry or exit,
or expecting to catch the full wave,
are things that are incredibly
rare. I still struggle with this.
Most of your trades will be far from perfect
and this is the tough reality of trading.
If you expect perfection, you will
suffer through a lot of frustration.
And it goes without saying but, also,
there is no perfect trading strategy.
A perfect trading strategy is one
that makes money in the long run,
not a system that makes money with every trade.
You may already have a profitable trading
strategy in your hands, you just don’t
know it because after every losing trade,
you change it or you want to adjust it so that
the loss you just took could have been avoided.
However, changing your system means you’re
opening it to other potential losses.
Accepting that no trade and no strategy
is perfect relieves you of a giant burden.
Things rarely ever go according to plan
Let’s face it, things rarely ever go according
to plan, even if you are organized and prepared.
If you refuse to accept this reality and if you
don’t work tirelessly on a solid trading plan
with an effective action plan that covers as many
possibilities as you might run into while trading,
you are not going to survive as a trader.
When you trade, it’s imperative that you know
what risks you’re willing to take and how you will
manage them if something goes wrong along the way.
In trading, all uncontrolled
elements are considered risks.
These are the factors that can
always go against your trade.
On the other hand, controlled elements are the
tools that help you restrain and reduce the risks.
Know what you can and can’t control in trading
So let’s talk about controlled and
uncontrolled elements in trading.
Your analysis is the first controlled element.
You control how thorough your analysis is. If
you invest the proper time and knowledge into it,
you’ll be able to come away with a well-educated
analysis and assessment of a market.
Timing The Entry / Exit is another
obvious controlled element.
You get to make the decision for
where and when to act in the market and at what
price to place your positions, targets, and stops.
The market and Time frame You Trade are also under
your control. You decide when, where, how long,
and under what settings you want to trade in.
Another controlled element: Risk-Reward. It’s
your decision to filter out trades that are not
deemed to provide a sufficient risk-reward ratio.
Position Sizing, another controlled
element. You decide how much you risk
on a position. It’s at your discretion
to set the margin for error and drawdown.
You can also time how to secure your exposed
position during major economic releases.
The schedule of these events are
pre-planned and published ahead of time,
so you have plenty of time to stay out, set stops
and targets, reduce exposure or any other mean of
protection from the upcoming high volatility.
Training Your Psychological State is another
thing which is somewhat under your control.
Knowing your mental strengths and what you
can put to use. This also means being aware
of the mental weakness you need to work on.
Capping your risk is also something
that’s definitely done by your decision.
So are shifting and securing profits
with stops and setting stop loss and
targets in realistic locations,
relative to the market conditions.
All these elements are under your control.
But how about elements you can’t control.
The trigger condition is the first one.
You can never time when all the right
conditions align to trigger a trade (or an
exit). This sometimes results in doing things
like missing the entry and jumping late on
a trade or prematurely entering a trade.
Available information is
another uncontrolled element.
As a retail trader, you are always
on the short end of receiving the
relevant information that can
affect your trade assessment.
For example, information such as increasing
volume is not available for forex trading.
Retail traders like you and me are left only
with little information, such as chart reading
and macroeconomic data. We simply don’t have
an information edge. And this is a risk.
Price Volatility is also out of your control.
When price moves in a strong manner, you can only
see it after it happens. It’s almost impossible
to get a heads-up before a major move occurs,
and your position will always be exposed
to such rough events at any given time.
Once you are in a trade, while the price moves,
you cannot really do anything as it happens.
The same thing goes for unexpected
news events that affect our positions.
You can never know when they’re about to erupt
and in which direction they’ll move the market in.
Also, setting trade targets does
not guarantee prices will reach it
before they reach your stop loss. We have no
control over what direction the market takes.
If you’re aiming for a specific RRR, it’s
not guaranteed you will get it as expected.
Your psychological readiness for
specific events can hit you by surprise.
Life Circumstances is
another uncontrolled element.
Maybe you’re having a bad day, or you’re facing
a challenging period in your life, you’re tired,
or demotivated. Life circumstances will not
always be optimal to support your trading.
The point is: always acknowledge that there
are more aspects that you’re not aware of,
that will affect your trading and expose
your position to risk. Acknowledge that
these events can pop out of
the blue and surprise you.
Eventually, you will be able to spot
new blind spots as they begin to form.
You
are overtrading, and you don’t even know it
Overtrading is one of the most challenging
lessons for a trader to understand. If
you tend to overtrade and you continue
to overtrade, you will lose a lot of money.
You expose your money to the market any time
you enter it. The fact is you could be
overtrading, and you don’t even know it.
If you are overtrading, there are several signs:
- If you close a trade for a loss and you believe
deep down that you shouldn’t have taken
the trade, you are guilty of overtrading.
- if you find yourself looking at lower time
frames like the 5-minute chart and “discover”
some trades, even though you planned to use
the H1 chart, again it’s a sign of overtrading
- if you’re spending too much time gazing
at charts, you become vulnerable to seeing
too much market activity, which
again, might turn into overtrading
- if you find yourself looking at charts for
hours, attempting to “force” a trade, that
is not that obvious, because you don’t want to
feel that you wasted time, again, a warning sign
The biggest issue is that many traders are clearly
unaware that they are over-trading at the moment.
It is really possible to get fixated on
a less-than-ideal trade setup, lose track
of your trading plan, and become uninformed
about whether or not you are over-trading.
If you are guilty of this, it is best to
go on the offensive against over-trading
and revisit your trading strategy and plan
a better a trading schedule ahead of time.
Not having a position is a position
The number of trades often does not translate
into large profits. Instead, the effectiveness
of individual trades makes the real difference.
After a successful trade and a significant profit,
you can be tempted to continue trading, but the
market doesn’t work according to your commands.
After a few successful
trades, you may start losing.
Here’s a quick piece of advice: Set a limit
on the number of trades you want to open in
a single day. Keep up with this plan, and
if you feel like opening one more trade,
remind yourself that there is always tomorrow.
Again, I’ve said many times in the past,
not having a position is a position. Some of the
best trades in life are the ones you do not take.
Get rid of anything that doesn’t bring you value
Each one of us has different ways of understanding
and processing trading situations. When we look at
a chart, we all see things differently and
we experience the market events uniquely.
When you have a teacher or mentor, you can
try to learn the concepts they share with you,
but you can’t expect to have the same results.
What works for them can contribute to your
success, but in order to really succeed,
you will need to custom tailor everything you
learn, to fit your special way of thinking.
This is why someone might trade supply and
demand successfully, while you may be failing,
despite both of you using the same concepts.
Don’t just use a strategy just because it’s
popular, or you read somewhere that this is the
best way to trade. Customize it to fit your need,
get rid of anything that doesn’t bring
value and adjust it to your own beliefs.
Now, if you’re looking to further
improve your trading psychology
and correct more mistakes, this
video will definitely help you.
And check out our academy program if you want to
further level up your trading. Until next time!