If I show you this chart, can you tell which
time frame I’m using?
NO!
If you view a chart on a one minute, hourly
or daily timeframe, you wouldn’t be able
to distinguish one from the other.
That is because the price action on the charts
have fractal characteristics.
We can see similar patterns at various time
frequencies.
This is a very important topic in trading
and today you’ll learn how to correctly
trade market fractals.
So if you could, like, subscribe to the channel
and stick around for the full video.
What are Fractals?
At the very core, a market fractal is the
basic building block of price movements up
and down.
Fractals indicate market turning points or
swing points.
Every support or resistance formed in your
charts first start with a fractal.
You can see why fractals are one of the best
tools especially when trading price action.
In any trading decision, it is critical to
find support and resistance areas, whatever
timeframe we are looking at.
Fractals were introduced by Bill Williams
in his book "Trading Chaos".
Fractals are centered on the idea that there
is repetition in price behavior and they can
provide an insight into the repetition patterns.
The indicator usually looks like a five bars
model which is aimed to identify possible
reversal points and detect the direction of
the price.
In order to detect a fractal formation you
must look at five successive price bars where
the third (or the middle) bar represents the
highest high or the lowest low.
In an up fractal the middle bar will have
a higher high than both of the bars at either
side of it.
In a down fractal the middle bar will have
a lower low than both of the bars at either
side of it.
Keep in mind that the fractal arrow appears
only above or below the third candlestick
if it is the highest or the lowest of the
five bars.
A bearish fractal pattern, which indicates
a market reversal to the downside, forms when
each of three successive candlesticks shows
price recoding a higher high, followed by
two candlesticks showing price action with
a lower high than the high of the preceding
candlestick.
Bearish fractal pattern serves as resistance.
A bullish fractal pattern, which indicates
a market reversal to the upside, forms when
each of three successive candlesticks show
price moving to a lower low, followed by two
candlesticks showing price action with a higher
low than the low of the preceding candlestick.
This fractal acts as a support level.
Fractals provide more reliable signals on
higher time frames, but it will also display
fewer signals.
Obviously, depending on what time frame you’re
using, the absolute amount of time required
to form a fractal pattern varies.
If you’re using the hourly chart, a fractal
pattern can form in five hours.
If you trade the daily chart, you will see
fractal patterns that form over the course
of five days.
One of the advantages of fractal pattern is
that it is relatively easy to spot on a chart.
Notice here how the middle bar within the
up fractal has the highest high of the entire
five bar structure, and how each of the two
bars preceding it and following it have a
lower high.
This creates a level of resistance in the
market, and the expectation is for price to
continue lower until the next down fractal
forms in the market.
When you look at the middle bar within a down
fractal, you can see that it has the lowest
low of the entire five bar structure, and
that each of the two bars immediately before
and after it have a higher low.
This creates a level of support in the market
and an expectation for price to move higher
until the next up fractal forms in the price
action.
The structure of the market fractals is fairly
simple to understand.
You can build many different trading rules
and models around the concept of fractals.
But, very important.
The fifth candle in a fractal pattern must
close before you make trading decisions.
This is because the price can move during
the time the fifth candle is forming.
If price moves either above the higher high
or below the lower low, while the pattern
is still forming, the fractal indicator will
disappear from your price chart.
So you must wait for the pattern to complete
in order to make sure that the fractal is
confirmed.
How To Read And Trade Market Fractals
The fractal pattern reveals a “V” or “U”
shaped bottom or top.
Such a pattern of price action may indicate
a market reversal – either a previous up
trending market gradually turning over to
the downside, or a previous down trending
market turning to the upside.
At a minimum, a fractal pattern is useful
for identifying at least a temporary level
of price support (with a bullish fractal)
or price resistance (with a bearish fractal).
So you can use fractals to determine the possible
direction of price.
One way in which you could do this, is by
looking for broken fractals.
A fractal is considered broken when it has
been confirmed and then the price breaks through
either the high or the low of the pattern.
If the price breaks an up fractal then the
direction of the market is considered up and
if the price breaks a down fractal then the
market is considered down.
But this is not enough.
On their own, fractals will offer many false
signals.
As a standalone price action tool, fractals
are quite unreliable.
The main problem with fractals is that there
are so many of them.
Therefore, to get the best out of them, you
must filter the signals with some other indicators
or forms of analysis.
You must view a fractal pattern in relation
to other confluence factors, such as support/resistance
levels, supply and demand areas, pivot points,
Fibonacci levels or round numbers, in order
to evaluate the strength of the fractal.
For example, if the high point of a bearish
fractal coincides with a supply area that
also identifies that price point as a potential
resistance level, then the fractal pattern
is more reliable – and more likely to be
an accurate indicator of a market reversal.
Trend Continuation & Breakouts
Fractals can help assessing the potential
direction of a price move.
For example, if a down fractal has recently
printed on the price chart and the overall
trend is higher, then we can expect price
to continue higher.
Along the same lines, if an up fractal has
recently been breached by a new price leg
that is moving higher, that upside breakout
can indicate that price momentum may continue
higher.
So, if the market is in a strong uptrend,
there will be more fractals that are broken
to the upside than the downside.
That being said, the inability to break through
the previous fractal can give you a hint that
the market is getting ready to consolidate,
or perhaps even change trends.
The question then is whether or not the market
is going to turn around and break through
the opposite direction fractal, because at
that point, the previous trend very well could
be rolling over and changing.
Fractals + Moving Average or AVWAP
Another way to use Fractals is with a moving
average or with Anchored VWAP.
I’ve talked about the power of this tool
in this video.
Adding a dynamic level of support and resistance
allows you to stay on the right side of the
trend.
For example, if you get a fractal that forms
in the other direction of the trend, you simply
ignore it, at least until the moving average
or VWAP tell you it’s time to go in that
direction as well.
If you have a 50 period exponential moving
average that is moving to the upside, then
you are looking for up fractals being broken
as you not only have the fractal indicator
pointing in that direction, but you have the
longer-term traders supporting the move as
well.
Or, if a down fractal appears and is located
near the moving average, then you can treat
the previous move as a pullback, with price
founding support in an uptrend, near a moving
average.
3 confluence factors that signal that the
price is more likely to continue higher.
Fractals & Trade management process
Fractals can also be used during the trade
management process.
We know that an up fractal can serve as resistance
during a rising market, and that a down fractal
can serve as support during a declining market.
As such, you can use these important levels
for the placement of stop loss and take profit
orders.
When multiple fractals appear around the same
area, let’s say a resistance area, you can
set your stop loss level when entering a short
position above the highest fractal.
Make sure you don’t place it right above
or below a fractal, leave a bigger margin,
in case there’s some sort of liquidity hunt.
Taking profits could also involve the use
of fractals.
For example, if going long on a fractal, you
could exit the position once a price hits
a bearish fractal.
I heard some traders close their positions
when an opposite fractal appears, but this
is a bad money management approach, because
the fractal signal will lag by a couple of
bars.
At least two closed bars are needed for a
fractal to be completed, meaning that when
it provides a signal, the price may be at
another level compared to the signal.
So don’t rely on this approach to take profits.
Fractals are excellent for visualizing major
highs and lows and act as a support and resistance
level.
A better approach to take profits is a few
points above or below previous fractals.
Multiple time frames approach
It is best to plot fractals in multiple time
frames.
For example, trade short-term fractals in
the direction of the long-term ones.
And focus on long signals during larger uptrends,
and on short signals during larger downtrends.
In day trading setups for example, you could
base your trades on support and resistance
areas offered by fractals on 4hour and daily
chart.
You can check the 30 minutes or the hourly
time frame to look for entries, but you’ll
use fractal periods on the higher timeframes
to spot support and resistance areas.
In this example, you look for reactions at
this resistance level, given by the fractals
on H4 and Daily time frame and trade on 30M
timeframe.
Trading in lower timeframe lets you to read
price action while watching important support
/ resistance levels on higher timeframe.
If price breaks this major resistance here,
it can be a potential breakout setup.
If it rejects the resistance, it can be a
decent reversal setup.
This price action approach might not be suited
for beginner traders, but if you are an experienced
trader, fractals could be of great help, perfect
for finding areas of value on your chart.
Look for areas where multiple fractals form.
And mark those areas.
If multiple fractals form around a certain
level, and price is unable to go through,
that zone is an important one.
Fractals limitations
Now let’s be clear, Fractals do not predict
the price.
They offer lagging signals.
The arrows for the pattern are typically drawn
over the high or low point, which is the middle
of the fractal, not where the fractal completes.
Therefore, the arrows can be visually deceiving.
So be careful, since the pattern is actually
completing two bars to the right of the arrow,
the first available entry point after seeing
an arrow is the opening price of the third
bar to the right of the arrow.
I wouldn’t base my entries on the appearance
of a single fractal.
Fractals has practical meaning only as part
of a comprehensive strategy, and only for
periods of more than one hour.
Another disadvantage of trading fractals is
the fact they occur quite frequently in the
ordinary course of price action movement – therefore,
the pattern is prone to giving many false
signals.
That’s why few traders rely only on the
fractal indicator for trading signals, instead
they are using it in conjunction with other
technical indicators.
Remember: the longer the time period of the
chart, the more reliable the pattern.
So look for fractals on the hourly, H4 and
daily time frames.
If you found value and learned something new,
leave us a like.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.