hello and welcome today we'll cover the
abcd harmonic pattern and you'll learn
how to trade it and we'll also showcase
how to find the best signals to trade
market reversals
so if you could like subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full
video
abcd is a harmonic chart pattern that
contains two impulsive waves of equal
length and is considered a reversal
formation
in fact it's the most popular and the
simplest harmonic pattern to forecast
reversals in the market
i know that harmonic patterns seem
complicated and difficult to trade so
i'll keep it as simple as possible the
length of the two waves of the abcd
pattern is based on fibonacci ratios
basically there are three waves in the
abcd pattern two impulsive waves and one
retracement wave
abcd harmonic pattern can show in two
different types
bullish and bearish
the price action behavior of the abcd
pattern starts with the price moving in
a new direction point a which later
creates an important swing level point b
then retraces a portion of the a-leg at
point c
and finally resumes to take out the
important swing created at point b
and continues until it reaches a
distance equivalent to a b point d
and when the cd lag reaches an
equivalent distance to the a b leg we
expect a reversal of the cd price move
at the same time bc and cd legs should
respond to specific fibonacci levels
bc lag is 61.8 retracement of a b lag
and cd lag is 1 to 7.2 extension of bc
lag
when the abcd pattern is confirmed you
will look to trade the reversal after
the cd lag
so to keep it simple after dividing this
pattern into three components you will
be able to correctly identify and trade
the abcd pattern
remember a b is an impulsive wave bc
must be a retracement wave and cd is an
impulsive wave
first step is to find the abcd points on
the chart and that is by looking where
the swing moves are on the chart you
find the swing points by looking where
the market is making a large move and
then reverses back and then makes again
a new swing and again reverses
this is the four-step setup which will
make the abcd pattern on the chart
now those wings can be made at any time
frame on the market so you need to train
your eyes to easily spot the abcd
patterns or you can use a harmonic
indicator or a scanner to detect the
pattern
as a first step use the first swing
which will make the a b leg
when you have the first leg then you
need to wait until the market reverses
back from the point b towards point a
if the market reverses back 61.8 percent
from the b point to a point then you
look at the busy lag from this point you
wait for the market to make another move
in the direction of the av lag
if the price goes beyond point b
then you need to prepare a fibonacci
ratio of 1 to 7.2 extension of bc lag
when the market reaches that extension
you need to wait for a reversal signal
to appear near that point
the signal can be some sort of price
action signal like a candlestick pattern
an engulfing bar or a pin bar or a
trendline breakout
or maybe a divergence on a momentum
indicator or a confluence with a support
or resistance level on that point
support and resistance levels increase
the potential market reversal which abcd
harmonic pattern is used for this is the
best confluence setup involving this
pattern
bullish abcd harmonic pattern appears on
the market when the price is moving down
and then you expect the market to
reverse
a b c d pattern will show you when the
market will reverse by making the d
point on the chart the d point will be
below the other three points of the abcd
pattern
the a point is the start point and then
b point the end of the first downswing
then you have the c point which is a
retrace of the a b leg by 61.8 fibonacci
ratio
this means the price returns from the b
point to
8.461.8 of the a b leg
then the price continues the same
direction as the a b leg which is down
and reaches the d point which is below b
point
the cd lag is the same length as the av
lag but the d point must come to an
extension of 1 to 7.2 of bc wave when
the price comes to the d point you can
expect the price to reverse and change
direction so you need to enter into a
buy position
so to keep it simple it's easier if you
write down the main rules to identify a
bullish pattern on the price chart the a
b wave starts from the top to bottom
bc must retrace downward to 61.8
fibonacci level of a b wave
and point d must form at 1 to 7.2
fibonacci extension level of bc wave
[Music]
bearish abcd harmonic patterns appear on
the market when the price is moving up
and then you expect the market to
reverse
again a b c d pattern will show you when
the market will reverse by making the d
point on the chart the d point will be
above the other three points of the abcd
pattern
the a point is the start point and then
the b point the end of the first upswing
then you have the c point which is a
retrace of the av lake by 61.8 fibonacci
ratio
then the price continues the same
direction as the av lag and reaches the
d point which is above b point
the cd leg is the same length as the a b
leg but the d point must come to an
extension of 1 to 7.2 of the bc leg
when the price comes to the d point you
can expect the price to move down so you
need to enter into a cell position
again write down the main rules to find
the bearish pattern the a b wave starts
from the bottom to top and is the
initial wave
the bc wave must retrace upward to 61.8
fibonacci level of a b wave and point t
must form at 1 to 7.2 fibonacci
extension level of bc wave
[Music]
the abcd harmonic pattern has its own
set of rules for trading to enter the
market on the abcd chart pattern you'd
first need to get confirmation for the
pattern's validity this means you will
need to find two parallel price swings
which are equal in size
then you look for the fibonacci
requirements if bc wave represents
61.8 retracement level of a b and the ct
wave is the one to 7.2 extension of bc
wave meanwhile a b wave should also
equal the cd wave in terms of time if
you are able to identify these
characteristics on the price chart then
you are probably looking at a valid abcd
pattern
after you confirm the pattern you should
enter the market at the moment when the
price action bounces from the 1 to 7.2
extension of the bc move you initiate a
trade in the direction of the bounce
which is counter to the cd lag when you
open a position based on an abcd pattern
you also need a stop loss in case of
unexpected price moves against your
trade the proper location of your stop
loss would be just beyond the price
extreme formed at the end of the cd move
the minimum target which you should
pursue is a price move which is equal to
the cd lag in size
in this manner the place where the cd
move started emerging is your target
basically the 100 fibonacci retracement
of the cd wave this is the minimum
potential of the formation the price
could extend its move further and it
might be to your advantage if you keep a
portion of the trade open to catch a
bigger move
therefore after the price completes the
minimum target you could close 50
percent of the position size and keep 50
open to try to write the continued
momentum and when doing so it's
important to keep an eye out for price
action clues using support and
resistance levels trend lines price
channels or candlestick formations
[Music]
when the abcd pattern forms at a key
level or support resistance breakout
level it will often act as a fake out or
as a false breakout i've talked in the
previous videos about smart money and
the liquidation of a large number of
stop orders at once before price moves
back in the opposite direction this is a
common market function in which big
players known as the smart money are
searching for clusters of stop orders to
be able to take sizeable high volume
positions this is why the abcd pattern
is so powerful it has a high probability
of winning in the case of a fake out if
you are able to understand how the smart
money thinks then even as a retail
trader you'll be able to take advantage
of the situation
at the cd leg smart money can stop hunt
the liquidity sitting just beyond the
support or resistance level taking
advantage of retail traders who don't
know how to set up their stop loss
properly if you correctly identify the
pattern you'll be able to identify
positions on the chart where you expect
clusters of stop-loss orders to be
sitting and come up with a stop-hunting
strategy to take advantage
also candlestick formation are great
confluence signals to trade this pattern
the main drawback is that you don't know
when the market will reverse and
sometimes all the condition will meet
the criteria but the point d will extend
further from 1 to 7.2 to 161.8
so to filter out the best signals look
for reversal candlestick patterns
mostly beam bars and engulfing bars
here we found the abcd pattern see that
the a b wave is approximately equal to
the cd wave
also a b takes approximately the same
time to develop as the cd wave
bc is the 61.8 fibonacci retracement of
the ap move and the cd wave is the one
to 7.2 extension of the bc wave
therefore this formation is valid
because the a b and the cd swing points
are downwards we expect this valid abcd
pattern to lead to a bullish price move
also look at this false breakout where
most likely a lot of retail traders had
their stop loss orders
once you have noticed this it's time to
execute a long trade you place your stop
loss order below the lowest point of the
cd swing
and after some time the price reaches
the minimum target of the pattern here
at the level of the point c
at this area you have two viable options
to either close the trade in full and to
look for other trades or to close a
portion of the trade and keep a part
open in order to catch a further price
move
in this particular case if you had
decided to stay in the trade for further
profit your decision would have been
rewarded
observe that on the way up the price
creates only higher loss and doesn't
test any critical support areas from my
experience the best course of action is
to hold the trade further until the
price breaks an important support level
[Music]
if you found value and learned something
new leave us a like this we will know if
you'd like to see more videos like this
one and check out our academy program if
you want to further level up your
trading
until next time