Hello and welcome.
Today we'll look at the point and figure chart,
we'll cover its features, as well as discuss
how they're useful to day trading, scalping
and swing trading and we’ll also see how
to spot supply and demand zones using this
type of analysis.
So if you could… like, subscribe to the
channel and stick around for the full video.
Here we have a chart showing data from past
24 hours.
On the right we have a classic candlestick
chart and on the left a point and figure chart.
Both charts are showing the same thing, the
display is different.
The candlestick chart displays the price as
the linear function of time, shows how the
market behaved during certain periods of time,
in this example 1 trading day.
But the problem is that sometimes, you don’t
need to know how price changed in time, all
you needs is to know is what the prevailing
force on the market is at the moment — demand
or supply.
That is where P&F charts come handy.
They show the price changes graphically, independently
on the time during which the changes have
occurred.
Here we have 5 days of price action.
Point and figure charts provide a simple,
yet disciplined method of identifying current
or emerging trends in prices.
They rely only on price movements and not
time intervals during the creation of the
chart.
In this way, these charts are similar to Renko.
So Point and Figure charting reduces the importance
of time on a chart and instead focuses on
price movements.
These charts are also excellent at filtering
the non-moving days.
Point and Figure charts map out the relationship
between supply (created by sellers) and demand
(created by buyers) at different price levels.
When demand exceeds supply (more buyers than
sellers), prices rise and this is reflected
by a column of Xs on the chart.
Conversely, when supply exceeds demand, (more
sellers than buyers) prices fall and this
is reflected by a column of Os on the chart.
The objective of a Point and Figure chart
is to identify the points at which established
supply/demand relationships change (these
are known as breakouts).
These changes will very probably lead to a
future significant move in the price.
The green X's are the price increases and
the red O's are the price decreases.
A column of X's represent an uptrend, while
the column of O's represents a downtrend.
In each particular column, there can be only
X's or O's.
When one trend ends, a new column starts.
So, X columns represent rising prices, while
columns consisting of O's denote falling prices.
There are two inputs to a Point and Figure
chart: Box size and Reversal amount.
The X's and O's that make up each column occupy
a space called the Box Size.
The box size is the size of movement required
to add an X or an O.
The box size value is determined by each trader.
When price moves enough in the same direction
as the current column, a new X or O is added
to that column.
When price closes far enough away in the opposite
direction, a new column begins with either
an X or an O (the opposite of the previous
column).
The amount that price must move is determined
by the reversal distance.
This value is created by multiplying the box
size by another value defined by the trader,
the Reversal Amount.
The reversal amount is the number of boxes
price must move in order for a new letter
to be drawn or a new column to be created.
Therefore if the box size is set to 1 ($1)
and the reversal amount is set to 3, then
price must move $3 in order for a new letter
to be added to the chart.
There are two different methods for calculating
reversal distance:
First is the Average True Range (ATR).
This method uses the values generated by the
Average True Range (ATR) indicator.
The ATR is used to filter out the normal noise
or volatility of a financial instrument.
It calculates what the ATR value would be
in a regular candlestick chart and then makes
this value the reversal distance.
The second method is the box size.
New boxes are only created when price movement
is larger than the pre-determined reversal
amount.
The upside to this method is that it is very
straightforward and it is easy to anticipate
when and where new boxes will form.
The downside is that selecting the correct
box size for a specific instrument will take
some back test.
I wish I had the perfect box size that will
work on any market, but this isn’t the case.
We all have to backtest and find the right
size for out trading style.
Here are some tips regarding how to set the
correct size of the box, if you’re not using
the ATR method.
So the box size is based on the scale you
wish to use for a particular market and it
represents the value given to each box (X
or O) on the chart.
It’s the minimum price change needed to
continue the trend—meaning to add an X to
the top of the column of X’s (or the minimum
price decrease needed to add an O to the bottom
of a column of O’s).
The reason that this is an issue is because
a reversal of $3 for a $10 stock is more dramatic,
on a different scale, than a $3 reversal on
a $100 stock.
Furthermore, since point and figure charts
are used to filter out “noise” in the
market, you will want to be sure that you
are filtering out just enough to eliminate
momentary price reversals, yet at the same
time, you can identify when a significant
reversal is taking place.
As you use point and figure charts, you may
find that different box sizes work better
for your trading style or for a particular
market.
I don’t use the ATR method, because I prefer
to have full control, so I set the box size
manually, depending on the market I’m trading.
For Forex, box sizes of 10 or 20 pips are
a good start to backtest.
For stocks valued between 20 dollars to 100
dollars, I use a 1 dollar box.
For stocks above 100 dollars I use a 2 dollar
box.
If you trade penny stocks, use 50 cents or
25 cents boxes.
These are just a good starting point.
You can adjust the box size depending on the
market you’re trading and your trading style.
Now, another important aspect to consider.
Old school traders typically prefer the high
and low prices for the period, while others
may focus strictly on a single price such
as the close.
Depending on the price(s) you use, you may
get different results.
There are two rules regarding the letters
and columns.
Each column has to be either X's or O's.
There can never be two different letters in
the same column.
X columns and O columns will always alternate.
You will never see two X columns side by side
and vice versa.
If there are three or more X’s in a column,
demand is in charge and has overcome supply.
The reverse is also true.
When the chart produces three O’s in a column,
this indicates supply has overcome demand.
In this way, Point and Figure charts show
the establishment of trends and trend reversals
in a clear and organized manner.
Their usefulness lies in their ability to
filter out market “noise”—short-term
price fluctuations that occur during longer,
more established trends.
They do not take trading volume into account
and they are only affected by price movements.
Ok, how to use point & figure to find supply
and demand zones.
Now that we have gone through the process
of creating a point and figure chart, the
next step is to understand how to use this
chart as part of your trading decision-making
process.
Point and Figure charts are great for visualizing,
support and resistance levels, trend lines
and breakouts.
First let’s talk about support and resistance
using Point and Figure charts.
A support level is a level at which traders
believe prices will start to move higher after
hitting the level mark.
Have a look at these several O's in the example.
An horizontal row of O's is what you are looking
for when zeroing in on a trend reversal and
an uptrend to begin.
An horizontal row of X's marks the resistance
levels you need to be looking for in the P&F
charts.
So support levels are identified as a horizontal
row of Os which represents a level at which
demand overcomes supply, meaning where buyers
feel confident to step in.
Resistance levels are identified as a horizontal
row of Xs which represents a level at which
supply overcomes demand, meaning where sellers
feel confident to step in.
Have a look at this chart.
At this level, there is more supply than demand
as sellers step in and prices retreat.
At this level, there is more demand than supply
as buyers step in and prices rise.
A simple analysis of long term point & figure
charts will often reveal levels at which prices
consistently find support or resistance.
These are key areas, from which we will be
actively watching for new point & figure bull
or bear trends to emerge.
At support, we will look for further confirmation
such as selling climaxes (particularly if
on high volume), but this a more advanced
topic for another video.
Conversely, pay attention when price is reaching
areas where they find major resistance.
These are levels at which the next price moves
are likely to be downward.
Trend lines are very important in point & figure
analysis.
With point and figure charts, drawing trendlines
is easier than with other charts because much
of the subjectivity is eliminated.
According to the point & figure theory, when
the time doesn’t distort the price action
anymore, the rising and falling angle of a
market is close to 45-degrees.
There are four different types of trendlines
you can use with point and figure charts:
Bullish support,
Bullish resistance,
Bearish support, and
Bearish resistance.
The bullish support line is used to identify
those markets that are in an uptrend, and
to alert you to potential reversals in an
uptrend.
Markets above their bullish support line should
be assumed to be in long term uptrends.
The trend line does not connect points and
can therefore be drawn immediately when an
uptrend begins.
It is drawn from the lowest point made after
the completion of a bear trend or a significant
down move.
And it is drawn at a 45 degree angle.
However, you can also draw trend line, the
classic way, at any angle you want and backtest
future price action.
As a rule of thumb, you should not buy prices
that are trading below their bullish support
lines.
A break of a bullish uptrend line (that has
been in place for a considerable amount of
time) is considered to be a bearish event.
Markets below their bearish resistance line
should be considered to be in long term downtrends.
The trend line is drawn from the highest point
after the completion of a significant uptrend
and is extended downwards at an angle of 45
degrees as far right as possible.
Again, you can experiment with other angles.
Short positions should be considered while
the price is below the line and any buy signals
found below this line should be disregarded.
A break of the bearish resistance line is
considered to be a bullish event.
This video was intended to familiarize you
with Point and Figure charts and the basic
supply and demand theory.
It is important that you fully understand
how these charts are forming, the box sizes
and reversals.
Without a sound knowledge of this information
it will be difficult to understand the following
videos and the more in depth features of Point
and Figure.
I’m currently backtesting these charts,
mainly for support and resistance, and I must
say, I’m having good results.
I can see support and resistance levels much
clearer on these charts.
I’m planning another video with the main
Point and Figure chart patterns, and several
breakout strategies you could apply for swing
trading and day trading.
But, I don’t know if this topic is interesting
to you, I know that these charts are considered
old and outdated.
So if you a follow up video on Point and figure
trading, leave a like and subscribe.
This way we’ll know if you'd like to see
more videos like this one.
And check out our academy program if you want
to further level up your trading.
Until next time.